Hebrews 8

8

^1Now in the things which we are saying the chief point is this: We have such a high priest, who sat down on the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in the heavens, ^2a minister of the sanctuary, and of the true tabernacle, which the Lord pitched, not man. ^3For every high priest is appointed to offer both gifts and sacrifices: wherefore it is necessary that this high priest also have somewhat to offer. ^4Now if he were on earth, he would not be a priest at all, seeing there are those who offer the gifts according to the law; ^5who serve that which is a copy and shadow of the heavenly things, even as Moses is warned of God when he is about to make the tabernacle: for, See, saith he, that thou make all things according to the pattern that was showed thee in the mount. ^6But now hath he obtained a ministry the more excellent, by so much as he is also the mediator of a better covenant, which hath been enacted upon better promises. ^7For if that first covenant had been faultless, then would no place have been sought for a second. ^8For finding fault with them, he saith,

Behold, the days come, saith the Lord,

That I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah;

^9Not according to the covenant that I made with their fathers

In the day that I took them by the hand to lead them forth out of the land of Egypt;

For they continued not in my covenant,

And I regarded them not, saith the Lord.

^10For this is the covenant that I will make with the house of Israel

After those days, saith the Lord;

I will put my laws into their mind,

And on their heart also will I write them:

And I will be to them a God,

And they shall be to me a people:

^11And they shall not teach every man his fellow-citizen,

And every man his brother, saying, Know the Lord:

For all shall know me,

From the least to the greatest of them.

^12For I will be merciful to their iniquities,

And their sins will I remember no more.

^13In that he saith, A new covenant he hath made the first old. But that which is becoming old and waxeth aged is nigh unto vanishing away.

Hebrews 9

9

^1Now even a first covenant had ordinances of divine service, and its sanctuary, a sanctuary of this world. ^2For there was a tabernacle prepared, the first, wherein were the candlestick, and the table, and the showbread; which is called the Holy place. ^3And after the second veil, the tabernacle which is called the Holy of holies; ^4having a golden altar of incense, and the ark of the covenant overlaid round about with gold, wherein was a golden pot holding the manna, and Aaron's rod that budded, and the tables of the covenant; ^5and above it cherubim of glory overshadowing the mercy-seat; of which things we cannot now speak severally. ^6Now these things having been thus prepared, the priests go in continually into the first tabernacle, accomplishing the services; ^7but into the second the high priest alone, once in the year, not without blood, which he offereth for himself, and for the errors of the people: ^8the Holy Spirit this signifying, that the way into the holy place hath not yet been made manifest, while the first tabernacle is yet standing; ^9which is a figure for the time present; according to which are offered both gifts and sacrifices that cannot, as touching the conscience, make the worshipper perfect, ^10being only (with meats and drinks and divers washings) carnal ordinances, imposed until a time of reformation. ^11But Christ having come a high priest of the good things to come, through the greater and more perfect tabernacle, not made with hands, that is to say, not of this creation, ^12nor yet through the blood of goats and calves, but through his own blood, entered in once for all into the holy place, having obtained eternal redemption. ^13For if the blood of goats and bulls, and the ashes of a heifer sprinkling them that have been defiled, sanctify unto the cleanness of the flesh: ^14how much more shall the blood of Christ, who through the eternal Spirit offered himself without blemish unto God, cleanse your conscience from dead works to serve the living God? ^15And for this cause he is the mediator of a new covenant, that a death having taken place for the redemption of the transgressions that were under the first covenant, they that have been called may receive the promise of the eternal inheritance. ^16For where a testament is, there must of necessity be the death of him that made it. ^17For a testament is of force where there hath been death: for it doth never avail while he that made it liveth. ^18Wherefore even the first covenant hath not been dedicated without blood. ^19For when every commandment had been spoken by Moses unto all the people according to the law, he took the blood of the calves and the goats, with water and scarlet wool and hyssop, and sprinkled both the book itself and all the people, ^20saying, This is the blood of the covenant which God commanded to you-ward. ^21Moreover the tabernacle and all the vessels of the ministry he sprinkled in like manner with the blood. ^22And according to the law, I may almost say, all things are cleansed with blood, and apart from shedding of blood there is no remission. ^23It was necessary therefore that the copies of the things in the heavens should be cleansed with these; but the heavenly things themselves with better sacrifices than these. ^24For Christ entered not into a holy place made with hands, like in pattern to the true; but into heaven itself, now to appear before the face of God for us: ^25nor yet that he should offer himself often, as the high priest entereth into the holy place year by year with blood not his own; ^26else must he often have suffered since the foundation of the world: but now once at the end of the ages hath he been manifested to put away sin by the sacrifice of himself. ^27And inasmuch as it is appointed unto men once to die, and after this cometh judgment; ^28so Christ also, having been once offered to bear the sins of many, shall appear a second time, apart from sin, to them that wait for him, unto salvation.

Hebrews 10

10

^1For the law having a shadow of the good things to come, not the very image of the things, can never with the same sacrifices year by year, which they offer continually, make perfect them that draw nigh. ^2Else would they not have ceased to be offered? because the worshippers, having been once cleansed, would have had no more consciousness of sins. ^3But in those sacrifices there is a remembrance made of sins year by year. ^4For it is impossible that the blood of bulls and goats should take away sins. ^5Wherefore when he cometh into the world, he saith,

Sacrifice and offering thou wouldest not,

But a body didst thou prepare for me;

^6In whole burnt offerings and sacrifices for sin thou hadst no pleasure:

^7Then said I, Lo, I am come (In the roll of the book it is written of me)

To do thy will, O God.

^8Saying above, Sacrifices and offerings and whole burnt offerings and sacrifices for sin thou wouldest not, neither hadst pleasure therein (the which are offered according to the law), ^9then hath he said, Lo, I am come to do thy will. He taketh away the first, that he may establish the second. ^10By which will we have been sanctified through the offering of the body of Jesus Christ once for all. ^11And every priest indeed standeth day by day ministering and offering oftentimes the same sacrifices, the which can never take away sins: ^12but he, when he had offered one sacrifice for sins for ever, sat down on the right hand of God; ^13henceforth expecting till his enemies be made the footstool of his feet. ^14For by one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are sanctified. ^15And the Holy Spirit also beareth witness to us; for after he hath said,

^16This is the covenant that I will make with them

After those days, saith the Lord:

I will put my laws on their heart,

And upon their mind also will I write them;

then saith he,

^17And their sins and their iniquities will I remember no more.

^18Now where remission of these is, there is no more offering for sin. ^19Having therefore, brethren, boldness to enter into the holy place by the blood of Jesus, ^20by the way which he dedicated for us, a new and living way, through the veil, that is to say, his flesh; ^21and having a great priest over the house of God; ^22let us draw near with a true heart in fulness of faith, having our hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience: and having our body washed with pure water, ^23let us hold fast the confession of our hope that it waver not; for he is faithful that promised: ^24and let us consider one another to provoke unto love and good works; ^25not forsaking our own assembling together, as the custom of some is, but exhorting one another; and so much the more, as ye see the day drawing nigh. ^26For if we sin wilfully after that we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more a sacrifice for sins, ^27but a certain fearful expectation of judgment, and a fierceness of fire which shall devour the adversaries. ^28A man that hath set at nought Moses law dieth without compassion on the word of two or three witnesses: ^29of how much sorer punishment, think ye, shall he be judged worthy, who hath trodden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the covenant wherewith he was sanctified an unholy thing, and hath done despite unto the Spirit of grace? ^30For we know him that said, Vengeance belongeth unto me, I will recompense. And again, The Lord shall judge his people. ^31It is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God. ^32But call to remembrance the former days, in which, after ye were enlightened, ye endured a great conflict of sufferings; ^33partly, being made a gazingstock both by reproaches and afflictions; and partly, becoming partakers with them that were so used. ^34For ye both had compassion on them that were in bonds, and took joyfully the spoiling of your possessions, knowing that ye have for yourselves a better possession and an abiding one. ^35Cast not away therefore your boldness, which hath great recompense of reward. ^36For ye have need of patience, that, having done the will of God, ye may receive the promise.

^37For yet a very little while,

He that cometh shall come, and shall not tarry.

^38But my righteous one shall live by faith:

And if he shrink back, my soul hath no pleasure in him.

^39But we are not of them that shrink back unto perdition; but of them that have faith unto the saving of the soul.

Hebrews 11

11

^1Now faith is assurance of things hoped for, a conviction of things not seen. ^2For therein the elders had witness borne to them. ^3By faith we understand that the worlds have been framed by the word of God, so that what is seen hath not been made out of things which appear. ^4By faith Abel offered unto God a more excellent sacrifice than Cain, through which he had witness borne to him that he was righteous, God bearing witness in respect of his gifts: and through it he being dead yet speaketh. ^5By faith Enoch was translated that he should not see death; and he was not found, because God translated him: for he hath had witness borne to him that before his translation he had been well-pleasing unto God: ^6And without faith it is impossible to be well-pleasing unto him; for he that cometh to God must believe that he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that seek after him. ^7By faith Noah, being warned of God concerning things not seen as yet, moved with godly fear, prepared an ark to the saving of his house; through which he condemned the world, and became heir of the righteousness which is according to faith. ^8By faith Abraham, when he was called, obeyed to go out unto a place which he was to receive for an inheritance; and he went out, not knowing whither he went. ^9By faith he became a sojourner in the land of promise, as in a land not his own, dwelling in tents, with Isaac and Jacob, the heirs with him of the same promise: ^10for he looked for the city which hath the foundations, whose builder and maker is God. ^11By faith even Sarah herself received power to conceive seed when she was past age, since she counted him faithful who had promised: ^12wherefore also there sprang of one, and him as good as dead, so many as the stars of heaven in multitude, and as the sand, which is by the sea-shore, innumerable. ^13These all died in faith, not having received the promises, but having seen them and greeted them from afar, and having confessed that they were strangers and pilgrims on the earth. ^14For they that say such things make it manifest that they are seeking after a country of their own. ^15And if indeed they had been mindful of that country from which they went out, they would have had opportunity to return. ^16But now they desire a better country, that is, a heavenly: wherefore God is not ashamed of them, to be called their God; for he hath prepared for them a city. ^17By faith Abraham, being tried, offered up Isaac: yea, he that had gladly received the promises was offering up his only begotten son; ^18even he to whom it was said, In Isaac shall thy seed be called: ^19accounting that God is able to raise up, even from the dead; from whence he did also in a figure receive him back. ^20By faith Isaac blessed Jacob and Esau, even concerning things to come. ^21By faith Jacob, when he was dying, blessed each of the sons of Joseph; and worshipped, leaning upon the top of his staff. ^22By faith Joseph, when his end was nigh, made mention of the departure of the children of Israel; and gave commandment concerning his bones. ^23By faith Moses, when he was born, was hid three months by his parents, because they saw he was a goodly child; and they were not afraid of the king's commandment. ^24By faith Moses, when he was grown up, refused to be called the son of Pharaoh's daughter; ^25choosing rather to share ill treatment with the people of God, than to enjoy the pleasures of sin for a season; ^26accounting the reproach of Christ greater riches than the treasures of Egypt: for he looked unto the recompense of reward. ^27By faith he forsook Egypt, not fearing the wrath of the king: for he endured, as seeing him who is invisible. ^28By faith he kept the passover, and the sprinkling of the blood, that the destroyer of the firstborn should not touch them. ^29By faith they passed through the Red sea as by dry land: which the Egyptians assaying to do were swallowed up. ^30By faith the walls of Jericho fell down, after they had been compassed about for seven days. ^31By faith Rahab the harlot perished not with them that were disobedient, having received the spies with peace. ^32And what shall I more say? for the time will fail me if I tell of Gideon, Barak, Samson, Jephthah; of David and Samuel and the prophets: ^33who through faith subdued kingdoms, wrought righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions, ^34quenched the power of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, from weakness were made strong, waxed mighty in war, turned to flight armies of aliens. ^35Women received their dead by a resurrection: and others were tortured, not accepting their deliverance; that they might obtain a better resurrection: ^36and others had trial of mockings and scourgings, yea, moreover of bonds and imprisonment: ^37they were stoned, they were sawn asunder, they were tempted, they were slain with the sword: they went about in sheepskins, in goatskins; being destitute, afflicted, ill-treated ^38(of whom the world was not worthy), wandering in deserts and mountains and caves, and the holes of the earth. ^39And these all, having had witness borne to them through their faith, received not the promise, ^40God having provided some better thing concerning us, that apart from us they should not be made perfect.

Hebrews 12

12

^1Therefore let us also, seeing we are compassed about with so great a cloud of witnesses, lay aside every weight, and the sin which doth so easily beset us, and let us run with patience the race that is set before us, ^2looking unto Jesus the author and perfecter of our faith, who for the joy that was set before him endured the cross, despising shame, and hath sat down at the right hand of the throne of God. ^3For consider him that hath endured such gainsaying of sinners against himself, that ye wax not weary, fainting in your souls. ^4Ye have not yet resisted unto blood, striving against sin: ^5and ye have forgotten the exhortation which reasoneth with you as with sons,

My son, regard not lightly the chastening of the Lord,

Nor faint when thou art reproved of him;

^6For whom the Lord loveth he chasteneth,

And scourgeth every son whom he receiveth.

^7It is for chastening that ye endure; God dealeth with you as with sons; for what son is there whom his father chasteneth not? ^8But if ye are without chastening, whereof all have been made partakers, then are ye bastards, and not sons. ^9Furthermore, we had the fathers of our flesh to chasten us, and we gave them reverence: shall we not much rather be in subjection unto the Father of spirits, and live? ^10For they indeed for a few days chastened us as seemed good to them; but he for our profit, that we may be partakers of his holiness. ^11All chastening seemeth for the present to be not joyous but grievous; yet afterward it yieldeth peaceable fruit unto them that have been exercised thereby, even the fruit of righteousness. ^12Wherefore lift up the hands that hang down, and the palsied knees; ^13and make straight paths for your feet, that that which is lame be not turned out of the way, but rather be healed. ^14Follow after peace with all men, and the sanctification without which no man shall see the Lord: ^15looking carefully lest there be any man that falleth short of the grace of God; lest any root of bitterness springing up trouble you, and thereby the many be defiled; ^16lest there be any fornication, or profane person, as Esau, who for one mess of meat sold his own birthright. ^17For ye know that even when he afterward desired to inherit the blessing, he was rejected; for he found no place for a change of mind in his father, though he sought it diligently with tears. ^18For ye are not come unto a mount that might be touched, and that burned with fire, and unto blackness, and darkness, and tempest, ^19and the sound of a trumpet, and the voice of words; which voice they that heard entreated that no word more should be spoken unto them; ^20for they could not endure that which was enjoined, If even a beast touch the mountain, it shall be stoned; ^21and so fearful was the appearance, that Moses said, I exceedingly fear and quake: ^22but ye are come unto mount Zion, and unto the city of the living God, the heavenly Jerusalem, and to innumerable hosts of angels, ^23to the general assembly and church of the firstborn who are enrolled in heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the spirits of just men made perfect, ^24and to Jesus the mediator of a new covenant, and to the blood of sprinkling that speaketh better than that of Abel. ^25See that ye refuse not him that speaketh. For if they escaped not when they refused him that warned them on earth, much more shall not we escape who turn away from him that warneth from heaven: ^26whose voice then shook the earth: but now he hath promised, saying, Yet once more will I make to tremble not the earth only, but also the heaven. ^27And this word, Yet once more, signifieth the removing of those things that are shaken, as of things that have been made, that those things which are not shaken may remain. ^28Wherefore, receiving a kingdom that cannot be shaken, let us have grace, whereby we may offer service well-pleasing to God with reverence and awe: ^29for our God is a consuming fire.

Hebrews 13

13

^1Let love of the brethren continue. ^2Forget not to show love unto strangers: for thereby some have entertained angels unawares. ^3Remember them that are in bonds, as bound with them; them that are illtreated, as being yourselves also in the body. ^4Let marriage be had in honor among all, and let the bed be undefiled: for fornicators and adulterers God will judge. ^5Be ye free from the love of money; content with such things as ye have: for himself hath said, I will in no wise fail thee, neither will I in any wise forsake thee. ^6So that with good courage we say,

The Lord is my helper; I will not fear:

What shall man do unto me?

^7Remember them that had the rule over you, men that spake unto you the word of God; and considering the issue of their life, imitate their faith. ^8Jesus Christ is the same yesterday and to-day, yea and for ever. ^9Be not carried away by divers and strange teachings: for it is good that the heart be established by grace; not by meats, wherein they that occupied themselves were not profited. ^10We have an altar, whereof they have no right to eat that serve the tabernacle. ^11For the bodies of those beasts whose blood is brought into the holy place by the high priest as an offering for sin, are burned without the camp. ^12Wherefore Jesus also, that he might sanctify the people through his own blood, suffered without the gate. ^13Let us therefore go forth unto him without the camp, bearing his reproach. ^14For we have not here an abiding city, but we seek after the city which is to come. ^15Through him then let us offer up a sacrifice of praise to God continually, that is, the fruit of lips which make confession to his name. ^16But to do good and to communicate forget not: for with such sacrifices God is well pleased. ^17Obey them that have the rule over you, and submit to them: for they watch in behalf of your souls, as they that shall give account; that they may do this with joy, and not with grief: for this were unprofitable for you. ^18Pray for us: for we are persuaded that we have a good conscience, desiring to live honorably in all things. ^19And I exhort you the more exceedingly to do this, that I may be restored to you the sooner. ^20Now the God of peace, who brought again from the dead the great shepherd of the sheep with the blood of an eternal covenant, even our Lord Jesus, ^21make you perfect in every good thing to do his will, working in us that which is well-pleasing in his sight, through Jesus Christ; to whom be the glory for ever and ever. Amen. ^22But I exhort you, brethren, bear with the word of exhortation, for I have written unto you in few words. ^23Know ye that our brother Timothy hath been set at liberty; with whom, if he come shortly, I will see you. ^24Salute all them that have the rule over you, and all the saints. They of Italy salute you. ^25Grace be with you all. Amen.

Hosea 2

2

^1Say ye unto your brethren, Ammi; and to your sisters, Ruhamah. ^2Contend with your mother, contend; for she is not my wife, neither am I her husband; and let her put away her whoredoms from her face, and her adulteries from between her breasts; ^3lest I strip her naked, and set her as in the day that she was born, and make her as a wilderness, and set her like a dry land, and slay her with thirst. ^4Yea, upon her children will I have no mercy; for they are children of whoredom; ^5for their mother hath played the harlot; she that conceived them hath done shamefully; for she said, I will go after my lovers, that give me my bread and my water, my wool and my flax, mine oil and my drink. ^6Therefore, behold, I will hedge up thy way with thorns, and I will build a wall against her, that she shall not find her paths. ^7And she shall follow after her lovers, but she shall not overtake them; and she shall seek them, but shall not find them: then shall she say, I will go and return to my first husband; for then was it better with me than now. ^8For she did not know that I gave her the grain, and the new wine, and the oil, and multiplied unto her silver and gold, which they used for Baal. ^9Therefore will I take back my grain in the time thereof, and my new wine in the season thereof, and will pluck away my wool and my flax which should have covered her nakedness. ^10And now will I uncover her lewdness in the sight of her lovers, and none shall deliver her out of my hand. ^11I will also cause all her mirth to cease, her feasts, her new moons, and her sabbaths, and all her solemn assemblies. ^12And I will lay waste her vines and her fig-trees, whereof she hath said, These are my hire that my lovers have given me; and I will make them a forest, and the beasts of the field shall eat them. ^13And I will visit upon her the days of the Baalim, unto which she burned incense, when she decked herself with her earrings and her jewels, and went after her lovers, and forgat me, saith Jehovah. ^14Therefore, behold, I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderness, and speak comfortably unto her. ^15And I will give her her vineyards from thence, and the valley of Achor for a door of hope; and she shall make answer there, as in the days of her youth, and as in the day when she came up out of the land of Egypt. ^16And it shall be at that day, saith Jehovah, that thou shalt call me Ishi, and shalt call me no more Baali. ^17For I will take away the names of the Baalim out of her mouth, and they shall no more be mentioned by their name. ^18And in that day will I make a covenant for them with the beasts of the field, and with the birds of the heavens, and with the creeping things of the ground: and I will break the bow and the sword and the battle out of the land, and will make them to lie down safely. ^19And I will betroth thee unto me for ever; yea, I will betroth thee unto me in righteousness, and in justice, and in lovingkindness, and in mercies. ^20I will even betroth thee unto me in faithfulness; and thou shalt know Jehovah. ^21And it shall come to pass in that day, I will answer, saith Jehovah, I will answer the heavens, and they shall answer the earth; ^22and the earth shall answer the grain, and the new wine, and the oil; and they shall answer Jezreel. ^23And I will sow her unto me in the earth; and I will have mercy upon her that had not obtained mercy; and I will say to them that were not my people, Thou art my people; and they shall say, Thou art my God.

Hosea 4

4

^1Hear the word of Jehovah, ye children of Israel; for Jehovah hath a controversy with the inhabitants of the land, because there is no truth, nor goodness, nor knowledge of God in the land. ^2There is nought but swearing and breaking faith, and killing, and stealing, and committing adultery; they break out, and blood toucheth blood. ^3Therefore shall the land mourn, and every one that dwelleth therein shall languish, with the beasts of the field and the birds of the heavens; yea, the fishes of the sea also shall be taken away. ^4Yet let no man strive, neither let any man reprove; for thy people are as they that strive with the priest. ^5And thou shalt stumble in the day, and the prophet also shall stumble with thee in the night; and I will destroy thy mother. ^6My people are destroyed for lack of knowledge: because thou hast rejected knowledge, I will also reject thee, that thou shalt be no priest to me: seeing thou hast forgotten the law of thy God, I also will forget thy children. ^7As they were multiplied, so they sinned against me: I will change their glory into shame. ^8They feed on the sin of my people, and set their heart on their iniquity. ^9And it shall be, like people, like priest; and I will punish them for their ways, and will requite them their doings. ^10And they shall eat, and not have enough; they shall play the harlot, and shall not increase; because they have left off taking heed to Jehovah. ^11Whoredom and wine and new wine take away the understanding. ^12My people ask counsel at their stock, and their staff declareth unto them; for the spirit of whoredom hath caused them to err, and they have played the harlot, departing from under their God. ^13They sacrifice upon the tops of the mountains, and burn incense upon the hills, under oaks and poplars and terebinths, because the shadow thereof is good: therefore your daughters play the harlot, and your brides commit adultery. ^14I will not punish your daughters when they play the harlot, nor your brides when they commit adultery; for the men themselves go apart with harlots, and they sacrifice with the prostitutes; and the people that doth not understand shall be overthrown. ^15Though thou, Israel, play the harlot, yet let not Judah offend; and come not ye unto Gilgal, neither go ye up to Beth-aven, nor swear, As Jehovah liveth. ^16For Israel hath behaved himself stubbornly, like a stubborn heifer: now will Jehovah feed them as a lamb in a large place. ^17Ephraim is joined to idols; let him alone. ^18Their drink is become sour; they play the harlot continually; her rulers dearly love shame. ^19The wind hath wrapped her up in its wings; and they shall be put to shame because of their sacrifices.

Hosea 5

5

^1Hear this, O ye priests, and hearken, O house of Israel, and give ear, O house of the king; for unto you pertaineth the judgment; for ye have been a snare at Mizpah, and a net spread upon Tabor. ^2And the revolters are gone deep in making slaughter; but I am a rebuker of them all. ^3I know Ephraim, and Israel is not hid from me; for now, O Ephraim, thou hast played the harlot, Israel is defiled. ^4Their doings will not suffer them to turn unto their God; for the spirit of whoredom is within them, and they know not Jehovah. ^5And the pride of Israel doth testify to his face: therefore Israel and Ephraim shall stumble in their iniquity; Judah also shall stumble with them. ^6They shall go with their flocks and with their herds to seek Jehovah; but they shall not find him: he hath withdrawn himself from them. ^7They have dealt treacherously against Jehovah; for they have borne strange children: now shall the new moon devour them with their fields. ^8Blow ye the cornet in Gibeah, and the trumpet in Ramah: sound an alarm at Beth-aven; behind thee, O Benjamin. ^9Ephraim shall become a desolation in the day of rebuke: among the tribes of Israel have I made known that which shall surely be. ^10The princes of Judah are like them that remove the landmark: I will pour out my wrath upon them like water. ^11Ephraim is oppressed, he is crushed in judgment; because he was content to walk after man's command. ^12Therefore am I unto Ephraim as a moth, and to the house of Judah as rottenness. ^13When Ephraim saw his sickness, and Judah saw his wound, then went Ephraim to Assyria, and sent to king Jareb: but he is not able to heal you, neither will he cure you of your wound. ^14For I will be unto Ephraim as a lion, and as a young lion to the house of Judah: I, even I, will tear and go away; I will carry off, and there shall be none to deliver. ^15I will go and return to my place, till they acknowledge their offence, and seek my face: in their affliction they will seek me earnestly.

Hosea 6

6

^1Come, and let us return unto Jehovah; for he hath torn, and he will heal us; he hath smitten, and he will bind us up. ^2After two days will he revive us: on the third day he will raise us up, and we shall live before him. ^3And let us know, let us follow on to know Jehovah: his going forth is sure as the morning; and he will come unto us as the rain, as the latter rain that watereth the earth. ^4O Ephraim, what shall I do unto thee? O Judah, what shall I do unto thee? for your goodness is as a morning cloud, and as the dew that goeth early away. ^5Therefore have I hewed them by the prophets; I have slain them by the words of my mouth: and thy judgments are as the light that goeth forth. ^6For I desire goodness, and not sacrifice; and the knowledge of God more than burnt-offerings. ^7But they like Adam have transgressed the covenant: there have they dealt treacherously against me. ^8Gilead is a city of them that work iniquity; it is stained with blood. ^9And as troops of robbers wait for a man, so the company of priests murder in the way toward Shechem; yea, they have committed lewdness. ^10In the house of Israel I have seen a horrible thing: there whoredom is found in Ephraim, Israel is defiled. ^11Also, O Judah, there is a harvest appointed for thee, when I bring back the captivity of my people.

Hosea 7

7

^1When I would heal Israel, then is the iniquity of Ephraim uncovered, and the wickedness of Samaria; for they commit falsehood, and the thief entereth in, and the troop of robbers ravageth without. ^2And they consider not in their hearts that I remember all their wickedness: now have their own doings beset them about; they are before my face. ^3They make the king glad with their wickedness, and the princes with their lies. ^4They are all adulterers; they are as an oven heated by the baker; he ceaseth to stir the fire, from the kneading of the dough, until it be leavened. ^5On the day of our king the princes made themselves sick with the heat of wine; he stretched out his hand with scoffers. ^6For they have made ready their heart like an oven, while they lie in wait: their baker sleepeth all the night; in the morning it burneth as a flaming fire. ^7They are all hot as an oven, and devour their judges; all their kings are fallen: there is none among them that calleth unto me. ^8Ephraim, he mixeth himself among the peoples; Ephraim is a cake not turned. ^9Strangers have devoured his strength, and he knoweth it not: yea, gray hairs are here and there upon him, and he knoweth it not. ^10And the pride of Israel doth testify to his face: yet they have not returned unto Jehovah their God, nor sought him, for all this. ^11And Ephraim is like a silly dove, without understanding: they call unto Egypt, they go to Assyria. ^12When they shall go, I will spread my net upon them; I will bring them down as the birds of the heavens; I will chastise them, as their congregation hath heard. ^13Woe unto them! for they have wandered from me; destruction unto them! for they have trespassed against me: though I would redeem them, yet they have spoken lies against me. ^14And they have not cried unto me with their heart, but they howl upon their beds: they assemble themselves for grain and new wine; they rebel against me. ^15Though I have taught and strengthened their arms, yet do they devise mischief against me. ^16They return, but not to him that is on high; they are like a deceitful bow; their princes shall fall by the sword for the rage of their tongue: this shall be their derision in the land of Egypt.

Hosea 8

8

^1Set the trumpet to thy mouth. As an eagle he cometh against the house of Jehovah, because they have transgressed my covenant, and trespassed against my law. ^2They shall cry unto me, My God, we Israel know thee. ^3Israel hath cast off that which is good: the enemy shall pursue him. ^4They have set up kings, but not by me; they have made princes, and I knew it not: of their silver and their gold have they made them idols, that they may be cut off. ^5He hath cast off thy calf, O Samaria; mine anger is kindled against them: how long will it be ere they attain to innocency? ^6For from Israel is even this; the workman made it, and it is no God; yea, the calf of Samaria shall be broken in pieces. ^7For they sow the wind, and they shall reap the whirlwind: he hath no standing grain; the blade shall yield no meal; if so be it yield, strangers shall swallow it up. ^8Israel is swallowed up: now are they among the nations as a vessel wherein none delighteth. ^9For they are gone up to Assyria, like a wild ass alone by himself: Ephraim hath hired lovers. ^10Yea, though they hire among the nations, now will I gather them; and they begin to be diminished by reason of the burden of the king of princes. ^11Because Ephraim hath multiplied altars for sinning, altars have been unto him for sinning. ^12I wrote for him the ten thousand things of my law; but they are counted as a strange thing. ^13As for the sacrifices of mine offerings, they sacrifice flesh and eat it; but Jehovah accepteth them not: now will he remember their iniquity, and visit their sins; they shall return to Egypt. ^14For Israel hath forgotten his Maker, and builded palaces; and Judah hath multiplied fortified cities: but I will send a fire upon his cities, and it shall devour the castles thereof.

Hosea 9

9

^1Rejoice not, O Israel, for joy, like the peoples; for thou hast played the harlot, departing from thy God; thou hast loved hire upon every grain-floor. ^2The threshing-floor and the winepress shall not feed them, and the new wine shall fail her. ^3They shall not dwell in Jehovah's land; but Ephraim shall return to Egypt, and they shall eat unclean food in Assyria. ^4They shall not pour out wine-offerings to Jehovah, neither shall they be pleasing unto him: their sacrifices shall be unto them as the bread of mourners; all that eat thereof shall be polluted; for their bread shall be for their appetite; it shall not come into the house of Jehovah. ^5What will ye do in the day of solemn assembly, and in the day of the feast of Jehovah? ^6For, lo, they are gone away from destruction; yet Egypt shall gather them up, Memphis shall bury them; their pleasant things of silver, nettles shall possess them; thorns shall be in their tents. ^7The days of visitation are come, the days of recompense are come; Israel shall know it: the prophet is a fool, the man that hath the spirit is mad, for the abundance of thine iniquity, and because the enmity is great. ^8Ephraim was a watchman with my God: as for the prophet, a fowler's snare is in all his ways, and enmity in the house of his God. ^9They have deeply corrupted themselves, as in the days of Gibeah: he will remember their iniquity, he will visit their sins. ^10I found Israel like grapes in the wilderness; I saw your fathers as the first-ripe in the fig-tree at its first season: but they came to Baal-peor, and consecrated themselves unto the shameful thing, and became abominable like that which they loved. ^11As for Ephraim, their glory shall fly away like a bird: there shall be no birth, and none with child, and no conception. ^12Though they bring up their children, yet will I bereave them, so that not a man shall be left: yea, woe also to them when I depart from them! ^13Ephraim, like as I have seen Tyre, is planted in a pleasant place: but Ephraim shall bring out his children to the slayer. ^14Give them, O Jehovah-what wilt thou give? give them a miscarrying womb and dry breasts. ^15All their wickedness is in Gilgal; for there I hated them: because of the wickedness of their doings I will drive them out of my house; I will love them no more; all their princes are revolters. ^16Ephraim is smitten, their root is dried up, they shall bear no fruit: yea, though they bring forth, yet will I slay the beloved fruit of their womb. ^17My God will cast them away, because they did not hearken unto him; and they shall be wanderers among the nations.

Hosea 10

10

^1Israel is a luxuriant vine, that putteth forth his fruit: according to the abundance of his fruit he hath multiplied his altars; according to the goodness of their land they have made goodly pillars. ^2Their heart is divided; now shall they be found guilty: he will smite their altars, he will destroy their pillars. ^3Surely now shall they say, We have no king; for we fear not Jehovah; and the king, what can he do for us? ^4They speak vain words, swearing falsely in making covenants: therefore judgment springeth up as hemlock in the furrows of the field. ^5The inhabitants of Samaria shall be in terror for the calves of Beth-aven; for the people thereof shall mourn over it, and the priests thereof that rejoiced over it, for the glory thereof, because it is departed from it. ^6It also shall be carried unto Assyria for a present to king Jareb: Ephraim shall receive shame, and Israel shall be ashamed of his own counsel. ^7As for Samaria, her king is cut off, as foam upon the water. ^8The high places also of Aven, the sin of Israel, shall be destroyed: the thorn and the thistle shall come up on their altars; and they shall say to the mountains, Cover us; and to the hills, Fall on us. ^9O Israel, thou hast sinned from the days of Gibeah: there they stood; the battle against the children of iniquity doth not overtake them in Gibeah. ^10When it is my desire, I will chastise them; and the peoples shall be gathered against them, when they are bound to their two transgressions. ^11And Ephraim is a heifer that is taught, that loveth to tread out the grain; but I have passed over upon her fair neck: I will set a rider on Ephraim; Judah shall plow, Jacob shall break his clods. ^12Sow to yourselves in righteousness, reap according to kindness; break up your fallow ground; for it is time to seek Jehovah, till he come and rain righteousness upon you. ^13Ye have plowed wickedness, ye have reaped iniquity; ye have eaten the fruit of lies; for thou didst trust in thy way, in the multitude of thy mighty men. ^14Therefore shall a tumult arise among thy people, and all thy fortresses shall be destroyed, as Shalman destroyed Beth-arbel in the day of battle: the mother was dashed in pieces with her children. ^15So shall Beth-el do unto you because of your great wickedness: at daybreak shall the king of Israel be utterly cut off.

Hosea 11

11

^1When Israel was a child, then I loved him, and called my son out of Egypt. ^2The more the prophets called them, the more they went from them: they sacrificed unto the Baalim, and burned incense to graven images. ^3Yet I taught Ephraim to walk; I took them on my arms; but they knew not that I healed them. ^4I drew them with cords of a man, with bands of love; and I was to them as they that lift up the yoke on their jaws; and I laid food before them. ^5They shall not return into the land of Egypt; but the Assyrian shall be their king, because they refused to return to me. ^6And the sword shall fall upon their cities, and shall consume their bars, and devour them, because of their own counsels. ^7And my people are bent on backsliding from me: though they call them to him that is on high, none at all will exalt him. ^8How shall I give thee up, Ephraim? how shall I cast thee off, Israel? how shall I make thee as Admah? how shall I set thee as Zeboiim? my heart is turned within me, my compassions are kindled together. ^9I will not execute the fierceness of mine anger, I will not return to destroy Ephraim: for I am God, and not man; the Holy One in the midst of thee; and I will not come in wrath. ^10They shall walk after Jehovah, who will roar like a lion; for he will roar, and the children shall come trembling from the west. ^11They shall come trembling as a bird out of Egypt, and as a dove out of the land of Assyria; and I will make them to dwell in their houses, saith Jehovah. ^12Ephraim compasseth me about with falsehood, and the house of Israel with deceit; but Judah yet ruleth with God, and is faithful with the Holy One.

Hosea 12

12

^1Ephraim feedeth on wind, and followeth after the east wind: he continually multiplieth lies and desolation; and they make a covenant with Assyria, and oil is carried into Egypt. ^2Jehovah hath also a controversy with Judah, and will punish Jacob according to his ways; according to his doings will he recompense him. ^3In the womb he took his brother by the heel; and in his manhood he had power with God: ^4yea, he had power over the angel, and prevailed; he wept, and made supplication unto him: he found him at Beth-el, and there he spake with us, ^5even Jehovah, the God of hosts; Jehovah is his memorial name. ^6Therefore turn thou to thy God: keep kindness and justice, and wait for thy God continually. ^7He is a trafficker, the balances of deceit are in his hand: he loveth to oppress. ^8And Ephraim said, Surely I am become rich, I have found me wealth: in all my labors they shall find in me no iniquity that were sin. ^9But I am Jehovah thy God from the land of Egypt; I will yet again make thee to dwell in tents, as in the days of the solemn feast. ^10I have also spoken unto the prophets, and I have multiplied visions; and by the ministry of the prophets have I used similitudes. ^11Is Gilead iniquity? they are altogether false; in Gilgal they sacrifice bullocks; yea, their altars are as heaps in the furrows of the field. ^12And Jacob fled into the field of Aram, and Israel served for a wife, and for a wife he kept sheep. ^13And by a prophet Jehovah brought Israel up out of Egypt, and by a prophet was he preserved. ^14Ephraim hath provoked to anger most bitterly: therefore shall his blood be left upon him, and his reproach shall his Lord return unto him.

Hosea 13

13

^1When Ephraim spake, there was trembling; he exalted himself in Israel; but when he offended in Baal, he died. ^2And now they sin more and more, and have made them molten images of their silver, even idols according to their own understanding, all of them the work of the craftsmen: they say of them, Let the men that sacrifice kiss the calves. ^3Therefore they shall be as the morning cloud, and as the dew that passeth early away, as the chaff that is driven with the whirlwind out of the threshing-floor, and as the smoke out of the chimney. ^4Yet I am Jehovah thy God from the land of Egypt; and thou shalt know no god but me, and besides me there is no saviour. ^5I did know thee in the wilderness, in the land of great drought. ^6According to their pasture, so were they filled; they were filled, and their heart was exalted: therefore have they forgotten me. ^7Therefore am I unto them as a lion; as a leopard will I watch by the way; ^8I will meet them as a bear that is bereaved of her whelps, and will rend the caul of their heart; and there will I devour them like a lioness; the wild beast shall tear them. ^9It is thy destruction, O Israel, that thou art against me, against thy help. ^10Where now is thy king, that he may save thee in all thy cities? and thy judges, of whom thou saidst, Give me a king and princes? ^11I have given thee a king in mine anger, and have taken him away in my wrath. ^12The iniquity of Ephraim is bound up; his sin is laid up in store. ^13The sorrows of a travailing woman shall come upon him: he is an unwise son; for it is time he should not tarry in the place of the breaking forth of children. ^14I will ransom them from the power of Sheol; I will redeem them from death: O death, where are thy plagues? O Sheol, where is thy destruction? repentance shall be hid from mine eyes. ^15Though he be fruitful among his brethren, an east wind shall come, the breath of Jehovah coming up from the wilderness; and his spring shall become dry, and his fountain shall be dried up: he shall make spoil of the treasure of all goodly vessels. ^16Samaria shall bear her guilt; for she hath rebelled against her God: they shall fall by the sword; their infants shall be dashed in pieces, and their women with child shall be ripped up.

Hosea 14

14

^1O Israel, return unto Jehovah thy God; for thou hast fallen by thine iniquity. ^2Take with you words, and return unto Jehovah: say unto him, Take away all iniquity, and accept that which is good: so will we render as bullocks the offering of our lips. ^3Assyria shall not save us; we will not ride upon horses; neither will we say any more to the work of our hands, Ye are our gods; for in thee the fatherless findeth mercy. ^4I will heal their backsliding, I will love them freely; for mine anger is turned away from him. ^5I will be as the dew unto Israel; he shall blossom as the lily, and cast forth his roots as Lebanon. ^6His branches shall spread, and his beauty shall be as the olive-tree, and his smell as Lebanon. ^7They that dwell under his shadow shall return; they shall revive as the grain, and blossom as the vine: the scent thereof shall be as the wine of Lebanon. ^8Ephraim shall say, What have I to do any more with idols? I have answered, and will regard him: I am like a green fir-tree; from me is thy fruit found. ^9Who is wise, that he may understand these things? prudent, that he may know them? for the ways of Jehovah are right, and the just shall walk in them; but transgressors shall fall therein.

1 Chronicles 2

2

^1These are the sons of Israel: Reuben, Simeon, Levi, and Judah, Issachar, and Zebulun, ^2Dan, Joseph, and Benjamin, Naphtali, Gad, and Asher.

^3The sons of Judah: Er, and Onan, and Shelah; which three were born unto him of Shua's daughter the Canaanitess. And Er, Judah's first-born, was wicked in the sight of Jehovah; and he slew him. ^4And Tamar his daughter-in-law bare him Perez and Zerah. All the sons of Judah were five.

^5The sons of Perez: Hezron, and Hamul. ^6And the sons of Zerah: Zimri, and Ethan, and Heman, and Calcol, and Dara; five of them in all. ^7And the sons of Carmi: Achar, the troubler of Israel, who committed a trespass in the devoted thing. ^8And the sons of Ethan: Azariah.

^9The sons also of Hezron, that were born unto him: Jerahmeel, and Ram, and Chelubai. ^10And Ram begat Amminadab, and Amminadab begat Nahshon, prince of the children of Judah; ^11and Nahshon begat Salma, and Salma begat Boaz, ^12and Boaz begat Obed, and Obed begat Jesse; ^13and Jesse begat his first-born Eliab, and Abinadab the second, and Shimea the third, ^14Nethanel the fourth, Raddai the fifth, ^15Ozem the sixth, David the seventh; ^16and their sisters were Zeruiah and Abigail. And the sons of Zeruiah: Abishai, and Joab, and Asahel, three. ^17And Abigail bare Amasa; and the father of Amasa was Jether the Ishmaelite.

^18And Caleb the son of Hezron begat children of Azubah his wife, and of Jerioth; and these were her sons: Jesher, and Shobab, and Ardon. ^19And Azubah died, and Caleb took unto him Ephrath, who bare him Hur. ^20And Hur begat Uri, and Uri begat Bezalel.

^21And afterward Hezron went in to the daughter of Machir the father of Gilead, whom he took to wife when he was threescore years old; and she bare him Segub. ^22And Segub begat Jair, who had three and twenty cities in the land of Gilead. ^23And Geshur and Aram took the towns of Jair from them, with Kenath, and the villages thereof, even threescore cities. All these were the sons of Machir the father of Gilead. ^24And after that Hezron was dead in Caleb-ephrathah, then Abijah Hezron's wife bare him Ashhur the father of Tekoa.

^25And the sons of Jerahmeel the first-born of Hezron were Ram the first-born, and Bunah, and Oren, and Ozem, Ahijah. ^26And Jerahmeel had another wife, whose name was Atarah; she was the mother of Onam. ^27And the sons of Ram the first-born of Jerahmeel were Maaz, and Jamin, and Eker. ^28And the sons of Onam were Shammai, and Jada. And the sons of Shammai: Nadab, and Abishur. ^29And the name of the wife of Abishur was Abihail; and she bare him Ahban, and Molid. ^30And the sons of Nadab: Seled, and Appaim; but Seled died without children. ^31And the sons of Appaim: Ishi. And the sons of Ishi: Sheshan. And the sons of Sheshan: Ahlai. ^32And the sons of Jada the brother of Shammai: Jether, and Jonathan; and Jether died without children. ^33And the sons of Jonathan: Peleth, and Zaza. These were the sons of Jerahmeel. ^34Now Sheshan had no sons, but daughters. And Sheshan had a servant, an Egyptian, whose name was Jarha. ^35And Sheshan gave his daughter to Jarha his servant to wife; and she bare him Attai. ^36And Attai begat Nathan, and Nathan begat Zabad, ^37and Zabad begat Ephlal, and Ephlal begat Obed, ^38and Obed begat Jehu, and Jehu begat Azariah, ^39and Azariah begat Helez, and Helez begat Eleasah, ^40and Eleasah begat Sismai, and Sismai begat Shallum, ^41and Shallum begat Jekamiah, and Jekamiah begat Elishama.

^42And the sons of Caleb the brother of Jerahmeel were Mesha his first-born, who was the father of Ziph; and the sons of Mareshah the father of Hebron. ^43And the sons of Hebron: Korah, and Tappuah, and Rekem, and Shema. ^44And Shema begat Raham, the father of Jorkeam; and Rekem begat Shammai. ^45And the son of Shammai was Maon; and Maon was the father of Beth-zur. ^46And Ephah, Caleb's concubine, bare Haran, and Moza, and Gazez; and Haran begat Gazez. ^47And the sons of Jahdai: Regem, and Jothan, and Geshan, and Pelet, and Ephah, and Shaaph. ^48Maacah, Caleb's concubine, bare Sheber and Tirhanah. ^49She bare also Shaaph the father of Madmannah, Sheva the father of Machbena, and the father of Gibea; and the daughter of Caleb was Achsah.

^50These were the sons of Caleb, the son of Hur, the first-born of Ephrathah: Shobal the father of Kiriath-jearim, ^51Salma the father of Beth-lehem, Hareph the father of Beth-gader. ^52And Shobal the father of Kiriath-jearim had sons: Haroeh, half of the Menuhoth. ^53And the families of Kiriath-jearim: The Ithrites, and the Puthites, and the Shumathites, and the Mishraites; of them came the Zorathites and the Eshtaolites. ^54The sons of Salma: Beth-lehem, and the Netophathites, Atroth-beth-joab, and half of the Manahathites, the Zorites. ^55And the families of scribes that dwelt at Jabez: the Tirathites, the Shimeathites, the Sucathites. These are the Kenites that came of Hammath, the father of the house of Rechab.

1 Chronicles 4

4

^1The sons of Judah: Perez, Hezron, and Carmi, and Hur, and Shobal. ^2And Reaiah the son of Shobal begat Jahath; and Jahath begat Ahumai and Lahad. These are the families of the Zorathites. ^3And these were the sons of the father of Etam: Jezreel, and Ishma, and Idbash; and the name of their sister was Hazzelelponi; ^4and Penuel the father of Gedor, and Ezer the father of Hushah. These are the sons of Hur, the first-born of Ephrathah, the father of Beth-lehem. ^5And Ashhur the father of Tekoa had two wives, Helah and Naarah. ^6And Naarah bare him Ahuzzam, and Hepher, and Temeni, and Haahashtari. These were the sons of Naarah. ^7And the sons of Helah were Zereth, Izhar, and Ethnan. ^8And Hakkoz begat Anub, and Zobebah, and the families of Aharhel the son of Harum. ^9And Jabez was more honorable than his brethren: and his mother called his name Jabez, saying, Because I bare him with sorrow. ^10And Jabez called on the God of Israel, saying, Oh that thou wouldest bless me indeed, and enlarge my border, and that thy hand might be with me, and that thou wouldest keep me from evil, that it be not to my sorrow! And God granted him that which he requested. ^11And Chelub the brother of Shuhah begat Mehir, who was the father of Eshton. ^12And Eshton begat Beth-rapha, and Paseah, and Tehinnah the father of Ir-nahash. These are the men of Recah. ^13And the sons of Kenaz: Othniel, and Seraiah. And the sons of Othniel: Hathath. ^14And Meonothai begat Ophrah: and Seraiah begat Joab the father of Ge-harashim; for they were craftsmen. ^15And the sons of Caleb the son of Jephunneh: Iru, Elah, and Naam; and the sons of Elah; and Kenaz. ^16And the sons of Jehallelel: Ziph, and Ziphah, Tiria, and Asarel. ^17And the sons of Ezrah: Jether, and Mered, and Epher, and Jalon; and she bare Miriam, and Shammai, and Ishbah the father of Eshtemoa. ^18And his wife the Jewess bare Jered the father of Gedor, and Heber the father of Soco, and Jekuthiel the father of Zanoah. And these are the sons of Bithiah the daughter of Pharaoh, whom Mered took. ^19And the sons of the wife of Hodiah, the sister of Naham, were the father of Keilah the Garmite, and Eshtemoa the Maacathite. ^20And the sons of Shimon: Amnon, and Rinnah, Ben-hanan, and Tilon. And the sons of Ishi: Zoheth, and Ben-zoheth. ^21The sons of Shelah the son of Judah: Er the father of Lecah, and Laadah the father of Mareshah, and the families of the house of them that wrought fine linen, of the house of Ashbea; ^22and Jokim, and the men of Cozeba, and Joash, and Saraph, who had dominion in Moab, and Jashubilehem. And the records are ancient. ^23These were the potters, and the inhabitants of Netaim and Gederah: there they dwelt with the king for his work.

^24The sons of Simeon: Nemuel, and Jamin, Jarib, Zerah, Shaul; ^25Shallum his son, Mibsam his son, Mishma his son. ^26And the sons of Mishma: Hammuel his son, Zaccur his son, Shimei his son. ^27And Shimei had sixteen sons and six daughters; but his brethren had not many children, neither did all their family multiply like to the children of Judah. ^28And they dwelt at Beer-sheba, and Moladah, and Hazarshual, ^29and at Bilhah, and at Ezem, and at Tolad, ^30and at Bethuel, and at Hormah, and at Ziklag, ^31and at Beth-marcaboth, and Hazar-susim, and at Beth-biri, and at Shaaraim. These were their cities unto the reign of David. ^32And their villages were Etam, and Ain, Rimmon, and Tochen, and Ashan, five cities; ^33and all their villages that were round about the same cities, unto Baal. These were their habitations, and they have their genealogy. ^34And Meshobab, and Jamlech, and Joshah the son of Amaziah, ^35and Joel, and Jehu the son of Joshibiah, the son of Seraiah, the son of Asiel, ^36and Elioenai, and Jaakobah, and Jeshohaiah, and Asaiah, and Adiel, and Jesimiel, and Benaiah, ^37and Ziza the son of Shiphi, the son of Allon, the son of Jedaiah, the son of Shimri, the son of Shemaiah- ^38these mentioned by name were princes in their families: and their fathers' houses increased greatly. ^39And they went to the entrance of Gedor, even unto the east side of the valley, to seek pasture for their flocks. ^40And they found fat pasture and good, and the land was wide, and quiet, and peaceable; for they that dwelt there aforetime were of Ham. ^41And these written by name came in the days of Hezekiah king of Judah, and smote their tents, and the Meunim that were found there, and destroyed them utterly unto this day, and dwelt in their stead; because there was pasture there for their flocks. ^42And some of them, even of the sons of Simeon, five hundred men, went to mount Seir, having for their captains Pelatiah, and Neariah, and Rephaiah, and Uzziel, the sons of Ishi. ^43And they smote the remnant of the Amalekites that escaped, and have dwelt there unto this day.

1 Chronicles 5

5

^1And the sons of Reuben the first-born of Israel (for he was the first-born; but, forasmuch as he defiled his father's couch, his birthright was given unto the sons of Joseph the son of Israel; and the genealogy is not to be reckoned after the birthright. ^2For Judah prevailed above his brethren, and of him came the prince; but the birthright was Joseph's:) ^3the sons of Reuben the first-born of Israel: Hanoch, and Pallu, Hezron, and Carmi. ^4The sons of Joel: Shemaiah his son, Gog his son, Shimei his son, ^5Micah his son, Reaiah his son, Baal his son, ^6Beerah his son, whom Tilgath-pilneser king of Assyria carried away captive: he was prince of the Reubenites. ^7And his brethren by their families, when the genealogy of their generations was reckoned: the chief, Jeiel, and Zechariah, ^8and Bela the son of Azaz, the son of Shema, the son of Joel, who dwelt in Aroer, even unto Nebo and Baal-meon: ^9and eastward he dwelt even unto the entrance of the wilderness from the river Euphrates, because their cattle were multiplied in the land of Gilead. ^10And in the days of Saul, they made war with the Hagrites, who fell by their hand; and they dwelt in their tents throughout all the land east of Gilead.

^11And the sons of Gad dwelt over against them, in the land of Bashan unto Salecah: ^12Joel the chief, and Shapham the second, and Janai, and Shaphat in Bashan. ^13And their brethren of their fathers' houses: Michael, and Meshullam, and Sheba, and Jorai, and Jacan, and Zia, and Eber, seven. ^14These were the sons of Abihail, the son of Huri, the son of Jaroah, the son of Gilead, the son of Michael, the son of Jeshishai, the son of Jahdo, the son of Buz; ^15Ahi the son of Abdiel, the son of Guni, chief of their fathers' houses. ^16And they dwelt in Gilead in Bashan, and in its towns, and in all the suburbs of Sharon, as far as their borders. ^17All these were reckoned by genealogies in the days of Jotham king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam king of Israel.

^18The sons of Reuben, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, of valiant men, men able to bear buckler and sword, and to shoot with bow, and skilful in war, were forty and four thousand seven hundred and threescore, that were able to go forth to war. ^19And they made war with the Hagrites, with Jetur, and Naphish, and Nodab. ^20And they were helped against them, and the Hagrites were delivered into their hand, and all that were with them; for they cried to God in the battle, and he was entreated of them, because they put their trust in him. ^21And they took away their cattle; of their camels fifty thousand, and of sheep two hundred and fifty thousand, and of asses two thousand, and of men a hundred thousand. ^22For there fell many slain, because the war was of God. And they dwelt in their stead until the captivity.

^23And the children of the half-tribe of Manasseh dwelt in the land: they increased from Bashan unto Baal-hermon and Senir and mount Hermon. ^24And these were the heads of their fathers' houses: even Epher, and Ishi, and Eliel, and Azriel, and Jeremiah, and Hodaviah, and Jahdiel, mighty men of valor, famous men, heads of their fathers' houses.

^25And they trespassed against the God of their fathers, and played the harlot after the gods of the peoples of the land, whom God destroyed before them. ^26And the God of Israel stirred up the spirit of Pul king of Assyria, and the spirit of Tilgath-pilneser king of Assyria, and he carried them away, even the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of Manasseh, and brought them unto Halah, and Habor, and Hara, and to the river of Gozan, unto this day.

1 Chronicles 6

6

^1The sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari. ^2And the sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel. ^3And the children of Amram: Aaron, and Moses, and Miriam. And the sons of Aaron: Nadab, and Abihu, Eleazar, and Ithamar. ^4Eleazar begat Phinehas, Phinehas begat Abishua, ^5and Abishua begat Bukki, and Bukki begat Uzzi, ^6and Uzzi begat Zerahiah, and Zerahiah begat Meraioth, ^7Meraioth begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub, ^8and Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Ahimaaz, ^9and Ahimaaz begat Azariah, and Azariah begat Johanan, ^10and Johanan begat Azariah, (he it is that executed the priest's office in the house that Solomon built in Jerusalem), ^11and Azariah begat Amariah, and Amariah begat Ahitub, ^12and Ahitub begat Zadok, and Zadok begat Shallum, ^13and Shallum begat Hilkiah, and Hilkiah begat Azariah, ^14and Azariah begat Seraiah, and Seraiah begat Jehozadak; ^15And Jehozadak went into captivity, when Jehovah carried away Judah and Jerusalem by the hand of Nebuchadnezzar.

^16The sons of Levi: Gershom, Kohath, and Merari. ^17And these are the names of the sons of Gershom: Libni and Shimei. ^18And the sons of Kohath were Amram, and Izhar, and Hebron, and Uzziel. ^19The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. And these are the families of the Levites according to their fathers' houses. ^20Of Gershom: Libni his son, Jahath his son, Zimmah his son, ^21Joah his son, Iddo his son, Zerah his son, Jeatherai his son. ^22The sons of Kohath: Amminadab his son, Korah his son, Assir his son, ^23Elkanah his son, and Ebiasaph his son, and Assir his son, ^24Tahath his son, Uriel his son, Uzziah his son, and Shaul his son. ^25And the sons of Elkanah: Amasai, and Ahimoth. ^26As for Elkanah, the sons of Elkanah: Zophai his son, and Nahath his son, ^27Eliab his son, Jeroham his son, Elkanah his son. ^28And the sons of Samuel: the first-born Joel, and the second Abijah. ^29The sons of Merari: Mahli, Libni his son, Shimei his son, Uzzah his son, ^30Shimea his son, Haggiah his son, Asaiah his son.

^31And these are they whom David set over the service of song in the house of Jehovah, after that the ark had rest. ^32And they ministered with song before the tabernacle of the tent of meeting, until Solomon had built the house of Jehovah in Jerusalem: and they waited on their office according to their order. ^33And these are they that waited, and their sons. Of the sons of the Kohathites: Heman the singer, the son of Joel, the son of Samuel, ^34the son of Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Eliel, the son of Toah, ^35the son of Zuph, the son of Elkanah, the son of Mahath, the son of Amasai, ^36the son of Elkanah, the son of Joel, the son of Azariah, the son of Zephaniah, ^37the son of Tahath, the son of Assir, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, ^38the son of Izhar, the son of Kohath, the son of Levi, the son of Israel. ^39And his brother Asaph, who stood on his right hand, even Asaph the son of Berechiah, the son of Shimea, ^40the son of Michael, the son of Baaseiah, the son of Malchijah, ^41the son of Ethni, the son of Zerah, the son of Adaiah, ^42the son of Ethan, the son of Zimmah, the son of Shimei, ^43the son of Jahath, the son of Gershom, the son of Levi. ^44And on the left hand their brethren the sons of Merari: Ethan the son of Kishi, the son of Abdi, the son of Malluch, ^45the son of Hashabiah, the son of Amaziah, the son of Hilkiah, ^46the son of Amzi, the son of Bani, the son of Shemer, ^47the son of Mahli, the son of Mushi, the son of Merari, the son of Levi. ^48And their brethren the Levites were appointed for all the service of the tabernacle of the house of God.

^49But Aaron and his sons offered upon the altar of burnt-offering, and upon the altar of incense, for all the work of the most holy place, and to make atonement for Israel, according to all that Moses the servant of God had commanded. ^50And these are the sons of Aaron: Eleazar his son, Phinehas his son, Abishua his son, ^51Bukki his son, Uzzi his son, Zerahiah his son, ^52Meraioth his son, Amariah his son, Ahitub his son, ^53Zadok his son, Ahimaaz his son.

^54Now these are their dwelling-places according to their encampments in their borders: to the sons of Aaron, of the families of the Kohathites (for theirs was the first lot), ^55to them they gave Hebron in the land of Judah, and the suburbs thereof round about it; ^56but the fields of the city, and the villages thereof, they gave to Caleb the son of Jephunneh. ^57And to the sons of Aaron they gave the cities of refuge, Hebron; Libnah also with its suburbs, and Jattir, and Eshtemoa with its suburbs, ^58and Hilen with its suburbs, Debir with its suburbs, ^59and Ashan with its suburbs, and Beth-shemesh with its suburbs; ^60and out of the tribe of Benjamin, Geba with its suburbs, and Allemeth with its suburbs, and Anathoth with its suburbs. All their cities throughout their families were thirteen cities.

^61And unto the rest of the sons of Kohath were given by lot, out of the family of the tribe, out of the half-tribe, the half of Manasseh, ten cities. ^62And to the sons of Gershom, according to their families, out of the tribe of Issachar, and out of the tribe of Asher, and out of the tribe of Naphtali, and out of the tribe of Manasseh in Bashan, thirteen cities. ^63Unto the sons of Merari were given by lot, according to their families, out of the tribe of Reuben, and out of the tribe of Gad, and out of the tribe of Zebulun, twelve cities. ^64And the children of Israel gave to the Levites the cities with their suburbs. ^65And they gave by lot out of the tribe of the children of Judah, and out of the tribe of the children of Simeon, and out of the tribe of the children of Benjamin, these cities which are mentioned by name.

^66And some of the families of the sons of Kohath had cities of their borders out of the tribe of Ephraim. ^67And they gave unto them the cities of refuge, Shechem in the hill-country of Ephraim with its suburbs; Gezer also with its suburbs, ^68and Jokmeam with its suburbs, and Beth-horon with its suburbs, ^69and Aijalon with its suburbs, and Gath-rimmon with its suburbs; ^70and out of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Aner with its suburbs, and Bileam with its suburbs, for the rest of the family of the sons of Kohath.

^71Unto the sons of Gershom were given, out of the family of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Golan in Bashan with its suburbs, and Ashtaroth with its suburbs; ^72and out of the tribe of Issachar, Kedesh with its suburbs, Daberath with its suburbs, ^73and Ramoth with its suburbs, and Anem with its suburbs; ^74and out of the tribe of Asher, Mashal with its suburbs, and Abdon with its suburbs, ^75and Hukok with its suburbs, and Rehob with its suburbs; ^76and out of the tribe of Naphtali, Kedesh in Galilee with its suburbs, and Hammon with its suburbs, and Kiriathaim with its suburbs.

^77Unto the rest of the Levites, the sons of Merari, were given, out of the tribe of Zebulun, Rimmono with its suburbs, Tabor with its suburbs; ^78and beyond the Jordan at Jericho, on the east side of the Jordan, were given them, out of the tribe of Reuben, Bezer in the wilderness with its suburbs, and Jahzah with its suburbs, ^79and Kedemoth with its suburbs, and Mephaath with its suburbs; ^80and out of the tribe of Gad, Ramoth in Gilead with its suburbs, and Mahanaim with its suburbs, ^81and Heshbon with its suburbs, and Jazer with its suburbs.

1 Chronicles 7

7

^1And of the sons of Issachar: Tola, and Puah, Jashub, and Shimron, four. ^2And the sons of Tola: Uzzi, and Rephaiah, and Jeriel, and Jahmai, and Ibsam, and Shemuel, heads of their fathers' houses, to wit, of Tola; mighty men of valor in their generations: their number in the days of David was two and twenty thousand and six hundred. ^3And the sons of Uzzi: Izrahiah. And the sons of Izrahiah: Michael, and Obadiah, and Joel, Isshiah, five; all of them chief men. ^4And with them, by their generations, after their fathers' houses, were bands of the host for war, six and thirty thousand; for they had many wives and sons. ^5And their brethren among all the families of Issachar, mighty men of valor, reckoned in all by genealogy, were fourscore and seven thousand.

^6The sons of Benjamin: Bela, and Becher, and Jediael, three. ^7And the sons of Bela: Ezbon, and Uzzi, and Uzziel, and Jerimoth, and Iri, five; heads of fathers' houses, mighty men of valor; and they were reckoned by genealogy twenty and two thousand and thirty and four. ^8And the sons of Becher: Zemirah, and Joash, and Eliezer, and Elioenai, and Omri, and Jeremoth, and Abijah, and Anathoth, and Alemeth. All these were the sons of Becher. ^9And they were reckoned by genealogy, after their generations, heads of their fathers' houses, mighty men of valor, twenty thousand and two hundred. ^10And the sons of Jediael: Bilhan. And the sons of Bilhan: Jeush, and Benjamin, and Ehud, and Chenaanah, and Zethan, and Tarshish, and Ahishahar. ^11All these were sons of Jediael, according to the heads of their fathers' houses, mighty men of valor, seventeen thousand and two hundred, that were able to go forth in the host for war. ^12Shuppim also, and Huppim, the sons of Ir, Hushim, the sons of Aher.

^13The sons of Naphtali: Jahziel, and Guni, and Jezer, and Shallum, the sons of Bilhah.

^14The sons of Manasseh: Asriel, whom his concubine the Aramitess bare: she bare Machir the father of Gilead: ^15and Machir took a wife of Huppim and Shuppim, whose sister's name was Maacah; and the name of the second was Zelophehad: and Zelophehad had daughters. ^16And Maacah the wife of Machir bare a son, and she called his name Peresh; and the name of his brother was Sheresh; and his sons were Ulam and Rakem. ^17And the sons of Ulam: Bedan. These were the sons of Gilead the son of Machir, the son of Manasseh. ^18And his sister Hammolecheth bare Ishhod, and Abiezer, and Mahlah. ^19And the sons of Shemida were Ahian, and Shechem, and Likhi, and Aniam.

^20And the sons of Ephraim: Shuthelah, and Bered his son, and Tahath his son, and Eleadah his son, and Tahath his son, ^21and Zabad his son, and Shuthelah his son, and Ezer, and Elead, whom the men of Gath that were born in the land slew, because they came down to take away their cattle. ^22And Ephraim their father mourned many days, and his brethren came to comfort him. ^23And he went in to his wife, and she conceived, and bare a son, and he called his name Beriah, because it went evil with his house. ^24And his daughter was Sheerah, who built Beth-horon the nether and the upper, and Uzzen-sheerah. ^25And Rephah was his son, and Resheph, and Telah his son, and Tahan his son, ^26Ladan his son, Ammihud his son, Elishama his son, ^27Nun his son, Joshua his son.

^28And their possessions and habitations were Beth-el and the towns thereof, and eastward Naaran, and westward Gezer, with the towns thereof; Shechem also and the towns thereof, unto Azzah and the towns thereof; ^29and by the borders of the children of Manasseh, Beth-shean and its towns, Taanach and its towns, Megiddo and its towns, Dor and its towns. In these dwelt the children of Joseph the son of Israel.

^30The sons of Asher: Imnah, and Ishvah, and Ishvi, and Beriah, and Serah their sister. ^31And the sons of Beriah: Heber, and Malchiel, who was the father of Birzaith. ^32And Heber begat Japhlet, and Shomer, and Hotham, and Shua their sister. ^33And the sons of Japhlet: Pasach, and Bimhal, and Ashvath. These are the children of Japhlet. ^34And the sons of Shemer: Ahi, and Rohgah, Jehubbah, and Aram. ^35And the sons of Helem his brother: Zophah, and Imna, and Shelesh, and Amal. ^36The sons of Zophah: Suah, and Harnepher, and Shual, and Beri, and Imrah, ^37Bezer, and Hod, and Shamma, and Shilshah, and Ithran, and Beera. ^38And the sons of Jether: Jephunneh, and Pispa, and Ara. ^39And the sons of Ulla: Arah, and Hanniel, and Rizia. ^40All these were the children of Asher, heads of the fathers' houses, choice and mighty men of valor, chief of the princes. And the number of them reckoned by genealogy for service in war was twenty and six thousand men.

1 Chronicles 9

9

^1So all Israel were reckoned by genealogies; and, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel: and Judah was carried away captive to Babylon for their transgression. ^2Now the first inhabitants that dwelt in their possessions in their cities were Israel, the priests, the Levites, and the Nethinim. ^3And in Jerusalem dwelt of the children of Judah, and of the children of Benjamin, and of the children of Ephraim and Manasseh: ^4Uthai the son of Ammihud, the son of Omri, the son of Imri, the son of Bani, of the children of Perez the son of Judah. ^5And of the Shilonites: Asaiah the first-born, and his sons. ^6And of the sons of Zerah: Jeuel, and their brethren, six hundred and ninety. ^7And of the sons of Benjamin: Sallu the son of Meshullam, the son of Hodaviah, the son of Hassenuah, ^8and Ibneiah the son of Jeroham, and Elah the son of Uzzi, the son of Michri, and Meshullam the son of Shephatiah, the son of Reuel, the son of Ibnijah; ^9and their brethren, according to their generations, nine hundred and fifty and six. All these men were heads of fathers' houses by their fathers' houses.

^10And of the priests: Jedaiah, and Jehoiarib, Jachin, ^11and Azariah the son of Hilkiah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Zadok, the son of Meraioth, the son of Ahitub, the ruler of the house of God; ^12and Adaiah the son of Jeroham, the son of Pashhur, the son of Malchijah, and Maasai the son of Adiel, the son of Jahzerah, the son of Meshullam, the son of Meshillemith, the son of Immer; ^13and their brethren, heads of their fathers' houses, a thousand and seven hundred and threescore; very able men for the work of the service of the house of God.

^14And of the Levites: Shemaiah the son of Hasshub, the son of Azrikam, the son of Hashabiah, of the sons of Merari; ^15and Bakbakkar, Heresh, and Galal, and Mattaniah the son of Mica, the son of Zichri, the son of Asaph, ^16and Obadiah the son of Shemaiah, the son of Galal, the son of Jeduthun, and Berechiah the son of Asa, the son of Elkanah, that dwelt in the villages of the Netophathites.

^17And the porters: Shallum, and Akkub, and Talmon, and Ahiman, and their brethren (Shallum was the chief), ^18who hitherto waited in the king's gate eastward: they were the porters for the camp of the children of Levi. ^19And Shallum the son of Kore, the son of Ebiasaph, the son of Korah, and his brethren, of his father's house, the Korahites, were over the work of the service, keepers of the thresholds of the tent: and their fathers had been over the camp of Jehovah, keepers of the entry. ^20And Phinehas the son of Eleazar was ruler over them in time past, and Jehovah was with him. ^21Zechariah the son of Meshelemiah was porter of the door of the tent of meeting. ^22All these that were chosen to be porters in the thresholds were two hundred and twelve. These were reckoned by genealogy in their villages, whom David and Samuel the seer did ordain in their office of trust. ^23So they and their children had the oversight of the gates of the house of Jehovah, even the house of the tent, by wards. ^24On the four sides were the porters, toward the east, west, north, and south. ^25And their brethren, in their villages, were to come in every seven days from time to time to be with them: ^26for the four chief porters, who were Levites, were in an office of trust, and were over the chambers and over the treasuries in the house of God. ^27And they lodged round about the house of God, because the charge thereof was upon them; and to them pertained the opening thereof morning by morning.

^28And certain of them had charge of the vessels of service; for by count were these brought in and by count were these taken out. ^29Some of them also were appointed over the furniture, and over all the vessels of the sanctuary, and over the fine flour, and the wine, and the oil, and the frankincense, and the spices. ^30And some of the sons of the priests prepared the confection of the spices. ^31And Mattithiah, one of the Levites, who was the first-born of Shallum the Korahite, had the office of trust over the things that were baked in pans. ^32And some of their brethren, of the sons of the Kohathites, were over the showbread, to prepare it every sabbath.

^33And these are the singers, heads of fathers' houses of the Levites, who dwelt in the chambers and were free from other service; for they were employed in their work day and night. ^34These were heads of fathers' houses of the Levites, throughout their generations, chief men: these dwelt at Jerusalem.

^35And in Gibeon there dwelt the father of Gibeon, Jeiel, whose wife's name was Maacah: ^36and his first-born son Abdon, and Zur, and Kish, and Baal, and Ner, and Nadab, ^37and Gedor, and Ahio, and Zechariah, and Mikloth. ^38And Mikloth begat Shimeam. And they also dwelt with their brethren in Jerusalem, over against their brethren. ^39And Ner begat Kish; and Kish begat Saul; and Saul begat Jonathan, and Malchishua, and Abinadab, and Eshbaal. ^40And the son of Jonathan was Merib-baal; and Merib-baal begat Micah. ^41And the sons of Micah: Pithon, and Melech, and Tahrea, and Ahaz. ^42And Ahaz begat Jarah; and Jarah begat Alemeth, and Azmaveth, and Zimri; and Zimri begat Moza; ^43and Moza begat Binea; and Rephaiah his son, Eleasah his son, Azel his son. ^44And Azel had six sons, whose names are these: Azrikam, Bocheru, and Ishmael, and Sheariah, and Obadiah, and Hanan: these were the sons of Azel.

1 Chronicles 10

10

^1Now the Philistines fought against Israel: and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down slain in mount Gilboa. ^2And the Philistines followed hard after Saul and after his sons; and the Philistines slew Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Malchi-shua, the sons of Saul. ^3And the battle went sore against Saul, and the archers overtook him; and he was distressed by reason of the archers. ^4Then said Saul unto his armor-bearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through therewith, lest these uncircumcised come and abuse me. But his armor-bearer would not; for he was sore afraid. Therefore Saul took his sword, and fell upon it. ^5And when his armor-bearer saw that Saul was dead, he likewise fell upon his sword, and died. ^6So Saul died, and his three sons; and all his house died together.

^7And when all the men of Israel that were in the valley saw that they fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they forsook their cities, and fled; and the Philistines came and dwelt in them. ^8And it came to pass on the morrow, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his sons fallen in mount Gilboa. ^9And they stripped him, and took his head, and his armor, and sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to carry the tidings unto their idols, and to the people. ^10And they put his armor in the house of their gods, and fastened his head in the house of Dagon. ^11And when all Jabesh-gilead heard all that the Philistines had done to Saul, ^12all the valiant men arose, and took away the body of Saul, and the bodies of his sons, and brought them to Jabesh, and buried their bones under the oak in Jabesh, and fasted seven days.

^13So Saul died for his trespass which he committed against Jehovah, because of the word of Jehovah, which he kept not; and also for that he asked counsel of one that had a familiar spirit, to inquire thereby, ^14and inquired not of Jehovah: therefore he slew him, and turned the kingdom unto David the son of Jesse.

1 Chronicles 11

11

^1Then all Israel gathered themselves to David unto Hebron, saying, Behold, we are thy bone and thy flesh. ^2In times past, even when Saul was king, it was thou that leddest out and broughtest in Israel: and Jehovah thy God said unto thee, Thou shalt be shepherd of my people Israel, and thou shalt be prince over my people Israel. ^3So all the elders of Israel came to the king to Hebron; and David made a covenant with them in Hebron before Jehovah; and they anointed David king over Israel, according to the word of Jehovah by Samuel.

^4And David and all Israel went to Jerusalem (the same is Jebus); and the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land, were there. ^5And the inhabitants of Jebus said to David, Thou shalt not come in hither. Nevertheless David took the stronghold of Zion; the same is the city of David. ^6And David said, Whosoever smiteth the Jebusites first shall be chief and captain. And Joab the son of Zeruiah went up first, and was made chief. ^7And David dwelt in the stronghold; therefore they called it the city of David. ^8And he built the city round about, from Millo even round about; and Joab repaired the rest of the city. ^9And David waxed greater and greater; for Jehovah of hosts was with him.

^10Now these are the chief of the mighty men whom David had, who showed themselves strong with him in his kingdom, together with all Israel, to make him king, according to the word of Jehovah concerning Israel. ^11And this is the number of the mighty men whom David had: Jashobeam, the son of a Hachmonite, the chief of the thirty; he lifted up his spear against three hundred and slew them at one time. ^12And after him was Eleazar the son of Dodo, the Ahohite, who was one of the three mighty men. ^13He was with David at Pasdammim, and there the Philistines were gathered together to battle, where was a plot of ground full of barley; and the people fled from before the Philistines. ^14And they stood in the midst of the plot, and defended it, and slew the Philistines; and Jehovah saved them by a great victory.

^15And three of the thirty chief men went down to the rock to David, into the cave of Adullam; and the host of the Philistines were encamped in the valley of Rephaim. ^16And David was then in the stronghold, and the garrison of the Philistines was then in Beth-lehem. ^17And David longed, and said, Oh that one would give me water to drink of the well of Beth-lehem, which is by the gate! ^18And the three brake through the host of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Beth-lehem, that was by the gate, and took it, and brought it to David: but David would not drink thereof, but poured it out unto Jehovah, ^19and said, My God forbid it me, that I should do this: shall I drink the blood of these men that have put their lives in jeopardy? for with the jeopardy of their lives they brought it. Therefore he would not drink it. These things did the three mighty men.

^20And Abishai, the brother of Joab, he was chief of the three; for he lifted up his spear against three hundred and slew them, and had a name among the three. ^21Of the three, he was more honorable than the two, and was made their captain: howbeit he attained not to the first three.

^22Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man of Kabzeel, who had done mighty deeds, he slew the two sons of Ariel of Moab: he went down also and slew a lion in the midst of a pit in time of snow. ^23And he slew an Egyptian, a man of great stature, five cubits high; and in the Egyptian's hand was a spear like a weaver's beam; and he went down to him with a staff, and plucked the spear out of the Egyptian's hand, and slew him with his own spear. ^24These things did Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and had a name among the three mighty men. ^25Behold, he was more honorable than the thirty, but he attained not to the first three: and David set him over his guard.

^26Also the mighty men of the armies: Asahel the brother of Joab, Elhanan the son of Dodo of Beth-lehem, ^27Shammoth the Harorite, Helez the Pelonite, ^28Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, Abiezer the Anathothite, ^29Sibbecai the Hushathite, Ilai the Ahohite, ^30Maharai the Netophathite, Heled the son of Baanah the Netophathite, ^31Ithai the son of Ribai of Gibeah of the children of Benjamin, Benaiah the Pirathonite, ^32Hurai of the brooks of Gaash, Abiel the Arbathite, ^33Azmaveth the Baharumite, Eliahba the Shaalbonite, ^34the sons of Hashem the Gizonite, Jonathan the son of Shagee the Hararite, ^35Ahiam the son of Sacar the Hararite, Eliphal the son of Ur, ^36Hepher the Mecherathite, Ahijah the Pelonite, ^37Hezro the Carmelite, Naarai the son of Ezbai, ^38Joel the brother of Nathan, Mibhar the son of Hagri, ^39Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Berothite, the armorbearer of Joab the son of Zeruiah, ^40Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite, ^41Uriah the Hittite, Zabad the son of Ahlai, ^42Adina the son of Shiza the Reubenite, a chief of the Reubenites, and thirty with him, ^43Hanan the son of Maacah, and Joshaphat the Mithnite, ^44Uzzia the Ashterathite, Shama and Jeiel the sons of Hotham the Aroerite, ^45Jediael the son of Shimri, and Joha his brother, the Tizite, ^46Eliel the Mahavite, and Jeribai, and Joshaviah, the sons of Elnaam, and Ithmah the Moabite, ^47Eliel, and Obed, and Jaasiel the Mezobaite.

1 Chronicles 12

12

^1Now these are they that came to David to Ziklag, while he yet kept himself close because of Saul the son of Kish; and they were among the mighty men, his helpers in war. ^2They were armed with bows, and could use both the right hand and the left in slinging stones and in shooting arrows from the bow: they were of Saul's brethren of Benjamin. ^3The chief was Ahiezer; then Joash, the sons of Shemaah the Gibeathite, and Jeziel, and Pelet, the sons of Azmaveth, and Beracah, and Jehu the Anathothite, ^4and Ishmaiah the Gibeonite, a mighty man among the thirty, and over the thirty, and Jeremiah, and Jahaziel, and Johanan, and Jozabad the Gederathite, ^5Eluzai, and Jerimoth, and Bealiah, and Shemariah, and Shephatiah the Haruphite, ^6Elkanah, and Isshiah, and Azarel, and Joezer, and Jashobeam, the Korahites, ^7and Joelah, and Zebadiah, the sons of Jeroham of Gedor.

^8And of the Gadites there separated themselves unto David to the stronghold in the wilderness, mighty men of valor, men trained for war, that could handle shield and spear; whose faces were like the faces of lions, and they were as swift as the roes upon the mountains; ^9Ezer the chief, Obadiah the second, Eliab the third, ^10Mishmannah the fourth, Jeremiah the fifth, ^11Attai the sixth, Eliel the seventh, ^12Johanan the eighth, Elzabad the ninth, ^13Jeremiah the tenth, Machbannai the eleventh. ^14These of the sons of Gad were captains of the host: he that was least was equal to a hundred, and the greatest to a thousand. ^15These are they that went over the Jordan in the first month, when it had overflowed all its banks; and they put to flight all them of the valleys, both toward the east, and toward the west.

^16And there came of the children of Benjamin and Judah to the stronghold unto David. ^17And David went out to meet them, and answered and said unto them, If ye be come peaceably unto me to help me, my heart shall be knit unto you; but if ye be come to betray me to mine adversaries, seeing there is no wrong in my hands, the God of our fathers look thereon, and rebuke it. ^18Then the Spirit came upon Amasai, who was chief of the thirty, and he said, Thine are we, David, and on thy side, thou son of Jesse: peace, peace be unto thee, and peace be to thy helpers; for thy God helpeth thee. Then David received them, and made them captains of the band.

^19Of Manasseh also there fell away some to David, when he came with the Philistines against Saul to battle: but they helped them not; for the lords of the Philistines upon advisement sent him away, saying, He will fall away to his master Saul to the jeopardy of our heads. ^20As he went to Ziklag, there fell to him of Manasseh, Adnah, and Jozabad, and Jediael, and Michael, and Jozabad, and Elihu, and Zillethai, captains of thousands that were of Manasseh. ^21And they helped David against the band of rovers: for they were all mighty men of valor, and were captains in the host. ^22For from day to day men came to David to help him, until there was a great host, like the host of God.

^23And these are the numbers of the heads of them that were armed for war, who came to David to Hebron, to turn the kingdom of Saul to him, according to the word of Jehovah. ^24The children of Judah that bare shield and spear were six thousand and eight hundred, armed for war. ^25Of the children of Simeon, mighty men of valor for the war, seven thousand and one hundred. ^26Of the children of Levi four thousand and six hundred. ^27And Jehoiada was the leader of the house of Aaron; and with him were three thousand and seven hundred, ^28and Zadok, a young man mighty of valor, and of his father's house twenty and two captains. ^29And of the children of Benjamin, the brethren of Saul, three thousand: for hitherto the greatest part of them had kept their allegiance to the house of Saul. ^30And of the children of Ephraim twenty thousand and eight hundred, mighty men of valor, famous men in their fathers' houses. ^31And of the half-tribe of Manasseh eighteen thousand, who were mentioned by name, to come and make David king. ^32And of the children of Issachar, men that had understanding of the times, to know what Israel ought to do, the heads of them were two hundred; and all their brethren were at their commandment. ^33Of Zebulun, such as were able to go out in the host, that could set the battle in array, with all manner of instruments of war, fifty thousand, and that could order the battle array, and were not of double heart. ^34And of Naphtali a thousand captains, and with them with shield and spear thirty and seven thousand. ^35And of the Danites that could set the battle in array, twenty and eight thousand and six hundred. ^36And of Asher, such as were able to go out in the host, that could set the battle in array, forty thousand. ^37And on the other side of the Jordan, of the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and of the half-tribe of Manasseh, with all manner of instruments of war for the battle, a hundred and twenty thousand.

^38All these being men of war, that could order the battle array, came with a perfect heart to Hebron, to make David king over all Israel: and all the rest also of Israel were of one heart to make David king. ^39And they were there with David three days, eating and drinking; for their brethren had made preparation for them. ^40Moreover they that were nigh unto them, even as far as Issachar and Zebulun and Naphtali, brought bread on asses, and on camels, and on mules, and on oxen, victuals of meal, cakes of figs, and clusters of raisins, and wine, and oil, and oxen, and sheep in abundance: for there was joy in Israel.

1 Chronicles 13

13

^1And David consulted with the captains of thousands and of hundreds, even with every leader. ^2And David said unto all the assembly of Israel, If it seem good unto you, and if it be of Jehovah our God, let us send abroad every where unto our brethren that are left in all the land of Israel, with whom the priests and Levites are in their cities that have suburbs, that they may gather themselves unto us; ^3and let us bring again the ark of our God to us: for we sought not unto it in the days of Saul. ^4And all the assembly said that they would do so; for the thing was right in the eyes of all the people. ^5So David assembled all Israel together, from the Shihor the brook of Egypt even unto the entrance of Hamath, to bring the ark of God from Kiriath-jearim. ^6And David went up, and all Israel, to Baalah, that is, to Kiriath-jearim, which belonged to Judah, to bring up from thence the ark of God Jehovah that sitteth above the cherubim, that is called by the Name. ^7And they carried the ark of God upon a new cart, and brought it out of the house of Abinadab: and Uzza and Ahio drove the cart. ^8And David and all Israel played before God with all their might, even with songs, and with harps, and with psalteries, and with timbrels, and with cymbals, and with trumpets.

^9And when they came unto the threshing-floor of Chidon, Uzza put forth his hand to hold the ark; for the oxen stumbled. ^10And the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Uzza, and he smote him, because he put forth his hand to the ark; and there he died before God. ^11And David was displeased, because Jehovah had broken forth upon Uzza; and he called that place Perez-uzza, unto this day. ^12And David was afraid of God that day, saying, How shall I bring the ark of God home to me? ^13So David removed not the ark unto him into the city of David, but carried it aside into the house of Obed-edom the Gittite. ^14And the ark of God remained with the family of Obed-edom in his house three months: and Jehovah blessed the house of Obed-edom, and all that he had.

1 Chronicles 14

14

^1And Hiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David, and cedar-trees, and masons, and carpenters, to build him a house. ^2And David perceived that Jehovah had established him king over Israel; for his kingdom was exalted on high, for his people Israel's sake.

^3And David took more wives at Jerusalem; and David begat more sons and daughters. ^4And these are the names of the children whom he had in Jerusalem: Shammua, and Shobab, Nathan, and Solomon, ^5and Ibhar, and Elishua, and Elpelet, ^6and Nogah, and Nepheg, and Japhia, ^7and Elishama, and Beeliada, and Eliphelet.

^8And when the Philistines heard that David was anointed king over all Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David: and David heard of it, and went out against them. ^9Now the Philistines had come and made a raid in the valley of Rephaim. ^10And David inquired of God, saying, Shall I go up against the Philistines? and wilt thou deliver them into my hand? And Jehovah said unto him, Go up; for I will deliver them into thy hand. ^11So they came up to Baal-perazim, and David smote them there; and David said, God hath broken mine enemies by my hand, like the breach of waters. Therefore they called the name of that place Baal-perazim. ^12And they left their gods there; and David gave commandment, and they were burned with fire.

^13And the Philistines yet again made a raid in the valley. ^14And David inquired again of God; and God said unto him, Thou shalt not go up after them: turn away from them, and come upon them over against the mulberry-trees. ^15And it shall be, when thou hearest the sound of marching in the tops of the mulberry-trees, that then thou shalt go out to battle; for God is gone out before thee to smite the host of the Philistines. ^16And David did as God commanded him: and they smote the host of the Philistines from Gibeon even to Gezer. ^17And the fame of David went out into all lands; and Jehovah brought the fear of him upon all nations.

1 Chronicles 15

15

^1And David made him houses in the city of David; and he prepared a place for the ark of God, and pitched for it a tent. ^2Then David said, None ought to carry the ark of God but the Levites: for them hath Jehovah chosen to carry the ark of God, and to minister unto him for ever. ^3And David assembled all Israel at Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of Jehovah unto its place, which he had prepared for it. ^4And David gathered together the sons of Aaron, and the Levites: ^5of the sons of Kohath, Uriel the chief, and his brethren a hundred and twenty; ^6of the sons of Merari, Asaiah the chief, and his brethren two hundred and twenty; ^7of the sons of Gershom, Joel the chief, and his brethren a hundred and thirty; ^8of the sons of Elizaphan, Shemaiah the chief, and his brethren two hundred; ^9of the sons of Hebron, Eliel the chief, and his brethren fourscore; ^10of the sons of Uzziel, Amminadab the chief, and his brethren a hundred and twelve. ^11And David called for Zadok and Abiathar the priests, and for the Levites, for Uriel, Asaiah, and Joel, Shemaiah, and Eliel, and Amminadab, ^12and said unto them, Ye are the heads of the fathers' houses of the Levites: sanctify yourselves, both ye and your brethren, that ye may bring up the ark of Jehovah, the God of Israel, unto the place that I have prepared for it. ^13For because ye bare it not at the first, Jehovah our God made a breach upon us, for that we sought him not according to the ordinance. ^14So the priests and the Levites sanctified themselves to bring up the ark of Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^15And the children of the Levites bare the ark of God upon their shoulders with the staves thereon, as Moses commanded according to the word of Jehovah.

^16And David spake to the chief of the Levites to appoint their brethren the singers, with instruments of music, psalteries and harps and cymbals, sounding aloud and lifting up the voice with joy. ^17So the Levites appointed Heman the son of Joel; and of his brethren, Asaph the son of Berechiah; and of the sons of Merari their brethren, Ethan the son of Kushaiah; ^18and with them their brethren of the second degree, Zechariah, Ben, and Jaaziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, Eliab, and Benaiah, and Maaseiah, and Mattithiah, and Eliphelehu, and Mikneiah, and Obed-edom, and Jeiel, the doorkeepers. ^19So the singers, Heman, Asaph, and Ethan, were appointed with cymbals of brass to sound aloud; ^20and Zechariah, and Aziel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehiel, and Unni, and Eliab, and Maaseiah, and Benaiah, with psalteries set to Alamoth; ^21and Mattithiah, and Eliphelehu, and Mikneiah, and Obed-edom, and Jeiel, and Azaziah, with harps set to the Sheminith, to lead. ^22And Chenaniah, chief of the Levites, was over the song: he instructed about the song, because he was skilful. ^23And Berechiah and Elkanah were doorkeepers for the ark. ^24And Shebaniah, and Joshaphat, and Nethanel, and Amasai, and Zechariah, and Benaiah, and Eliezer, the priests, did blow the trumpets before the ark of God: and Obed-edom and Jehiah were doorkeepers for the ark.

^25So David, and the elders of Israel, and the captains over thousands, went to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah out of the house of Obed-edom with joy. ^26And it came to pass, when God helped the Levites that bare the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, that they sacrificed seven bullocks and seven rams. ^27And David was clothed with a robe of fine linen, and all the Levites that bare the ark, and the singers, and Chenaniah the master of the song with the singers: and David had upon him an ephod of linen. ^28Thus all Israel brought up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah with shouting, and with sound of the cornet, and with trumpets, and with cymbals, sounding aloud with psalteries and harps.

^29And it came to pass, as the ark of the covenant of Jehovah came to the city of David, that Michal the daughter of Saul looked out at the window, and saw king David dancing and playing; and she despised him in her heart.

1 Chronicles 17

17

^1And it came to pass, when David dwelt in his house, that David said to Nathan the prophet, Lo, I dwell in a house of cedar, but the ark of the covenant of Jehovah dwelleth under curtains. ^2And Nathan said unto David, Do all that is in thy heart; for God is with thee. ^3And it came to pass the same night, that the word of God came to Nathan, saying, ^4Go and tell David my servant, Thus saith Jehovah, Thou shalt not build me a house to dwell in: ^5for I have not dwelt in a house since the day that I brought up Israel, unto this day, but have gone from tent to tent, and from one tabernacle to another. ^6In all places wherein I have walked with all Israel, spake I a word with any of the judges of Israel, whom I commanded to be shepherd of my people, saying, Why have ye not built me a house of cedar? ^7Now therefore thus shalt thou say unto my servant David, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, I took thee from the sheepcote, from following the sheep, that thou shouldest be prince over my people Israel: ^8and I have been with thee whithersoever thou hast gone, and have cut off all thine enemies from before thee; and I will make thee a name, like unto the name of the great ones that are in the earth. ^9And I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, that they may dwell in their own place, and be moved no more; neither shall the children of wickedness waste them any more, as at the first, ^10and as from the day that I commanded judges to be over my people Israel; and I will subdue all thine enemies. Moreover I tell thee that Jehovah will build thee a house. ^11And it shall come to pass, when thy days are fulfilled that thou must go to be with thy fathers, that I will set up thy seed after thee, who shall be of thy sons; and I will establish his kingdom. ^12He shall build me a house, and I will establish his throne for ever. ^13I will be his father, and he shall be my son: and I will not take my lovingkindness away from him, as I took it from him that was before thee; ^14but I will settle him in my house and in my kingdom for ever; and his throne shall be established for ever. ^15According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speak unto David.

^16Then David the king went in, and sat before Jehovah; and he said, Who am I, O Jehovah God, and what is my house, that thou hast brought me thus far? ^17And this was a small thing in thine eyes, O God; but thou hast spoken of thy servant's house for a great while to come, and hast regarded me according to the estate of a man of high degree, O Jehovah God. ^18What can David say yet more unto thee concerning the honor which is done to thy servant? for thou knowest thy servant. ^19O Jehovah, for thy servant's sake, and according to thine own heart, hast thou wrought all this greatness, to make known all these great things. ^20O Jehovah, there is none like thee, neither is there any God besides thee, according to all that we have heard with our ears. ^21And what one nation in the earth is like thy people Israel, whom God went to redeem unto himself for a people, to make thee a name by great and terrible things, in driving out nations from before thy people, whom thou redeemest out of Egypt? ^22For thy people Israel didst thou make thine own people for ever; and thou, Jehovah, becamest their God. ^23And now, O Jehovah, let the word that thou hast spoken concerning thy servant, and concerning his house, be established for ever, and do as thou hast spoken. ^24And let thy name be established and magnified for ever, saying, Jehovah of hosts is the God of Israel, even a God to Israel: and the house of David thy servant is established before thee. ^25For thou, O my God, hast revealed to thy servant that thou wilt build him a house: therefore hath thy servant found in his heart to pray before thee. ^26And now, O Jehovah, thou art God, and hast promised this good thing unto thy servant: ^27and now it hath pleased thee to bless the house of thy servant, that it may continue for ever before thee: for thou, O Jehovah, hast blessed, and it is blessed for ever.

1 Chronicles 18

18

^1And after this it came to pass, that David smote the Philistines, and subdued them, and took Gath and its towns out of the hand of the Philistines. ^2And he smote Moab; and the Moabites became servants to David, and brought tribute.

^3And David smote Hadarezer king of Zobah unto Hamath, as he went to establish his dominion by the river Euphrates. ^4And David took from him a thousand chariots, and seven thousand horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen; and David hocked all the chariot horses, but reserved of them for a hundred chariots.

^5And when the Syrians of Damascus came to succor Hadarezer king of Zobah, David smote of the Syrians two and twenty thousand men. ^6Then David put garrisons in Syria of Damascus; and the Syrians became servants to David, and brought tribute. And Jehovah gave victory to David whithersoever he went. ^7And David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadarezer, and brought them to Jerusalem. ^8And from Tibhath and from Cun, cities of Hadarezer, David took very much brass, wherewith Solomon made the brazen sea, and the pillars, and the vessels of brass.

^9And when Tou king of Hamath heard that David had smitten all the host of Hadarezer king of Zobah, ^10he sent Hadoram his son to king David, to salute him, and to bless him, because he had fought against Hadarezer and smitten him; (for Hadarezer had wars with Tou;) and he had with him all manner of vessels of gold and silver and brass. ^11These also did king David dedicate unto Jehovah, with the silver and the gold that he carried away from all the nations; from Edom, and from Moab, and from the children of Ammon, and from the Philistines, and from Amalek.

^12Moreover Abishai the son of Zeruiah smote of the Edomites in the Valley of Salt eighteen thousand. ^13And he put garrisons in Edom; and all the Edomites became servants to David. And Jehovah gave victory to David whithersoever he went.

^14And David reigned over all Israel; and he executed justice and righteousness unto all his people. ^15And Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the host; and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was recorder; ^16and Zadok the son of Ahitub, and Abimelech the son of Abiathar, were priests; and Shavsha was scribe; ^17and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and the sons of David were chief about the king.

1 Chronicles 19

19

^1And it came to pass after this, that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon died, and his son reigned in his stead. ^2And David said, I will show kindness unto Hanun the son of Nahash, because his father showed kindness to me. So David sent messengers to comfort him concerning his father. And David's servants came into the land of the children of Ammon to Hanun, to comfort him. ^3But the princes of the children of Ammon said to Hanun, Thinkest thou that David doth honor thy father, in that he hath sent comforters unto thee? are not his servants come unto thee to search, and to overthrow, and to spy out the land? ^4So Hanun took David's servants, and shaved them, and cut off their garments in the middle, even to their buttocks, and sent them away. ^5Then there went certain persons, and told David how the men were served. And he sent to meet them; for the men were greatly ashamed. And the king said, Tarry at Jericho until your beards be grown, and then return.

^6And when the children of Ammon saw that they had made themselves odious to David, Hanun and the children of Ammon sent a thousand talents of silver to hire them chariots and horsemen out of Mesopotamia, and out of Arammaacah, and out of Zobah. ^7So they hired them thirty and two thousand chariots, and the king of Maacah and his people, who came and encamped before Medeba. And the children of Ammon gathered themselves together from their cities, and came to battle. ^8And when David heard of it, he sent Joab, and all the host of the mighty men. ^9And the children of Ammon came out, and put the battle in array at the gate of the city: and the kings that were come were by themselves in the field.

^10Now when Joab saw that the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose of all the choice men of Israel, and put them in array against the Syrians. ^11And the rest of the people he committed into the hand of Abishai his brother; and they put themselves in array against the children of Ammon. ^12And he said, If the Syrians be too strong for me, then thou shalt help me; but if the children of Ammon be too strong for thee, then I will help thee. ^13Be of good courage, and let us play the man for our people, and for the cities of our God: and Jehovah do that which seemeth him good. ^14So Joab and the people that were with him drew nigh before the Syrians unto the battle; and they fled before him. ^15And when the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians were fled, they likewise fled before Abishai his brother, and entered into the city. Then Joab came to Jerusalem.

^16And when the Syrians saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they sent messengers, and drew forth the Syrians that were beyond the River, with Shophach the captain of the host of Hadarezer at their head. ^17And it was told David; and he gathered all Israel together, and passed over the Jordan, and came upon them, and set the battle in array against them. So when David had put the battle in array against the Syrians, they fought with him. ^18And the Syrians fled before Israel; and David slew of the Syrians the men of seven thousand chariots, and forty thousand footmen, and killed Shophach the captain of the host. ^19And when the servants of Hadarezer saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they made peace with David, and served him: neither would the Syrians help the children of Ammon any more.

1 Chronicles 20

20

^1And it came to pass, at the time of the return of the year, at the time when kings go out to battle, that Joab led forth the army, and wasted the country of the children of Ammon, and came and besieged Rabbah. But David tarried at Jerusalem. And Joab smote Rabbah, and overthrew it. ^2And David took the crown of their king from off his head, and found it to weigh a talent of gold, and there were precious stones in it; and it was set upon David's head: and he brought forth the spoil of the city, exceeding much. ^3And he brought forth the people that were therein, and cut them with saws, and with harrows of iron, and with axes. And thus did David unto all the cities of the children of Ammon. And David and all the people returned to Jerusalem.

^4And it came to pass after this, that there arose war at Gezer with the Philistines: then Sibbecai the Hushathite slew Sippai, of the sons of the giant; and they were subdued. ^5And there was again war with the Philistines; and Elhanan the son of Jair slew Lahmi the brother of Goliath the Gittite, the staff of whose spear was like a weaver's beam. ^6And there was again war at Gath, where was a man of great stature, whose fingers and toes were four and twenty, six on each hand, and six on each foot; and he also was born unto the giant. ^7And when he defied Israel, Jonathan the son of Shimea David's brother slew him. ^8These were born unto the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.

1 Chronicles 21

21

^1And Satan stood up against Israel, and moved David to number Israel. ^2And David said to Joab and to the princes of the people, Go, number Israel from Beer-sheba even to Dan; and bring me word, that I may know the sum of them. ^3And Joab said, Jehovah make his people a hundred times as many as they are: but, my lord the king, are they not all my lord's servants? why doth my lord require this thing? why will he be a cause of guilt unto Israel? ^4Nevertheless the king's word prevailed against Joab. Wherefore Joab departed, and went throughout all Israel, and came to Jerusalem. ^5And Joab gave up the sum of the numbering of the people unto David. And all they of Israel were a thousand thousand and a hundred thousand men that drew sword: and Judah was four hundred threescore and ten thousand men that drew sword. ^6But Levi and Benjamin counted he not among them; for the king's word was abominable to Joab. ^7And God was displeased with this thing; therefore he smote Israel. ^8And David said unto God, I have sinned greatly, in that I have done this thing: but now, put away, I beseech thee, the iniquity of thy servant; for I have done very foolishly.

^9And Jehovah spake unto Gad, David's seer, saying, ^10Go and speak unto David, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, I offer thee three things: choose thee one of them, that I may do it unto thee. ^11So Gad came to David, and said unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, Take which thou wilt: ^12either three years of famine; or three months to be consumed before thy foes, while the sword of thine enemies overtaketh thee; or else three days the sword of Jehovah, even pestilence in the land, and the angel of Jehovah destroying throughout all the borders of Israel. Now therefore consider what answer I shall return to him that sent me. ^13And David said unto Gad, I am in a great strait: let me fall, I pray, into the hand of Jehovah; for very great are his mercies: and let me not fall into the hand of man. ^14So Jehovah sent a pestilence upon Israel; and there fell of Israel seventy thousand men. ^15And God sent an angel unto Jerusalem to destroy it: and as he was about to destroy, Jehovah beheld, and he repented him of the evil, and said to the destroying angel, It is enough; now stay thy hand. And the angel of Jehovah was standing by the threshing-floor of Ornan the Jebusite. ^16And David lifted up his eyes, and saw the angel of Jehovah standing between earth and heaven, having a drawn sword in his hand stretched out over Jerusalem. Then David and the elders, clothed in sackcloth, fell upon their faces. ^17And David said unto God, Is it not I that commanded the people to be numbered? even I it is that have sinned and done very wickedly; but these sheep, what have they done? let thy hand, I pray thee, O Jehovah my God, be against me, and against my father's house; but not against thy people, that they should be plagued.

^18Then the angel of Jehovah commanded Gad to say to David, that David should go up, and rear an altar unto Jehovah in the threshing-floor of Ornan the Jebusite. ^19And David went up at the saying of Gad, which he spake in the name of Jehovah. ^20And Ornan turned back, and saw the angel; and his four sons that were with him hid themselves. Now Ornan was threshing wheat. ^21And as David came to Ornan, Ornan looked and saw David, and went out of the threshing-floor, and bowed himself to David with his face to the ground. ^22Then David said to Ornan, Give me the place of this threshing-floor, that I may build thereon an altar unto Jehovah: for the full price shalt thou give it me, that the plague may be stayed from the people. ^23And Ornan said unto David, Take it to thee, and let my lord the king do that which is good in his eyes: lo, I give thee the oxen for burnt-offerings, and the threshing instruments for wood, and the wheat for the meal-offering; I give it all. ^24And king David said to Ornan, Nay; but I will verily buy it for the full price: for I will not take that which is thine for Jehovah, nor offer a burnt-offering without cost. ^25So David gave to Ornan for the place six hundred shekels of gold by weight. ^26And David built there an altar unto Jehovah, and offered burnt-offerings and peace-offerings, and called upon Jehovah; and he answered him from heaven by fire upon the altar of burnt-offering. ^27And Jehovah commanded the angel; and he put up his sword again into the sheath thereof.

^28At that time, when David saw that Jehovah had answered him in the threshing-floor of Ornan the Jebusite, then he sacrificed there. ^29For the tabernacle of Jehovah, which Moses made in the wilderness, and the altar of burnt-offering, were at that time in the high place at Gibeon. ^30But David could not go before it to inquire of God; for he was afraid because of the sword of the angel of Jehovah.

1 Chronicles 22

22

^1Then David said, This is the house of Jehovah God, and this is the altar of burnt-offering for Israel. ^2And David commanded to gather together the sojourners that were in the land of Israel; and he set masons to hew wrought stones to build the house of God. ^3And David prepared iron in abundance for the nails for the doors of the gates, and for the couplings; and brass in abundance without weight; ^4and cedar-trees without number: for the Sidonians and they of Tyre brought cedar-trees in abundance to David. ^5And David said, Solomon my son is young and tender, and the house that is to be builded for Jehovah must be exceeding magnificent, of fame and of glory throughout all countries: I will therefore make preparation for it. So David prepared abundantly before his death.

^6Then he called for Solomon his son, and charged him to build a house for Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^7And David said to Solomon his son, As for me, it was in my heart to build a house unto the name of Jehovah my God. ^8But the word of Jehovah came to me, saying, Thou hast shed blood abundantly, and hast made great wars: thou shalt not build a house unto my name, because thou hast shed much blood upon the earth in my sight. ^9Behold, a son shall be born to thee, who shall be a man of rest; and I will give him rest from all his enemies round about; for his name shall be Solomon, and I will give peace and quietness unto Israel in his days: ^10he shall build a house for my name; and he shall be my son, and I will be his father; and I will establish the throne of his kingdom over Israel for ever. ^11Now, my son, Jehovah be with thee; and prosper thou, and build the house of Jehovah thy God, as he hath spoken concerning thee. ^12Only Jehovah give thee discretion and understanding, and give thee charge concerning Israel; that so thou mayest keep the law of Jehovah thy God. ^13Then shalt thou prosper, if thou observe to do the statutes and the ordinances which Jehovah charged Moses with concerning Israel: be strong, and of good courage; fear not, neither be dismayed. ^14Now, behold, in my affliction I have prepared for the house of Jehovah a hundred thousand talents of gold, and a thousand thousand talents of silver, and of brass and iron without weight; for it is in abundance: timber also and stone have I prepared; and thou mayest add thereto. ^15Moreover there are workmen with thee in abundance, hewers and workers of stone and timber, and all men that are skilful in every manner of work: ^16of the gold, the silver, and the brass, and the iron, there is no number. Arise and be doing, and Jehovah be with thee.

^17David also commanded all the princes of Israel to help Solomon his son, saying, ^18Is not Jehovah your God with you? and hath he not given you rest on every side? for he hath delivered the inhabitants of the land into my hand; and the land is subdued before Jehovah, and before his people. ^19Now set your heart and your soul to seek after Jehovah your God; arise therefore, and build ye the sanctuary of Jehovah God, to bring the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, and the holy vessels of God, into the house that is to be built to the name of Jehovah.

1 Chronicles 23

23

^1Now David was old and full of days; and he made Solomon his son king over Israel. ^2And he gathered together all the princes of Israel, with the priests and the Levites. ^3And the Levites were numbered from thirty years old and upward: and their number by their polls, man by man, was thirty and eight thousand. ^4Of these, twenty and four thousand were to oversee the work of the house of Jehovah; and six thousand were officers and judges; ^5and four thousand were doorkeepers; and four thousand praised Jehovah with the instruments which I made, said David, to praise therewith. ^6And David divided them into courses according to the sons of Levi: Gershon, Kohath, and Merari.

^7Of the Gershonites: Ladan and Shimei. ^8The sons of Ladan: Jehiel the chief, and Zetham, and Joel, three. ^9The sons of Shimei: Shelomoth, and Haziel, and Haran, three. These were the heads of the fathers' houses of Ladan. ^10And the sons of Shimei: Jahath, Zina, and Jeush, and Beriah. These four were the sons of Shimei. ^11And Jahath was the chief, and Zizah the second: but Jeush and Beriah had not many sons; therefore they became a fathers' house in one reckoning.

^12The sons of Kohath: Amram, Izhar, Hebron, and Uzziel, four. ^13The sons of Amram: Aaron and Moses; and Aaron was separated, that he should sanctify the most holy things, he and his sons, for ever, to burn incense before Jehovah, to minister unto him, and to bless in his name, for ever. ^14But as for Moses the man of God, his sons were named among the tribe of Levi. ^15The sons of Moses: Gershom and Eliezer. ^16The sons of Gershom: Shebuel the chief. ^17And the sons of Eliezer were: Rehabiah the chief; and Eliezer had no other sons; but the sons of Rehabiah were very many. ^18The sons of Izhar: Shelomith the chief. ^19The sons of Hebron: Jeriah the chief, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, and Jekameam the fourth. ^20The sons of Uzziel: Micah the chief, and Isshiah the second.

^21The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi. The sons of Mahli: Eleazar and Kish. ^22And Eleazar died, and had no sons, but daughters only: and their brethren the sons of Kish took them to wife. ^23The sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jeremoth, three.

^24These were the sons of Levi after their fathers' houses, even the heads of the fathers' houses of those of them that were counted, in the number of names by their polls, who did the work for the service of the house of Jehovah, from twenty years old and upward. ^25For David said, Jehovah, the God of Israel, hath given rest unto his people; and he dwelleth in Jerusalem for ever: ^26and also the Levites shall no more have need to carry the tabernacle and all the vessels of it for the service thereof. ^27For by the last words of David the sons of Levi were numbered, from twenty years old and upward. ^28For their office was to wait on the sons of Aaron for the service of the house of Jehovah, in the courts, and in the chambers, and in the purifying of all holy things, even the work of the service of the house of God; ^29for the showbread also, and for the fine flour for a meal-offering, whether of unleavened wafers, or of that which is baked in the pan, or of that which is soaked, and for all manner of measure and size; ^30and to stand every morning to thank and praise Jehovah, and likewise at even; ^31and to offer all burnt-offerings unto Jehovah, on the sabbaths, on the new moons, and on the set feasts, in number according to the ordinance concerning them, continually before Jehovah; ^32and that they should keep the charge of the tent of meeting, and the charge of the holy place, and the charge of the sons of Aaron their brethren, for the service of the house of Jehovah.

1 Chronicles 24

24

^1And the courses of the sons of Aaron were these. The sons of Aaron: Nadab and Abihu, Eleazar and Ithamar. ^2But Nadab and Abihu died before their father, and had no children: therefore Eleazar and Ithamar executed the priest's office. ^3And David with Zadok of the sons of Eleazar, and Ahimelech of the sons of Ithamar, divided them according to their ordering in their service. ^4And there were more chief men found of the sons of Eleazar than of the sons of Ithamar; and thus were they divided: of the sons of Eleazar there were sixteen, heads of fathers' houses; and of the sons of Ithamar, according to their fathers' houses, eight. ^5Thus were they divided by lot, one sort with another; for there were princes of the sanctuary, and princes of God, both of the sons of Eleazar, and of the sons of Ithamar. ^6And Shemaiah the son of Nethanel the scribe, who was of the Levites, wrote them in the presence of the king, and the princes, and Zadok the priest, and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, and the heads of the fathers' houses of the priests and of the Levites; one fathers' house being taken for Eleazar, and one taken for Ithamar.

^7Now the first lot came forth to Jehoiarib, the second to Jedaiah, ^8the third to Harim, the fourth to Seorim, ^9the fifth to Malchijah, the sixth to Mijamin, ^10the seventh to Hakkoz, the eighth to Abijah, ^11the ninth to Jeshua, the tenth to Shecaniah, ^12the eleventh to Eliashib, the twelfth to Jakim, ^13the thirteenth to Huppah, the fourteenth to Jeshebeab, ^14the fifteenth to Bilgah, the sixteenth to Immer, ^15the seventeenth to Hezir, the eighteenth to Happizzez, ^16the nineteenth to Pethahiah, the twentieth to Jehezkel, ^17the one and twentieth to Jachin, the two and twentieth to Gamul, ^18the three and twentieth to Delaiah, the four and twentieth to Maaziah. ^19This was the ordering of them in their service, to come into the house of Jehovah according to the ordinance given unto them by Aaron their father, as Jehovah, the God of Israel, had commanded him.

^20And of the rest of the sons of Levi: of the sons of Amram, Shubael; of the sons of Shubael, Jehdeiah. ^21Of Rehabiah: of the sons of Rehabiah, Isshiah the chief. ^22Of the Izharites, Shelomoth; of the sons of Shelomoth, Jahath. ^23And the sons of Hebron: Jeriah the chief, Amariah the second, Jahaziel the third, Jekameam the fourth. ^24The sons of Uzziel, Micah; of the sons of Micah, Shamir. ^25The brother of Micah, Isshiah; of the sons of Isshiah, Zechariah. ^26The sons of Merari: Mahli and Mushi; the sons of Jaaziah: Beno. ^27The sons of Merari: of Jaaziah, Beno, and Shoham, and Zaccur, and Ibri. ^28Of Mahli: Eleazar, who had no sons. ^29Of Kish; the sons of Kish: Jerahmeel. ^30And the sons of Mushi: Mahli, and Eder, and Jerimoth. These were the sons of the Levites after their fathers' houses. ^31These likewise cast lots even as their brethren the sons of Aaron in the presence of David the king, and Zadok, and Ahimelech, and the heads of the fathers' houses of the priests and of the Levites; the fathers' houses of the chief even as those of his younger brother.

1 Chronicles 26

26

^1For the courses of the doorkeepers: of the Korahites, Meshelemiah the son of Kore, of the sons of Asaph. ^2And Meshelemiah had sons: Zechariah the first-born, Jediael the second, Zebadiah the third, Jathniel the fourth, ^3Elam the fifth, Jehohanan the sixth, Eliehoenai the seventh. ^4And Obed-edom had sons: Shemaiah the first-born, Jehozabad the second, Joah the third, and Sacar the fourth, and Nethanel the fifth, ^5Ammiel the sixth, Issachar the seventh, Peullethai the eighth; for God blessed him. ^6Also unto Shemaiah his son were sons born, that ruled over the house of their father; for they were mighty men of valor. ^7The sons of Shemaiah: Othni, and Rephael, and Obed, Elzabad, whose brethren were valiant men, Elihu, and Semachiah. ^8All these were of the sons of Obed-edom: they and their sons and their brethren, able men in strength for the service; threescore and two of Obed-edom. ^9And Meshelemiah had sons and brethren, valiant men, eighteen. ^10Also Hosah, of the children of Merari, had sons: Shimri the chief, (for though he was not the first-born, yet his father made him chief), ^11Hilkiah the second, Tebaliah the third, Zechariah the fourth: all the sons and brethren of Hosah were thirteen.

^12Of these were the courses of the doorkeepers, even of the chief men, having offices like their brethren, to minister in the house of Jehovah. ^13And they cast lots, as well the small as the great, according to their fathers' houses, for every gate. ^14And the lot eastward fell to Shelemiah. Then for Zechariah his son, a discreet counsellor, they cast lots; and his lot came out northward. ^15To Obed-edom southward; and to his sons the store-house. ^16To Shuppim and Hosah westward, by the gate of Shallecheth, at the causeway that goeth up, watch against watch. ^17Eastward were six Levites, northward four a day, southward four a day, and for the store-house two and two. ^18For Parbar westward, four at the causeway, and two at Parbar. ^19These were the courses of the doorkeepers; of the sons of the Korahites, and of the sons of Merari.

^20And of the Levites, Ahijah was over the treasures of the house of God, and over the treasures of the dedicated things. ^21The sons of Ladan, the sons of the Gershonites belonging to Ladan, the heads of the fathers' houses belonging to Ladan the Gershonite: Jehieli. ^22The sons of Jehieli: Zetham, and Joel his brother, over the treasures of the house of Jehovah. ^23Of the Amramites, of the Izharites, of the Hebronites, of the Uzzielites: ^24and Shebuel the son of Gershom, the son of Moses, was ruler over the treasures. ^25And his brethren: of Eliezer came Rehabiah his son, and Jeshaiah his son, and Joram his son, and Zichri his son, and Shelomoth his son. ^26This Shelomoth and his brethren were over all the treasures of the dedicated things, which David the king, and the heads of the fathers' houses, the captains over thousands and hundreds, and the captains of the host, had dedicated. ^27Out of the spoil won in battles did they dedicate to repair the house of Jehovah. ^28And all that Samuel the seer, and Saul the son of Kish, and Abner the son of Ner, and Joab the son of Zeruiah, had dedicated, whosoever had dedicated anything, it was under the hand of Shelomoth, and of his brethren.

^29Of the Izharites, Chenaniah and his sons were for the outward business over Israel, for officers and judges. ^30Of the Hebronites, Hashabiah and his brethren, men of valor, a thousand and seven hundred, had the oversight of Israel beyond the Jordan westward, for all the business of Jehovah, and for the service of the king. ^31Of the Hebronites was Jerijah the chief, even of the Hebronites, according to their generations by fathers' houses. In the fortieth year of the reign of David they were sought for, and there were found among them mighty men of valor at Jazer of Gilead. ^32And his brethren, men of valor, were two thousand and seven hundred, heads of fathers' houses, whom king David made overseers over the Reubenites, and the Gadites, and the half-tribe of the Manassites, for every matter pertaining to God, and for the affairs of the king.

1 Chronicles 27

27

^1Now the children of Israel after their number, to wit, the heads of fathers' houses and the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and their officers that served the king, in any matter of the courses which came in and went out month by month throughout all the months of the year-of every course were twenty and four thousand. ^2Over the first course for the first month was Jashobeam the son of Zabdiel: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^3He was of the children of Perez, the chief of all the captains of the host for the first month. ^4And over the course of the second month was Dodai the Ahohite, and his course; and Mikloth the ruler: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^5The third captain of the host for the third month was Benaiah, the son of Jehoiada the priest, chief: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^6This is that Benaiah, who was the mighty man of the thirty, and over the thirty: and of his course was Ammizabad his son. ^7The fourth captain for the fourth month was Asahel the brother of Joab, and Zebadiah his son after him: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^8The fifth captain for this fifth month was Shamhuth the Izrahite: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^9The sixth captain for the sixth month was Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^10The seventh captain for the seventh month was Helez the Pelonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^11The eighth captain for the eighth month was Sibbecai the Hushathite, of the Zerahites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^12The ninth captain for the ninth month was Abiezer the Anathothite, of the Benjamites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^13The tenth captain for the tenth month was Maharai the Netophathite, of the Zerahites: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^14The eleventh captain for the eleventh month was Benaiah the Pirathonite, of the children of Ephraim: and in his course were twenty and four thousand. ^15The twelfth captain for the twelfth month was Heldai the Netophathite, of Othniel: and in his course were twenty and four thousand.

^16Furthermore over the tribes of Israel: of the Reubenites was Eliezer the son of Zichri the ruler: of the Simeonites, Shephatiah the son of Maacah: ^17of Levi, Hashabiah the son of Kemuel: of Aaron, Zadok: ^18of Judah, Elihu, one of the brethren of David: of Issachar, Omri the son of Michael: ^19of Zebulun, Ishmaiah the son of Obadiah: of Naphtali, Jeremoth the son of Azriel: ^20of the children of Ephraim, Hoshea the son of Azaziah: of the half-tribe of Manasseh, Joel the son of Pedaiah: ^21of the half -tribe of Manasseh in Gilead, Iddo the son of Zechariah: of Benjamin, Jaasiel the son of Abner: ^22of Dan, Azarel the son of Jeroham. These were the captains of the tribes of Israel. ^23But David took not the number of them from twenty years old and under, because Jehovah had said he would increase Israel like to the stars of heaven. ^24Joab the son of Zeruiah began to number, but finished not; and there came wrath for this upon Israel; neither was the number put into the account in the chronicles of king David.

^25And over the king's treasures was Azmaveth the son of Adiel: and over the treasures in the fields, in the cities, and in the villages, and in the castles, was Jonathan the son of Uzziah: ^26And over them that did the work of the field for tillage of the ground was Ezri the son of Chelub: ^27and over the vineyards was Shimei the Ramathite: and over the increase of the vineyards for the wine-cellars was Zabdi the Shiphmite: ^28and over the olive-trees and the sycomore-trees that were in the lowland was Baal-hanan the Gederite: and over the cellars of oil was Joash: ^29and over the herds that fed in Sharon was Shitrai the Sharonite: and over the herds that were in the valleys was Shaphat the son of Adlai: ^30and over the camels was Obil the Ishmaelite: and over the asses was Jehdeiah the Meronothite: and over the flocks was Jaziz the Hagrite. ^31All these were the rulers of the substance which was king David's.

^32Also Jonathan, David's uncle, was a counsellor, a man of understanding, and a scribe: and Jehiel the son of Hachmoni was with the king's sons: ^33And Ahithophel was the king's counsellor: and Hushai the Archite was the king's friend: ^34and after Ahithophel was Jehoiada the son of Benaiah, and Abiathar: and the captain of the king's host was Joab.

1 Corinthians 2

2

^1And I, brethren, when I came unto you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom, proclaiming to you the testimony of God. ^2For I determined not to know anything among you, save Jesus Christ, and him crucified. ^3And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and in much trembling. ^4And my speech and my preaching were not in persuasive words of wisdom, but in demonstration of the Spirit and of power: ^5that your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God. ^6We speak wisdom, however, among them that are fullgrown: yet a wisdom not of this world, nor of the rulers of this world, who are coming to nought: ^7but we speak God's wisdom in a mystery, even the wisdom that hath been hidden, which God foreordained before the worlds unto our glory: ^8which none of the rulers of this world hath known: for had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of glory: ^9but as it is written,

Things which eye saw not, and ear heard not,

And which entered not into the heart of man,

Whatsoever things God prepared for them that love him.

^10But unto us God revealed them through the Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God. ^11For who among men knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of the man, which is in him? even so the things of God none knoweth, save the Spirit of God. ^12But we received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is from God; that we might know the things that were freely given to us of God. ^13Which things also we speak, not in words which man's wisdom teacheth, but which the Spirit teacheth; combining spiritual things with spiritual words. ^14Now the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness unto him; and he cannot know them, because they are spiritually judged. ^15But he that is spiritual judgeth all things, and he himself is judged of no man. ^16For who hath known the mind of the Lord, that he should instruct him? But we have the mind of Christ.

1 Corinthians 3

3

^1And I, brethren, could not speak unto you as unto spiritual, but as unto carnal, as unto babes in Christ. ^2I fed you with milk, not with meat; for ye were not yet able to bear it: nay, not even now are ye able; ^3for ye are yet carnal: for whereas there is among you jealousy and strife, are ye not carnal, and do ye not walk after the manner of men? ^4For when one saith, I am of Paul; and another, I am of Apollos; are ye not men? ^5What then is Apollos? and what is Paul? Ministers through whom ye believed; and each as the Lord gave to him. ^6I planted, Apollos watered; but God gave the increase. ^7So then neither is he that planteth anything, neither he that watereth; but God that giveth the increase. ^8Now he that planteth and he that watereth are one: but each shall receive his own reward according to his own labor. ^9For we are God's fellow-workers: ye are God's husbandry, God's building. ^10According to the grace of God which was given unto me, as a wise masterbuilder I laid a foundation; and another buildeth thereon. But let each man take heed how he buildeth thereon. ^11For other foundation can no man lay than that which is laid, which is Jesus Christ. ^12But if any man buildeth on the foundation gold, silver, costly stones, wood, hay, stubble; ^13each man's work shall be made manifest: for the day shall declare it, because it is revealed in fire; and the fire itself shall prove each man's work of what sort it is. ^14If any man's work shall abide which he built thereon, he shall receive a reward. ^15If any man's work shall be burned, he shall suffer loss: but he himself shall be saved; yet so as through fire. ^16Know ye not that ye are a temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you? ^17If any man destroyeth the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy, and such are ye. ^18Let no man deceive himself. If any man thinketh that he is wise among you in this world, let him become a fool, that he may become wise. ^19For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God. For it is written, He that taketh the wise in their craftiness: ^20and again, The Lord knoweth the reasonings of the wise that they are vain. ^21Wherefore let no one glory in men. For all things are yours; ^22whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things present, or things to come; all are yours; ^23and ye are Christ's; and Christ is God's.

1 Corinthians 4

4

^1Let a man so account of us, as of ministers of Christ, and stewards of the mysteries of God. ^2Here, moreover, it is required in stewards, that a man be found faithful. ^3But with me it is a very small thing that I should be judged of you, or of man's judgment: yea, I judge not mine own self. ^4For I know nothing against myself; yet am I not hereby justified: but he that judgeth me is the Lord. ^5Wherefore judge nothing before the time, until the Lord come, who will both bring to light the hidden things of darkness, and make manifest the counsels of the hearts; and then shall each man have his praise from God. ^6Now these things, brethren, I have in a figure transferred to myself and Apollos for your sakes; that in us ye might learn not to go beyond the things which are written; that no one of you be puffed up for the one against the other. ^7For who maketh thee to differ? and what hast thou that thou didst not receive? but if thou didst receive it, why dost thou glory as if thou hadst not received it? ^8Already are ye filled, already ye are become rich, ye have come to reign without us: yea and I would that ye did reign, that we also might reign with you. ^9For, I think, God hath set forth us the apostles last of all, as men doomed to death: for we are made a spectacle unto the world, both to angels and men. ^10We are fools for Christ's sake, but ye are wise in Christ; we are weak, but ye are strong; ye have glory, but we have dishonor. ^11Even unto this present hour we both hunger, and thirst, and are naked, and are buffeted, and have no certain dwelling-place; ^12and we toil, working with our own hands: being reviled, we bless; being persecuted, we endure; ^13being defamed, we entreat: we are made as the filth of the world, the offscouring of all things, even until now. ^14I write not these things to shame you, but to admonish you as my beloved children. ^15For though ye have ten thousand tutors in Christ, yet have ye not many fathers; for in Christ Jesus I begat you through the gospel. ^16I beseech you therefore, be ye imitators of me. ^17For this cause have I sent unto you Timothy, who is my beloved and faithful child in the Lord, who shall put you in remembrance of my ways which are in Christ, even as I teach everywhere in every church. ^18Now some are puffed up, as though I were not coming to you. ^19But I will come to you shortly, if the Lord will; and I will know, not the word of them that are puffed up, but the power. ^20For the kingdom of God is not in word, but in power. ^21What will ye? shall I come unto you with a rod, or in love and a spirit of gentleness?

1 Corinthians 5

5

^1It is actually reported that there is fornication among you, and such fornication as is not even among the Gentiles, that one of you hath his father's wife. ^2And ye are puffed up, and did not rather mourn, that he that had done this deed might be taken away from among you. ^3For I verily, being absent in body but present in spirit, have already as though I were present judged him that hath so wrought this thing, ^4in the name of our Lord Jesus, ye being gathered together, and my spirit, with the power of our Lord Jesus, ^5to deliver such a one unto Satan for the destruction of the flesh, that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus. ^6Your glorying is not good. Know ye not that a little leaven leaveneth the whole lump? ^7Purge out the old leaven, that ye may be a new lump, even as ye are unleavened. For our passover also hath been sacrificed, even Christ: ^8wherefore let us keep the feast, not with old leaven, neither with the leaven of malice and wickedness, but with the unleavened bread of sincerity and truth. ^9I wrote unto you in my epistle to have no company with fornicators; ^10not at all meaning with the fornicators of this world, or with the covetous and extortioners, or with idolaters; for then must ye needs go out of the world: ^11but as it is, I wrote unto you not to keep company, if any man that is named a brother be a fornicator, or covetous, or an idolater, or a reviler, or a drunkard, or an extortioner; with such a one no, not to eat. ^12For what have I to do with judging them that are without? Do not ye judge them that are within? ^13But them that are without God judgeth. Put away the wicked man from among yourselves.

1 Corinthians 6

6

^1Dare any of you, having a matter against his neighbor, go to law before the unrighteous, and not before the saints? ^2Or know ye not that the saints shall judge the world? and if the world is judged by you, are ye unworthy to judge the smallest matters? ^3Know ye not that we shall judge angels? how much more, things that pertain to this life? ^4If then ye have to judge things pertaining to this life, do ye set them to judge who are of no account in the church? ^5I say this to move you to shame. What, cannot there be found among you one wise man who shall be able to decide between his brethren, ^6but brother goeth to law with brother, and that before unbelievers? ^7Nay, already it is altogether a defect in you, that ye have lawsuits one with another. Why not rather take wrong? why not rather be defrauded? ^8Nay, but ye yourselves do wrong, and defraud, and that your brethren. ^9Or know ye not that the unrighteous shall not inherit the kingdom of God? Be not deceived: neither fornicators, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abusers of themselves with men, ^10nor thieves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revilers, nor extortioners, shall inherit the kingdom of God. ^11And such were some of you: but ye were washed, but ye were sanctified, but ye were justified in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, and in the Spirit of our God. ^12All things are lawful for me; but not all things are expedient. All things are lawful for me; but I will not be brought under the power of any. ^13Meats for the belly, and the belly for meats: but God shall bring to nought both it and them. But the body is not for fornication, but for the Lord; and the Lord for the body: ^14and God both raised the Lord, and will raise up as through his power. ^15Know ye not that your bodies are members of Christ? shall I then take away the members of Christ, and make them members of a harlot? God forbid. ^16Or know ye not that he that is joined to a harlot is one body? for, The twain, saith he, shall become one flesh. ^17But he that is joined unto the Lord is one spirit. ^18Flee fornication. Every sin that a man doeth is without the body; but he that committeth fornication sinneth against his own body. ^19Or know ye not that your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit which is in you, which ye have from God? and ye are not your own; ^20for ye were bought with a price: glorify God therefore in your body.

1 Corinthians 7

7

^1Now concerning the things whereof ye wrote: It is good for a man not to touch a woman. ^2But, because of fornications, let each man have his own wife, and let each woman have her own husband. ^3Let the husband render unto the wife her due: and likewise also the wife unto the husband. ^4The wife hath not power over her own body, but the husband: and likewise also the husband hath not power over his own body, but the wife. ^5Defraud ye not one the other, except it be by consent for a season, that ye may give yourselves unto prayer, and may be together again, that Satan tempt you not because of your incontinency. ^6But this I say by way of concession, not of commandment. ^7Yet I would that all men were even as I myself. Howbeit each man hath his own gift from God, one after this manner, and another after that. ^8But I say to the unmarried and to widows, It is good for them if they abide even as I. ^9But if they have not continency, let them marry: for it is better to marry than to burn. ^10But unto the married I give charge, yea not I, but the Lord, That the wife depart not from her husband ^11(but should she depart, let her remain unmarried, or else be reconciled to her husband); and that the husband leave not his wife. ^12But to the rest say I, not the Lord: If any brother hath an unbelieving wife, and she is content to dwell with him, let him not leave her. ^13And the woman that hath an unbelieving husband, and he is content to dwell with her, let her not leave her husband. ^14For the unbelieving husband is sanctified in the wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified in the brother: else were your children unclean; but now are they holy. ^15Yet if the unbelieving departeth, let him depart: the brother or the sister is not under bondage in such cases: but God hath called us in peace. ^16For how knowest thou, O wife, whether thou shalt save thy husband? Or how knowest thou, O husband, whether thou shalt save thy wife? ^17Only, as the Lord hath distributed to each man, as God hath called each, so let him walk. And so ordain I in all the churches. ^18Was any man called being circumcised? Let him not become uncircumcised. Hath any been called in uncircumcision? Let him not be circumcised. ^19Circumcision is nothing, and uncircumcision is nothing; but the keeping of the commandments of God. ^20Let each man abide in that calling wherein he was called. ^21Wast thou called being a bondservant? Care not for it: nay, even if thou canst become free, use it rather. ^22For he that was called in the Lord being a bondservant, is the Lord's freedman: likewise he that was called being free, is Christ's bondservant. ^23Ye were bought with a price; become not bondservants of men. ^24Brethren, let each man, wherein he was called, therein abide with God. ^25Now concerning virgins I have no commandment of the Lord: but I give my judgment, as one that hath obtained mercy of the Lord to be trustworthy. ^26I think therefore that this is good by reason of the distress that is upon us, namely, that it is good for a man to be as he is. ^27Art thou bound unto a wife? Seek not to be loosed. Art thou loosed from a wife? Seek not a wife. ^28But shouldest thou marry, thou hast not sinned; and if a virgin marry, she hath not sinned. Yet such shall have tribulation in the flesh: and I would spare you. ^29But this I say, brethren, the time is shortened, that henceforth both those that have wives may be as though they had none; ^30and those that weep, as though they wept not; and those that rejoice, as though they rejoiced not; and those that buy, as though they possessed not; ^31and those that use the world, as not using it to the full: for the fashion of this world passeth away. ^32But I would have you to be free from cares. He that is unmarried is careful for the things of the Lord, how he may please the Lord: ^33but he that is married is careful for the things of the world, how he may please his wife, ^34and is divided. So also the woman that is unmarried and the virgin is careful for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in body and in spirit: but she that is married is careful for the things of the world, how she may please her husband. ^35And this I say for your own profit; not that I may cast a snare upon you, but for that which is seemly, and that ye may attend upon the Lord without distraction. ^36But if any man thinketh that he behaveth himself unseemly toward his virgin daughter, if she be past the flower of her age, and if need so requireth, let him do what he will; he sinneth not; let them marry. ^37But he that standeth stedfast in his heart, having no necessity, but hath power as touching in his own heart, to keep his own virgin daughter, shall do well. ^38So then both he that giveth his own virgin daughter in marriage doeth well; and he that giveth her not in marriage shall do better. ^39A wife is bound for so long time as her husband liveth; but if the husband be dead, she is free to be married to whom she will; only in the Lord. ^40But she is happier if she abide as she is, after my judgment: and I think that I also have the Spirit of God.

1 Corinthians 8

8

^1Now concerning things sacrificed to idols: We know that we all have knowledge. Knowledge puffeth up, but love edifieth. ^2If any man thinketh that he knoweth anything, he knoweth not yet as he ought to know; ^3but if any man loveth God, the same is known by him. ^4Concerning therefore the eating of things sacrificed to idols, we know that no idol is anything in the world, and that there is no God but one. ^5For though there be that are called gods, whether in heaven or on earth; as there are gods many, and lords many; ^6yet to us there is one God, the Father, of whom are all things, and we unto him; and one Lord, Jesus Christ, through whom are all things, and we through him. ^7Howbeit there is not in all men that knowledge: but some, being used until now to the idol, eat as of a thing sacrificed to an idol; and their conscience being weak is defiled. ^8But food will not commend us to God: neither, if we eat not, are we the worse; nor, if we eat, are we the better. ^9But take heed lest by any means this liberty of yours become a stumblingblock to the weak. ^10For if a man see thee who hast knowledge sitting at meat in an idol's temple, will not his conscience, if he is weak, be emboldened to eat things sacrificed to idols? ^11For through thy knowledge he that is weak perisheth, the brother for whose sake Christ died. ^12And thus, sinning against the brethren, and wounding their conscience when it is weak, ye sin against Christ. ^13Wherefore, if meat causeth my brother to stumble, I will eat no flesh for evermore, that I cause not my brother to stumble.

1 Corinthians 9

9

^1Am I not free? Am I not an apostle? Have I not seen Jesus our Lord? Are not ye my work in the Lord? ^2If to others I am not an apostle, yet at least I am to you; for the seal of mine apostleship are ye in the Lord. ^3My defence to them that examine me is this. ^4Have we no right to eat and to drink? ^5Have we no right to lead about a wife that is a believer, even as the rest of the apostles, and the brethren of the Lord, and Cephas? ^6Or I only and Barnabas, have we not a right to forbear working? ^7What soldier ever serveth at his own charges? who planteth a vineyard, and eateth not the fruit thereof? Or who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock? ^8Do I speak these things after the manner of men? or saith not the law also the same? ^9For it is written in the law of Moses, Thou shalt not muzzle the ox when he treadeth out the corn. Is it for the oxen that God careth, ^10or saith he it assuredly for our sake? Yea, for our sake it was written: because he that ploweth ought to plow in hope, and he that thresheth, to thresh in hope of partaking. ^11If we sowed unto you spiritual things, is it a great matter if we shall reap your carnal things? ^12If others partake of this right over you, do not we yet more? Nevertheless we did not use this right; but we bear all things, that we may cause no hindrance to the gospel of Christ. ^13Know ye not that they that minister about sacred things eat of the things of the temple, and they that wait upon the altar have their portion with the altar? ^14Even so did the Lord ordain that they that proclaim the gospel should live of the gospel. ^15But I have used none of these things: and I write not these things that it may be so done in my case; for it were good for me rather to die, than that any man should make my glorifying void. ^16For if I preach the gospel, I have nothing to glory of; for necessity is laid upon me; for woe is unto me, if I preach not the gospel. ^17For if I do this of mine own will, I have a reward: but if not of mine own will, I have a stewardship intrusted to me. ^18What then is my reward? That, when I preach the gospel, I may make the gospel without charge, so as not to use to the full my right in the gospel. ^19For though I was free from all men, I brought myself under bondage to all, that I might gain the more. ^20And to the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain Jews; to them that are under the law, as under the law, not being myself under the law, that I might gain them that are under the law; ^21to them that are without law, as without law, not being without law to God, but under law to Christ, that I might gain them that are without law. ^22To the weak I became weak, that I might gain the weak: I am become all things to all men, that I may by all means save some. ^23And I do all things for the gospel's sake, that I may be a joint partaker thereof. ^24Know ye not that they that run in a race run all, but one receiveth the prize? Even so run; that ye may attain. ^25And every man that striveth in the games exerciseth self-control in all things. Now they do it to receive a corruptible crown; but we an incorruptible. ^26I therefore so run, as not uncertainly; so fight I, as not beating the air: ^27but I buffet my body, and bring it into bondage: lest by any means, after that I have preached to others, I myself should be rejected.

1 Corinthians 10

10

^1For I would not, brethren, have you ignorant, that our fathers were all under the cloud, and all passed through the sea; ^2and were all baptized unto Moses in the cloud and in the sea; ^3and did all eat the same spiritual food; ^4and did all drink the same spiritual drink: for they drank of a spiritual rock that followed them: and the rock was Christ. ^5Howbeit with most of them God was not well pleased: for they were overthrown in the wilderness. ^6Now these things were our examples, to the intent we should not lust after evil things, as they also lusted. ^7Neither be ye idolaters, as were some of them; as it is written, The people sat down to eat and drink, and rose up to play. ^8Neither let us commit fornication, as some of them committed, and fell in one day three and twenty thousand. ^9Neither let us make trial of the Lord, as some of them made trial, and perished by the serpents. ^10Neither murmur ye, as some of them murmured, and perished by the destroyer. ^11Now these things happened unto them by way of example; and they were written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the ages are come. ^12Wherefore let him that thinketh he standeth take heed lest he fall. ^13There hath no temptation taken you but such as man can bear: but God is faithful, who will not suffer you to be tempted above that ye are able; but will with the temptation make also the way of escape, that ye may be able to endure it. ^14Wherefore, my beloved, flee from idolatry. ^15I speak as to wise men; judge ye what I say. ^16The cup of blessing which we bless, is it not a communion of the blood of Christ? The bread which we break, is it not a communion of the body of Christ? ^17seeing that we, who are many, are one bread, one body: for we are all partake of the one bread. ^18Behold Israel after the flesh: have not they that eat the sacrifices communion with the altar? ^19What say I then? that a thing sacrificed to idols is anything, or that an idol is anything? ^20But I say, that the things which the Gentiles sacrifice, they sacrifice to demons, and not to God: and I would not that ye should have communion with demons. ^21Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of demons: ye cannot partake of the table of the Lord, and of the table of demons. ^22Or do we provoke the Lord to jealousy? are we stronger than he? ^23All things are lawful; but not all things are expedient. All things are lawful; but not all things edify. ^24Let no man seek his own, but each his neighbor's good. ^25Whatsoever is sold in the shambles, eat, asking no question for conscience' sake, ^26for the earth is the Lord's, and the fulness thereof. ^27If one of them that believe not biddeth you to a feast, and ye are disposed to go; whatsoever is set before you, eat, asking no question for conscience' sake. ^28But if any man say unto you, This hath been offered in sacrifice, eat not, for his sake that showed it, and for conscience sake: ^29conscience, I say, not thine own, but the other's; for why is my liberty judged by another conscience? ^30If I partake with thankfulness, why am I evil spoken of for that for which I give thanks? ^31Whether therefore ye eat, or drink, or whatsoever ye do, do all to the glory of God. ^32Give no occasions of stumbling, either to Jews, or to Greeks, or to the church of God: ^33even as I also please all men in all things, not seeking mine own profit, but the profit of the many, that they may be saved.

1 Corinthians 11

11

^1Be ye imitators of me, even as I also am of Christ. ^2Now I praise you that ye remember me in all things, and hold fast the traditions, even as I delivered them to you. ^3But I would have you know, that the head of every man is Christ; and the head of the woman is the man; and the head of Christ is God. ^4Every man praying or prophesying, having his head covered, dishonoreth his head. ^5But every woman praying or prophesying with her head unveiled dishonoreth her head; for it is one and the same thing as if she were shaven. ^6For if a woman is not veiled, let her also be shorn: but if it is a shame to a woman to be shorn or shaven, let her be veiled. ^7For a man indeed ought not to have his head veiled, forasmuch as he is the image and glory of God: but the woman is the glory of the man. ^8For the man is not of the woman; but the woman of the man: ^9for neither was the man created for the woman; but the woman for the man: ^10for this cause ought the woman to have a sign of authority on her head, because of the angels. ^11Nevertheless, neither is the woman without the man, nor the man without the woman, in the Lord. ^12For as the woman is of the man, so is the man also by the woman; but all things are of God. ^13Judge ye in yourselves: is it seemly that a woman pray unto God unveiled? ^14Doth not even nature itself teach you, that, if a man have long hair, it is a dishonor to him? ^15But if a woman have long hair, it is a glory to her: for her hair is given her for a covering. ^16But if any man seemeth to be contentious, we have no such custom, neither the churches of God. ^17But in giving you this charge, I praise you not, that ye come together not for the better but for the worse. ^18For first of all, when ye come together in the church, I hear that divisions exist among you; and I partly believe it. ^19For there must be also factions among you, that they that are approved may be made manifest among you. ^20When therefore ye assemble yourselves together, it is not possible to eat the Lord's supper: ^21for in your eating each one taketh before other his own supper; and one is hungry, and another is drunken. ^22What, have ye not houses to eat and to drink in? or despise ye the church of God, and put them to shame that have not? What shall I say to you? shall I praise you? In this I praise you not. ^23For I received of the Lord that which also I delivered unto you, that the Lord Jesus in the night in which he was betrayed took bread; ^24and when he had given thanks, he brake it, and said, This is my body, which is for you: this do in remembrance of me. ^25In like manner also the cup, after supper, saying, This cup is the new covenant in my blood: this do, as often as ye drink it, in remembrance of me. ^26For as often as ye eat this bread, and drink the cup, ye proclaim the Lord's death till he come. ^27Wherefore whosoever shall eat the bread or drink the cup of the Lord in an unworthy manner, shall be guilty of the body and the blood of the Lord. ^28But let a man prove himself, and so let him eat of the bread, and drink of the cup. ^29For he that eateth and drinketh, eateth and drinketh judgment unto himself, if he discern not the body. ^30For this cause many among you are weak and sickly, and not a few sleep. ^31But if we discerned ourselves, we should not be judged. ^32But when we are judged, we are chastened of the Lord, that we may not be condemned with the world. ^33Wherefore, my brethren, when ye come together to eat, wait one for another. ^34If any man is hungry, let him eat at home; that your coming together be not unto judgment. And the rest will I set in order whensoever I come.

1 Corinthians 12

12

^1Now concerning spiritual gifts, brethren, I would not have you ignorant. ^2Ye know that when ye were Gentiles ye were led away unto those dumb idols, howsoever ye might led. ^3Wherefore I make known unto you, that no man speaking in the Spirit of God saith, Jesus is anathema; and no man can say, Jesus is Lord, but in the Holy Spirit. ^4Now there are diversities of gifts, but the same Spirit. ^5And there are diversities of ministrations, and the same Lord. ^6And there are diversities of workings, but the same God, who worketh all things in all. ^7But to each one is given the manifestation of the Spirit to profit withal. ^8For to one is given through the Spirit the word of wisdom; and to another the word of knowledge, according to the same Spirit: ^9to another faith, in the same Spirit; and to another gifts of healings, in the one Spirit; ^10and to another workings of miracles; and to another prophecy; and to another discernings of spirits; to another divers kinds of tongues; and to another the interpretation of tongues: ^11but all these worketh the one and the same Spirit, dividing to each one severally even as he will. ^12For as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of the body, being many, are one body; so also is Christ. ^13For in one Spirit were we all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether bond or free; and were all made to drink of one Spirit. ^14For the body is not one member, but many. ^15If the foot shall say, Because I am not the hand, I am not of the body; it is not therefore not of the body. ^16And if the ear shall say, Because I am not the eye, I am not of the body; it is not therefore not of the body. ^17If the whole body were an eye, where were the hearing? If the whole were hearing, where were the smelling? ^18But now hath God set the members each one of them in the body, even as it pleased him. ^19And if they were all one member, where were the body? ^20But now they are many members, but one body. ^21And the eye cannot say to the hand, I have no need of thee: or again the head to the feet, I have no need of you. ^22Nay, much rather, those members of the body which seem to be more feeble are necessary: ^23and those parts of the body, which we think to be less honorable, upon these we bestow more abundant honor; and our uncomely parts have more abundant comeliness; ^24whereas our comely parts have no need: but God tempered the body together, giving more abundant honor to that part which lacked; ^25that there should be no schism in the body; but that the members should have the same care one for another. ^26And whether one member suffereth, all the members suffer with it; or one member is honored, all the members rejoice with it. ^27Now ye are the body of Christ, and severally members thereof. ^28And God hath set some in the church, first apostles, secondly prophets, thirdly teachers, then miracles, then gifts of healings, helps, governments, divers kinds of tongues. ^29Are all apostles? are all prophets? are all teachers? are all workers of miracles? ^30have all gifts of healings? do all speak with tongues? do all interpret? ^31But desire earnestly the greater gifts. And moreover a most excellent way show I unto you.

1 Corinthians 14

14

^1Follow after love; yet desire earnestly spiritual gifts, but rather that ye may prophesy. ^2For he that speaketh in a tongue speaketh not unto men, but unto God; for no man understandeth; but in the spirit he speaketh mysteries. ^3But he that prophesieth speaketh unto men edification, and exhortation, and consolation. ^4He that speaketh in a tongue edifieth himself; but he that prophesieth edifieth the church. ^5Now I would have you all speak with tongues, but rather that ye should prophesy: and greater is he that prophesieth than he that speaketh with tongues, except he interpret, that the church may receive edifying. ^6But now, brethren, if I come unto you speaking with tongues, what shall I profit you, unless I speak to you either by way of revelation, or of knowledge, or of prophesying, or of teaching? ^7Even things without life, giving a voice, whether pipe or harp, if they give not a distinction in the sounds, how shall it be known what is piped or harped? ^8For if the trumpet give an uncertain voice, who shall prepare himself for war? ^9So also ye, unless ye utter by the tongue speech easy to understood, how shall it be known what is spoken? for ye will be speaking into the air. ^10There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and no kind is without signification. ^11If then I know not the meaning of the voice, I shall be to him that speaketh a barbarian, and he that speaketh will be a barbarian unto me. ^12So also ye, since ye are zealous of spiritual gifts, seek that ye may abound unto the edifying of the church. ^13Wherefore let him that speaketh in a tongue pray that he may interpret. ^14For if I pray in a tongue, my spirit prayeth, but my understanding is unfruitful. ^15What is it then? I will pray with the spirit, and I will pray with the understanding also: I will sing with the spirit, and I will sing with the understanding also. ^16Else if thou bless with the spirit, how shall he that filleth the place of the unlearned say the Amen at thy giving of thanks, seeing he knoweth not what thou sayest? ^17For thou verily givest thanks well, but the other is not edified. ^18I thank God, I speak with tongues more than you all: ^19howbeit in the church I had rather speak five words with my understanding, that I might instruct others also, than ten thousand words in a tongue. ^20Brethren, be not children in mind: yet in malice be ye babes, but in mind be men. ^21In the law it is written, By men of strange tongues and by the lips of strangers will I speak unto this people; and not even thus will they hear me, saith the Lord. ^22Wherefore tongues are for a sign, not to them that believe, but to the unbelieving: but prophesying is for a sign, not to the unbelieving, but to them that believe. ^23If therefore the whole church be assembled together and all speak with tongues, and there come in men unlearned or unbelieving, will they not say that ye are mad? ^24But if all prophesy, and there come in one unbelieving or unlearned, he is reproved by all, he is judged by all; ^25the secrets of his heart are made manifest; and so he will fall down on his face and worship God, declaring that God is among you indeed. ^26What is it then, brethren? When ye come together, each one hath a psalm, hath a teaching, hath a revelation, hath a tongue, hath an interpretation. Let all things be done unto edifying. ^27If any man speaketh in a tongue, let it be by two, or at the most three, and that in turn; and let one interpret: ^28but if there be no interpreter, let him keep silence in the church; and let him speak to himself, and to God. ^29And let the prophets speak by two or three, and let the others discern. ^30But if a revelation be made to another sitting by, let the first keep silence. ^31For ye all can prophesy one by one, that all may learn, and all may be exhorted; ^32and the spirits of the prophets are subject to the prophets; ^33for God is not a God of confusion, but of peace. As in all the churches of the saints, ^34let the women keep silence in the churches: for it is not permitted unto them to speak; but let them be in subjection, as also saith the law. ^35And if they would learn anything, let them ask their own husbands at home: for it is shameful for a woman to speak in the church. ^36What? was it from you that the word of God went forth? or came it unto you alone? ^37If any man thinketh himself to be a prophet, or spiritual, let him take knowledge of the things which I write unto you, that they are the commandment of the Lord. ^38But if any man is ignorant, let him be ignorant. ^39Wherefore, my brethren, desire earnestly to prophesy, and forbid not to speak with tongues. ^40But let all things be done decently and in order.

1 Corinthians 15

15

^1Now I make known unto you brethren, the gospel which I preached unto you, which also ye received, wherein also ye stand, ^2by which also ye are saved, if ye hold fast the word which I preached unto you, except ye believed in vain. ^3For I delivered unto you first of all that which also I received: that Christ died for our sins according to the spans; ^4and that he was buried; and that he hath been raised on the third day according to the spans; ^5and that he appeared to Cephas; then to the twelve; ^6then he appeared to above five hundred brethren at once, of whom the greater part remain until now, but some are fallen asleep; ^7then he appeared to James; then to all the apostles; ^8and last of all, as to the child untimely born, he appeared to me also. ^9For I am the least of the apostles, that am not meet to be called an apostle, because I persecuted the church of God. ^10But by the grace of God I am what I am: and his grace which was bestowed upon me was not found vain; but I labored more abundantly than they all: yet not I, but the grace of God which was with me. ^11Whether then it be I or they, so we preach, and so ye believed. ^12Now if Christ is preached that he hath been raised from the dead, how say some among you that there is no resurrection of the dead? ^13But if there is no resurrection of the dead, neither hath Christ been raised: ^14and if Christ hath not been raised, then is our preaching vain, your faith also is vain. ^15Yea, we are found false witnesses of God; because we witnessed of God that he raised up Christ: whom he raised not up, if so be that the dead are not raised. ^16For if the dead are not raised, neither hath Christ been raised: ^17and if Christ hath not been raised, your faith is vain; ye are yet in your sins. ^18Then they also that are fallen asleep in Christ have perished. ^19If we have only hoped in Christ in this life, we are of all men most pitiable. ^20But now hath Christ been raised from the dead, the firstfruits of them that are asleep. ^21For since by man came death, by man came also the resurrection of the dead. ^22For as in Adam all die, so also in Christ shall all be made alive. ^23But each in his own order: Christ the firstfruits; then they that are Christ's, at his coming. ^24Then cometh the end, when he shall deliver up the kingdom to God, even the Father; when he shall have abolished all rule and all authority and power. ^25For he must reign, till he hath put all his enemies under his feet. ^26The last enemy that shall be abolished is death. ^27For, He put all things in subjection under his feet. But when he saith, All things are put in subjection, it is evident that he is excepted who did subject all things unto him. ^28And when all things have been subjected unto him, then shall the Son also himself be subjected to him that did subject all things unto him, that God may be all in all. ^29Else what shall they do that are baptized for the dead? If the dead are not raised at all, why then are they baptized for them? ^30Why do we also stand in jeopardy every hour? ^31I protest by that glorifying in you, brethren, which I have in Christ Jesus our Lord, I die daily. ^32If after the manner of men I fought with beasts at Ephesus, what doth it profit me? If the dead are not raised, let us eat and drink, for to-morrow we die. ^33Be not deceived: Evil companionships corrupt good morals. ^34Awake to soberness righteously, and sin not; for some have no knowledge of God: I speak this to move you to shame. ^35But some one will say, How are the dead raised? and with what manner of body do they come? ^36Thou foolish one, that which thou thyself sowest is not quickened except it die: ^37and that which thou sowest, thou sowest not the body that shall be, but a bare grain, it may chance of wheat, or of some other kind; ^38but God giveth it a body even as it pleased him, and to each seed a body of its own. ^39All flesh is not the same flesh: but there is one flesh of men, and another flesh of beasts, and another flesh of birds, and another of fishes. ^40There are also celestial bodies, and bodies terrestrial: but the glory of the celestial is one, and the glory of the terrestrial is another. ^41There is one glory of the sun, and another glory of the moon, and another glory of the stars; for one star differeth from another star in glory. ^42So also is the resurrection of the dead. It is sown in corruption; it is raised in incorruption: ^43it is sown in dishonor; it is raised in glory: it is sown in weakness; it is raised in power: ^44it is sown a natural body; it is raised a spiritual body. If there is a natural body, there is also a spiritual body. ^45So also it is written, The first man Adam became a living soul. The last Adam became a life-giving spirit. ^46Howbeit that is not first which is spiritual, but that which is natural; then that which is spiritual. ^47The first man is of the earth, earthy: the second man is of heaven. ^48As is the earthy, such are they also that are earthy: and as is the heavenly, such are they also that are heavenly. ^49And as we have borne the image of the earthy, we shall also bear the image of the heavenly. ^50Now this I say, brethren, that flesh and blood cannot inherit the kingdom of God; neither doth corruption inherit incorruption. ^51Behold, I tell you a mystery: We all shall not sleep, but we shall all be changed, ^52in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, at the last trump: for the trumpet shall sound, and the dead shall be raised incorruptible, and we shall be changed. ^53For this corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortal must put on immortality. ^54But when this corruptible shall have put on incorruption, and this mortal shall have put on immortality, then shall come to pass the saying that is written, Death is swallowed up in victory. ^55O death, where is thy victory? O death, where is thy sting? ^56The sting of death is sin; and the power of sin is the law: ^57but thanks be to God, who giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ. ^58Wherefore, my beloved brethren, be ye stedfast, unmoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, forasmuch as ye know that your labor is not vain in the Lord.

2 Chronicles 2

2

^1Now Solomon purposed to build a house for the name of Jehovah, and a house for his kingdom. ^2And Solomon counted out threescore and ten thousand men to bear burdens, and fourscore thousand men that were hewers in the mountains, and three thousand and six hundred to oversee them. ^3And Solomon sent to Huram the king of Tyre, saying, As thou didst deal with David my father, and didst send him cedars to build him a house to dwell therein, even so deal with me. ^4Behold, I am about to build a house for the name of Jehovah my God, to dedicate it to him, and to burn before him incense of sweet spices, and for the continual showbread, and for the burnt-offerings morning and evening, on the sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the set feasts of Jehovah our God. This is an ordinance for ever to Israel. ^5And the house which I build is great; for great is our God above all gods. ^6But who is able to build him a house, seeing heaven and the heaven of heavens cannot contain him? who am I then, that I should build him a house, save only to burn incense before him? ^7Now therefore send me a man skilful to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, and in iron, and in purple, and crimson, and blue, and that knoweth how to grave all manner of gravings, to be with the skilful men that are with me in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom David my father did provide. ^8Send me also cedar-trees, fir-trees, and algum-trees, out of Lebanon; for I know that thy servants know how to cut timber in Lebanon: and, behold, my servants shall be with thy servants, ^9even to prepare me timber in abundance; for the house which I am about to build shall be great and wonderful. ^10And, behold, I will give to thy servants, the hewers that cut timber, twenty thousand measures of beaten wheat, and twenty thousand measures of barley, and twenty thousand baths of wine, and twenty thousand baths of oil. ^11Then Huram the king of Tyre answered in writing, which he sent to Solomon, Because Jehovah loveth his people, he hath made thee king over them. ^12Huram said moreover, Blessed be Jehovah, the God of Israel, that made heaven and earth, who hath given to David the king a wise son, endued with discretion and understanding, that should build a house for Jehovah, and a house for his kingdom. ^13And now I have sent a skilful man, endued with understanding, of Huram my father's, ^14the son of a woman of the daughters of Dan; and his father was a man of Tyre, skilful to work in gold, and in silver, in brass, in iron, in stone, and in timber, in purple, in blue, and in fine linen, and in crimson, also to grave any manner of graving, and to devise any device; that there may be a place appointed unto him with thy skilful men, and with the skilful men of my lord David thy father. ^15Now therefore the wheat and the barley, the oil and the wine, which my lord hath spoken of, let him send unto his servants: ^16and we will cut wood out of Lebanon, as much as thou shalt need; and we will bring it to thee in floats by sea to Joppa; and thou shalt carry it up to Jerusalem. ^17And Solomon numbered all the sojourners that were in the land of Israel, after the numbering wherewith David his father had numbered them; and they were found a hundred and fifty thousand and three thousand and six hundred. ^18And he set threescore and ten thousand of them to bear burdens, and fourscore thousand that were hewers in the mountains, and three thousand and six hundred overseers to set the people at work.

2 Chronicles 3

3

^1Then Solomon began to build the house of Jehovah at Jerusalem on mount Moriah, where Jehovah appeared unto David his father, which he made ready in the place that David had appointed, in the threshing-floor of Ornan the Jebusite. ^2And he began to build in the second day of the second month, in the fourth year of his reign. ^3Now these are the foundations which Solomon laid for the building of the house of God. The length by cubits after the first measure was threescore cubits, and the breadth twenty cubits. ^4And the porch that was before the house, the length of it, according to the breadth of the house, was twenty cubits, and the height a hundred and twenty; and he overlaid it within with pure gold. ^5And the greater house he ceiled with fir-wood, which he overlaid with fine gold, and wrought thereon palm-trees and chains. ^6And he garnished the house with precious stones for beauty: and the gold was gold of Parvaim. ^7He overlaid also the house, the beams, the thresholds, and the walls thereof, and the doors thereof, with gold; and graved cherubim on the walls. ^8And he made the most holy house: the length thereof, according to the breadth of the house, was twenty cubits, and the breadth thereof twenty cubits; and he overlaid it with fine gold, amounting to six hundred talents. ^9And the weight of the nails was fifty shekels of gold. And he overlaid the upper chambers with gold. ^10And in the most holy house he made two cherubim of image work; and they overlaid them with gold. ^11And the wings of the cherubim were twenty cubits long: the wing of the one cherub was five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house; and the other wing was likewise five cubits, reaching to the wing of the other cherub. ^12And the wing of the other cherub was five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house; and the other wing was five cubits also, joining to the wing of the other cherub. ^13The wings of these cherubim spread themselves forth twenty cubits: and they stood on their feet, and their faces were toward the house. ^14And he made the veil of blue, and purple, and crimson, and fine linen, and wrought cherubim thereon. ^15Also he made before the house two pillars of thirty and five cubits high, and the capital that was on the top of each of them was five cubits. ^16And he made chains in the oracle, and put them on the tops of the pillars; and he made a hundred pomegranates, and put them on the chains. ^17And he set up the pillars before the temple, one on the right hand, and the other on the left; and called the name of that on the right hand Jachin, and the name of that on the left Boaz.

2 Chronicles 4

4

^1Moreover he made an altar of brass, twenty cubits the length thereof, and twenty cubits the breadth thereof, and ten cubits the height thereof. ^2Also he made the molten sea of ten cubits from brim to brim, round in compass; and the height thereof was five cubits; and a line of thirty cubits compassed it round about. ^3And under it was the likeness of oxen, which did compass it round about, for ten cubits, compassing the sea round about. The oxen were in two rows, cast when it was cast. ^4It stood upon twelve oxen, three looking toward the north, and three looking toward the west, and three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east: and the sea was set upon them above, and all their hinder parts were inward. ^5And it was a handbreadth thick; and the brim thereof was wrought like the brim of a cup, like the flower of a lily: it received and held three thousand baths. ^6He made also ten lavers, and put five on the right hand, and five on the left, to wash in them; such things as belonged to the burnt-offering they washed in them; but the sea was for the priests to wash in. ^7And he made the ten candlesticks of gold according to the ordinance concerning them; and he set them in the temple, five on the right hand, and five on the left. ^8He made also ten tables, and placed them in the temple, five on the right side, and five on the left. And he made a hundred basins of gold. ^9Furthermore he made the court of the priests, and the great court, and doors for the court, and overlaid the doors of them with brass. ^10And he set the sea on the right side of the house eastward, toward the south. ^11And Huram made the pots, and the shovels, and the basins. So Huram made an end of doing the work that he wrought for king Solomon in the house of God: ^12the two pillars, and the bowls, and the two capitals which were on the top of the pillars, and the two networks to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the top of the pillars, ^13and the four hundred pomegranates for the two networks; two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were upon the pillars. ^14He made also the bases, and the lavers made he upon the bases; ^15one sea, and the twelve oxen under it. ^16The pots also, and the shovels, and the flesh-hooks, and all the vessels thereof, did Huram his father make for king Solomon for the house of Jehovah of bright brass. ^17In the plain of the Jordan did the king cast them, in the clay ground between Succoth and Zeredah. ^18Thus Solomon made all these vessels in great abundance: for the weight of the brass could not be found out. ^19And Solomon made all the vessels that were in the house of God, the golden altar also, and the tables whereon was the showbread; ^20and the candlesticks with their lamps, to burn according to the ordinance before the oracle, of pure gold; ^21and the flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs, of gold, and that perfect gold; ^22and the snuffers, and the basins, and the spoons, and the firepans, of pure gold: and as for the entry of the house, the inner doors thereof for the most holy place, and the doors of the house, to wit, of the temple, were of gold.

2 Chronicles 5

5

^1Thus all the work that Solomon wrought for the house of Jehovah was finished. And Solomon brought in the things that David his father had dedicated, even the silver, and the gold, and all the vessels, and put them in the treasuries of the house of God. ^2Then Solomon assembled the elders of Israel, and all the heads of the tribes, the princes of the fathers' houses of the children of Israel, unto Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah out of the city of David, which is Zion. ^3nd all the men of Israel assembled themselves unto the king at the feast, which was in the seventh month. ^4And all the elders of Israel came: and the Levites took up the ark; ^5and they brought up the ark, and the tent of meeting, and all the holy vessels that were in the Tent; these did the priests the Levites bring up. ^6And king Solomon and all the congregation of Israel, that were assembled unto him, were before the ark, sacrificing sheep and oxen, that could not be counted nor numbered for multitude. ^7And the priests brought in the ark of the covenant of Jehovah unto its place, into the oracle of the house, to the most holy place, even under the wings of the cherubim. ^8For the cherubim spread forth their wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubim covered the ark and the staves thereof above. ^9And the staves were so long that the ends of the staves were seen from the ark before the oracle; but they were not seen without: and there it is unto this day. ^10There was nothing in the ark save the two tables which Moses put there at Horeb, when Jehovah made a covenant with the children of Israel, when they came out of Egypt. ^11And it came to pass, when the priests were come out of the holy place, (for all the priests that were present had sanctified themselves, and did not keep their courses; ^12also the Levites who were the singers, all of them, even Asaph, Heman, Jeduthun, and their sons and their brethren, arrayed in fine linen, with cymbals and psalteries and harps, stood at the east end of the altar, and with them a hundred and twenty priests sounding with trumpets;) ^13it came to pass, when the trumpeters and singers were as one, to make one sound to be heard in praising and thanking Jehovah; and when they lifted up their voice with the trumpets and cymbals and instruments of music, and praised Jehovah, saying, For he is good; for his lovingkindness endureth for ever; that then the house was filled with a cloud, even the house of Jehovah, ^14so that the priests could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud: for the glory of Jehovah filled the house of God.

2 Chronicles 7

7

^1Now when Solomon had made an end of praying, the fire came down from heaven, and consumed the burnt-offering and the sacrifices; and the glory of Jehovah filled the house. ^2And the priests could not enter into the house of Jehovah, because the glory of Jehovah filled Jehovah's house. ^3And all the children of Israel looked on, when the fire came down, and the glory of Jehovah was upon the house; and they bowed themselves with their faces to the ground upon the pavement, and worshipped, and gave thanks unto Jehovah, saying, For he is good; for his lovingkindness endureth for ever. ^4Then the king and all the people offered sacrifice before Jehovah. ^5And king Solomon offered a sacrifice of twenty and two thousand oxen, and a hundred and twenty thousand sheep. So the king and all the people dedicated the house of God. ^6And the priests stood, according to their offices; the Levites also with instruments of music of Jehovah, which David the king had made to give thanks unto Jehovah, (for his lovingkindness endureth for ever,) when David praised by their ministry: and the priests sounded trumpets before them; and all Israel stood. ^7Moreover Solomon hallowed the middle of the court that was before the house of Jehovah; for there he offered the burnt-offerings, and the fat of the peace-offerings, because the brazen altar which Solomon had made was not able to receive the burnt-offering, and the meal-offering, and the fat. ^8So Solomon held the feast at that time seven days, and all Israel with him, a very great assembly, from the entrance of Hamath unto the brook of Egypt. ^9And on the eighth day they held a solemn assembly: for they kept the dedication of the altar seven days, and the feast seven days. ^10And on the three and twentieth day of the seventh month he sent the people away unto their tents, joyful and glad of heart for the goodness that Jehovah had showed unto David, and to Solomon, and to Israel his people. ^11Thus Solomon finished the house of Jehovah, and the king's house: and all that came into Solomon's heart to make in the house of Jehovah, and in his own house, he prosperously effected. ^12And Jehovah appeared to Solomon by night, and said unto him, I have heard thy prayer, and have chosen this place to myself for a house of sacrifice. ^13If I shut up the heavens so that there is no rain, or if I command the locust to devour the land, or if I send pestilence among my people; ^14if my people, who are called by my name, shall humble themselves, and pray, and seek my face, and turn from their wicked ways; then will I hear from heaven, and will forgive their sin, and will heal their land. ^15Now mine eyes shall be open, and mine ears attent, unto the prayer that is made in this place. ^16For now have I chosen and hallowed this house, that my name may be there for ever; and mine eyes and my heart shall be there perpetually. ^17And as for thee, if thou wilt walk before me as David thy father walked, and do according to all that I have commanded thee, and wilt keep my statutes and mine ordinances; ^18then I will establish the throne of thy kingdom, according as I covenanted with David thy father, saying, There shall not fail thee a man to be ruler in Israel. ^19But if ye turn away, and forsake my statutes and my commandments which I have set before you, and shall go and serve other gods, and worship them; ^20then will I pluck them up by the roots out of my land which I have given them; and this house, which I have hallowed for my name, will I cast out of my sight, and I will make it a proverb and a byword among all peoples. ^21And this house, which is so high, every one that passeth by it shall be astonished, and shall say, Why hath Jehovah done thus unto this land, and to this house? ^22And they shall answer, Because they forsook Jehovah, the God of their fathers, who brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, and laid hold on other gods, and worshipped them, and served them: therefore hath he brought all this evil upon them.

2 Chronicles 8

8

^1And it came to pass at the end of twenty years, wherein Solomon had built the house of Jehovah, and his own house, ^2that the cities which Huram had given to Solomon, Solomon built them, and caused the children of Israel to dwell there. ^3And Solomon went to Hamath-zobah, and prevailed against it. ^4And he built Tadmor in the wilderness, and all the store-cities, which he built in Hamath. ^5Also he built Beth-horon the upper, and Beth-horon the nether, fortified cities, with walls, gates, and bars; ^6and Baalath, and all the store-cities that Solomon had, and all the cities for his chariots, and the cities for his horsemen, and all that Solomon desired to build for his pleasure in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion. ^7As for all the people that were left of the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, that were not of Israel; ^8of their children that were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel consumed not, of them did Solomon raise a levy of bondservants unto this day. ^9But of the children of Israel did Solomon make no servants for his work; but they were men of war, and chief of his captains, and rulers of his chariots and of his horsemen. ^10And these were the chief officers of king Solomon, even two hundred and fifty, that bare rule over the people. ^11And Solomon brought up the daughter of Pharaoh out of the city of David unto the house that he had built for her; for he said, My wife shall not dwell in the house of David king of Israel, because the places are holy, whereunto the ark of Jehovah hath come. ^12Then Solomon offered burnt-offerings unto Jehovah on the altar of Jehovah, which he had built before the porch, ^13even as the duty of every day required, offering according to the commandment of Moses, on the sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the set feasts, three times in the year, even in the feast of unleavened bread, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of tabernacles. ^14And he appointed, according to the ordinance of David his father, the courses of the priests to their service, and the Levites to their offices, to praise, and to minister before the priests, as the duty of every day required; the doorkeepers also by their courses at every gate: for so had David the man of God commanded. ^15And they departed not from the commandment of the king unto the priests and Levites concerning any matter, or concerning the treasures. ^16Now all the work of Solomon was prepared unto the day of the foundation of the house of Jehovah, and until it was finished. So the house of Jehovah was completed. ^17Then went Solomon to Ezion-geber, and to Eloth, on the seashore in the land of Edom. ^18And Huram sent him by the hands of his servants ships, and servants that had knowledge of the sea; and they came with the servants of Solomon to Ophir, and fetched from thence four hundred and fifty talents of gold, and brought them to king Solomon.

2 Chronicles 9

9

^1And when the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, she came to prove Solomon with hard questions at Jerusalem, with a very great train, and camels that bare spices, and gold in abundance, and precious stones: and when she was come to Solomon, she communed with him of all that was in her heart. ^2And Solomon told her all her questions; and there was not anything hid from Solomon which he told her not. ^3And when the queen of Sheba had seen the wisdom of Solomon, and the house that he had built, ^4and the food of his table, and the sitting of his servants, and the attendance of his ministers, and their apparel, his cupbearers also, and their apparel, and his ascent by which he went up unto the house of Jehovah; there was no more spirit in her. ^5And she said to the king, It was a true report that I heard in mine own land of thine acts, and of thy wisdom. ^6Howbeit I believed not their words, until I came, and mine eyes had seen it; and, behold, the half of the greatness of thy wisdom was not told me: thou exceedest the fame that I heard. ^7Happy are thy men, and happy are these thy servants, that stand continually before thee, and hear thy wisdom. ^8Blessed be Jehovah thy God, who delighted in thee, to set thee on his throne, to be king for Jehovah thy God: because thy God loved Israel, to establish them for ever, therefore made he thee king over them, to do justice and righteousness. ^9And she gave the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold, and spices in great abundance, and precious stones: neither was there any such spice as the queen of Sheba gave to king Solomon. ^10And the servants also of Huram, and the servants of Solomon, that brought gold from Ophir, brought algum-trees and precious stones. ^11And the king made of the algum-trees terraces for the house of Jehovah, and for the king's house, and harps and psalteries for the singers: and there were none such seen before in the land of Judah. ^12And king Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all her desire, whatsoever she asked, besides that which she had brought unto the king. So she turned, and went to her own land, she and her servants. ^13Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was six hundred and threescore and six talents of gold, ^14besides that which the traders and merchants brought: and all the kings of Arabia and the governors of the country brought gold and silver to Solomon. ^15And king Solomon made two hundred bucklers of beaten gold; six hundred shekels of beaten gold went to one buckler. ^16And he made three hundred shields of beaten gold; three hundred shekels of gold went to one shield: and the king put them in the house of the forest of Lebanon. ^17Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with pure gold. ^18nd there were six steps to the throne, with a footstool of gold, which were fastened to the throne, and stays on either side by the place of the seat, and two lions standing beside the stays. ^19And twelve lions stood there on the one side and on the other upon the six steps: there was not the like made in any kingdom. ^20And all king Solomon's drinking vessels were of gold, and all the vessels of the house of the forest of Lebanon were of pure gold: silver was nothing accounted of in the days of Solomon. ^21For the king had ships that went to Tarshish with the servants of Huram; once every three years came the ships of Tarshish, bringing gold, and silver, ivory, and apes, and peacocks. ^22So king Solomon exceeded all the kings of the earth in riches and wisdom. ^23And all the kings of the earth sought the presence of Solomon, to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart. ^24And they brought every man his tribute, vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and raiment, armor, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate year by year. ^25And Solomon had four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, that he bestowed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem. ^26And he ruled over all the kings from the River even unto the land of the Philistines, and to the border of Egypt. ^27And the king made silver to be in Jerusalem as stones, and cedars made he to be as the sycomore-trees that are in the lowland, for abundance. ^28And they brought horses for Solomon out of Egypt, and out of all lands. ^29Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, first and last, are they not written in the history of Nathan the prophet, and in the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the seer concerning Jeroboam the son of Nebat? ^30And Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years. ^31And Solomon slept with his fathers, and he was buried in the city of David his father: and Rehoboam his son reigned in his stead.

2 Chronicles 10

10

^1And Rehoboam went to Shechem; for all Israel were come to Shechem to make him king. ^2And it came to pass, when Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard of it, (for he was in Egypt, whither he had fled from the presence of king Solomon,) that Jeroboam returned out of Egypt. ^3And they sent and called him; and Jeroboam and all Israel came, and they spake to Rehoboam, saying, ^4Thy father made our yoke grievous: now therefore make thou the grievous service of thy father, and his heavy yoke which he put upon us, lighter, and we will serve thee. ^5And he said unto them, Come again unto me after three days. And the people departed. ^6And king Rehoboam took counsel with the old men, that had stood before Solomon his father while he yet lived, saying, What counsel give ye me to return answer to this people? ^7And they spake unto him, saying, If thou be kind to this people, and please them, and speak good words to them, then they will be thy servants for ever. ^8But he forsook the counsel of the old men which they had given him, and took counsel with the young men that were grown up with him, that stood before him. ^9And he said unto them, What counsel give ye, that we may return answer to this people, who have spoken to me, saying, Make the yoke that thy father did put upon us lighter? ^10And the young men that were grown up with him spake unto him, saying, Thus shalt thou say unto the people that spake unto thee, saying, Thy father made our yoke heavy, but make thou it lighter unto us; thus shalt thou say unto them, My little finger is thicker than my father's loins. ^11And now whereas my father did lade you with a heavy yoke, I will add to your yoke: my father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions. ^12So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the king bade, saying, Come to me again the third day. ^13And the king answered them roughly; and king Rehoboam forsook the counsel of the old men, ^14and spake to them after the counsel of the young men, saying, My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add thereto: my father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions. ^15So the king hearkened not unto the people; for it was brought about of God, that Jehovah might establish his word, which he spake by Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat. ^16And when all Israel saw that the king hearkened not unto them, the people answered the king, saying, What portion have we in David? neither have we inheritance in the son of Jesse: every man to your tents, O Israel: now see to thine own house, David. So all Israel departed unto their tents. ^17But as for the children of Israel that dwelt in the cities of Judah, Rehoboam reigned over them. ^18Then king Rehoboam sent Hadoram, who was over the men subject to taskwork; and the children of Israel stoned him to death with stones. And king Rehoboam made speed to get him up to his chariot, to flee to Jerusalem. ^19So Israel rebelled against the house of David unto this day.

2 Chronicles 11

11

^1And when Rehoboam was come to Jerusalem, he assembled the house of Judah and Benjamin, a hundred and fourscore thousand chosen men, that were warriors, to fight against Israel, to bring the kingdom again to Rehoboam. ^2But the word of Jehovah came to Shemaiah the man of God, saying, ^3Speak unto Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, saying, ^4Thus saith Jehovah, Ye shall not go up, nor fight against your brethren: return every man to his house; for this thing is of me. So they hearkened unto the words of Jehovah, and returned from going against Jeroboam. ^5And Rehoboam dwelt in Jerusalem, and built cities for defence in Judah. ^6He built Beth-lehem, and Etam, and Tekoa, ^7And Beth-zur, and Soco, and Adullam, ^8and Gath, and Mareshah, and Ziph, ^9and Adoraim, and Lachish, and Azekah, ^10and Zorah, and Aijalon, and Hebron, which are in Judah and in Benjamin, fortified cities. ^11And he fortified the strongholds, and put captains in them, and stores of victuals, and oil and wine. ^12And in every city he put shields and spears, and made them exceeding strong. And Judah and Benjamin belonged to him. ^13And the priests and the Levites that were in all Israel resorted to him out of all their border. ^14For the Levites left their suburbs and their possession, and came to Judah and Jerusalem: for Jeroboam and his sons cast them off, that they should not execute the priest's office unto Jehovah; ^15and he appointed him priests for the high places, and for the he-goats, and for the calves which he had made. ^16And after them, out of all the tribes of Israel, such as set their hearts to seek Jehovah, the God of Israel, came to Jerusalem to sacrifice unto Jehovah, the God of their fathers. ^17So they strengthened the kingdom of Judah, and made Rehoboam the son of Solomon strong, three years; for they walked three years in the way of David and Solomon. ^18And Rehoboam took him a wife, Mahalath the daughter of Jerimoth the son of David, and of Abihail the daughter of Eliab the son of Jesse; ^19and she bare him sons: Jeush, and Shemariah, and Zaham. ^20And after her he took Maacah the daughter of Absalom; and she bare him Abijah, and Attai, and Ziza, and Shelomith. ^21And Rehoboam loved Maacah the daughter of Absalom above all his wives and his concubines: (for he took eighteen wives, and threescore concubines, and begat twenty and eight sons and threescore daughters.) ^22And Rehoboam appointed Abijah the son of Maacah to be chief, even the prince among his brethren; for he was minded to make him king. ^23And he dealt wisely, and dispersed of all his sons throughout all the lands of Judah and Benjamin, unto every fortified city: and he gave them victuals in abundance. And he sought for them many wives.

2 Chronicles 12

12

^1And it came to pass, when the kingdom of Rehoboam was established, and he was strong, that he forsook the law of Jehovah, and all Israel with him. ^2And it came to pass in the fifth year of king Rehoboam, that Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, because they had trespassed against Jehovah, ^3with twelve hundred chariots, and threescore thousand horsemen. And the people were without number that came with him out of Egypt: the Lubim, the Sukkiim, and the Ethiopians. ^4And he took the fortified cities which pertained to Judah, and came unto Jerusalem. ^5Now Shemaiah the prophet came to Rehoboam, and to the princes of Judah, that were gathered together to Jerusalem because of Shishak, and said unto them, Thus saith Jehovah, Ye have forsaken me, therefore have I also left you in the hand of Shishak. ^6Then the princes of Israel and the king humbled themselves; and they said, Jehovah is righteous. ^7And when Jehovah saw that they humbled themselves, the word of Jehovah came to Shemaiah, saying, They have humbled themselves: I will not destroy them; but I will grant them some deliverance, and my wrath shall not be poured out upon Jerusalem by the hand of Shishak. ^8Nevertheless they shall be his servants, that they may know my service, and the service of the kingdoms of the countries. ^9So Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, and took away the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and the treasures of the king's house: he took all away: he took away also the shields of gold which Solomon had made. ^10And king Rehoboam made in their stead shields of brass, and committed them to the hands of the captains of the guard, that kept the door of the king's house. ^11And it was so, that, as oft as the king entered into the house of Jehovah, the guard came and bare them, and brought them back into the guard-chamber. ^12And when he humbled himself, the wrath of Jehovah turned from him, so as not to destroy him altogether: and moreover in Judah there were good things found. ^13So king Rehoboam strengthened himself in Jerusalem, and reigned: for Rehoboam was forty and one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city which Jehovah had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, to put his name there: and his mother's name was Naamah the Ammonitess. ^14And he did that which was evil, because he set not his heart to seek Jehovah. ^15Now the acts of Rehoboam, first and last, are they not written in the histories of Shemaiah the prophet and of Iddo the seer, after the manner of genealogies? And there were wars between Rehoboam and Jeroboam continually. ^16And Rehoboam slept with his fathers, and was buried in the city of David: and Abijah his son reigned in his stead.

2 Chronicles 13

13

^1In the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam began Abijah to reign over Judah. ^2Three years reigned he in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Micaiah the daughter of Uriel of Gibeah. And there was war between Abijah and Jeroboam. ^3And Abijah joined battle with an army of valiant men of war, even four hundred thousand chosen men: and Jeroboam set the battle in array against him with eight hundred thousand chosen men, who were mighty men of valor. ^4And Abijah stood up upon mount Zemaraim, which is in the hill-country of Ephraim, and said, Hear me, O Jeroboam and all Israel: ^5Ought ye not to know that Jehovah, the God of Israel, gave the kingdom over Israel to David for ever, even to him and to his sons by a covenant of salt? ^6Yet Jeroboam the son of Nebat, the servant of Solomon the son of David, rose up, and rebelled against his lord. ^7And there were gathered unto him worthless men, base fellows, that strengthened themselves against Rehoboam the son of Solomon, when Rehoboam was young and tender-hearted, and could not withstand them. ^8And now ye think to withstand the kingdom of Jehovah in the hand of the sons of David; and ye are a great multitude, and there are with you the golden calves which Jeroboam made you for gods. ^9Have ye not driven out the priests of Jehovah, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites, and made you priests after the manner of the peoples of other lands? so that whosoever cometh to consecrate himself with a young bullock and seven rams, the same may be a priest of them that are no gods. ^10But as for us, Jehovah is our God, and we have not forsaken him; and we have priests ministering unto Jehovah, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites in their work: ^11and they burn unto Jehovah every morning and every evening burnt-offerings and sweet incense: the showbread also set they in order upon the pure table; and the candlestick of gold with the lamps thereof, to burn every evening: for we keep the charge of Jehovah our God; but ye have forsaken him. ^12And, behold, God is with us at our head, and his priests with the trumpets of alarm to sound an alarm against you. O children of Israel, fight ye not against Jehovah, the God of your fathers; for ye shall not prosper. ^13But Jeroboam caused an ambushment to come about behind them: so they were before Judah, and the ambushment was behind them. ^14And when Judah looked back, behold, the battle was before and behind them; and they cried unto Jehovah, and the priests sounded with the trumpets. ^15Then the men of Judah gave a shout: and as the men of Judah shouted, it came to pass, that God smote Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah. ^16And the children of Israel fled before Judah; and God delivered them into their hand. ^17And Abijah and his people slew them with a great slaughter: so there fell down slain of Israel five hundred thousand chosen men. ^18Thus the children of Israel were brought under at that time, and the children of Judah prevailed, because they relied upon Jehovah, the God of their fathers. ^19And Abijah pursued after Jeroboam, and took cities from him, Beth-el with the towns thereof, and Jeshanah with the towns thereof, and Ephron with the towns thereof. ^20Neither did Jeroboam recover strength again in the days of Abijah: and Jehovah smote him, and he died. ^21But Abijah waxed mighty, and took unto himself fourteen wives, and begat twenty and two sons, and sixteen daughters. ^22And the rest of the acts of Abijah, and his ways, and his sayings, are written in the commentary of the prophet Iddo.

2 Chronicles 14

14

^1So Abijah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David; and Asa his son reigned in his stead. In his days the land was quiet ten years. ^2And Asa did that which was good and right in the eyes of Jehovah his God: ^3for he took away the foreign altars, and the high places, and brake down the pillars, and hewed down the Asherim, ^4and commanded Judah to seek Jehovah, the God of their fathers, and to do the law and the commandment. ^5Also he took away out of all the cities of Judah the high places and the sun-images: and the kingdom was quiet before him. ^6And he built fortified cities in Judah; for the land was quiet, and he had no war in those years, because Jehovah had given him rest. ^7For he said unto Judah, Let us build these cities, and make about them walls, and towers, gates, and bars; the land is yet before us, because we have sought Jehovah our God; we have sought him, and he hath given us rest on every side. So they built and prospered. ^8And Asa had an army that bare bucklers and spears, out of Judah three hundred thousand; and out of Benjamin, that bare shields and drew bows, two hundred and fourscore thousand: all these were mighty men of valor. ^9And there came out against them Zerah the Ethiopian with an army of a thousand thousand, and three hundred chariots; and he came unto Mareshah. ^10Then Asa went out to meet him, and they set the battle in array in the valley of Zephathah at Mareshah. ^11And Asa cried unto Jehovah his God, and said, Jehovah, there is none besides thee to help, between the mighty and him that hath no strength: help us, O Jehovah our God; for we rely on thee, and in thy name are we come against this multitude. O Jehovah, thou art our God; let not man prevail against thee. ^12So Jehovah smote the Ethiopians before Asa, and before Judah; and the Ethiopians fled. ^13And Asa and the people that were with him pursued them unto Gerar: and there fell of the Ethiopians so many that they could not recover themselves; for they were destroyed before Jehovah, and before his host; and they carried away very much booty. ^14And they smote all the cities round about Gerar; for the fear of Jehovah came upon them: and they despoiled all the cities; for there was much spoil in them. ^15They smote also the tents of cattle, and carried away sheep in abundance, and camels, and returned to Jerusalem.

2 Chronicles 15

15

^1And the Spirit of God came upon Azariah the son of Oded: ^2and he went out to meet Asa, and said unto him, Hear ye me, Asa, and all Judah and Benjamin: Jehovah is with you, while ye are with him; and if ye seek him, he will be found of you; but if ye forsake him, he will forsake you. ^3Now for a long season Israel was without the true God, and without a teaching priest, and without law: ^4But when in their distress they turned unto Jehovah, the God of Israel, and sought him, he was found of them. ^5And in those times there was no peace to him that went out, nor to him that came in; but great vexations were upon all the inhabitants of the lands. ^6And they were broken in pieces, nation against nation, and city against city; for God did vex them with all adversity. ^7But be ye strong, and let not your hands be slack; for your work shall be rewarded. ^8And when Asa heard these words, and the prophecy of Oded the prophet, he took courage, and put away the abominations out of all the land of Judah and Benjamin, and out of the cities which he had taken from the hill-country of Ephraim; and he renewed the altar of Jehovah, that was before the porch of Jehovah. ^9And he gathered all Judah and Benjamin, and them that sojourned with them out of Ephraim and Manasseh, and out of Simeon: for they fell to him out of Israel in abundance, when they saw that Jehovah his God was with him. ^10So they gathered themselves together at Jerusalem in the third month, in the fifteenth year of the reign of Asa. ^11And they sacrificed unto Jehovah in that day, of the spoil which they had brought, seven hundred oxen and seven thousand sheep. ^12And they entered into the covenant to seek Jehovah, the God of their fathers, with all their heart and with all their soul; ^13and that whosoever would not seek Jehovah, the God of Israel, should be put to death, whether small or great, whether man or woman. ^14And they sware unto Jehovah with a loud voice, and with shouting, and with trumpets, and with cornets. ^15And all Judah rejoiced at the oath; for they had sworn with all their heart, and sought him with their whole desire; and he was found of them: and Jehovah gave them rest round about. ^16And also Maacah, the mother of Asa the king, he removed from being queen, because she had made an abominable image for an Asherah; and Asa cut down her image, and made dust of it, and burnt it at the brook Kidron. ^17But the high places were not taken away out of Israel: nevertheless the heart of Asa was perfect all his days. ^18And he brought into the house of God the things that his father had dedicated, and that he himself had dedicated, silver, and gold, and vessels. ^19And there was no more war unto the five and thirtieth year of the reign of Asa.

2 Chronicles 16

16

^1In the six and thirtieth year of the reign of Asa, Baasha king of Israel went up against Judah, and built Ramah, that he might not suffer any one to go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. ^2Then Asa brought out silver and gold out of the treasures of the house of Jehovah and of the king's house, and sent to Ben-hadad king of Syria, that dwelt at Damascus, saying, ^3There is a league between me and thee, as there was between my father and thy father: behold, I have sent thee silver and gold; go, break thy league with Baasha king of Israel, that he may depart from me. ^4And Ben-hadad hearkened unto king Asa, and sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel; and they smote Ijon, and Dan, and Abel-maim, and all the store-cities of Naphtali. ^5And it came to pass, when Baasha heard thereof, that he left off building Ramah, and let his work cease. ^6Then Asa the king took all Judah; and they carried away the stones of Ramah, and the timber thereof, wherewith Baasha had builded; and he built therewith Geba and Mizpah. ^7And at that time Hanani the seer came to Asa king of Judah, and said unto him, Because thou hast relied on the king of Syria, and hast not relied on Jehovah thy God, therefore is the host of the king of Syria escaped out of thy hand. ^8Were not the Ethiopians and the Lubim a huge host, with chariots and horsemen exceeding many? yet, because thou didst rely on Jehovah, he delivered them into thy hand. ^9For the eyes of Jehovah run to and fro throughout the whole earth, to show himself strong in the behalf of them whose heart is perfect toward him. Herein thou hast done foolishly; for from henceforth thou shalt have wars. ^10Then Asa was wroth with the seer, and put him in the prison-house; for he was in a rage with him because of this thing. And Asa oppressed some of the people at the same time. ^11And, behold, the acts of Asa, first and last, lo, they are written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. ^12And in the thirty and ninth year of his reign Asa was diseased in his feet; his disease was exceeding great: yet in his disease he sought not to Jehovah, but to the physicians. ^13And Asa slept with his fathers, and died in the one and fortieth year of his reign. ^14And they buried him in his own sepulchres, which he had hewn out for himself in the city of David, and laid him in the bed which was filled with sweet odors and divers kinds of spices prepared by the perfumers' art: and they made a very great burning for him.

2 Chronicles 17

17

^1And Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his stead, and strengthened himself against Israel. ^2And he placed forces in all the fortified cities of Judah, and set garrisons in the land of Judah, and in the cities of Ephraim, which Asa his father had taken. ^3And Jehovah was with Jehoshaphat, because he walked in the first ways of his father David, and sought not unto the Baalim, ^4but sought to the God of his father, and walked in his commandments, and not after the doings of Israel. ^5Therefore Jehovah established the kingdom in his hand; and all Judah brought to Jehoshaphat tribute; and he had riches and honor in abundance. ^6And his heart was lifted up in the ways of Jehovah: and furthermore he took away the high places and the Asherim out of Judah. ^7Also in the third year of his reign he sent his princes, even Ben-hail, and Obadiah, and Zechariah, and Nethanel, and Micaiah, to teach in the cities of Judah; ^8and with them the Levites, even Shemaiah, and Nethaniah, and Zebadiah, and Asahel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehonathan, and Adonijah, and Tobijah, and Tob-adonijah, the Levites; and with them Elishama and Jehoram, the priests. ^9And they taught in Judah, having the book of the law of Jehovah with them; and they went about throughout all the cities of Judah, and taught among the people. ^10And the fear of Jehovah fell upon all the kingdoms of the lands that were round about Judah, so that they made no war against Jehoshaphat. ^11And some of the Philistines brought Jehoshaphat presents, and silver for tribute; the Arabians also brought him flocks, seven thousand and seven hundred rams, and seven thousand and seven hundred he-goats. ^12And Jehoshaphat waxed great exceedingly; and he built in Judah castles and cities of store. ^13And he had many works in the cities of Judah; and men of war, mighty men of valor, in Jerusalem. ^14And this was the numbering of them according to their fathers' houses: Of Judah, the captains of thousands: Adnah the captain, and with him mighty men of valor three hundred thousand; ^15and next to him Jehohanan the captain, and with him two hundred and fourscore thousand; ^16and next to him Amasiah the son of Zichri, who willingly offered himself unto Jehovah; and with him two hundred thousand mighty men of valor. ^17And of Benjamin: Eliada a mighty man of valor, and with him two hundred thousand armed with bow and shield; ^18and next to him Jehozabad and with him a hundred and fourscore thousand ready prepared for war. ^19These were they that waited on the king, besides those whom the king put in the fortified cities throughout all Judah.

2 Chronicles 18

18

^1Now Jehoshaphat had riches and honor in abundance; and he joined affinity with Ahab. ^2And after certain years he went down to Ahab to Samaria. And Ahab killed sheep and oxen for him in abundance, and for the people that were with him, and moved him to go up with him to Ramoth-gilead. ^3And Ahab king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat king of Judah, Wilt thou go with me to Ramoth-gilead? And he answered him, I am as thou art, and my people as thy people; and we will be with thee in the war. ^4And Jehoshaphat said unto the king of Israel, Inquire first, I pray thee, for the word of Jehovah. ^5Then the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, four hundred men, and said unto them, Shall we go to Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I forbear? And they said, Go up; for God will deliver it into the hand of the king. ^6But Jehoshaphat said, Is there not here a prophet of Jehovah besides, that we may inquire of him? ^7And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, There is yet one man by whom we may inquire of Jehovah: but I hate him; for he never prophesieth good concerning me, but always evil: the same is Micaiah the son of Imla. And Jehoshaphat said, Let not the king say so. ^8Then the king of Israel called an officer, and said, Fetch quickly Micaiah the son of Imla. ^9Now the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah sat each on his throne, arrayed in their robes, and they were sitting in an open place at the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets were prophesying before them. ^10And Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah made him horns of iron, and said, Thus saith Jehovah, With these shalt thou push the Syrians, until they be consumed. ^11And all the prophets prophesied so, saying, Go up to Ramoth-gilead, and prosper; for Jehovah will deliver it into the hand of the king. ^12And the messenger that went to call Micaiah spake to him, saying, Behold, the words of the prophets declare good to the king with one mouth: let thy word therefore, I pray thee, be like one of theirs, and speak thou good. ^13And Micaiah said, As Jehovah liveth, what my God saith, that will I speak. ^14And when he was come to the king, the king said unto him, Micaiah, shall we go to Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I forbear? And he said, Go ye up, and prosper; and they shall be delivered into your hand. ^15And the king said to him, How many times shall I adjure thee that thou speak unto me nothing but the truth in the name of Jehovah? ^16And he said, I saw all Israel scattered upon the mountains, as sheep that have no shepherd: and Jehovah said, These have no master; let them return every man to his house in peace. ^17And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, Did I not tell thee that he would not prophesy good concerning me, but evil? ^18And Micaiah said, Therefore hear ye the word of Jehovah: I saw Jehovah sitting upon his throne, and all the host of heaven standing on his right hand and on his left. ^19And Jehovah said, Who shall entice Ahab king of Israel, that he may go up and fall at Ramoth-gilead? And one spake saying after this manner, and another saying after that manner. ^20And there came forth a spirit, and stood before Jehovah, and said, I will entice him. And Jehovah said unto him, Wherewith? ^21And he said, I will go forth, and will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets. And he said, Thou shalt entice him, and shalt prevail also: go forth, and do so. ^22Now therefore, behold, Jehovah hath put a lying spirit in the mouth of these thy prophets; and Jehovah hath spoken evil concerning thee. ^23Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah came near, and smote Micaiah upon the cheek, and said, Which way went the Spirit of Jehovah from me to speak unto thee? ^24And Micaiah said, Behold, thou shalt see on that day, when thou shalt go into an inner chamber to hide thyself. ^25And the king of Israel said, Take ye Micaiah, and carry him back unto Amon the governor of the city, and to Joash the king's son; ^26and say, Thus saith the king, Put this fellow in the prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction, until I return in peace. ^27And Micaiah said, If thou return at all in peace, Jehovah hath not spoken by me. And he said, Hear, ye peoples, all of you. ^28So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth-gilead. ^29And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, I will disguise myself, and go into the battle; but put thou on thy robes. So the king of Israel disguised himself; and they went into the battle. ^30Now the king of Syria had commanded the captains of his chariots, saying, Fight neither with small nor great, save only with the king of Israel. ^31And it came to pass, when the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, that they said, It is the king of Israel. Therefore they turned about to fight against him: but Jehoshaphat cried out, and Jehovah helped him; and God moved them to depart from him. ^32And it came to pass, when the captains of the chariots saw that it was not the king of Israel, that they turned back from pursuing him. ^33And a certain man drew his bow at a venture, and smote the king of Israel between the joints of the armor: wherefore he said to the driver of the chariot, Turn thy hand, and carry me out of the host; for I am sore wounded. ^34And the battle increased that day: howbeit the king of Israel stayed himself up in his chariot against the Syrians until the even; and about the time of the going down of the sun he died.

2 Chronicles 19

19

^1And Jehoshaphat the king of Judah returned to his house in peace to Jerusalem. ^2And Jehu the son of Hanani the seer went out to meet him, and said to king Jehoshaphat, Shouldest thou help the wicked, and love them that hate Jehovah? for this thing wrath is upon thee from before Jehovah. ^3Nevertheless there are good things found in thee, in that thou hast put away the Asheroth out of the land, and hast set thy heart to seek God. ^4And Jehoshaphat dwelt at Jerusalem: and he went out again among the people from Beer-sheba to the hill-country of Ephraim, and brought them back unto Jehovah, the God of their fathers. ^5And he set judges in the land throughout all the fortified cities of Judah, city by city, ^6and said to the judges, Consider what ye do: for ye judge not for man, but for Jehovah; and he is with you in the judgment. ^7Now therefore let the fear of Jehovah be upon you; take heed and do it: for there is no iniquity with Jehovah our God, nor respect of persons, nor taking of bribes. ^8Moreover in Jerusalem did Jehoshaphat set of the Levites and the priests, and of the heads of the fathers' houses of Israel, for the judgment of Jehovah, and for controversies. And they returned to Jerusalem. ^9And he charged them, saying, Thus shall ye do in the fear of Jehovah, faithfully, and with a perfect heart. ^10And whensoever any controversy shall come to you from your brethren that dwell in their cities, between blood and blood, between law and commandment, statutes and ordinances, ye shall warn them, that they be not guilty towards Jehovah, and so wrath come upon you and upon your brethren: this do, and ye shall not be guilty. ^11And, behold, Amariah the chief priest is over you in all matters of Jehovah; and Zebadiah the son of Ishmael, the ruler of the house of Judah, in all the king's matters: also the Levites shall be officers before you. Deal courageously, and Jehovah be with the good.

2 Chronicles 20

20

^1And it came to pass after this, that the children of Moab, and the children of Ammon, and with them some of the Ammonites, came against Jehoshaphat to battle. ^2Then there came some that told Jehoshaphat, saying, There cometh a great multitude against thee from beyond the sea from Syria; and, behold, they are in Hazazon-tamar (the same is En-gedi). ^3And Jehoshaphat feared, and set himself to seek unto Jehovah; and he proclaimed a fast throughout all Judah. ^4And Judah gathered themselves together, to seek help of Jehovah: even out of all the cities of Judah they came to seek Jehovah. ^5And Jehoshaphat stood in the assembly of Judah and Jerusalem, in the house of Jehovah, before the new court; ^6and he said, O Jehovah, the God of our fathers, art not thou God in heaven? and art not thou ruler over all the kingdoms of the nations? and in thy hand is power and might, so that none is able to withstand thee. ^7Didst not thou, O our God, drive out the inhabitants of this land before thy people Israel, and give it to the seed of Abraham thy friend for ever? ^8And they dwelt therein, and have built thee a sanctuary therein for thy name, saying, ^9If evil come upon us, the sword, judgment, or pestilence, or famine, we will stand before this house, and before thee, (for thy name is in this house,) and cry unto thee in our affliction, and thou wilt hear and save. ^10And now, behold, the children of Ammon and Moab and mount Seir, whom thou wouldest not let Israel invade, when they came out of the land of Egypt, but they turned aside from them, and destroyed them not; ^11behold, how they reward us, to come to cast us out of thy possession, which thou hast given us to inherit. ^12O our God, wilt thou not judge them? for we have no might against this great company that cometh against us; neither know we what to do: but out eyes are upon thee. ^13And all Judah stood before Jehovah, with their little ones, their wives, and their children. ^14Then upon Jahaziel the son of Zechariah, the son of Benaiah, the son of Jeiel, the son of Mattaniah, the Levite, of the sons of Asaph, came the Spirit of Jehovah in the midst of the assembly; ^15and he said, Hearken ye, all Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem, and thou king Jehoshaphat: Thus saith Jehovah unto you, Fear not ye, neither be dismayed by reason of this great multitude; for the battle is not yours, but God's. ^16To-morrow go ye down against them: behold, they come up by the ascent of Ziz; and ye shall find them at the end of the valley, before the wilderness of Jeruel. ^17Ye shall not need to fight in this battle: set yourselves, stand ye still, and see the salvation of Jehovah with you, O Judah and Jerusalem; fear not, nor be dismayed: to-morrow go out against them: for Jehovah is with you. ^18And Jehoshaphat bowed his head with his face to the ground; and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell down before Jehovah, worshipping Jehovah. ^19And the Levites, of the children of the Kohathites and of the children of the Korahites, stood up to praise Jehovah, the God of Israel, with an exceeding loud voice. ^20And they rose early in the morning, and went forth into the wilderness of Tekoa: and as they went forth, Jehoshaphat stood and said, Hear me, O Judah, and ye inhabitants of Jerusalem: believe in Jehovah your God, so shall ye be established; believe his prophets, so shall ye prosper. ^21And when he had taken counsel with the people, he appointed them that should sing unto Jehovah, and give praise in holy array, as they went out before the army, and say, Give thanks unto Jehovah; for his lovingkindness endureth for ever. ^22And when they began to sing and to praise, Jehovah set liers-in-wait against the children of Ammon, Moab, and mount Seir, that were come against Judah; and they were smitten. ^23For the children of Ammon and Moab stood up against the inhabitants of mount Seir, utterly to slay and destroy them: and when they had made an end of the inhabitants of Seir, every one helped to destroy another. ^24And when Judah came to the watch-tower of the wilderness, they looked upon the multitude; and, behold, they were dead bodies fallen to the earth, and there were none that escaped. ^25And when Jehoshaphat and his people came to take the spoil of them, they found among them in abundance both riches and dead bodies, and precious jewels, which they stripped off for themselves, more than they could carry away: and they were three days in taking the spoil, it was so much. ^26And on the fourth day they assembled themselves in the valley of Beracah; for there they blessed Jehovah: therefore the name of that place was called The valley of Beracah unto this day. ^27Then they returned, every man of Judah and Jerusalem, and Jehoshaphat in the forefront of them, to go again to Jerusalem with joy; for Jehovah had made them to rejoice over their enemies. ^28And they came to Jerusalem with psalteries and harps and trumpets unto the house of Jehovah. ^29And the fear of God was on all the kingdoms of the countries, when they heard that Jehovah fought against the enemies of Israel. ^30So the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet; for his God gave him rest round about. ^31And Jehoshaphat reigned over Judah: he was thirty and five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty and five years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. ^32And he walked in the way of Asa his father, and turned not aside from it, doing that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah. ^33Howbeit the high places were not taken away; neither as yet had the people set their hearts unto the God of their fathers. ^34Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, first and last, behold, they are written in the history of Jehu the son of Hanani, which is inserted in the book of the kings of Israel. ^35And after this did Jehoshaphat king of Judah join himself with Ahaziah king of Israel; the same did very wickedly: ^36and he joined himself with him to make ships to go to Tarshish; and they made the ships in Ezion-geber. ^37Then Eliezer the son of Dodavahu of Mareshah prophesied against Jehoshaphat, saying, Because thou hast joined thyself with Ahaziah, Jehovah hath destroyed thy works. And the ships were broken, so that they were not able to go to Tarshish.

2 Chronicles 21

21

^1And Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David: and Jehoram his son reigned in his stead. ^2And he had brethren, the sons of Jehoshaphat: Azariah, and Jehiel, and Zechariah, and Azariah, and Michael, and Shephatiah; all these were the sons of Jehoshaphat king of Israel. ^3And their father gave them great gifts, of silver, and of gold, and of precious things, with fortified cities in Judah: but the kingdom gave he to Jehoram, because he was the first-born. ^4Now when Jehoram was risen up over the kingdom of his father, and had strengthened himself, he slew all his brethren with the sword, and divers also of the princes of Israel. ^5Jehoram was thirty and two years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem. ^6And he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, as did the house of Ahab; for he had the daughter of Ahab to wife: and he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah. ^7Howbeit Jehovah would not destroy the house of David, because of the covenant that he had made with David, and as he promised to give a lamp to him and to his children alway. ^8In his days Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah, and made a king over themselves. ^9Then Jehoram passed over with his captains, and all his chariots with him: and he rose up by night, and smote the Edomites that compassed him about, and the captains of the chariots. ^10So Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah unto this day: then did Libnah revolt at the same time from under his hand, because he had forsaken Jehovah, the God of his fathers. ^11Moreover he made high places in the mountains of Judah, and made the inhabitants of Jerusalem to play the harlot, and led Judah astray. ^12And there came a writing to him from Elijah the prophet, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of David thy father, Because thou hast not walked in the ways of Jehoshaphat thy father, nor in the ways of Asa king of Judah, ^13but hast walked in the way of the kings of Israel, and hast made Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to play the harlot, like as the house of Ahab did, and also hast slain thy brethren of thy father's house, who were better than thyself: ^14behold, Jehovah will smite with a great plague thy people, and thy children, and thy wives, and all thy substance; ^15and thou shalt have great sickness by disease of thy bowels, until thy bowels fall out by reason of the sickness, day by day. ^16And Jehovah stirred up against Jehoram the spirit of the Philistines, and of the Arabians that are beside the Ethiopians: ^17and they came up against Judah, and brake into it, and carried away all the substance that was found in the king's house, and his sons also, and his wives; so that there was never a son left him, save Jehoahaz, the youngest of his sons. ^18And after all this Jehovah smote him in his bowels with an incurable disease. ^19And it came to pass, in process of time, at the end of two years, that his bowels fell out by reason of his sickness, and he died of sore diseases. And his people made no burning for him, like the burning of his fathers. ^20Thirty and two years old was he when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem eight years: and he departed without being desired; and they buried him in the city of David, but not in the sepulchres of the kings.

2 Chronicles 22

22

^1And the inhabitants of Jerusalem made Ahaziah his youngest son king in his stead; for the band of men that came with the Arabians to the camp had slain all the eldest. So Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah reigned. ^2Forty and two years old was Ahaziah when he began to reign; and he reigned one year in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Athaliah the daughter of Omri. ^3He also walked in the ways of the house of Ahab; for his mother was his counsellor to do wickedly. ^4And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, as did the house of Ahab; for they were his counsellors after the death of his father, to his destruction. ^5He walked also after their counsel, and went with Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth-gilead: and the Syrians wounded Joram. ^6And he returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds which they had given him at Ramah, when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. And Azariah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Jehoram the son of Ahab in Jezreel, because he was sick. ^7Now the destruction of Ahaziah was of God, in that he went unto Joram: for when he was come, he went out with Jehoram against Jehu the son of Nimshi, whom Jehovah had anointed to cut off the house of Ahab. ^8And it came to pass, when Jehu was executing judgment upon the house of Ahab, that he found the princes of Judah, and the sons of the brethren of Ahaziah, ministering to Ahaziah, and slew them. ^9And he sought Ahaziah, and they caught him (now he was hiding in Samaria), and they brought him to Jehu, and slew him; and they buried him, for they said, He is the son of Jehoshaphat, who sought Jehovah with all his heart. And the house of Ahaziah had no power to hold the kingdom. ^10Now when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the seed royal of the house of Judah. ^11But Jehoshabeath, the daughter of the king, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him away from among the king's sons that were slain, and put him and his nurse in the bedchamber. So Jehoshabeath, the daughter of king Jehoram, the wife of Jehoiada the priest (for she was the sister of Ahaziah), hid him from Athaliah, so that she slew him not. ^12And he was with them hid in the house of God six years: and Athaliah reigned over the land.

2 Chronicles 23

23

^1And in the seventh year Jehoiada strengthened himself, and took the captains of hundreds, Azariah the son of Jeroham, and Ishmael the son of Jehohanan, and Azariah the son of Obed, and Maaseiah the son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat the son of Zichri, into covenant with him. ^2And they went about in Judah, and gathered the Levites out of all the cities of Judah, and the heads of fathers' houses of Israel, and they came to Jerusalem. ^3And all the assembly made a covenant with the king in the house of God. And he said unto them, Behold, the king's son shall reign, as Jehovah hath spoken concerning the sons of David. ^4This is the thing that ye shall do: a third part of you, that come in on the sabbath, of the priests and of the Levites, shall be porters of the thresholds; ^5and a third part shall be at the king's house; and a third part at the gate of the foundation: and all the people shall be in the courts of the house of Jehovah. ^6But let none come into the house of Jehovah, save the priests, and they that minister of the Levites; they shall come in, for they are holy: but all the people shall keep the charge of Jehovah. ^7And the Levites shall compass the king round about, every man with his weapons in his hand; and whosoever cometh into the house, let him be slain: and be ye with the king when he cometh in, and when he goeth out. ^8So the Levites and all Judah did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded: and they took every man his men, those that were to come in on the sabbath; with those that were to go out on the sabbath; for Jehoiada the priest dismissed not the courses. ^9And Jehoiada the priest delivered to the captains of hundreds the spears, and bucklers, and shields, that had been king David's, which were in the house of God. ^10And he set all the people, every man with his weapon in his hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, along by the altar and the house, by the king round about. ^11Then they brought out the king's son, and put the crown upon him, and gave him the testimony, and made him king: and Jehoiada and his sons anointed him; and they said, Long live the king. ^12And when Athaliah heard the noise of the people running and praising the king, she came to the people into the house of Jehovah: ^13and she looked, and, behold, the king stood by his pillar at the entrance, and the captains and the trumpets by the king; and all the people of the land rejoiced, and blew trumpets; the singers also played on instruments of music, and led the singing of praise. Then Athaliah rent her clothes, and said, Treason! treason! ^14And Jehoiada the priest brought out the captains of hundreds that were set over the host, and said unto them, Have her forth between the ranks; and whoso followeth her, let him be slain with the sword: for the priest said, Slay her not in the house of Jehovah. ^15So they made way for her; and she went to the entrance of the horse gate to the king's house: and they slew her there. ^16And Jehoiada made a covenant between himself, and all the people, and the king, that they should be Jehovah's people. ^17And all the people went to the house of Baal, and brake it down, and brake his altars and his images in pieces, and slew Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. ^18And Jehoiada appointed the officers of the house of Jehovah under the hand of the priests the Levites, whom David had distributed in the house of Jehovah, to offer the burnt-offerings of Jehovah, as it is written in the law of Moses, with rejoicing and with singing, according to the order of David. ^19And he set the porters at the gates of the house of Jehovah, that none that was unclean in anything should enter in. ^20And he took the captains of hundreds, and the nobles, and the governors of the people, and all the people of the land, and brought down the king from the house of Jehovah: and they came through the upper gate unto the king's house, and set the king upon the throne of the kingdom. ^21So all the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was quiet. And Athaliah they had slain with the sword.

2 Chronicles 24

24

^1Joash was seven years old when he began to reign; and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Zibiah, of Beer-sheba. ^2And Joash did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah all the days of Jehoiada the priest. ^3And Jehoiada took for him two wives; and he begat sons and daughters. ^4And it came to pass after this, that Joash was minded to restore the house of Jehovah. ^5And he gathered together the priests and the Levites, and said to them, Go out unto the cities of Judah, and gather of all Israel money to repair the house of your God from year to year; and see that ye hasten the matter. Howbeit the Levites hastened it not. ^6And the king called for Jehoiada the chief, and said unto him, Why hast thou not required of the Levites to bring in out of Judah and out of Jerusalem the tax of Moses the servant of Jehovah, and of the assembly of Israel, for the tent of the testimony? ^7For the sons of Athaliah, that wicked woman, had broken up the house of God; and also all the dedicated things of the house of Jehovah did they bestow upon the Baalim. ^8So the king commanded, and they made a chest, and set it without at the gate of the house of Jehovah. ^9And they made a proclamation through Judah and Jerusalem, to bring in for Jehovah the tax that Moses the servant of God laid upon Israel in the wilderness. ^10And all the princes and all the people rejoiced, and brought in, and cast into the chest, until they had made an end. ^11And it was so, that, at what time the chest was brought unto the king's officers by the hand of the Levites, and when they saw that there was much money, the king's scribe and the chief priest's officer came and emptied the chest, and took it, and carried it to its place again. Thus they did day by day, and gathered money in abundance. ^12And the king and Jehoiada gave it to such as did the work of the service of the house of Jehovah; and they hired masons and carpenters to restore the house of Jehovah, and also such as wrought iron and brass to repair the house of Jehovah. ^13So the workmen wrought, and the work of repairing went forward in their hands, and they set up the house of God in its state, and strengthened it. ^14And when they had made an end, they brought the rest of the money before the king and Jehoiada, whereof were made vessels for the house of Jehovah, even vessels wherewith to minister and to offer, and spoons, and vessels of gold and silver. And they offered burnt-offerings in the house of Jehovah continually all the days of Jehoiada. ^15But Jehoiada waxed old and was full of days, and he died; a hundred and thirty years old was he when he died. ^16And they buried him in the city of David among the kings, because he had done good in Israel, and toward God and his house. ^17Now after the death of Jehoiada came the princes of Judah, and made obeisance to the king. Then the king hearkened unto them. ^18And they forsook the house of Jehovah, the God of their fathers, and served the Asherim and the idols: and wrath came upon Judah and Jerusalem for this their guiltiness. ^19Yet he sent prophets to them, to bring them again unto Jehovah; and they testified against them: but they would not give ear. ^20And the Spirit of God came upon Zechariah the son of Jehoiada the priest; and he stood above the people, and said unto them, Thus saith God, Why transgress ye the commandments of Jehovah, so that ye cannot prosper? because ye have forsaken Jehovah, he hath also forsaken you. ^21And they conspired against him, and stoned him with stones at the commandment of the king in the court of the house of Jehovah. ^22Thus Joash the king remembered not the kindness which Jehoiada his father had done to him, but slew his son. And when he died, he said, Jehovah look upon it, and require it. ^23And it came to pass at the end of the year, that the army of the Syrians came up against him: and they came to Judah and Jerusalem, and destroyed all the princes of the people from among the people, and sent all the spoil of them unto the king of Damascus. ^24For the army of the Syrians came with a small company of men; and Jehovah delivered a very great host into their hand, because they had forsaken Jehovah, the God of their fathers. So they executed judgment upon Joash. ^25And when they were departed for him (for they left him very sick), his own servants conspired against him for the blood of the sons of Jehoiada the priest, and slew him on his bed, and he died; and they buried him in the city of David, but they buried him not in the sepulchres of the kings. ^26And these are they that conspired against him: Zabad the son of Shimeath the Ammonitess, and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith the Moabitess. ^27Now concerning his sons, and the greatness of the burdens laid upon him, and the rebuilding of the house of God, behold, they are written in the commentary of the book of the kings. And Amaziah his son reigned in his stead.

2 Chronicles 25

25

^1Amaziah was twenty and five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty and nine years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Jehoaddan, of Jerusalem. ^2And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, but not with a perfect heart. ^3Now it came to pass, when the kingdom was established unto him, that he slew his servants that had killed the king his father. ^4But he put not their children to death, but did according to that which is written in the law in the book of Moses, as Jehovah commanded, saying, The fathers shall not die for the children, neither shall the children die for the fathers; but every man shall die for his own sin. ^5Moreover Amaziah gathered Judah together, and ordered them according to their fathers' houses, under captains of thousands and captains of hundreds, even all Judah and Benjamin: and he numbered them from twenty years old and upward, and found them three hundred thousand chosen men, able to go forth to war, that could handle spear and shield. ^6He hired also a hundred thousand mighty men of valor out of Israel for a hundred talents of silver. ^7But there came a man of God to him, saying, O king, let not the army of Israel go with thee; for Jehovah is not with Israel, to wit, with all the children of Ephraim. ^8But if thou wilt go, do valiantly, be strong for the battle: God will cast thee down before the enemy; for God hath power to help, and to cast down. ^9And Amaziah said to the man of God, But what shall we do for the hundred talents which I have given to the army of Israel? And the man of God answered, Jehovah is able to give thee much more than this. ^10Then Amaziah separated them, to wit, the army that was come to him out of Ephraim, to go home again: wherefore their anger was greatly kindled against Judah, and they returned home in fierce anger. ^11And Amaziah took courage, and led forth his people, and went to the Valley of Salt, and smote of the children of Seir ten thousand. ^12And other ten thousand did the children of Judah carry away alive, and brought them unto the top of the rock, and cast them down from the top of the rock, so that they all were broken in pieces. ^13But the men of the army whom Amaziah sent back, that they should not go with him to battle, fell upon the cities of Judah, from Samaria even unto Beth-horon, and smote of them three thousand, and took much spoil. ^14Now it came to pass, after that Amaziah was come from the slaughter of the Edomites, that he brought the gods of the children of Seir, and set them up to be his gods, and bowed down himself before them, and burned incense unto them. ^15Wherefore the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Amaziah, and he sent unto him a prophet, who said unto him, Why hast thou sought after the gods of the people, which have not delivered their own people out of thy hand? ^16And it came to pass, as he talked with him, that the king said unto him, Have we made thee of the king's counsel? forbear; why shouldest thou be smitten? Then the prophet forbare, and said, I know that God hath determined to destroy thee, because thou hast done this, and hast not hearkened unto my counsel. ^17Then Amaziah king of Judah took advice, and sent to Joash, the son of Jehoahaz the son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, Come, let us look one another in the face. ^18And Joash king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, The thistle that was in Lebanon sent to the cedar that was in Lebanon, saying, Give thy daughter to my son to wife: and there passed by a wild beast that was in Lebanon, and trod down the thistle. ^19Thou sayest, Lo, thou hast smitten Edom; and thy heart lifteth thee up to boast: abide now at home; why shouldest thou meddle to thy hurt, that thou shouldest fall, even thou, and Judah with thee? ^20But Amaziah would not hear; for it was of God, that he might deliver them into the hand of their enemies, because they had sought after the gods of Edom. ^21So Joash king of Israel went up; and he and Amaziah king of Judah looked one another in the face at Beth-shemesh, which belongeth to Judah. ^22And Judah was put to the worse before Israel; and they fled every man to his tent. ^23And Joash king of Israel took Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Joash the son of Jehoahaz, at Beth-shemesh, and brought him to Jerusalem, and brake down the wall of Jerusalem from the gate of Ephraim unto the corner gate, four hundred cubits. ^24And he took all the gold and silver, and all the vessels that were found in the house of God with Obed-edom, and the treasures of the king's house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria. ^25And Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah lived after the death of Joash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel fifteen years. ^26Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, first and last, behold, are they not written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel? ^27Now from the time that Amaziah did turn away from following Jehovah they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem; and he fled to Lachish: but they sent after him to Lachish, and slew him there. ^28And they brought him upon horses, and buried him with his fathers in the city of Judah.

2 Chronicles 26

26

^1And all the people of Judah took Uzziah, who was sixteen years old, and made him king in the room of his father Amaziah. ^2He built Eloth, and restored it to Judah, after that the king slept with his fathers. ^3Sixteen years old was Uzziah when he began to reign; and he reigned fifty and two years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Jechiliah, of Jerusalem. ^4And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that his father Amaziah had done. ^5And he set himself to seek God in the days of Zechariah, who had understanding in the vision of God: and as long as he sought Jehovah, God made him to prosper. ^6And he went forth and warred against the Philistines, and brake down the wall of Gath, and the wall of Jabneh, and the wall of Ashdod; and he built cities in the country of Ashdod, and among the Philistines. ^7And God helped him against the Philistines, and against the Arabians that dwelt in Gur-baal, and the Meunim. ^8And the Ammonites gave tribute to Uzziah: and his name spread abroad even to the entrance of Egypt; for he waxed exceeding strong. ^9Moreover Uzziah built towers in Jerusalem at the corner gate, and at the valley gate, and at the turning of the wall, and fortified them. ^10And he built towers in the wilderness, and hewed out many cisterns, for he had much cattle; in the lowland also, and in the plain: and he had husbandmen and vinedressers in the mountains and in the fruitful fields; for he loved husbandry. ^11Moreover Uzziah had an army of fighting men, that went out to war by bands, according to the number of their reckoning made by Jeiel the scribe and Maaseiah the officer, under the hand of Hananiah, one of the king's captains. ^12The whole number of the heads of fathers' houses, even the mighty men of valor, was two thousand and six hundred. ^13And under their hand was an army, three hundred thousand and seven thousand and five hundred, that made war with mighty power, to help the king against the enemy. ^14And Uzziah prepared for them, even for all the host, shields, and spears, and helmets, and coats of mail, and bows, and stones for slinging. ^15And he made in Jerusalem engines, invented by skilful men, to be on the towers and upon the battlements, wherewith to shoot arrows and great stones. And his name spread far abroad; for he was marvellously helped, till he was strong. ^16But when he was strong, his heart was lifted up, so that he did corruptly, and he trespassed against Jehovah his God; for he went into the temple of Jehovah to burn incense upon the altar of incense. ^17And Azariah the priest went in after him, and with him fourscore priests of Jehovah, that were valiant men: ^18and they withstood Uzziah the king, and said unto him, It pertaineth not unto thee, Uzziah, to burn incense unto Jehovah, but to the priests the sons of Aaron, that are consecrated to burn incense: go out of the sanctuary; for thou hast trespassed; neither shall it be for thine honor from Jehovah God. ^19Then Uzziah was wroth; and he had a censer in his hand to burn incense; and while he was wroth with the priests, the leprosy brake forth in his forehead before the priests in the house of Jehovah, beside the altar of incense. ^20And Azariah the chief priest, and all the priests, looked upon him, and, behold, he was leprous in his forehead, and they thrust him out quickly from thence; yea, himself hasted also to go out, because Jehovah had smitten him. ^21And Uzziah the king was a leper unto the day of his death, and dwelt in a separate house, being a leper; for he was cut off from the house of Jehovah: and Jotham his son was over the king's house, judging the people of the land. ^22Now the rest of the acts of Uzziah, first and last, did Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, write. ^23So Uzziah slept with his fathers; and they buried him with his fathers in the field of burial which belonged to the kings; for they said, He is a leper: and Jotham his son reigned in his stead.

2 Chronicles 27

27

^1Jotham was twenty and five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Jerushah the daughter of Zadok. ^2And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that his father Uzziah had done: howbeit he entered not into the temple of Jehovah. And the people did yet corruptly. ^3He built the upper gate of the house of Jehovah, and on the wall of Ophel he built much. ^4Moreover he built cities in the hill-country of Judah, and in the forests he built castles and towers. ^5He fought also with the king of the children of Ammon, and prevailed against them. And the children of Ammon gave him the same year a hundred talents of silver, and ten thousand measures of wheat, and ten thousand of barley. So much did the children of Ammon render unto him, in the second year also, and in the third. ^6So Jotham became mighty, because he ordered his ways before Jehovah his God. ^7Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all his wars, and his ways, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. ^8He was five and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. ^9And Jotham slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David: and Ahaz his son reigned in his stead.

2 Chronicles 28

28

^1Ahaz was twenty years old when he began to reign; and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem: and he did not that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, like David his father; ^2but he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel, and made also molten images for the Baalim. ^3Moreover he burnt incense in the valley of the son of Hinnom, and burnt his children in the fire, according to the abominations of the nations whom Jehovah cast out before the children of Israel. ^4And he sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places, and on the hills, and under every green tree. ^5Wherefore Jehovah his God delivered him into the hand of the king of Syria; and they smote him, and carried away of his a great multitude of captives, and brought them to Damascus. And he was also delivered into the hand of the king of Israel, who smote him with a great slaughter. ^6For Pekah the son of Remaliah slew in Judah a hundred and twenty thousand in one day, all of them valiant men; because they had forsaken Jehovah, the God of their fathers. ^7And Zichri, a mighty man of Ephraim, slew Maaseiah the king's son, and Azrikam the ruler of the house, and Elkanah that was next to the king. ^8And the children of Israel carried away captive of their brethren two hundred thousand, women, sons, and daughters, and took also away much spoil from them, and brought the spoil to Samaria. ^9But a prophet of Jehovah was there, whose name was Oded: and he went out to meet the host that came to Samaria, and said unto them, Behold, because Jehovah, the God of your fathers, was wroth with Judah, he hath delivered them into your hand, and ye have slain them in a rage which hath reached up to heaven. ^10And now ye purpose to keep under the children of Judah and Jerusalem for bondmen and bondwomen unto you: but are there not even with you trespasses of your own against Jehovah your God? ^11Now hear me therefore, and send back the captives, that ye have taken captive of your brethren; for the fierce wrath of Jehovah is upon you. ^12Then certain of the heads of the children of Ephraim, Azariah the son of Johanan, Berechiah the son of Meshillemoth, and Jehizkiah the son of Shallum, and Amasa the son of Hadlai, stood up against them that came from the war, ^13and said unto them, Ye shall not bring in the captives hither: for ye purpose that which will bring upon us a trespass against Jehovah, to add unto our sins and to our trespass; for our trespass is great, and there is fierce wrath against Israel. ^14So the armed men left the captives and the spoil before the princes and all the assembly. ^15And the men that have been mentioned by name rose up, and took the captives, and with the spoil clothed all that were naked among them, and arrayed them, and shod them, and gave them to eat and to drink, and anointed them, and carried all the feeble of them upon asses, and brought them to Jericho, the city of palm-trees, unto their brethren: then they returned to Samaria. ^16At that time did king Ahaz send unto the kings of Assyria to help him. ^17For again the Edomites had come and smitten Judah, and carried away captives. ^18The Philistines also had invaded the cities of the lowland, and of the South of Judah, and had taken Beth-shemesh, and Aijalon, and Gederoth, and Soco with the towns thereof, and Timnah with the towns thereof, Gimzo also and the towns thereof: and they dwelt there. ^19For Jehovah brought Judah low because of Ahaz king of Israel; for he had dealt wantonly in Judah, and trespassed sore against Jehovah. ^20And Tilgath-pilneser king of Assyria came unto him, and distressed him, but strengthened him not. ^21For Ahaz took away a portion out of the house of Jehovah, and out of the house of the king and of the princes, and gave it unto the king of Assyria: but it helped him not. ^22And in the time of his distress did he trespass yet more against Jehovah, this same king Ahaz. ^23For he sacrificed unto the gods of Damascus, which smote him; and he said, Because the gods of the kings of Syria helped them, therefore will I sacrifice to them, that they may help me. But they were the ruin of him, and of all Israel. ^24And Ahaz gathered together the vessels of the house of God, and cut in pieces the vessels of the house of God, and shut up the doors of the house of Jehovah; and he made him altars in every corner of Jerusalem. ^25And in every city of Judah he made high places to burn incense unto other gods, and provoked to anger Jehovah, the God of his fathers. ^26Now the rest of his acts, and all his ways, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. ^27And Ahaz slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city, even in Jerusalem; for they brought him not into the sepulchres of the kings of Israel: and Hezekiah his son reigned in his stead.

2 Chronicles 29

29

^1Hezekiah began to reign when he was five and twenty years old; and he reigned nine and twenty years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Abijah, the daughter of Zechariah. ^2And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that David his father had done. ^3He in the first year of his reign, in the first month, opened the doors of the house of Jehovah, and repaired them. ^4And he brought in the priests and the Levites, and gathered them together into the broad place on the east, ^5and said unto them, Hear me, ye Levites; now sanctify yourselves, and sanctify the house of Jehovah, the God of your fathers, and carry forth the filthiness out of the holy place. ^6For our fathers have trespassed, and done that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah our God, and have forsaken him, and have turned away their faces from the habitation of Jehovah, and turned their backs. ^7Also they have shut up the doors of the porch, and put out the lamps, and have not burned incense nor offered burnt-offerings in the holy place unto the God of Israel. ^8Wherefore the wrath of Jehovah was upon Judah and Jerusalem, and he hath delivered them to be tossed to and fro, to be an astonishment, and a hissing, as ye see with your eyes. ^9For, lo, our fathers have fallen by the sword, and our sons and our daughters and our wives are in captivity for this. ^10Now it is in my heart to make a covenant with Jehovah, the God of Israel, that his fierce anger may turn away from us. ^11My sons, be not now negligent; for Jehovah hath chosen you to stand before him, to minister unto him, and that ye should be his ministers, and burn incense. ^12Then the Levites arose, Mahath, the son of Amasai, and Joel the son of Azariah, of the sons of the Kohathites; and of the sons of Merari, Kish the son of Abdi, and Azariah the son of Jehallelel; and of the Gershonites, Joah the son of Zimmah, and Eden the son of Joah; ^13and of the sons of Elizaphan, Shimri and Jeuel; and of the sons of Asaph, Zechariah and Mattaniah; ^14and of the sons of Heman, Jehuel and Shimei; and of the sons of Jeduthun, Shemaiah and Uzziel. ^15And they gathered their brethren, and sanctified themselves, and went in, according to the commandment of the king by the words of Jehovah, to cleanse the house of Jehovah. ^16And the priests went in unto the inner part of the house of Jehovah, to cleanse it, and brought out all the uncleanness that they found in the temple of Jehovah into the court of the house of Jehovah. And the Levites took it, to carry it out abroad to the brook Kidron. ^17Now they began on the first day of the first month to sanctify, and on the eighth day of the month came they to the porch of Jehovah; and they sanctified the house of Jehovah in eight days: and on the sixteenth day of the first month they made an end. ^18Then they went in to Hezekiah the king within the palace, and said, We have cleansed all the house of Jehovah, and the altar of burnt-offering, with all the vessels thereof, and the table of showbread, with all the vessels thereof. ^19Moreover all the vessels, which king Ahaz in his reign did cast away when he trespassed, have we prepared and sanctified; and, behold, they are before the altar of Jehovah. ^20Then Hezekiah the king arose early, and gathered the princes of the city, and went up to the house of Jehovah. ^21And they brought seven bullocks, and seven rams, and seven lambs, and seven he-goats, for a sin-offering for the kingdom and for the sanctuary and for Judah. And he commanded the priests the sons of Aaron to offer them on the altar of Jehovah. ^22So they killed the bullocks, and the priests received the blood, and sprinkled it on the altar: and they killed the rams, and sprinkled the blood upon the altar: they killed also the lambs, and sprinkled the blood upon the altar. ^23And they brought near the he-goats for the sin-offering before the king and the assembly; and they laid their hands upon them: ^24and the priests killed them, and they made a sin-offering with their blood upon the altar, to make atonement for all Israel; for the king commanded that the burnt-offering and the sin-offering should be made for all Israel. ^25And he set the Levites in the house of Jehovah with cymbals, with psalteries, and with harps, according to the commandment of David, and of Gad the king's seer, and Nathan the prophet; for the commandment was of Jehovah by his prophets. ^26And the Levites stood with the instruments of David, and the priests with the trumpets. ^27And Hezekiah commanded to offer the burnt-offering upon the altar. And when the burnt-offering began, the song of Jehovah began also, and the trumpets, together with the instruments of David king of Israel. ^28And all the assembly worshipped, and the singers sang, and the trumpeters sounded; all this continued until the burnt-offering was finished. ^29And when they had made an end of offering, the king and all that were present with him bowed themselves and worshipped. ^30Moreover Hezekiah the king and the princes commanded the Levites to sing praises unto Jehovah with the words of David, and of Asaph the seer. And they sang praises with gladness, and they bowed their heads and worshipped. ^31Then Hezekiah answered and said, Now ye have consecrated yourselves unto Jehovah; come near and bring sacrifices and thank-offerings into the house of Jehovah. And the assembly brought in sacrifices and thank-offerings; and as many as were of a willing heart brought burnt-offerings. ^32And the number of the burnt-offerings which the assembly brought was threescore and ten bullocks, a hundred rams, and two hundred lambs: all these were for a burnt-offering to Jehovah. ^33And the consecrated things were six hundred oxen and three thousand sheep. ^34But the priests were too few, so that they could not flay all the burnt-offerings: wherefore their brethren the Levites did help them, till the work was ended, and until the priests had sanctified themselves; for the Levites were more upright in heart to sanctify themselves than the priests. ^35And also the burnt-offerings were in abundance, with the fat of the peace-offerings, and with the drink-offerings for every burnt-offering. So the service of the house of Jehovah was set in order. ^36And Hezekiah rejoiced, and all the people, because of that which God had prepared for the people: for the thing was done suddenly.

2 Chronicles 30

30

^1And Hezekiah sent to all Israel and Judah, and wrote letters also to Ephraim and Manasseh, that they should come to the house of Jehovah at Jerusalem, to keep the passover unto Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^2For the king had taken counsel, and his princes, and all the assembly in Jerusalem, to keep the passover in the second month. ^3For they could not keep it at that time, because the priests had not sanctified themselves in sufficient number, neither had the people gathered themselves together to Jerusalem. ^4And the thing was right in the eyes of the king and of all the assembly. ^5So they established a decree to make proclamation throughout all Israel, from Beer-sheba even to Dan, that they should come to keep the passover unto Jehovah, the God of Israel, at Jerusalem: for they had not kept it in great numbers in such sort as it is written. ^6So the posts went with the letters from the king and his princes throughout all Israel and Judah, and according to the commandment of the king, saying, Ye children of Israel, turn again unto Jehovah, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, that he may return to the remnant that are escaped of you out of the hand of the kings of Assyria. ^7And be not ye like your fathers, and like your brethren, who trespassed against Jehovah, the God of their fathers, so that he gave them up to desolation, as ye see. ^8Now be ye not stiffnecked, as your fathers were; but yield yourselves unto Jehovah, and enter into his sanctuary, which he hath sanctified for ever, and serve Jehovah your God, that his fierce anger may turn away from you. ^9For if ye turn again unto Jehovah, your brethren and your children shall find compassion before them that led them captive, and shall come again into this land: for Jehovah your God is gracious and merciful, and will not turn away his face from you, if ye return unto him. ^10So the posts passed from city to city through the country of Ephraim and Manasseh, even unto Zebulun: but they laughed them to scorn, and mocked them. ^11Nevertheless certain men of Asher and Manasseh and of Zebulun humbled themselves, and came to Jerusalem. ^12Also upon Judah came the hand of God to give them one heart, to do the commandment of the king and of the princes by the word of Jehovah. ^13And there assembled at Jerusalem much people to keep the feast of unleavened bread in the second month, a very great assembly. ^14And they arose and took away the altars that were in Jerusalem, and all the altars for incense took they away, and cast them into the brook Kidron. ^15Then they killed the passover on the fourteenth day of the second month: and the priests and the Levites were ashamed, and sanctified themselves, and brought burnt-offerings into the house of Jehovah. ^16And they stood in their place after their order, according to the law of Moses the man of God: the priests sprinkled the blood which they received of the hand of the Levites. ^17For there were many in the assembly that had not sanctified themselves: therefore the Levites had the charge of killing the passovers for every one that was not clean, to sanctify them unto Jehovah. ^18For a multitude of the people, even many of Ephraim and Manasseh, Issachar and Zebulun, had not cleansed themselves, yet did they eat the passover otherwise than it is written. For Hezekiah had prayed for them, saying, The good Jehovah pardon every one ^19that setteth his heart to seek God, Jehovah, the God of his fathers, though he be not cleansed according to the purification of the sanctuary. ^20And Jehovah hearkened to Hezekiah, and healed the people. ^21And the children of Israel that were present at Jerusalem kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with great gladness; and the Levites and the priests praised Jehovah day by day, singing with loud instruments unto Jehovah. ^22And Hezekiah spake comfortably unto all the Levites that had good understanding in the service of Jehovah. So they did eat throughout the feast for the seven days, offering sacrifices of peace-offerings, and making confession to Jehovah, the God of their fathers. ^23And the whole assembly took counsel to keep other seven days; and they kept other seven days with gladness. ^24For Hezekiah king of Judah did give to the assembly for offerings a thousand bullocks and seven thousand sheep; and the princes gave to the assembly a thousand bullocks and ten thousand sheep: and a great number of priests sanctified themselves. ^25And all the assembly of Judah, with the priests and the Levites, and all the assembly that came out of Israel, and the sojourners that came out of the land of Israel, and that dwelt in Judah, rejoiced. ^26So there was great joy in Jerusalem; for since the time of Solomon the son of David king of Israel there was not the like in Jerusalem. ^27Then the priests the Levites arose and blessed the people: and their voice was heard, and their prayer came up to his holy habitation, even unto heaven.

2 Chronicles 31

31

^1Now when all this was finished, all Israel that were present went out to the cities of Judah, and brake in pieces the pillars, and hewed down the Asherim, and brake down the high places and the altars out of all Judah and Benjamin, in Ephraim also and Manasseh, until they had destroyed them all. Then all the children of Israel returned, every man to his possession, into their own cities. ^2And Hezekiah appointed the courses of the priests and the Levites after their courses, every man according to his service, both the priests and the Levites, for burnt-offerings and for peace-offerings, to minister, and to give thanks, and to praise in the gates of the camp of Jehovah. ^3He appointed also the king's portion of his substance for the burnt-offerings, to wit, for the morning and evening burnt-offerings, and the burnt-offerings for the sabbaths, and for the new moons, and for the set feasts, as it is written in the law of Jehovah. ^4Moreover he commanded the people that dwelt in Jerusalem to give the portion of the priests and the Levites, that they might give themselves to the law of Jehovah. ^5And as soon as the commandment came abroad, the children of Israel gave in abundance the first-fruits of grain, new wine, and oil, and honey, and of all the increase of the field; and the tithe of all things brought they in abundantly. ^6And the children of Israel and Judah, that dwelt in the cities of Judah, they also brought in the tithe of oxen and sheep, and the tithe of dedicated things which were consecrated unto Jehovah their God, and laid them by heaps. ^7In the third month they began to lay the foundation of the heaps, and finished them in the seventh month. ^8And when Hezekiah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they blessed Jehovah, and his people Israel. ^9Then Hezekiah questioned the priests and the Levites concerning the heaps. ^10And Azariah the chief priest, of the house of Zadok, answered him and said, Since the people began to bring the oblations into the house of Jehovah, we have eaten and had enough, and have left plenty: for Jehovah hath blessed his people; and that which is left is this great store. ^11Then Hezekiah commanded to prepare chambers in the house of Jehovah; and they prepared them. ^12And they brought in the oblations and the tithes and the dedicated things faithfully: and over them Conaniah the Levite was ruler, and Shimei his brother was second. ^13And Jehiel, and Azaziah, and Nahath, and Asahel, and Jerimoth, and Jozabad, and Eliel, and Ismachiah, and Mahath, and Benaiah, were overseers under the hand of Conaniah and Shimei his brother, by the appointment of Hezekiah the king, and Azariah the ruler of the house of God. ^14And Kore the son of Imnah the Levite, the porter at the east gate, was over the freewill-offerings of God, to distribute the oblations of Jehovah, and the most holy things. ^15And under him were Eden, and Miniamin, and Jeshua, and Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah, in the cities of the priests, in their office of trust, to give to their brethren by courses, as well to the great as to the small: ^16besides them that were reckoned by genealogy of males, from three years old and upward, even every one that entered into the house of Jehovah, as the duty of every day required, for their service in their offices according to their courses; ^17and them that were reckoned by genealogy of the priests by their fathers' houses, and the Levites from twenty years old and upward, in their offices by their courses; ^18and them that were reckoned by genealogy of all their little ones, their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, through all the congregation: for in their office of trust they sanctified themselves in holiness. ^19Also for the sons of Aaron the priests, that were in the fields of the suburbs of their cities, in every city, there were men that were mentioned by name, to give portions to all the males among the priests, and to all that were reckoned by genealogy among the Levites. ^20And thus did Hezekiah throughout all Judah; and he wrought that which was good and right and faithful before Jehovah his God. ^21And in every work that he began in the service of the house of God, and in the law, and in the commandments, to seek his God, he did it with all his heart, and prospered.

2 Chronicles 32

32

^1After these things, and this faithfulness, Sennacherib king of Assyria came, and entered into Judah, and encamped against the fortified cities, and thought to win them for himself. ^2And when Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib was come, and that he was purposed to fight against Jerusalem, ^3he took counsel with his princes and his mighty men to stop the waters of the fountains which were without the city; and they helped him. ^4So there was gathered much people together, and they stopped all the fountains, and the brook that flowed through the midst of the land, saying, Why should the kings of Assyria come, and find much water? ^5And he took courage, and built up all the wall that was broken down, and raised it up to the towers, and the other wall without, and strengthened Millo in the city of David, and made weapons and shields in abundance. ^6And he set captains of war over the people, and gathered them together to him in the broad place at the gate of the city, and spake comfortably to them, saying, ^7Be strong and of good courage, be not afraid nor dismayed for the king of Assyria, nor for all the multitude that is with him; for there is a greater with us than with him: ^8with him is an arm of flesh; but with us is Jehovah our God to help us, and to fight our battles. And the people rested themselves upon the words of Hezekiah king of Judah. ^9After this did Sennacherib king of Assyria send his servants to Jerusalem, (now he was before Lachish, and all his power with him,) unto Hezekiah king of Judah, and unto all Judah that were at Jerusalem, saying, ^10Thus saith Sennacherib king of Assyria, Whereon do ye trust, that ye abide the siege in Jerusalem? ^11Doth not Hezekiah persuade you, to give you over to die by famine and by thirst, saying, Jehovah our God will deliver us out of the hand of the king of Assyria? ^12Hath not the same Hezekiah taken away his high places and his altars, and commanded Judah and Jerusalem, saying, Ye shall worship before one altar, and upon it shall ye burn incense? ^13Know ye not what I and my fathers have done unto all the peoples of the lands? Were the gods of the nations of the lands in any wise able to deliver their land out of my hand? ^14Who was there among all the gods of those nations which my fathers utterly destroyed, that could deliver his people out of my hand, that your God should be able to deliver you out of my hand? ^15Now therefore let not Hezekiah deceive you, nor persuade you after this manner, neither believe ye him; for no god of any nation or kingdom was able to deliver his people out of my hand, and out of the hand of my fathers: how much less shall your God deliver you out of my hand? ^16And his servants spake yet more against Jehovah God, and against his servant Hezekiah. ^17He wrote also letters, to rail on Jehovah, the God of Israel, and to speak against him, saying, As the gods of the nations of the lands, which have not delivered their people out of my hand, so shall not the God of Hezekiah deliver his people out of my hand. ^18And they cried with a loud voice in the Jews' language unto the people of Jerusalem that were on the wall, to affright them, and to trouble them; that they might take the city. ^19And they spake of the God of Jerusalem, as of the gods of the peoples of the earth, which are the work of men's hands. ^20And Hezekiah the king, and Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz, prayed because of this, and cried to heaven. ^21And Jehovah sent an angel, who cut off all the mighty men of valor, and the leaders and captains, in the camp of the king of Assyria. So he returned with shame of face to his own land. And when he was come into the house of his god, they that came forth from his own bowels slew him there with the sword. ^22Thus Jehovah saved Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of Sennacherib the king of Assyria, and from the hand of all others, and guided them on every side. ^23And many brought gifts unto Jehovah to Jerusalem, and precious things to Hezekiah king of Judah; so that he was exalted in the sight of all nations from thenceforth. ^24In those days Hezekiah was sick even unto death: and he prayed unto Jehovah; and he spake unto him, and gave him a sign. ^25But Hezekiah rendered not again according to the benefit done unto him; for his heart was lifted up: therefore there was wrath upon him, and upon Judah and Jerusalem. ^26Notwithstanding Hezekiah humbled himself for the pride of his heart, both he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the wrath of Jehovah came not upon them in the days of Hezekiah. ^27And Hezekiah had exceeding much riches and honor: and he provided him treasuries for silver, and for gold, and for precious stones, and for spices, and for shields, and for all manner of goodly vessels; ^28store-houses also for the increase of grain and new wine and oil; and stalls for all manner of beasts, and flocks in folds. ^29Moreover he provided him cities, and possessions of flocks and herds in abundance; for God had given him very much substance. ^30This same Hezekiah also stopped the upper spring of the waters of Gihon, and brought them straight down on the west side of the city of David. And Hezekiah prospered in all his works. ^31Howbeit in the business of the ambassadors of the princes of Babylon, who sent unto him to inquire of the wonder that was done in the land, God left him, to try him, that he might know all that was in his heart. ^32Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and his good deeds, behold, they are written in the vision of Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz, in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. ^33And Hezekiah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the ascent of the sepulchres of the sons of David: and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem did him honor at his death. And Manasseh his son reigned in his stead.

2 Chronicles 33

33

^1Manasseh was twelve years old when he began to reign; and he reigned fifty and five years in Jerusalem. ^2And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, after the abominations of the nations whom Jehovah cast out before the children of Israel. ^3For he built again the high places which Hezekiah his father had broken down; and he reared up altars for the Baalim, and made Asheroth, and worshipped all the host of heaven, and served them. ^4And he built altars in the house of Jehovah, whereof Jehovah said, In Jerusalem shall my name be for ever. ^5And he built altars for all the host of heaven in the two courts of the house of Jehovah. ^6He also made his children to pass through the fire in the valley of the son of Hinnom; and he practised augury, and used enchantments, and practised sorcery, and dealt with them that had familiar spirits, and with wizards: he wrought much evil in the sight of Jehovah, to provoke him to anger. ^7And he set the graven image of the idol, which he had made, in the house of God, of which God said to David and to Solomon his son, In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, will I put my name for ever: ^8neither will I any more remove the foot of Israel from off the land which I have appointed for your fathers, if only they will observe to do all that I have commanded them, even all the law and the statutes and the ordinances given by Moses. ^9And Manasseh seduced Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that they did evil more than did the nations whom Jehovah destroyed before the children of Israel. ^10And Jehovah spake to Manasseh, and to his people; but they gave no heed. ^11Wherefore Jehovah brought upon them the captains of the host of the king of Assyria, who took Manasseh in chains, and bound him with fetters, and carried him to Babylon. ^12And when he was in distress, he besought Jehovah his God, and humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers. ^13And he prayed unto him; and he was entreated of him, and heard his supplication, and brought him again to Jerusalem into his kingdom. Then Manasseh knew that Jehovah he was God. ^14Now after this he built an outer wall to the city of David, on the west side of Gihon, in the valley, even to the entrance at the fish gate; and he compassed Ophel about with it, and raised it up to a very great height: and he put valiant captains in all the fortified cities of Judah. ^15And he took away the foreign gods, and the idol out of the house of Jehovah, and all the altars that he had built in the mount of the house of Jehovah, and in Jerusalem, and cast them out of the city. ^16And he built up the altar of Jehovah, and offered thereon sacrifices of peace-offerings and of thanksgiving, and commanded Judah to serve Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^17Nevertheless the people sacrificed still in the high places, but only unto Jehovah their God. ^18Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and his prayer unto his God, and the words of the seers that spake to him in the name of Jehovah, the God of Israel, behold, they are written among the acts of the kings of Israel. ^19His prayer also, and how God was entreated of him, and all his sin and his trespass, and the places wherein he built high places, and set up the Asherim and the graven images, before he humbled himself: behold, they are written in the history of Hozai. ^20So Manasseh slept with his fathers, and they buried him in his own house: and Amon his son reigned in his stead. ^21Amon was twenty and two years old when he began to reign; and he reigned two years in Jerusalem. ^22And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, as did Manasseh his father; and Amon sacrificed unto all the graven images which Manasseh his father had made, and served them. ^23And he humbled not himself before Jehovah, as Manasseh his father had humbled himself; but this same Amon trespassed more and more. ^24And his servants conspired against him, and put him to death in his own house. ^25But the people of the land slew all them that had conspired against king Amon; and the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his stead.

2 Chronicles 34

34

^1Josiah was eight years old when he began to reign; and he reigned thirty and one years in Jerusalem. ^2And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, and walked in the ways of David his father, and turned not aside to the right hand or to the left. ^3For in the eighth year of his reign, while he was yet young, he began to seek after the God of David his father; and in the twelfth year he began to purge Judah and Jerusalem from the high places, and the Asherim, and the graven images, and the molten images. ^4And they brake down the altars of the Baalim in his presence; and the sun-images that were on high above them he hewed down; and the Asherim, and the graven images, and the molten images, he brake in pieces, and made dust of them, and strewed it upon the graves of them that had sacrificed unto them. ^5And he burnt the bones of the priests upon their altars, and purged Judah and Jerusalem. ^6And so did he in the cities of Manasseh and Ephraim and Simeon, even unto Naphtali, in their ruins round about. ^7And he brake down the altars, and beat the Asherim and the graven images into powder, and hewed down all the sun-images throughout all the land of Israel, and returned to Jerusalem. ^8Now in the eighteenth year of his reign, when he had purged the land and the house, he sent Shaphan the son of Azaliah, and Maaseiah the governor of the city, and Joah the son of Joahaz the recorder, to repair the house of Jehovah his God. ^9And they came to Hilkiah the high priest, and delivered the money that was brought into the house of God, which the Levites, the keepers of the threshold, had gathered of the hand of Manasseh and Ephraim, and of all the remnant of Israel, and of all Judah and Benjamin, and of the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^10And they delivered it into the hand of the workmen that had the oversight of the house of Jehovah; and the workmen that wrought in the house of Jehovah gave it to mend and repair the house; ^11even to the carpenters and to the builders gave they it, to buy hewn stone, and timber for couplings, and to make beams for the houses which the kings of Judah had destroyed. ^12And the men did the work faithfully: and the overseers of them were Jahath and Obadiah, the Levites, of the sons of Merari; and Zechariah and Meshullam, of the sons of the Kohathites, to set it forward; and others of the Levites, all that were skilful with instruments of music. ^13Also they were over the bearers of burdens, and set forward all that did the work in every manner of service: and of the Levites there were scribes, and officers, and porters. ^14And when they brought out the money that was brought into the house of Jehovah, Hilkiah the priest found the book of the law of Jehovah given by Moses. ^15And Hilkiah answered and said to Shaphan the scribe, I have found the book of the law in the house of Jehovah. And Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan. ^16And Shaphan carried the book to the king, and moreover brought back word to the king, saying, All that was committed to thy servants, they are doing. ^17And they have emptied out the money that was found in the house of Jehovah, and have delivered it into the hand of the overseers, and into the hand of the workmen. ^18And Shaphan the scribe told the king, saying, Hilkiah the priest hath delivered me a book. And Shaphan read therein before the king. ^19And it came to pass, when the king had heard the words of the law, that he rent his clothes. ^20And the king commanded Hilkiah, and Ahikam the son of Shaphan, and Abdon the son of Micah, and Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah the king's servant, saying, ^21Go ye, inquire of Jehovah for me, and for them that are left in Israel and in Judah, concerning the words of the book that is found; for great is the wrath of Jehovah that is poured out upon us, because our fathers have not kept the word of Jehovah, to do according unto all that is written in this book. ^22So Hilkiah, and they whom the king had commanded, went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tokhath, the son of Hasrah, keeper of the wardrobe; (now she dwelt in Jerusalem in the second quarter;) and they spake to her to that effect. ^23And she said unto them, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel: Tell ye the man that sent you unto me, ^24Thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will bring evil upon this place, and upon the inhabitants thereof, even all the curses that are written in the book which they have read before the king of Judah. ^25Because they have forsaken me, and have burned incense unto other gods, that they might provoke me to anger with all the works of their hands; therefore is my wrath poured out upon this place, and it shall not be quenched. ^26But unto the king of Judah, who sent you to inquire of Jehovah, thus shall ye say to him, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel: As touching the words which thou hast heard, ^27because thy heart was tender, and thou didst humble thyself before God, when thou heardest his words against this place, and against the inhabitants thereof, and hast humbled thyself before me, and hast rent thy clothes, and wept before me; I also have heard thee, saith Jehovah. ^28Behold, I will gather thee to thy fathers, and thou shalt be gathered to thy grave in peace, neither shall thine eyes see all the evil that I will bring upon this place, and upon the inhabitants thereof. And they brought back word to the king. ^29Then the king sent and gathered together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. ^30And the king went up to the house of Jehovah, and all the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and the priests, and the Levites, and all the people, both great and small: and he read in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant that was found in the house of Jehovah. ^31And the king stood in his place, and made a covenant before Jehovah, to walk after Jehovah, and to keep his commandments, and his testimonies, and his statutes, with all his heart, and with all his soul, to perform the words of the covenant that were written in this book. ^32And he caused all that were found in Jerusalem and Benjamin to stand to it. And the inhabitants of Jerusalem did according to the covenant of God, the God of their fathers. ^33And Josiah took away all the abominations out of all the countries that pertained to the children of Israel, and made all that were found in Israel to serve, even to serve Jehovah their God. All his days they departed not from following Jehovah, the God of their fathers.

2 Chronicles 35

35

^1And Josiah kept a passover unto Jehovah in Jerusalem: and they killed the passover on the fourteenth day of the first month. ^2And he set the priests in their offices, and encouraged them to the service of the house of Jehovah. ^3And he said unto the Levites that taught all Israel, that were holy unto Jehovah, Put the holy ark in the house which Solomon the son of David king of Israel did build; there shall no more be a burden upon your shoulders: now serve Jehovah your God, and his people Israel. ^4And prepare yourselves after your fathers' houses by your courses, according to the writing of David king of Israel, and according to the writing of Solomon his son. ^5And stand in the holy place according to the divisions of the fathers' houses of your brethren the children of the people, and let there be for each a portion of a fathers' house of the Levites. ^6And kill the passover, and sanctify yourselves, and prepare for your brethren, to do according to the word of Jehovah by Moses. ^7And Josiah gave to the children of the people, of the flock, lambs and kids, all of them for the passover-offerings, unto all that were present, to the number of thirty thousand, and three thousand bullocks: these were of the king's substance. ^8And his princes gave for a freewill-offering unto the people, to the priests, and to the Levites. Hilkiah and Zechariah and Jehiel, the rulers of the house of God, gave unto the priests for the passover-offerings two thousand and six hundred small cattle, and three hundred oxen. ^9Conaniah also, and Shemaiah and Nethanel, his brethren, and Hashabiah and Jeiel and Jozabad, the chiefs of the Levites, gave unto the Levites for the passover-offerings five thousand small cattle, and five hundred oxen. ^10So the service was prepared, and the priests stood in their place, and the Levites by their courses, according to the king's commandment. ^11And they killed the passover, and the priests sprinkled the blood which they received of their hand, and the Levites flayed them. ^12And they removed the burnt-offerings, that they might give them according to the divisions of the fathers' houses of the children of the people, to offer unto Jehovah, as it is written in the book of Moses. And so did they with the oxen. ^13And they roasted the passover with fire according to the ordinance: and the holy offerings boiled they in pots, and in caldrons, and in pans, and carried them quickly to all the children of the people. ^14And afterward they prepared for themselves, and for the priests, because the priests the sons of Aaron were busied in offering the burnt-offerings and the fat until night: therefore the Levites prepared for themselves, and for the priests the sons of Aaron. ^15And the singers the sons of Asaph were in their place, according to the commandment of David, and Asaph, and Heman, and Jeduthun the king's seer; and the porters were at every gate: they needed not to depart from their service; for their brethren the Levites prepared for them. ^16So all the service of Jehovah was prepared the same day, to keep the passover, and to offer burnt-offerings upon the altar of Jehovah, according to the commandment of king Josiah. ^17And the children of Israel that were present kept the passover at that time, and the feast of unleavened bread seven days. ^18And there was no passover like to that kept in Israel from the days of Samuel the prophet; neither did any of the kings of Israel keep such a passover as Josiah kept, and the priests, and the Levites, and all Judah and Israel that were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^19In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah was this passover kept. ^20After all this, when Josiah had prepared the temple, Neco king of Egypt went up to fight against Carchemish by the Euphrates: and Josiah went out against him. ^21But he sent ambassadors to him, saying, What have I to do with thee, thou king of Judah? I come not against thee this day, but against the house wherewith I have war; and God hath commanded me to make haste: forbear thee from meddling with God, who is with me, that he destroy thee not. ^22Nevertheless Josiah would not turn his face from him, but disguised himself, that he might fight with him, and hearkened not unto the words of Neco from the mouth of God, and came to fight in the valley of Megiddo. ^23And the archers shot at king Josiah; and the king said to his servants, Have me away; for I am sore wounded. ^24So his servants took him out of the chariot, and put him in the second chariot that he had, and brought him to Jerusalem; and he died, and was buried in the sepulchres of his fathers. And all Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah. ^25And Jeremiah lamented for Josiah: and all the singing men and singing women spake of Josiah in their lamentations unto this day; and they made them an ordinance in Israel: and, behold, they are written in the lamentations. ^26Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and his good deeds, according to that which is written in the law of Jehovah, ^27and his acts, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah.

2 Chronicles 36

36

^1Then the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and made him king in his father's stead in Jerusalem. ^2Joahaz was twenty and three years old when he began to reign; and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. ^3And the king of Egypt deposed him at Jerusalem, and fined the land a hundred talents of silver and a talent of gold. ^4And the king of Egypt made Eliakim his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem, and changed his name to Jehoiakim. And Neco took Joahaz his brother, and carried him to Egypt. ^5Jehoiakim was twenty and five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: and he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah his God. ^6Against him came up Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and bound him in fetters, to carry him to Babylon. ^7Nebuchadnezzar also carried of the vessels of the house of Jehovah to Babylon, and put them in his temple at Babylon. ^8Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and his abominations which he did, and that which was found in him, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah: and Jehoiachin his son reigned in his stead. ^9Jehoiachin was eight years old when he began to reign; and he reigned three months and ten days in Jerusalem: and he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah. ^10And at the return of the year king Nebuchadnezzar sent, and brought him to Babylon, with the goodly vessels of the house of Jehovah, and made Zedekiah his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem. ^11Zedekiah was twenty and one years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: ^12and he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah his God; he humbled not himself before Jeremiah the prophet speaking from the mouth of Jehovah. ^13And he also rebelled against king Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear by God: but he stiffened his neck, and hardened his heart against turning unto Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^14Moreover all the chiefs of the priests, and the people, trespassed very greatly after all the abominations of the nations; and they polluted the house of Jehovah which he had hallowed in Jerusalem. ^15And Jehovah, the God of their fathers, sent to them by his messengers, rising up early and sending, because he had compassion on his people, and on his dwelling-place: ^16but they mocked the messengers of God, and despised his words, and scoffed at his prophets, until the wrath of Jehovah arose against his people, till there was no remedy. ^17Therefore he brought upon them the king of the Chaldeans, who slew their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary, and had no compassion upon young man or virgin, old man or hoary-headed: he gave them all into his hand. ^18And all the vessels of the house of God, great and small, and the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and the treasures of the king, and of his princes, all these he brought to Babylon. ^19And they burnt the house of God, and brake down the wall of Jerusalem, and burnt all the palaces thereof with fire, and destroyed all the goodly vessels thereof. ^20And them that had escaped from the sword carried he away to Babylon; and they were servants to him and his sons until the reign of the kingdom of Persia: ^21to fulfil the word of Jehovah by the mouth of Jeremiah, until the land had enjoyed its sabbaths: for as long as it lay desolate it kept sabbath, to fulfil threescore and ten years. ^22Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the word of Jehovah by the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, Jehovah stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, so that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and put it also in writing, saying, ^23Thus saith Cyrus king of Persia, All the kingdoms of the earth hath Jehovah, the God of heaven, given me; and he hath charged me to build him a house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. Whosoever there is among you of all his people, Jehovah his God be with him, and let him go up.

2 Corinthians 2

2

^1But I determined this for myself, that I would not come again to you with sorrow. ^2For if I make you sorry, who then is he that maketh me glad but he that is made sorry by me? ^3And I wrote this very thing, lest, when I came, I should have sorrow from them of whom I ought to rejoice; having confidence in you all, that my joy is the joy of you all. ^4For out of much affliction and anguish of heart I wrote unto you with many tears; not that ye should be made sorry, but that ye might know the love that I have more abundantly unto you. ^5But if any hath caused sorrow, he hath caused sorrow, not to me, but in part (that I press not too heavily) to you all. ^6Sufficient to such a one is this punishment which was inflicted by the many; ^7so that contrariwise ye should rather forgive him and comfort him, lest by any means such a one should be swallowed up with his overmuch sorrow. ^8Wherefore I beseech you to confirm your love toward him. ^9For to this end also did I write, that I might know the proof of you, whether ye are obedient in all things. ^10But to whom ye forgive anything, I forgive also: for what I also have forgiven, if I have forgiven anything, for your sakes have I forgiven it in the presence of Christ; ^11that no advantage may be gained over us by Satan: for we are not ignorant of his devices. ^12Now when I came to Troas for the gospel of Christ, and when a door was opened unto me in the Lord, ^13I had no relief for my spirit, because I found not Titus my brother: but taking my leave of them, I went forth into Macedonia. ^14But thanks be unto God, who always leadeth us in triumph in Christ, and maketh manifest through us the savor of his knowledge in every place. ^15For we are a sweet savor of Christ unto God, in them that are saved, and in them that perish; ^16to the one a savor from death unto death; to the other a savor from life unto life. And who is sufficient for these things? ^17For we are not as the many, corrupting the word of God: but as of sincerity, but as of God, in the sight of God, speak we in Christ.

2 Corinthians 3

3

^1Are we beginning again to commend ourselves? or need we, as do some, epistles of commendation to you or from you? ^2Ye are our epistle, written in our hearts, known and read of all men; ^3being made manifest that ye are an epistle of Christ, ministered by us, written not with ink, but with the Spirit of the living God; not in tables of stone, but in tables that are hearts of flesh. ^4And such confidence have we through Christ to God-ward: ^5not that we are sufficient of ourselves, to account anything as from ourselves; but our sufficiency is from God; ^6who also made us sufficient as ministers of a new covenant; not of the letter, but of the spirit: for the letter killeth, but the spirit giveth life. ^7But if the ministration of death, written, and engraven on stones, came with glory, so that the children of Israel could not look stedfastly upon the face of Moses for the glory of his face; which glory was passing away: ^8how shall not rather the ministration of the spirit be with glory? ^9For if the ministration of condemnation hath glory, much rather doth the ministration of righteousness exceed in glory. ^10For verily that which hath been made glorious hath not been made glorious in this respect, by reason of the glory that surpasseth. ^11For if that which passeth away was with glory, much more that which remaineth is in glory. ^12Having therefore such a hope, we use great boldness of speech, ^13and are not as Moses, who put a veil upon his face, that the children of Israel should not look stedfastly on the end of that which was passing away: ^14but their minds were hardened: for until this very day at the reading of the old covenant the same veil remaineth, it not being revealed to them that it is done away in Christ. ^15But unto this day, whensoever Moses is read, a veil lieth upon their heart. ^16But whensoever it shall turn to the Lord, the veil is taken away. ^17Now the Lord is the Spirit: and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty. ^18But we all, with unveiled face beholding as in a mirror the glory of the Lord, are transformed into the same image from glory to glory, even as from the Lord the Spirit.

2 Corinthians 4

4

^1Therefore seeing we have this ministry, even as we obtained mercy, we faint not: ^2but we have renounced the hidden things of shame, not walking in craftiness, nor handling the word of God deceitfully; but by the manifestation of the truth commending ourselves to every man's conscience in the sight of God. ^3And even if our gospel is veiled, it is veiled in them that perish: ^4in whom the god of this world hath blinded the minds of the unbelieving, that the light of the gospel of the glory of Christ, who is the image of God, should not dawn upon them. ^5For we preach not ourselves, but Christ Jesus as Lord, and ourselves as your servants for Jesus' sake. ^6Seeing it is God, that said, Light shall shine out of darkness, who shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ. ^7But we have this treasure in earthen vessels, that the exceeding greatness of the power may be of God, and not from ourselves; ^8we are pressed on every side, yet not straitened; perplexed, yet not unto despair; ^9pursued, yet not forsaken; smitten down, yet not destroyed; ^10always bearing about in the body the dying of Jesus, that the life also of Jesus may be manifested in our body. ^11For we who live are always delivered unto death for Jesus' sake, that the life also of Jesus may be manifested in our mortal flesh. ^12So then death worketh in us, but life in you. ^13But having the same spirit of faith, according to that which is written, I believed, and therefore did I speak; we also believe, and therefore also we speak; ^14knowing that he that raised up the Lord Jesus shall raise up us also with Jesus, and shall present us with you. ^15For all things are for your sakes, that the grace, being multiplied through the many, may cause the thanksgiving to abound unto the glory of God. ^16Wherefore we faint not; but though our outward man is decaying, yet our inward man is renewed day by day. ^17For our light affliction, which is for the moment, worketh for us more and more exceedingly an eternal weight of glory; ^18while we look not at the things which are seen, but at the things which are not seen: for the things which are seen are temporal; but the things which are not seen are eternal.

2 Corinthians 5

5

^1For we know that if the earthly house of our tabernacle be dissolved, we have a building from God, a house not made with hands, eternal, in the heavens. ^2For verily in this we groan, longing to be clothed upon with our habitation which is from heaven: ^3if so be that being clothed we shall not be found naked. ^4For indeed we that are in this tabernacle do groan, being burdened; not for that we would be unclothed, but that we would be clothed upon, that what is mortal may be swallowed up of life. ^5Now he that wrought us for this very thing is God, who gave unto us the earnest of the Spirit. ^6Being therefore always of good courage, and knowing that, whilst we are at home in the body, we are absent from the Lord ^7(for we walk by faith, not by sight); ^8we are of good courage, I say, and are willing rather to be absent from the body, and to be at home with the Lord. ^9Wherefore also we make it our aim, whether at home or absent, to be well-pleasing unto him. ^10For we must all be made manifest before the judgment-seat of Christ; that each one may receive the things done in the body, according to what he hath done, whether it be good or bad. ^11Knowing therefore the fear of the Lord, we persuade men, but we are made manifest unto God; and I hope that we are made manifest also in your consciences. ^12We are not again commending ourselves unto you, but speak as giving you occasion of glorying on our behalf, that ye may have wherewith to answer them that glory in appearance, and not in heart. ^13For whether we are beside ourselves, it is unto God; or whether we are of sober mind, it is unto you. ^14For the love of Christ constraineth us; because we thus judge, that one died for all, therefore all died; ^15and he died for all, that they that live should no longer live unto themselves, but unto him who for their sakes died and rose again. ^16Wherefore we henceforth know no man after the flesh: even though we have known Christ after the flesh, yet now we know him so no more. ^17Wherefore if any man is in Christ, he is a new creature: the old things are passed away; behold, they are become new. ^18But all things are of God, who reconciled us to himself through Christ, and gave unto us the ministry of reconciliation; ^19to wit, that God was in Christ reconciling the world unto himself, not reckoning unto them their trespasses, and having committed unto us the word of reconciliation. ^20We are ambassadors therefore on behalf of Christ, as though God were entreating by us: we beseech you on behalf of Christ, be ye reconciled to God. ^21Him who knew no sin he made to be sin on our behalf; that we might become the righteousness of God in him.

2 Corinthians 7

7

^1Having therefore these promises, beloved, let us cleanse ourselves from all defilement of flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God. ^2Open your hearts to us: we wronged no man, we corrupted no man, we took advantage of no man. ^3I say it not to condemn you: for I have said before, that ye are in our hearts to die together and live together. ^4Great is my boldness of speech toward you, great is my glorying on your behalf: I am filled with comfort, I overflow with joy in all our affliction. ^5For even when we were come into Macedonia our flesh had no relief, but we were afflicted on every side; without were fightings, within were fears. ^6Nevertheless he that comforteth the lowly, even God, comforted us by the coming of Titus; ^7and not by his coming only, but also by the comfort wherewith he was comforted in you, while he told us your longing, your mourning, your zeal for me; so that I rejoiced yet more. ^8For though I made you sorry with my epistle, I do not regret it: though I did regret it (for I see that that epistle made you sorry, though but for a season), ^9I now rejoice, not that ye were made sorry, but that ye were made sorry unto repentance; for ye were made sorry after a godly sort, that ye might suffer loss by us in nothing. ^10For godly sorrow worketh repentance unto salvation, a repentance which bringeth no regret: but the sorrow of the world worketh death. ^11For behold, this selfsame thing, that ye were made sorry after a godly sort, what earnest care it wrought in you, yea what clearing of yourselves, yea what indignation, yea what fear, yea what longing, yea what zeal, yea what avenging! In everything ye approved yourselves to be pure in the matter. ^12So although I wrote unto you, I wrote not for his cause that did the wrong, nor for his cause that suffered the wrong, but that your earnest care for us might be made manifest unto you in the sight of God. ^13Therefore we have been comforted: And in our comfort we joyed the more exceedingly for the joy of Titus, because his spirit hath been refreshed by you all. ^14For if in anything I have gloried to him on your behalf, I was not put to shame; but as we spake all things to you in truth, so our glorying also which I made before Titus was found to be truth. ^15And his affection is more abundantly toward you, while he remembereth the obedience of you all, how with fear and trembling ye received him. ^16I rejoice that in everything I am of good courage concerning you.

2 Corinthians 8

8

^1Moreover, brethren, we make known to you the grace of God which hath been given in the churches of Macedonia; ^2how that in much proof of affliction the abundance of their joy and their deep poverty abounded unto the riches of their liberality. ^3For according to their power, I bear witness, yea and beyond their power, they gave of their own accord, ^4beseeching us with much entreaty in regard of this grace and the fellowship in the ministering to the saints: ^5and this, not as we had hoped, but first they gave their own selves to the Lord, and to us through the will of God. ^6Insomuch that we exhorted Titus, that as he made a beginning before, so he would also complete in you this grace also. ^7But as ye abound in everything, in faith, and utterance, and knowledge, and in all earnestness, and in your love to us, see that ye abound in this grace also. ^8I speak not by way of commandment, but as proving through the earnestness of others the sincerity also of your love. ^9For ye know the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ, that, though he was rich, yet for your sakes he became poor, that ye through his poverty might become rich. ^10And herein I give my judgment: for this is expedient for you, who were the first to make a beginning a year ago, not only to do, but also to will. ^11But now complete the doing also; that as there was the readiness to will, so there may be the completion also out of your ability. ^12For if the readiness is there, it is acceptable according as a man hath, not according as he hath not. ^13For I say not this that others may be eased and ye distressed; ^14but by equality: your abundance being a supply at this present time for their want, that their abundance also may become a supply for your want; that there may be equality: ^15as it is written, He that gathered much had nothing over; and he that gathered little had no lack. ^16But thanks be to God, who putteth the same earnest care for you into the heart of Titus. ^17For he accepted indeed our exhortation; but being himself very earnest, he went forth unto you of his own accord. ^18And we have sent together with him the brother whose praise in the gospel is spread through all the churches; ^19and not only so, but who was also appointed by the churches to travel with us in the matter of this grace, which is ministered by us to the glory of the Lord, and to show our readiness: ^20Avoiding this, that any man should blame us in the matter of this bounty which is ministered by us: ^21for we take thought for things honorable, not only in the sight of the Lord, but also in the sight of men. ^22and we have sent with them our brother, whom we have many times proved earnest in many things, but now much more earnest, by reason of the great confidence which he hath in you. ^23Whether any inquire about Titus, he is my partner and my fellow-worker to you-ward, or our brethren, they are the messengers of the churches, they are the glory of Christ. ^24Show ye therefore unto them in the face of the churches the proof of your love, and of our glorying on your behalf.

2 Corinthians 9

9

^1For as touching the ministering to the saints, it is superfluous for me to write to you: ^2for I know your readiness, of which I glory on your behalf to them of Macedonia, that Achaia hath been prepared for a year past; and your zeal hath stirred up very many of them. ^3But I have sent the brethren, that our glorying on your behalf may not be made void in this respect; that, even as I said, ye may be prepared: ^4lest by any means, if there come with me any of Macedonia and find you unprepared, we (that we say not, ye) should be put to shame in this confidence. ^5I thought it necessary therefore to entreat the brethren, that they would go before unto you, and make up beforehand your aforepromised bounty, that the same might be ready as a matter of bounty, and not of extortion. ^6But this I say, He that soweth sparingly shall reap also sparingly; and he that soweth bountifully shall reap also bountifully. ^7Let each man do according as he hath purposed in his heart: not grudgingly, or of necessity: for God loveth a cheerful giver. ^8And God is able to make all grace abound unto you; that ye, having always all sufficiency in everything, may abound unto every good work: ^9as it is written,

He hath scattered abroad, he hath given to the poor;

His righteousness abideth for ever.

^10And he that supplieth seed to the sower and bread for food, shall supply and multiply your seed for sowing, and increase the fruits of your righteousness: ^11ye being enriched in everything unto all liberality, which worketh through us thanksgiving to God. ^12For the ministration of this service not only filleth up the measure of the wants of the saints, but aboundeth also through many thanksgivings unto God; ^13seeing that through the proving of you by this ministration they glorify God for the obedience of your confession unto the gospel of Christ, and for the liberality of your contribution unto them and unto all; ^14while they themselves also, with supplication on your behalf, long after you by reason of the exceeding grace of God in you. ^15Thanks be to God for his unspeakable gift.

2 Corinthians 10

10

^1Now I Paul myself entreat you by the meekness and gentleness of Christ, I who in your presence am lowly among you, but being absent am of good courage toward you: ^2yea, I beseech you, that I may not when present show courage with the confidence wherewith I count to be bold against some, who count of us as if we walked according to the flesh. ^3For though we walk in the flesh, we do not war according to the flesh ^4(for the weapons of our warfare are not of the flesh, but mighty before God to the casting down of strongholds), ^5casting down imaginations, and every high thing that is exalted against the knowledge of God, and bringing every thought into captivity to the obedience of Christ; ^6and being in readiness to avenge all disobedience, when your obedience shall be made full. ^7Ye look at the things that are before your face. If any man trusteth in himself that he is Christ's, let him consider this again with himself, that, even as he is Christ's, so also are we. ^8For though I should glory somewhat abundantly concerning our authority (which the Lord gave for building you up, and not for casting you down), I shall not be put to shame: ^9that I may not seem as if I would terrify you by my letters. ^10For, His letters, they say, are weighty and strong; but his bodily presence is weak, and his speech of no account. ^11Let such a one reckon this, that, what we are in word by letters when we are absent, such are we also in deed when we are present. ^12For we are not bold to number or compare ourselves with certain of them that commend themselves: but they themselves, measuring themselves by themselves, and comparing themselves with themselves, are without understanding. ^13But we will not glory beyond our measure, but according to the measure of the province which God apportioned to us as a measure, to reach even unto you. ^14For we stretch not ourselves overmuch, as though we reached not unto you: for we came even as far as unto you in the gospel of Christ: ^15not glorying beyond our measure, that is, in other men's labors; but having hope that, as your faith groweth, we shall be magnified in you according to our province unto further abundance, ^16so as to preach the gospel even unto the parts beyond you, and not to glory in another's province in regard of things ready to our hand. ^17But he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord. ^18For not he that commendeth himself is approved, but whom the Lord commendeth.

2 Corinthians 11

11

^1Would that ye could bear with me in a little foolishness: but indeed ye do bear with me. ^2For I am jealous over you with a godly jealousy: for I espoused you to one husband, that I might present you as a pure virgin to Christ. ^3But I fear, lest by any means, as the serpent beguiled Eve in his craftiness, your minds should be corrupted from the simplicity and the purity that is toward Christ. ^4For if he that cometh preacheth another Jesus, whom we did not preach, or if ye receive a different spirit, which ye did not receive, or a different gospel, which ye did not accept, ye do well to bear with him. ^5For I reckon that I am not a whit behind the very chiefest apostles. ^6But though I be rude in speech, yet am I not in knowledge; nay, in every way have we made this manifest unto you in all things. ^7Or did I commit a sin in abasing myself that ye might be exalted, because I preached to you the gospel of God for nought? ^8I robbed other churches, taking wages of them that I might minister unto you; ^9and when I was present with you and was in want, I was not a burden on any man; for the brethren, when they came from Macedonia, supplied the measure of my want; and in everything I kept myself from being burdensome unto you, and so will I keep myself. ^10As the truth of Christ is in me, no man shall stop me of this glorying in the regions of Achaia. ^11Wherefore? because I love you not? God knoweth. ^12But what I do, that I will do, that I may cut off occasion from them that desire an occasion; that wherein they glory, they may be found even as we. ^13For such men are false apostles, deceitful workers, fashioning themselves into apostles of Christ. ^14And no marvel; for even Satan fashioneth himself into an angel of light. ^15It is no great thing therefore if his ministers also fashion themselves as ministers of righteousness, whose end shall be according to their works. ^16I say again, let no man think me foolish; but if ye do, yet as foolish receive me, that I also may glory a little. ^17That which I speak, I speak not after the Lord, but as in foolishness, in this confidence of glorying. ^18Seeing that many glory after the flesh, I will glory also. ^19For ye bear with the foolish gladly, being wise yourselves. ^20For ye bear with a man, if he bringeth you into bondage, if he devoureth you, if he taketh you captive, if he exalteth himself, if he smiteth you on the face. ^21I speak by way of disparagement, as though we had been weak. Yet whereinsoever any is bold (I speak in foolishness), I am bold also. ^22Are they Hebrews? so am I. Are they Israelites? so am I. Are they the seed of Abraham? so am I. ^23Are they ministers of Christ? (I speak as one beside himself) I more; in labors more abundantly, in prisons more abundantly, in stripes above measure, in deaths oft. ^24Of the Jews five times received I forty stripes save one. ^25Thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I stoned, thrice I suffered shipwreck, a night and a day have I been in the deep; ^26in journeyings often, in perils of rivers, in perils of robbers, in perils from my countrymen, in perils from the Gentiles, in perils in the city, in perils in the wilderness, in perils in the sea, in perils among false brethren; ^27in labor and travail, in watchings often, in hunger and thirst, in fastings often, in cold and nakedness. ^28Besides those things that are without, there is that which presseth upon me daily, anxiety for all the churches. ^29Who is weak, and I am not weak? who is caused to stumble, and I burn not? ^30If I must needs glory, I will glory of the things that concern my weakness. ^31The God and Father of the Lord Jesus, he who is blessed for evermore knoweth that I lie not. ^32In Damascus the governor under Aretas the king guarded the city of the Damascenes in order to take me: ^33and through a window was I let down in a basket by the wall, and escaped his hands.

2 Corinthians 12

12

^1I must needs glory, though it is not expedient; but I will come to visions and revelations of the Lord. ^2I know a man in Christ, fourteen years ago (whether in the body, I know not; or whether out of the body, I know not; God knoweth), such a one caught up even to the third heaven. ^3And I know such a man (whether in the body, or apart from the body, I know not; God knoweth), ^4how that he was caught up into Paradise, and heard unspeakable words, which it is not lawful for a man to utter. ^5On behalf of such a one will I glory: but on mine own behalf I will not glory, save in my weaknesses. ^6For if I should desire to glory, I shall not be foolish; for I shall speak the truth: but I forbear, lest any man should account of me above that which he seeth me to be, or heareth from me. ^7And by reason of the exceeding greatness of the revelations, that I should not be exalted overmuch, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, a messenger of Satan to buffet me, that I should not be exalted overmuch. ^8Concerning this thing I besought the Lord thrice, that it might depart from me. ^9And he hath said unto me, My grace is sufficient for thee: for my power is made perfect in weakness. Most gladly therefore will I rather glory in my weaknesses, that the power of Christ may rest upon me. ^10Wherefore I take pleasure in weaknesses, in injuries, in necessities, in persecutions, in distresses, for Christ's sake: for when I am weak, then am I strong. ^11I am become foolish: ye compelled me; for I ought to have been commended of you: for in nothing was I behind the very chiefest apostles, though I am nothing. ^12Truly the signs of an apostle were wrought among you in all patience, by signs and wonders and mighty works. ^13For what is there wherein ye were made inferior to the rest of the churches, except it be that I myself was not a burden to you? forgive me this wrong. ^14Behold, this is the third time I am ready to come to you; and I will not be a burden to you: for I seek not yours, but you: for the children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the children. ^15And I will most gladly spend and be spent for your souls. If I love you more abundantly, am I loved the less? ^16But be it so, I did not myself burden you; but, being crafty, I caught you with guile. ^17Did I take advantage of you by any one of them whom I have sent unto you? ^18I exhorted Titus, and I sent the brother with him. Did Titus take any advantage of you? walked we not in the same spirit? walked we not in the same steps? ^19Ye think all this time that we are excusing ourselves unto you. In the sight of God speak we in Christ. But all things, beloved, are for your edifying. ^20For I fear, lest by any means, when I come, I should find you not such as I would, and should myself be found of you such as ye would not; lest by any means there should be strife, jealousy, wraths, factions, backbitings, whisperings, swellings, tumults; ^21lest again when I come my God should humble me before you, and I should mourn for many of them that have sinned heretofore, and repented not of the uncleanness and fornication and lasciviousness which they committed.

2 Corinthians 13

13

^1This is the third time I am coming to you. At the mouth of two witnesses or three shall every word established. ^2I have said beforehand, and I do say beforehand, as when I was present the second time, so now, being absent, to them that have sinned heretofore, and to all the rest, that, if I come again, I will not spare; ^3seeing that ye seek a proof of Christ that speaketh in me; who to you-ward is not weak, but is powerful in you: ^4for he was crucified through weakness, yet he liveth through the power of God. For we also are weak in him, but we shall live with him through the power of God toward you. ^5Try your own selves, whether ye are in the faith; prove your own selves. Or know ye not as to your own selves, that Jesus Christ is in you? unless indeed ye be reprobate. ^6But I hope that ye shall know that we are not reprobate. ^7Now we pray to God that ye do no evil; not that we may appear approved, but that ye may do that which is honorable, though we be as reprobate. ^8For we can do nothing against the truth, but for the truth. ^9For we rejoice, when we are weak, and ye are strong: this we also pray for, even your perfecting. ^10For this cause I write these things while absent, that I may not when present deal sharply, according to the authority which the Lord gave me for building up, and not for casting down. ^11Finally, brethren, farewell. Be perfected; be comforted; be of the same mind; live in peace: and the God of love and peace shall be with you. ^12Salute one another with a holy kiss. ^13All the saints salute you. ^14The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the love of God, and the communion of the Holy Spirit, be with you all.

2 Kings 2

2

^1And it came to pass, when Jehovah would take up Elijah by a whirlwind into heaven, that Elijah went with Elisha from Gilgal. ^2And Elijah said unto Elisha, Tarry here, I pray thee; for Jehovah hath sent me as far as Beth-el. And Elisha said, As Jehovah liveth, and as thy soul liveth, I will not leave thee. So they went down to Beth-el. ^3And the sons of the prophets that were at Beth-el came forth to Elisha, and said unto him, Knowest thou that Jehovah will take away thy master from thy head to-day? And he said, Yea, I know it; hold ye your peace. ^4And Elijah said unto him, Elisha, tarry here, I pray thee; for Jehovah hath sent me to Jericho. And he said, As Jehovah liveth, and as thy soul liveth, I will not leave thee. So they came to Jericho. ^5And the sons of the prophets that were at Jericho came near to Elisha, and said unto him, Knowest thou that Jehovah will take away thy master from thy head to-day? And he answered, Yea, I know it; hold ye your peace. ^6And Elijah said unto him, Tarry here, I pray thee; for Jehovah hath sent me to the Jordan. And he said, As Jehovah liveth, and as thy soul liveth, I will not leave thee. And they two went on. ^7And fifty men of the sons of the prophets went, and stood over against them afar off: and they two stood by the Jordan. ^8And Elijah took his mantle, and wrapped it together, and smote the waters, and they were divided hither and thither, so that they two went over on dry ground. ^9And it came to pass, when they were gone over, that Elijah said unto Elisha, Ask what I shall do for thee, before I am taken from thee. And Elisha said, I pray thee, let a double portion of thy spirit be upon me. ^10And he said, Thou hast asked a hard thing: nevertheless, if thou see me when I am taken from thee, it shall be so unto thee; but if not, it shall not be so. ^11And it came to pass, as they still went on, and talked, that, behold, there appeared a chariot of fire, and horses of fire, which parted them both asunder; and Elijah went up by a whirlwind into heaven. ^12And Elisha saw it, and he cried, My father, my father, the chariots of Israel and the horsemen thereof!

And he saw him no more: and he took hold of his own clothes, and rent them in two pieces. ^13He took up also the mantle of Elijah that fell from him, and went back, and stood by the bank of the Jordan. ^14And he took the mantle of Elijah that fell from him, and smote the waters, and said, Where is Jehovah, the God of Elijah? and when he also had smitten the waters, they were divided hither and thither; and Elisha went over.

^15And when the sons of the prophets that were at Jericho over against him saw him, they said, The spirit of Elijah doth rest on Elisha. And they came to meet him, and bowed themselves to the ground before him. ^16And they said unto him, Behold now, there are with thy servants fifty strong men; let them go, we pray thee, and seek thy master, lest the Spirit of Jehovah hath taken him up, and cast him upon some mountain, or into some valley. And he said, Ye shall not send. ^17And when they urged him till he was ashamed, he said, Send. They sent therefore fifty men; and they sought three days, but found him not. ^18And they came back to him, while he tarried at Jericho; and he said unto them, Did I not say unto you, Go not?

^19And the men of the city said unto Elisha, Behold, we pray thee, the situation of this city is pleasant, as my lord seeth: but the water is bad, and the land miscarrieth. ^20And he said, Bring me a new cruse, and put salt therein. And they brought it to him. ^21And he went forth unto the spring of the waters, and cast salt therein, and said, Thus saith Jehovah, I have healed these waters; there shall not be from thence any more death or miscarrying. ^22So the waters were healed unto this day, according to the word of Elisha which he spake.

^23And he went up from thence unto Beth-el; and as he was going up by the way, there came forth young lads out of the city, and mocked him, and said unto him, Go up, thou baldhead; go up, thou baldhead. ^24And he looked behind him and saw them, and cursed them in the name of Jehovah. And there came forth two she-bears out of the wood, and tare forty and two lads of them. ^25And he went from thence to mount Carmel, and from thence he returned to Samaria.

2 Kings 3

3

^1Now Jehoram the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria in the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and reigned twelve years. ^2And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, but not like his father, and like his mother; for he put away the pillar of Baal that his father had made. ^3Nevertheless he cleaved unto the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin; he departed not therefrom.

^4Now Mesha king of Moab was a sheep-master; and he rendered unto the king of Israel the wool of a hundred thousand lambs, and of a hundred thousand rams. ^5But it came to pass, when Ahab was dead, that the king of Moab rebelled against the king of Israel. ^6And king Jehoram went out of Samaria at that time, and mustered all Israel. ^7And he went and sent to Jehoshaphat the king of Judah, saying, The king of Moab hath rebelled against me: wilt thou go with me against Moab to battle? And he said, I will go up: I am as thou art, my people as thy people, my horses as thy horses. ^8And he said, Which way shall we go up? And he answered, The way of the wilderness of Edom. ^9So the king of Israel went, and the king of Judah, and the king of Edom; and they made a circuit of seven days' journey: and there was no water for the host, nor for the beasts that followed them. ^10And the king of Israel said, Alas! for Jehovah hath called these three kings together to deliver them into the hand of Moab. ^11But Jehoshaphat said, Is there not here a prophet of Jehovah, that we may inquire of Jehovah by him? And one of the king of Israel's servants answered and said, Elisha the son of Shaphat is here, who poured water on the hands of Elijah. ^12And Jehoshaphat said, The word of Jehovah is with him. So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat and the king of Edom went down to him.

^13And Elisha said unto the king of Israel, What have I to do with thee? get thee to the prophets of thy father, and to the prophets of thy mother. And the king of Israel said unto him, Nay; for Jehovah hath called these three kings together to deliver them into the hand of Moab. ^14And Elisha said, As Jehovah of hosts liveth, before whom I stand, surely, were it not that I regard the presence of Jehoshaphat the king of Judah, I would not look toward thee, nor see thee. ^15But now bring me a minstrel. And it came to pass, when the minstrel played, that the hand of Jehovah came upon him. ^16And he said, Thus saith Jehovah, Make this valley full of trenches. ^17For thus saith Jehovah, Ye shall not see wind, neither shall ye see rain; yet that valley shall be filled with water, and ye shall drink, both ye and your cattle and your beasts. ^18And this is but a light thing in the sight of Jehovah: he will also deliver the Moabites into your hand. ^19And ye shall smite every fortified city, and every choice city, and shall fell every good tree, and stop all fountains of water, and mar every good piece of land with stones. ^20And it came to pass in the morning, about the time of offering the oblation, that, behold, there came water by the way of Edom, and the country was filled with water.

^21Now when all the Moabites heard that the kings were come up to fight against them, they gathered themselves together, all that were able to put on armor, and upward, and stood on the border. ^22And they rose up early in the morning, and the sun shone upon the water, and the Moabites saw the water over against them as red as blood: ^23and they said, This is blood; the kings are surely destroyed, and they have smitten each man his fellow: now therefore, Moab, to the spoil. ^24And when they came to the camp of Israel, the Israelites rose up and smote the Moabites, so that they fled before them; and they went forward into the land smiting the Moabites. ^25And they beat down the cities; and on every good piece of land they cast every man his stone, and filled it; and they stopped all the fountains of water, and felled all the good trees, until in Kir-hareseth only they left the stones thereof; howbeit the slingers went about it, and smote it. ^26And when the king of Moab saw that the battle was too sore for him, he took with him seven hundred men that drew sword, to break through unto the king of Edom; but they could not. ^27Then he took his eldest son that should have reigned in his stead, and offered him for a burnt-offering upon the wall. And there was great wrath against Israel: and they departed from him, and returned to their own land.

2 Kings 4

4

^1Now there cried a certain woman of the wives of the sons of the prophets unto Elisha, saying, Thy servant my husband is dead; and thou knowest that thy servant did fear Jehovah: and the creditor is come to take unto him my two children to be bondmen. ^2And Elisha said unto her, What shall I do for thee? tell me; what hast thou in the house? And she said, Thy handmaid hath not anything in the house, save a pot of oil. ^3Then he said, Go, borrow thee vessels abroad of all thy neighbors, even empty vessels; borrow not a few. ^4And thou shalt go in, and shut the door upon thee and upon thy sons, and pour out into all those vessels; and thou shalt set aside that which is full. ^5So she went from him, and shut the door upon her and upon her sons; they brought the vessels to her, and she poured out. ^6And it came to pass, when the vessels were full, that she said unto her son, Bring me yet a vessel. And he said unto her, There is not a vessel more. And the oil stayed. ^7Then she came and told the man of God. And he said, Go, sell the oil, and pay thy debt, and live thou and thy sons of the rest.

^8And it fell on a day, that Elisha passed to Shunem, where was a great woman; and she constrained him to eat bread. And so it was, that as oft as he passed by, he turned in thither to eat bread. ^9And she said unto her husband, Behold now, I perceive that this is a holy man of God, that passeth by us continually. ^10Let us make, I pray thee, a little chamber on the wall; and let us set for him there a bed, and a table, and a seat, and a candlestick: and it shall be, when he cometh to us, that he shall turn in thither. ^11And it fell on a day, that he came thither, and he turned into the chamber and lay there. ^12And he said to Gehazi his servant, Call this Shunammite. And when he had called her, she stood before him. ^13And he said unto him, Say now unto her, Behold, thou hast been careful for us with all this care; what is to be done for thee? wouldest thou be spoken for to the king, or to the captain of the host? And she answered, I dwell among mine own people. ^14And he said, What then is to be done for her? And Gehazi answered, Verily she hath no son, and her husband is old. ^15And he said, Call her. And when he had called her, she stood in the door. ^16And he said, At this season, when the time cometh round, thou shalt embrace a son. And she said, Nay, my lord, thou man of God, do not lie unto thy handmaid.

^17And the woman conceived, and bare a son at that season, when the time came round, as Elisha had said unto her. ^18And when the child was grown, it fell on a day, that he went out to his father to the reapers. ^19And he said unto his father, My head, my head. And he said to his servant, Carry him to his mother. ^20And when he had taken him, and brought him to his mother, he sat on her knees till noon, and then died. ^21And she went up and laid him on the bed of the man of God, and shut the door upon him, and went out. ^22And she called unto her husband, and said, Send me, I pray thee, one of the servants, and one of the asses, that I may run to the man of God, and come again. ^23And he said, Wherefore wilt thou go to him to-day? it is neither new moon nor sabbath. And she said, It shall be well. ^24Then she saddled an ass, and said to her servant, Drive, and go forward; slacken me not the riding, except I bid thee. ^25So she went, and came unto the man of God to mount Carmel.

And it came to pass, when the man of God saw her afar off, that he said to Gehazi his servant, Behold, yonder is the Shunammite: ^26run, I pray thee, now to meet her, and say unto her, Is it well with thee? is it well with thy husband? is it well with the child? And she answered, It is well. ^27And when she came to the man of God to the hill, she caught hold of his feet. And Gehazi came near to thrust her away; but the man of God said, Let her alone: for her soul is vexed within her; and Jehovah hath hid it from me, and hath not told me. ^28Then she said, Did I desire a son of my lord? did I not say, Do not deceive me? ^29Then he said to Gehazi, Gird up thy loins, and take my staff in thy hand, and go thy way: if thou meet any man, salute him not; and if any salute thee, answer him not again: and lay my staff upon the face of the child. ^30And the mother of the child said, As Jehovah liveth, and as thy soul liveth, I will not leave thee. And he arose, and followed her. ^31And Gehazi passed on before them, and laid the staff upon the face of the child; but there was neither voice, nor hearing. Wherefore he returned to meet him, and told him, saying, The child is not awaked.

^32And when Elisha was come into the house, behold, the child was dead, and laid upon his bed. ^33He went in therefore, and shut the door upon them twain, and prayed unto Jehovah. ^34And he went up, and lay upon the child, and put his mouth upon his mouth, and his eyes upon his eyes, and his hands upon his hands: and he stretched himself upon him; and the flesh of the child waxed warm. ^35Then he returned, and walked in the house once to and fro; and went up, and stretched himself upon him: and the child sneezed seven times, and the child opened his eyes. ^36And he called Gehazi, and said, Call this Shunammite. So he called her. And when she was come in unto him, he said, Take up thy son. ^37Then she went in, and fell at his feet, and bowed herself to the ground; and she took up her son, and went out.

^38And Elisha came again to Gilgal. And there was a dearth in the land; and the sons of the prophets were sitting before him; and he said unto his servant, Set on the great pot, and boil pottage for the sons of the prophets. ^39And one went out into the field to gather herbs, and found a wild vine, and gathered thereof wild gourds his lap full, and came and shred them into the pot of pottage; for they knew them not. ^40So they poured out for the men to eat. And it came to pass, as they were eating of the pottage, that they cried out, and said, O man of God, there is death in the pot. And they could not eat thereof. ^41But he said, Then bring meal. And he cast it into the pot; and he said, Pour out for the people, that they may eat. And there was no harm in the pot.

^42And there came a man from Baal-shalishah, and brought the man of God bread of the first-fruits, twenty loaves of barley, and fresh ears of grain in his sack. And he said, Give unto the people, that they may eat. ^43And his servant said, What, should I set this before a hundred men? But he said, Give the people, that they may eat; for thus saith Jehovah, They shall eat, and shall leave thereof. ^44So he set it before them, and they did eat, and left thereof, according to the word of Jehovah.

2 Kings 5

5

^1Now Naaman, captain of the host of the king of Syria, was a great man with his master, and honorable, because by him Jehovah had given victory unto Syria: he was also a mighty man of valor, but he was a leper. ^2And the Syrians had gone out in bands, and had brought away captive out of the land of Israel a little maiden; and she waited on Naaman's wife. ^3And she said unto her mistress, Would that my lord were with the prophet that is in Samaria! then would he recover him of his leprosy. ^4And one went in, and told his lord, saying, Thus and thus said the maiden that is of the land of Israel. ^5And the king of Syria said, Go now, and I will send a letter unto the king of Israel. And he departed, and took with him ten talents of silver, and six thousand pieces of gold, and ten changes of raiment. ^6And he brought the letter to the king of Israel, saying, And now when this letter is come unto thee, behold, I have sent Naaman my servant to thee, that thou mayest recover him of his leprosy. ^7And it came to pass, when the king of Israel had read the letter, that he rent his clothes, and said, Am I God, to kill and to make alive, that this man doth send unto me to recover a man of his leprosy? but consider, I pray you, and see how he seeketh a quarrel against me.

^8And it was so, when Elisha the man of God heard that the king of Israel had rent his clothes, that he sent to the king, saying, Wherefore hast thou rent thy clothes? let him come now to me, and he shall know that there is a prophet in Israel. ^9So Naaman came with his horses and with his chariots, and stood at the door of the house of Elisha. ^10And Elisha sent a messenger unto him, saying, Go and wash in the Jordan seven times, and thy flesh shall come again to thee, and thou shalt be clean. ^11But Naaman was wroth, and went away, and said, Behold, I thought, He will surely come out to me, and stand, and call on the name of Jehovah his God, and wave his hand over the place, and recover the leper. ^12Are not Abanah and Pharpar, the rivers of Damascus, better than all the waters of Israel? may I not wash in them, and be clean? So he turned and went away in a rage. ^13And his servants came near, and spake unto him, and said, My father, if the prophet had bid thee do some great thing, wouldest thou not have done it? how much rather then, when he saith to thee, Wash, and be clean? ^14Then went he down, and dipped himself seven times in the Jordan, according to the saying of the man of God; and his flesh came again like unto the flesh of a little child, and he was clean.

^15And he returned to the man of God, he and all his company, and came, and stood before him; and he said, Behold now, I know that there is no God in all the earth, but in Israel: now therefore, I pray thee, take a present of thy servant. ^16But he said, As Jehovah liveth, before whom I stand, I will receive none. And he urged him to take it; but he refused. ^17And Naaman said, If not, yet, I pray thee, let there be given to thy servant two mules' burden of earth; for thy servant will henceforth offer neither burnt-offering nor sacrifice unto other gods, but unto Jehovah. ^18In this thing Jehovah pardon thy servant: when my master goeth into the house of Rimmon to worship there, and he leaneth on my hand, and I bow myself in the house of Rimmon, when I bow myself in the house of Rimmon, Jehovah pardon thy servant in this thing. ^19And he said unto him, Go in peace. So he departed from him a little way.

^20But Gehazi the servant of Elisha the man of God, said, Behold, my master hath spared this Naaman the Syrian, in not receiving at his hands that which he brought: as Jehovah liveth, I will run after him, and take somewhat of him. ^21So Gehazi followed after Naaman. And when Naaman saw one running after him, he alighted from the chariot to meet him, and said, Is all well? ^22And he said, All is well. My master hath sent me, saying, Behold, even now there are come to me from the hill-country of Ephraim two young men of the sons of the prophets; give them, I pray thee, a talent of silver, and two changes of raiment. ^23And Naaman said, Be pleased to take two talents. And he urged him, and bound two talents of silver in two bags, with two changes of raiment, and laid them upon two of his servants; and they bare them before him. ^24And when he came to the hill, he took them from their hand, and bestowed them in the house; and he let the men go, and they departed. ^25But he went in, and stood before his master. And Elisha said unto him, Whence comest thou, Gehazi? And he said, Thy servant went no whither. ^26And he said unto him, Went not my heart with thee, when the man turned from his chariot to meet thee? Is it a time to receive money, and to receive garments, and oliveyards and vineyards, and sheep and oxen, and men-servants and maid-servants? ^27The leprosy therefore of Naaman shall cleave unto thee, and unto thy seed for ever. And he went out from his presence a leper as white as snow.

2 Kings 6

6

^1And the sons of the prophets said unto Elisha, Behold now, the place where we dwell before thee is too strait for us. ^2Let us go, we pray thee, unto the Jordan, and take thence every man a beam, and let us make us a place there, where we may dwell. And he answered, Go ye. ^3And one said, Be pleased, I pray thee, to go with thy servants. And he answered, I will go. ^4So he went with them. And when they came to the Jordan, they cut down wood. ^5But as one was felling a beam, the axe-head fell into the water; and he cried, and said, Alas, my master! for it was borrowed. ^6And the man of God said, Where fell it? And he showed him the place. And he cut down a stick, and cast it in thither, and made the iron to swim. ^7And he said, Take it up to thee. So he put out his hand, and took it.

^8Now the king of Syria was warring against Israel; and he took counsel with his servants, saying, In such and such a place shall be my camp. ^9And the man of God sent unto the king of Israel, saying, Beware that thou pass not such a place; for thither the Syrians are coming down. ^10And the king of Israel sent to the place which the man of God told him and warned him of; and he saved himself there, not once nor twice. ^11And the heart of the king of Syria was sore troubled for this thing; and he called his servants, and said unto them, Will ye not show me which of us is for the king of Israel? ^12And one of his servants said, Nay, my lord, O king; but Elisha, the prophet that is in Israel, telleth the king of Israel the words that thou speakest in thy bedchamber. ^13And he said, Go and see where he is, that I may send and fetch him. And it was told him, saying, Behold, he is in Dothan.

^14Therefore sent he thither horses, and chariots, and a great host: and they came by night, and compassed the city about. ^15And when the servant of the man of God was risen early, and gone forth, behold, a host with horses and chariots was round about the city. And his servant said unto him, Alas, my master! how shall we do? ^16And he answered, Fear not; for they that are with us are more than they that are with them. ^17And Elisha prayed, and said, Jehovah, I pray thee, open his eyes, that he may see. And Jehovah opened the eyes of the young man; and he saw: and, behold, the mountain was full of horses and chariots of fire round about Elisha. ^18And when they came down to him, Elisha prayed unto Jehovah, and said, Smite this people, I pray thee, with blindness. And he smote them with blindness according to the word of Elisha. ^19And Elisha said unto them, This is not the way, neither is this the city: follow me, and I will bring you to the man whom ye seek. And he led them to Samaria.

^20And it came to pass, when they were come into Samaria, that Elisha said, Jehovah, open the eyes of these men, that they may see. And Jehovah opened their eyes, and they saw; and, behold, they were in the midst of Samaria. ^21And the king of Israel said unto Elisha, when he saw them, My father, shall I smite them? shall I smite them? ^22And he answered, Thou shalt not smite them: wouldest thou smite those whom thou hast taken captive with thy sword and with thy bow? set bread and water before them, that they may eat and drink, and go to their master. ^23And he prepared great provision for them; and when they had eaten and drunk, he sent them away, and they went to their master. And the bands of Syria came no more into the land of Israel.

^24And it came to pass after this, that Benhadad king of Syria gathered all his host, and went up, and besieged Samaria. ^25And there was a great famine in Samaria: and, behold, they besieged it, until an ass's head was sold for fourscore pieces of silver, and the fourth part of a kab of dove's dung for five pieces of silver. ^26And as the king of Israel was passing by upon the wall, there cried a woman unto him, saying, Help, my lord, O king. ^27And he said, If Jehovah do not help thee, whence shall I help thee? out of the threshing-floor, or out of the winepress? ^28And the king said unto her, What aileth thee? And she answered, This woman said unto me, Give thy son, that we may eat him to-day, and we will eat my son to-morrow. ^29So we boiled my son, and did eat him: and I said unto her on the next day, Give thy son, that we may eat him; and she hath hid her son. ^30And it came to pass, when the king heard the words of the woman, that he rent his clothes (now he was passing by upon the wall); and the people looked, and, behold, he had sackcloth within upon his flesh. ^31Then he said, God do so to me, and more also, if the head of Elisha the son of Shaphat shall stand on him this day.

^32But Elisha was sitting in his house, and the elders were sitting with him; and the king sent a man from before him: but ere the messenger came to him, he said to the elders, See ye how this son of a murderer hath sent to take away my head? look, when the messenger cometh, shut the door, and hold the door fast against him: is not the sound of his master's feet behind him? ^33And while he was yet talking with them, behold, the messenger came down unto him: and he said, Behold, this evil is of Jehovah; why should I wait for Jehovah any longer?

2 Kings 7

7

^1And Elisha said, Hear ye the word of Jehovah: thus saith Jehovah, To-morrow about this time shall a measure of fine flour be sold for a shekel, and two measures of barley for a shekel, in the gate of Samaria. ^2Then the captain on whose hand the king leaned answered the man of God, and said, Behold, if Jehovah should make windows in heaven, might this thing be? And he said, Behold, thou shalt see it with thine eyes, but shalt not eat thereof.

^3Now there were four leprous men at the entrance of the gate: and they said one to another, Why sit we here until we die? ^4If we say, We will enter into the city, then the famine is in the city, and we shall die there; and if we sit still here, we die also. Now therefore come, and let us fall unto the host of the Syrians: if they save us alive, we shall live; and if they kill us, we shall but die. ^5And they rose up in the twilight, to go unto the camp of the Syrians; and when they were come to the outermost part of the camp of the Syrians, behold, there was no man there. ^6For the Lord had made the host of the Syrians to hear a noise of chariots, and a noise of horses, even the noise of a great host: and they said one to another, Lo, the king of Israel hath hired against us the kings of the Hittites, and the kings of the Egyptians, to come upon us. ^7Wherefore they arose and fled in the twilight, and left their tents, and their horses, and their asses, even the camp as it was, and fled for their life. ^8And when these lepers came to the outermost part of the camp, they went into one tent, and did eat and drink, and carried thence silver, and gold, and raiment, and went and hid it; and they came back, and entered into another tent, and carried thence also, and went and hid it.

^9Then they said one to another, We do not well; this day is a day of good tidings, and we hold our peace: if we tarry till the morning light, punishment will overtake us; now therefore come, let us go and tell the king's household. ^10So they came and called unto the porter of the city; and they told them, saying, We came to the camp of the Syrians, and, behold, there was no man there, neither voice of man, but the horses tied, and the asses tied, and the tents as they were. ^11And he called the porters; and they told it to the king's household within. ^12And the king arose in the night, and said unto his servants, I will now show you what the Syrians have done to us. They know that we are hungry; therefore are they gone out of the camp to hide themselves in the field, saying, When they come out of the city, we shall take them alive, and get into the city. ^13And one of his servants answered and said, Let some take, I pray thee, five of the horses that remain, which are left in the city (behold, they are as all the multitude of Israel that are left in it; behold, they are as all the multitude of Israel that are consumed); and let us send and see. ^14They took therefore two chariots with horses; and the king sent after the host of the Syrians, saying, Go and see. ^15And they went after them unto the Jordan: and, lo, all the way was full of garments and vessels, which the Syrians had cast away in their haste. And the messengers returned, and told the king.

^16And the people went out, and plundered the camp of the Syrians. So a measure of fine flour was sold for a shekel, and two measures of barley for a shekel, according to the word of Jehovah. ^17And the king appointed the captain on whose hand he leaned to have the charge of the gate: and the people trod upon him in the gate, and he died as the man of God had said, who spake when the king came down to him. ^18And it came to pass, as the man of God had spoken to the king, saying, Two measures of barley for a shekel, and a measure of fine flour for a shekel, shall be to-morrow about this time in the gate of Samaria; ^19and that captain answered the man of God, and said, Now, behold, if Jehovah should make windows in heaven, might such a thing be? and he said, Behold, thou shalt see it with thine eyes, but shalt not eat thereof: ^20it came to pass even so unto him; for the people trod upon him in the gate, and he died.

2 Kings 8

8

^1Now Elisha had spoken unto the woman, whose son he had restored to life, saying, Arise, and go thou and thy household, and sojourn wheresoever thou canst sojourn: for Jehovah hath called for a famine; and it shall also come upon the land seven years. ^2And the woman arose, and did according to the word of the man of God; and she went with her household, and sojourned in the land of the Philistines seven years. ^3And it came to pass at the seven years' end, that the woman returned out of the land of the Philistines: and she went forth to cry unto the king for her house and for her land. ^4Now the king was talking with Gehazi the servant of the man of God, saying, Tell me, I pray thee, all the great things that Elisha hath done. ^5And it came to pass, as he was telling the king how he had restored to life him that was dead, that, behold, the woman, whose son he had restored to life, cried to the king for her house and for her land. And Gehazi said, My lord, O king, this is the woman, and this is her son, whom Elisha restored to life. ^6And when the king asked the woman, she told him. So the king appointed unto her a certain officer, saying, Restore all that was hers, and all the fruits of the field since the day that she left the land, even until now.

^7And Elisha came to Damascus; and Benhadad the king of Syria was sick; and it was told him, saying, The man of God is come hither. ^8And the king said unto Hazael, Take a present in thy hand, and go, meet the man of God, and inquire of Jehovah by him, saying, Shall I recover of this sickness? ^9So Hazael went to meet him, and took a present with him, even of every good thing of Damascus, forty camels' burden, and came and stood before him, and said, Thy son Benhadad king of Syria hath sent me to thee, saying, Shall I recover of this sickness? ^10And Elisha said unto him, Go, say unto him, Thou shalt surely recover; howbeit Jehovah hath showed me that he shall surely die. ^11And he settled his countenance stedfastly upon him, until he was ashamed: and the man of God wept. ^12And Hazael said, Why weepeth my lord? And he answered, Because I know the evil that thou wilt do unto the children of Israel: their strongholds wilt thou set on fire, and their young men wilt thou slay with the sword, and wilt dash in pieces their little ones, and rip up their women with child. ^13And Hazael said, But what is thy servant, who is but a dog, that he should do this great thing? And Elisha answered, Jehovah hath showed me that thou shalt be king over Syria. ^14Then he departed from Elisha, and came to his master; who said to him, What said Elisha to thee? And he answered, He told me that thou wouldest surely recover. ^15And it came to pass on the morrow, that he took the coverlet, and dipped it in water, and spread it on his face, so that he died: and Hazael reigned in his stead.

^16And in the fifth year of Joram the son of Ahab king of Israel, Jehoshaphat being then king of Judah, Jehoram the son of Jehoshaphat king of Judah began to reign. ^17Thirty and two years old was he when he began to reign; and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem. ^18And he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, as did the house of Ahab: for he had the daughter of Ahab to wife; and he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah. ^19Howbeit Jehovah would not destroy Judah, for David his servant's sake, as he promised him to give unto him a lamp for his children alway.

^20In his days Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah, and made a king over themselves. ^21Then Joram passed over to Zair, and all his chariots with him: and he rose up by night, and smote the Edomites that compassed him about, and the captains of the chariots; and the people fled to their tents. ^22So Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah unto this day. Then did Libnah revolt at the same time. ^23And the rest of the acts of Joram, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^24And Joram slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David; and Ahaziah his son reigned in his stead.

^25In the twelfth year of Joram the son of Ahab king of Israel did Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah begin to reign. ^26Two and twenty years old was Ahaziah when he began to reign; and he reigned one year in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Athaliah the daughter of Omri king of Israel. ^27And he walked in the way of the house of Ahab, and did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, as did the house of Ahab; for he was the son-in-law of the house of Ahab. ^28And he went with Joram the son of Ahab to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth-gilead: and the Syrians wounded Joram. ^29And king Joram returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds which the Syrians had given him at Ramah, when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. And Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Joram the son of Ahab in Jezreel, because he was sick.

2 Kings 9

9

^1And Elisha the prophet called one of the sons of the prophets, and said unto him, Gird up thy loins, and take this vial of oil in thy hand, and go to Ramoth-gilead. ^2And when thou comest thither, look out there Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat the son of Nimshi, and go in, and make him arise up from among his brethren, and carry him to an inner chamber. ^3Then take the vial of oil, and pour it on his head, and say, Thus saith Jehovah, I have anointed thee king over Israel. Then open the door, and flee, and tarry not. ^4So the young man, even the young man the prophet, went to Ramoth-gilead. ^5And when he came, behold, the captains of the host were sitting; and he said, I have an errand to thee, O captain. And Jehu said, Unto which of us all? And he said, To thee, O captain. ^6And he arose, and went into the house; and he poured the oil on his head, and said unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, I have anointed thee king over the people of Jehovah, even over Israel. ^7And thou shalt smite the house of Ahab thy master, that I may avenge the blood of my servants the prophets, and the blood of all the servants of Jehovah, at the hand of Jezebel. ^8For the whole house of Ahab shall perish; and I will cut off from Ahab every man-child, and him that is shut up and him that is left at large in Israel. ^9And I will make the house of Ahab like the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and like the house of Baasha the son of Ahijah. ^10And the dogs shall eat Jezebel in the portion of Jezreel, and there shall be none to bury her. And he opened the door, and fled.

^11Then Jehu came forth to the servants of his lord: and one said unto him, Is all well? wherefore came this mad fellow to thee? And he said unto them, Ye know the man and what his talk was. ^12And they said, It is false; tell us now. And he said, Thus and thus spake he to me, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, I have anointed thee king over Israel. ^13Then they hasted, and took every man his garment, and put it under him on the top of the stairs, and blew the trumpet, saying, Jehu is king.

^14So Jehu the son of Jehoshaphat the son of Nimshi conspired against Joram. (Now Joram was keeping Ramoth-gilead, he and all Israel, because of Hazael king of Syria; ^15but king Joram was returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds which the Syrians had given him, when he fought with Hazael king of Syria.) And Jehu said, If this be your mind, then let none escape and go forth out of the city, to go to tell it in Jezreel. ^16So Jehu rode in a chariot, and went to Jezreel; for Joram lay there. And Ahaziah king of Judah was come down to see Joram.

^17Now the watchman was standing on the tower in Jezreel, and he spied the company of Jehu as he came, and said, I see a company. And Joram said, Take a horseman, and send to meet them, and let him say, Is it peace? ^18So there went one on horseback to meet him, and said, Thus saith the king, Is it peace? And Jehu said, What hast thou to do with peace? turn thee behind me. And the watchman told, saying, The messenger came to them, but he cometh not back. ^19Then he sent out a second on horseback, who came to them, and said, Thus saith the king, Is it peace? And Jehu answered, What hast thou to do with peace? turn thee behind me. ^20And the watchman told, saying, He came even unto them, and cometh not back: and the driving is like the driving of Jehu the son of Nimshi; for he driveth furiously.

^21And Joram said, Make ready. And they made ready his chariot. And Joram king of Israel and Ahaziah king of Judah went out, each in his chariot, and they went out to meet Jehu, and found him in the portion of Naboth the Jezreelite. ^22And it came to pass, when Joram saw Jehu, that he said, Is it peace, Jehu? And he answered, What peace, so long as the whoredoms of thy mother Jezebel and her witchcrafts are so many? ^23And Joram turned his hands, and fled, and said to Ahaziah, There is treachery, O Ahaziah. ^24And Jehu drew his bow with his full strength, and smote Joram between his arms; and the arrow went out at his heart, and he sunk down in his chariot. ^25Then said Jehu to Bidkar his captain, Take up, and cast him in the portion of the field of Naboth the Jezreelite; for remember how that, when I and thou rode together after Ahab his father, Jehovah laid this burden upon him: ^26Surely I have seen yesterday the blood of Naboth, and the blood of his sons, saith Jehovah; and I will requite thee in this plat, saith Jehovah. Now therefore take and cast him into the plat of ground, according to the word of Jehovah.

^27But when Ahaziah the king of Judah saw this, he fled by the way of the garden-house. And Jehu followed after him, and said, Smite him also in the chariot: and they smote him at the ascent of Gur, which is by Ibleam. And he fled to Megiddo, and died there. ^28And his servants carried him in a chariot to Jerusalem, and buried him in his sepulchre with his fathers in the city of David.

^29And in the eleventh year of Joram the son of Ahab began Ahaziah to reign over Judah. ^30And when Jehu was come to Jezreel, Jezebel heard of it; and she painted her eyes, and attired her head, and looked out at the window. ^31And as Jehu entered in at the gate, she said, Is it peace, thou Zimri, thy master's murderer? ^32And he lifted up his face to the window, and said, Who is on my side? who? And there looked out to him two or three eunuchs. ^33And he said, Throw her down. So they threw her down; and some of her blood was sprinkled on the wall, and on the horses: and he trod her under foot. ^34And when he was come in, he did eat and drink; and he said, See now to this cursed woman, and bury her; for she is a king's daughter. ^35And they went to bury her; but they found no more of her than the skull, and the feet, and the palms of her hands. ^36Wherefore they came back, and told him. And he said, This is the word of Jehovah, which he spake by his servant Elijah the Tishbite, saying, In the portion of Jezreel shall the dogs eat the flesh of Jezebel; ^37and the body of Jezebel shall be as dung upon the face of the field in the portion of Jezreel, so that they shall not say, This is Jezebel.

2 Kings 10

10

^1Now Ahab had seventy sons in Samaria. And Jehu wrote letters, and sent to Samaria, unto the rulers of Jezreel, even the elders, and unto them that brought up the sons of Ahab, saying, ^2And now as soon as this letter cometh to you, seeing your master's sons are with you, and there are with you chariots and horses, a fortified city also, and armor; ^3look ye out the best and meetest of your master's sons, and set him on his father's throne, and fight for your master's house. ^4But they were exceedingly afraid, and said, Behold, the two kings stood not before him: how then shall we stand? ^5And he that was over the household, and he that was over the city, the elders also, and they that brought up the children, sent to Jehu, saying, We are thy servants, and will do all that thou shalt bid us; we will not make any man king: do thou that which is good in thine eyes. ^6Then he wrote a letter the second time to them, saying, If ye be on my side, and if ye will hearken unto my voice, take ye the heads of the men your master's sons, and come to me to Jezreel by to-morrow this time. Now the king's sons, being seventy persons, were with the great men of the city, who brought them up. ^7And it came to pass, when the letter came to them, that they took the king's sons, and slew them, even seventy persons, and put their heads in baskets, and sent them unto him to Jezreel. ^8And there came a messenger, and told him, saying, They have brought the heads of the king's sons. And he said, Lay ye them in two heaps at the entrance of the gate until the morning. ^9And it came to pass in the morning, that he went out, and stood, and said to all the people, Ye are righteous: behold, I conspired against my master, and slew him; but who smote all these? ^10Know now that there shall fall unto the earth nothing of the word of Jehovah, which Jehovah spake concerning the house of Ahab: for Jehovah hath done that which he spake by his servant Elijah. ^11So Jehu smote all that remained of the house of Ahab in Jezreel, and all his great men, and his familiar friends, and his priests, until he left him none remaining.

^12And he arose and departed, and went to Samaria. And as he was at the shearing-house of the shepherds in the way, ^13Jehu met with the brethren of Ahaziah king of Judah, and said, Who are ye? And they answered, We are the brethren of Ahaziah: and we go down to salute the children of the king and the children of the queen. ^14And he said, Take them alive. And they took them alive, and slew them at the pit of the shearing-house, even two and forty men; neither left he any of them. ^15And when he was departed thence, he lighted on Jehonadab the son of Rechab coming to meet him; and he saluted him, and said to him, Is thy heart right, as my heart is with thy heart? And Jehonadab answered, It is. If it be, give me thy hand. And he gave him his hand; and he took him up to him into the chariot. ^16And he said, Come with me, and see my zeal for Jehovah. So they made him ride in his chariot. ^17And when he came to Samaria, he smote all that remained unto Ahab in Samaria, till he had destroyed him, according to the word of Jehovah, which he spake to Elijah.

^18And Jehu gathered all the people together, and said unto them, Ahab served Baal a little; but Jehu will serve him much. ^19Now therefore call unto me all the prophets of Baal, all his worshippers, and all his priests; let none be wanting: for I have a great sacrifice to do to Baal; whosoever shall be wanting, he shall not live. But Jehu did it in subtlety, to the intent that he might destroy the worshippers of Baal. ^20And Jehu said, Sanctify a solemn assembly for Baal. And they proclaimed it. ^21And Jehu sent through all Israel: and all the worshippers of Baal came, so that there was not a man left that came not. And they came into the house of Baal; and the house of Baal was filled from one end to another. ^22And he said unto him that was over the vestry, Bring forth vestments for all the worshippers of Baal. And he brought them forth vestments. ^23And Jehu went, and Jehonadab the son of Rechab, into the house of Baal; and he said unto the worshippers of Baal, Search, and look that there be here with you none of the servants of Jehovah, but the worshippers of Baal only. ^24And they went in to offer sacrifices and burnt-offerings. Now Jehu had appointed him fourscore men without, and said, If any of the men whom I bring into your hands escape, he that letteth him go, his life shall be for the life of him.

^25And it came to pass, as soon as he had made an end of offering the burnt-offering, that Jehu said to the guard and to the captains, Go in, and slay them; let none come forth. And they smote them with the edge of the sword; and the guard and the captains cast them out, and went to the city of the house of Baal. ^26And they brought forth the pillars that were in the house of Baal, and burned them. ^27And they brake down the pillar of Baal, and brake down the house of Baal, and made it a draught-house, unto this day. ^28Thus Jehu destroyed Baal out of Israel.

^29Howbeit from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin, Jehu departed not from after them, to wit, the golden calves that were in Beth-el, and that were in Dan. ^30And Jehovah said unto Jehu, Because thou hast done well in executing that which is right in mine eyes, and hast done unto the house of Ahab according to all that was in my heart, thy sons of the fourth generation shall sit on the throne of Israel. ^31But Jehu took no heed to walk in the law of Jehovah, the God of Israel, with all his heart: he departed not from the sins of Jeroboam, wherewith he made Israel to sin.

^32In those days Jehovah began to cut off from Israel: and Hazael smote them in all the borders of Israel; ^33from the Jordan eastward, all the land of Gilead, the Gadites, and the Reubenites, and the Manassites, from Aroer, which is by the valley of the Arnon, even Gilead and Bashan. ^34Now the rest of the acts of Jehu, and all that he did, and all his might, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^35And Jehu slept with his fathers; and they buried him in Samaria. And Jehoahaz his son reigned in his stead. ^36And the time that Jehu reigned over Israel in Samaria was twenty and eight years.

2 Kings 11

11

^1Now when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the seed royal. ^2But Jehosheba, the daughter of king Joram, sister of Ahaziah, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him away from among the king's sons that were slain, even him and his nurse, and put them in the bedchamber; and they hid him from Athaliah, so that he was not slain; ^3And he was with her hid in the house of Jehovah six years. And Athaliah reigned over the land.

^4And in the seventh year Jehoiada sent and fetched the captains over hundreds of the Carites and of the guard, and brought them to him into the house of Jehovah; and he made a covenant with them, and took an oath of them in the house of Jehovah, and showed them the king's son. ^5And he commanded them, saying, This is the thing that ye shall do: a third part of you, that come in on the sabbath, shall be keepers of the watch of the king's house; ^6And a third part shall be at the gate Sur; and a third part at the gate behind the guard: so shall ye keep the watch of the house, and be a barrier. ^7And the two companies of you, even all that go forth on the sabbath, shall keep the watch of the house of Jehovah about the king. ^8And ye shall compass the king round about, every man with his weapons in his hand; and he that cometh within the ranks, let him be slain: and be ye with the king when he goeth out, and when he cometh in.

^9And the captains over hundreds did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded; and they took every man his men, those that were to come in on the sabbath, with those that were to go out on the sabbath, and came to Jehoiada the priest. ^10And the priest delivered to the captains over hundreds the spears and shields that had been king David's, which were in the house of Jehovah. ^11And the guard stood, every man with his weapons in his hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, along by the altar and the house, by the king round about. ^12Then he brought out the king's son, and put the crown upon him, and gave him the testimony; and they made him king, and anointed him; and they clapped their hands, and said, Long live the king.

^13And when Athaliah heard the noise of the guard and of the people, she came to the people into the house of Jehovah: ^14and she looked, and, behold, the king stood by the pillar, as the manner was, and the captains and the trumpets by the king; and all the people of the land rejoiced, and blew trumpets. Then Athaliah rent her clothes, and cried, Treason! treason! ^15And Jehoiada the priest commanded the captains of hundreds that were set over the host, and said unto them, Have her forth between the ranks; and him that followeth her slay with the sword. For the priest said, Let her not be slain in the house of Jehovah. ^16So they made way for her; and she went by the way of the horses' entry to the king's house: and there was she slain.

^17And Jehoiada made a covenant between Jehovah and the king and the people, that they should be Jehovah's people; between the king also and the people. ^18And all the people of the land went to the house of Baal, and brake it down; his altars and his images brake they in pieces thoroughly, and slew Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. And the priest appointed officers over the house of Jehovah. ^19And he took the captains over hundreds, and the Carites, and the guard, and all the people of the land; and they brought down the king from the house of Jehovah, and came by the way of the gate of the guard unto the king's house. And he sat on the throne of the kings. ^20So all the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was quiet. And Athaliah they had slain with the sword at the king's house. ^21Jehoash was seven years old when he began to reign.

2 Kings 12

12

^1In the seventh year of Jehu began Jehoash to reign; and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Zibiah of Beer-sheba. ^2And Jehoash did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah all his days wherein Jehoiada the priest instructed him. ^3Howbeit the high places were not taken away; the people still sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places.

^4And Jehoash said to the priests, All the money of the hallowed things that is brought into the house of Jehovah, in current money, the money of the persons for whom each man is rated, and all the money that it cometh into any man's heart to bring into the house of Jehovah, ^5let the priests take it to them, every man from his acquaintance; and they shall repair the breaches of the house, wheresoever any breach shall be found. ^6But it was so, that in the three and twentieth year of king Jehoash the priests had not repaired the breaches of the house. ^7Then king Jehoash called for Jehoiada the priest, and for the other priests, and said unto them, Why repair ye not the breaches of the house? now therefore take no more money from your acquaintance, but deliver it for the breaches of the house. ^8And the priests consented that they should take no more money from the people, neither repair the breaches of the house.

^9But Jehoiada the priest took a chest, and bored a hole in the lid of it, and set it beside the altar, on the right side as one cometh into the house of Jehovah: and the priests that kept the threshold put therein all the money that was brought into the house of Jehovah. ^10And it was so, when they saw that there was much money in the chest, that the king's scribe and the high priest came up, and they put up in bags and counted the money that was found in the house of Jehovah. ^11And they gave the money that was weighed out into the hands of them that did the work, that had the oversight of the house of Jehovah: and they paid it out to the carpenters and the builders, that wrought upon the house of Jehovah, ^12and to the masons and the hewers of stone, and for buying timber and hewn stone to repair the breaches of the house of Jehovah, and for all that was laid out for the house to repair it. ^13But there were not made for the house of Jehovah cups of silver, snuffers, basins, trumpets, any vessels of gold, or vessels of silver, of the money that was brought into the house of Jehovah; ^14for they gave that to them that did the work, and repaired therewith the house of Jehovah. ^15Moreover they reckoned not with the men, into whose hand they delivered the money to give to them that did the work; for they dealt faithfully. ^16The money for the trespass-offerings, and the money for the sin-offerings, was not brought into the house of Jehovah: it was the priests'.

^17Then Hazael king of Syria went up, and fought against Gath, and took it; and Hazael set his face to go up to Jerusalem. ^18And Jehoash king of Judah took all the hallowed things that Jehoshaphat and Jehoram and Ahaziah, his fathers, kings of Judah, had dedicated, and his own hallowed things, and all the gold that was found in the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and of the king's house, and sent it to Hazael king of Syria: and he went away from Jerusalem.

^19Now the rest of the acts of Joash, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^20And his servants arose, and made a conspiracy, and smote Joash at the house of Millo, on the way that goeth down to Silla. ^21For Jozacar the son of Shimeath, and Jehozabad the son of Shomer, his servants, smote him, and he died; and they buried him with his fathers in the city of David: and Amaziah his son reigned in his stead.

2 Kings 13

13

^1In the three and twentieth year of Joash the son of Ahaziah, king of Judah, Jehoahaz the son of Jehu began to reign over Israel in Samaria, and reigned seventeen years. ^2And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and followed the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin; he departed not therefrom. ^3And the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Israel, and he delivered them into the hand of Hazael king of Syria, and into the hand of Benhadad the son of Hazael, continually. ^4And Jehoahaz besought Jehovah, and Jehovah hearkened unto him; for he saw the oppression of Israel, how that the king of Syria oppressed them. ^5(And Jehovah gave Israel a saviour, so that they went out from under the hand of the Syrians; and the children of Israel dwelt in their tents as beforetime. ^6Nevertheless they departed not from the sins of the house of Jeroboam, wherewith he made Israel to sin, but walked therein: and there remained the Asherah also in Samaria.) ^7For he left not to Jehoahaz of the people save fifty horsemen, and ten chariots, and ten thousand footmen; for the king of Syria destroyed them, and made them like the dust in threshing. ^8Now the rest of the acts of Jehoahaz, and all that he did, and his might, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^9And Jehoahaz slept with his fathers; and they buried him in Samaria: and Joash his son reigned in his stead.

^10In the thirty and seventh year of Joash king of Judah began Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz to reign over Israel in Samaria, and reigned sixteen years. ^11And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah; he departed not from all the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin; but he walked therein. ^12Now the rest of the acts of Joash, and all that he did, and his might wherewith he fought against Amaziah king of Judah, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^13And Joash slept with his fathers; and Jeroboam sat upon his throne: and Joash was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel.

^14Now Elisha was fallen sick of his sickness whereof he died: and Joash the king of Israel came down unto him, and wept over him, and said, My father, my father, the chariots of Israel and the horsemen thereof! ^15And Elisha said unto him, Take bow and arrows; and he took unto him bow and arrows. ^16And he said to the king of Israel, Put thy hand upon the bow; and he put his hand upon it. And Elisha laid his hands upon the king's hands. ^17And he said, Open the window eastward; and he opened it. Then Elisha said, Shoot; and he shot. And he said, Jehovah's arrow of victory, even the arrow of victory over Syria; for thou shalt smite the Syrians in Aphek, till thou have consumed them. ^18And he said, Take the arrows; and he took them. And he said unto the king of Israel, Smite upon the ground; and he smote thrice, and stayed. ^19And the man of God was wroth with him, and said, Thou shouldest have smitten five or six times: then hadst thou smitten Syria till thou hadst consumed it, whereas now thou shalt smite Syria but thrice.

^20And Elisha died, and they buried him. Now the bands of the Moabites invaded the land at the coming in of the year. ^21And it came to pass, as they were burying a man, that, behold, they spied a band; and they cast the man into the sepulchre of Elisha: and as soon as the man touched the bones of Elisha, he revived, and stood up on his feet.

^22And Hazael king of Syria oppressed Israel all the days of Jehoahaz. ^23But Jehovah was gracious unto them, and had compassion on them, and had respect unto them, because of his covenant with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and would not destroy them, neither cast he them from his presence as yet. ^24And Hazael king of Syria died; and Benhadad his son reigned in his stead. ^25And Jehoash the son of Jehoahaz took again out of the hand of Benhadad the son of Hazael the cities which he had taken out of the hand of Jehoahaz his father by war. Three times did Joash smite him, and recovered the cities of Israel.

2 Kings 14

14

^1In the second year of Joash son of Joahaz king of Israel began Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah to reign. ^2He was twenty and five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty and nine years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Jehoaddin of Jerusalem. ^3And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, yet not like David his father: he did according to all that Joash his father had done. ^4Howbeit the high places were not taken away: the people still sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places. ^5And it came to pass, as soon as the kingdom was established in his hand, that he slew his servants who had slain the king his father: ^6but the children of the murderers he put not to death; according to that which is written in the book of the law of Moses, as Jehovah commanded, saying, The fathers shall not be put to death for the children, nor the children be put to death for the fathers; but every man shall die for his own sin. ^7He slew of Edom in the Valley of Salt ten thousand, and took Sela by war, and called the name of it Joktheel, unto this day.

^8Then Amaziah sent messengers to Jehoash, the son of Jehoahaz son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, Come, let us look one another in the face. ^9And Jehoash the king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, The thistle that was in Lebanon sent to the cedar that was in Lebanon, saying, Give thy daughter to my son to wife: and there passed by a wild beast that was in Lebanon, and trod down the thistle. ^10Thou hast indeed smitten Edom, and thy heart hath lifted thee up: glory thereof, and abide at home; for why shouldest thou meddle to thy hurt, that thou shouldest fall, even thou, and Judah with thee?

^11But Amaziah would not hear. So Jehoash king of Israel went up; and he and Amaziah king of Judah looked one another in the face at Beth-shemesh, which belongeth to Judah. ^12And Judah was put to the worse before Israel; and they fled every man to his tent. ^13And Jehoash king of Israel took Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Jehoash the son of Ahaziah, at Beth-shemesh, and came to Jerusalem, and brake down the wall of Jerusalem from the gate of Ephraim unto the corner gate, four hundred cubits. ^14And he took all the gold and silver, and all the vessels that were found in the house of Jehovah, and in the treasures of the king's house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria.

^15Now the rest of the acts of Jehoash which he did, and his might, and how he fought with Amaziah king of Judah, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^16And Jehoash slept with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria with the kings of Israel; and Jeroboam his son reigned in his stead.

^17And Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah lived after the death of Jehoash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel fifteen years. ^18Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^19And they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem; and he fled to Lachish: but they sent after him to Lachish, and slew him there. ^20And they brought him upon horses; and he was buried at Jerusalem with his fathers in the city of David. ^21And all the people of Judah took Azariah, who was sixteen years old, and made him king in the room of his father Amaziah. ^22He built Elath, and restored it to Judah, after that the king slept with his fathers.

^23In the fifteenth year of Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah Jeroboam the son of Joash king of Israel began to reign in Samaria, and reigned forty and one years. ^24And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah: he departed not from all the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin. ^25He restored the border of Israel from the entrance of Hamath unto the sea of the Arabah, according to the word of Jehovah, the God of Israel, which he spake by his servant Jonah the son of Amittai, the prophet, who was of Gath-hepher. ^26For Jehovah saw the affliction of Israel, that it was very bitter; for there was none shut up nor left at large, neither was there any helper for Israel. ^27And Jehovah said not that he would blot out the name of Israel from under heaven; but he saved them by the hand of Jeroboam the son of Joash.

^28Now the rest of the acts of Jeroboam, and all that he did, and his might, how he warred, and how he recovered Damascus, and Hamath, which had belonged to Judah, for Israel, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^29And Jeroboam slept with his fathers, even with the kings of Israel; and Zechariah his son reigned in his stead.

2 Kings 15

15

^1In the twenty and seventh year of Jeroboam king of Israel began Azariah son of Amaziah king of Judah to reign. ^2Sixteen years old was he when he began to reign; and he reigned two and fifty years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Jecoliah of Jerusalem. ^3And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that his father Amaziah had done. ^4Howbeit the high places were not taken away: the people still sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places. ^5And Jehovah smote the king, so that he was a leper unto the day of his death, and dwelt in a separate house. And Jotham the king's son was over the household, judging the people of the land. ^6Now the rest of the acts of Azariah, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^7And Azariah slept with his fathers; and they buried him with his fathers in the city of David: and Jotham his son reigned in his stead.

^8In the thirty and eighth year of Azariah king of Judah did Zechariah the son of Jeroboam reign over Israel in Samaria six months. ^9And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, as his fathers had done: he departed not from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin. ^10And Shallum the son of Jabesh conspired against him, and smote him before the people, and slew him, and reigned in his stead. ^11Now the rest of the acts of Zechariah, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel. ^12This was the word of Jehovah which he spake unto Jehu, saying, Thy sons to the fourth generation shall sit upon the throne of Israel. And so it came to pass.

^13Shallum the son of Jabesh began to reign in the nine and thirtieth year of Uzziah king of Judah; and he reigned the space of a month in Samaria. ^14And Menahem the son of Gadi went up from Tirzah, and came to Samaria, and smote Shallum the son of Jabesh in Samaria, and slew him, and reigned in his stead. ^15Now the rest of the acts of Shallum, and his conspiracy which he made, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel. ^16Then Menahem smote Tiphsah, and all that were therein, and the borders thereof, from Tirzah: because they opened not to him, therefore he smote it; and all the women therein that were with child he ripped up.

^17In the nine and thirtieth year of Azariah king of Judah began Menahem the son of Gadi to reign over Israel, and reigned ten years in Samaria. ^18And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah: he departed not all his days from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin. ^19There came against the land Pul the king of Assyria; and Menahem gave Pul a thousand talents of silver, that his hand might be with him to confirm the kingdom in his hand. ^20And Menahem exacted the money of Israel, even of all the mighty men of wealth, of each man fifty shekels of silver, to give to the king of Assyria. So the king of Assyria turned back, and stayed not there in the land. ^21Now the rest of the acts of Menahem, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^22And Menahem slept with his fathers; and Pekahiah his son reigned in his stead.

^23In the fiftieth year of Azariah king of Judah Pekahiah the son of Menahem began to reign over Israel in Samaria, and reigned two years. ^24And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah: he departed not from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin. ^25And Pekah the son of Remaliah, his captain, conspired against him, and smote him in Samaria, in the castle of the king's house, with Argob and Arieh; and with him were fifty men of the Gileadites: and he slew him, and reigned in his stead. ^26Now the rest of the acts of Pekahiah, and all that he did, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.

^27In the two and fiftieth year of Azariah king of Judah Pekah the son of Remaliah began to reign over Israel in Samaria, and reigned twenty years. ^28And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah: he departed not from the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherewith he made Israel to sin.

^29In the days of Pekah king of Israel came Tiglath-pileser king of Assyria, and took Ijon, and Abel-beth-maacah, and Janoah, and Kedesh, and Hazor, and Gilead, and Galilee, all the land of Naphtali; and he carried them captive to Assyria. ^30And Hoshea the son of Elah made a conspiracy against Pekah the son of Remaliah, and smote him, and slew him, and reigned in his stead, in the twentieth year of Jotham the son of Uzziah. ^31Now the rest of the acts of Pekah, and all that he did, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel.

^32In the second year of Pekah the son of Remaliah king of Israel began Jotham the son of Uzziah king of Judah to reign. ^33Five and twenty years old was he when he began to reign; and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Jerusha the daughter of Zadok. ^34And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah; he did according to all that his father Uzziah had done. ^35Howbeit the high places were not taken away: the people still sacrificed and burned incense in the high places. He built the upper gate of the house of Jehovah. ^36Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^37In those days Jehovah began to send against Judah Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah the son of Remaliah. ^38And Jotham slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David his father: and Ahaz his son reigned in his stead.

2 Kings 16

16

^1In the seventeenth year of Pekah the son of Remaliah Ahaz the son of Jotham king of Judah began to reign. ^2Twenty years old was Ahaz when he began to reign; and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem: and he did not that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah his God, like David his father. ^3But he walked in the way of the kings of Israel, yea, and made his son to pass through the fire, according to the abominations of the nations, whom Jehovah cast out from before the children of Israel. ^4And he sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places, and on the hills, and under every green tree.

^5Then Rezin king of Syria and Pekah son of Remaliah king of Israel came up to Jerusalem to war: and they besieged Ahaz, but could not overcome him. ^6At that time Rezin king of Syria recovered Elath to Syria, and drove the Jews from Elath; and the Syrians came to Elath, and dwelt there, unto this day.

^7So Ahaz sent messengers to Tiglath-pileser king of Assyria, saying, I am thy servant and thy son: come up, and save me out of the hand of the king of Syria, and out of the hand of the king of Israel, who rise up against me. ^8And Ahaz took the silver and gold that was found in the house of Jehovah, and in the treasures of the king's house, and sent it for a present to the king of Assyria. ^9And the king of Assyria hearkened unto him; and the king of Assyria went up against Damascus, and took it, and carried the people of it captive to Kir, and slew Rezin.

^10And king Ahaz went to Damascus to meet Tiglath-pileser king of Assyria, and saw the altar that was at Damascus; and king Ahaz sent to Urijah the priest the fashion of the altar, and the pattern of it, according to all the workmanship thereof. ^11And Urijah the priest built an altar: according to all that king Ahaz had sent from Damascus, so did Urijah the priest make it against the coming of king Ahaz from Damascus. ^12And when the king was come from Damascus, the king saw the altar: and the king drew near unto the altar, and offered thereon. ^13And he burnt his burnt-offering and his meal-offering, and poured his drink-offering, and sprinkled the blood of his peace-offerings, upon the altar. ^14And the brazen altar, which was before Jehovah, he brought from the forefront of the house, from between his altar and the house of Jehovah, and put it on the north side of his altar. ^15And king Ahaz commanded Urijah the priest, saying, Upon the great altar burn the morning burnt-offering, and the evening meal-offering, and the king's burnt-offering, and his meal-offering, with the burnt-offering of all the people of the land, and their meal-offering, and their drink-offerings; and sprinkle upon it all the blood of the burnt-offering, and all the blood of the sacrifice: but the brazen altar shall be for me to inquire by. ^16Thus did Urijah the priest, according to all that king Ahaz commanded.

^17And king Ahaz cut off the panels of the bases, and removed the laver from off them, and took down the sea from off the brazen oxen that were under it, and put it upon a pavement of stone. ^18And the covered way for the sabbath that they had built in the house, and the king's entry without, turned he unto the house of Jehovah, because of the king of Assyria. ^19Now the rest of the acts of Ahaz which he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^20And Ahaz slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David: and Hezekiah his son reigned in his stead.

2 Kings 17

17

^1In the twelfth year of Ahaz king of Judah began Hoshea the son of Elah to reign in Samaria over Israel, and reigned nine years. ^2And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, yet not as the kings of Israel that were before him. ^3Against him came up Shalmaneser king of Assyria; and Hoshea became his servant, and brought him tribute. ^4And the king of Assyria found conspiracy in Hoshea; for he had sent messengers to So king of Egypt, and offered no tribute to the king of Assyria, as he had done year by year: therefore the king of Assyria shut him up, and bound him in prison. ^5Then the king of Assyria came up throughout all the land, and went up to Samaria, and besieged it three years. ^6In the ninth year of Hoshea the king of Assyria took Samaria, and carried Israel away unto Assyria, and placed them in Halah, and on the Habor, the river of Gozan, and in the cities of the Medes.

^7And it was so, because the children of Israel had sinned against Jehovah their God, who brought them up out of the land of Egypt from under the hand of Pharaoh king of Egypt, and had feared other gods, ^8and walked in the statutes of the nations, whom Jehovah cast out from before the children of Israel, and of the kings of Israel, which they made. ^9And the children of Israel did secretly things that were not right against Jehovah their God: and they built them high places in all their cities, from the tower of the watchmen to the fortified city; ^10and they set them up pillars and Asherim upon every high hill, and under every green tree; ^11and there they burnt incense in all the high places, as did the nations whom Jehovah carried away before them; and they wrought wicked things to provoke Jehovah to anger; ^12and they served idols, whereof Jehovah had said unto them, Ye shall not do this thing. ^13Yet Jehovah testified unto Israel, and unto Judah, by every prophet, and every seer, saying, Turn ye from your evil ways, and keep my commandments and my statutes, according to all the law which I commanded your fathers, and which I sent to you by my servants the prophets. ^14Notwithstanding, they would not hear, but hardened their neck, like to the neck of their fathers, who believed not in Jehovah their God. ^15And they rejected his statutes, and his covenant that he made with their fathers, and his testimonies which he testified unto them; and they followed vanity, and became vain, and went after the nations that were round about them, concerning whom Jehovah had charged them that they should not do like them. ^16And they forsook all the commandments of Jehovah their God, and made them molten images, even two calves, and made an Asherah, and worshipped all the host of heaven, and served Baal. ^17And they caused their sons and their daughters to pass through the fire, and used divination and enchantments, and sold themselves to do that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, to provoke him to anger. ^18Therefore Jehovah was very angry with Israel, and removed them out of his sight: there was none left but the tribe of Judah only.

^19Also Judah kept not the commandments of Jehovah their God, but walked in the statutes of Israel which they made. ^20And Jehovah rejected all the seed of Israel, and afflicted them, and delivered them into the hand of spoilers, until he had cast them out of his sight. ^21For he rent Israel from the house of David; and they made Jeroboam the son of Nebat king: and Jeroboam drove Israel from following Jehovah, and made them sin a great sin. ^22And the children of Israel walked in all the sins of Jeroboam which he did; they departed not from them; ^23until Jehovah removed Israel out of his sight, as he spake by all his servants the prophets. So Israel was carried away out of their own land to Assyria unto this day.

^24And the king of Assyria brought men from Babylon, and from Cuthah, and from Avva, and from Hamath and Sepharvaim, and placed them in the cities of Samaria instead of the children of Israel; and they possessed Samaria, and dwelt in the cities thereof. ^25And so it was, at the beginning of their dwelling there, that they feared not Jehovah: therefore Jehovah sent lions among them, which killed some of them. ^26Wherefore they spake to the king of Assyria, saying, The nations which thou hast carried away, and placed in the cities of Samaria, know not the law of the god of the land: therefore he hath sent lions among them, and, behold, they slay them, because they know not the law of the god of the land.

^27Then the king of Assyria commanded, saying, Carry thither one of the priests whom ye brought from thence; and let them go and dwell there, and let him teach them the law of the god of the land. ^28So one of the priests whom they had carried away from Samaria came and dwelt in Beth-el, and taught them how they should fear Jehovah. ^29Howbeit every nation made gods of their own, and put them in the houses of the high places which the Samaritans had made, every nation in their cities wherein they dwelt. ^30And the men of Babylon made Succoth-benoth, and the men of Cuth made Nergal, and the men of Hamath made Ashima, ^31and the Avvites made Nibhaz and Tartak; and the Sepharvites burnt their children in the fire to Adrammelech and Anammelech, the gods of Sepharvaim. ^32So they feared Jehovah, and made unto them from among themselves priests of the high places, who sacrificed for them in the houses of the high places. ^33They feared Jehovah, and served their own gods, after the manner of the nations from among whom they had been carried away.

^34Unto this day they do after the former manner: they fear not Jehovah, neither do they after their statutes, or after their ordinances, or after the law or after the commandment which Jehovah commanded the children of Jacob, whom he named Israel; ^35with whom Jehovah had made a covenant, and charged them, saying, Ye shall not fear other gods, nor bow yourselves to them, nor serve them, nor sacrifice to them: ^36but Jehovah, who brought you up out of the land of Egypt with great power and with an outstretched arm, him shall ye fear, and unto him shall ye bow yourselves, and to him shall ye sacrifice: ^37and the statutes and the ordinances, and the law and the commandment, which he wrote for you, ye shall observe to do for evermore; and ye shall not fear other gods: ^38and the covenant that I have made with you ye shall not forget; neither shall ye fear other gods: ^39but Jehovah your God shall ye fear; and he will deliver you out of the hand of all your enemies. ^40Howbeit they did not hearken, but they did after their former manner. ^41So these nations feared Jehovah, and served their graven images; their children likewise, and their children's children, as did their fathers, so do they unto this day.

2 Kings 18

18

^1Now it came to pass in the third year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, that Hezekiah the son of Ahaz king of Judah began to reign. ^2Twenty and five years old was he when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty and nine years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Abi the daughter of Zechariah. ^3And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that David his father had done. ^4He removed the high places, and brake the pillars, and cut down the Asherah: and he brake in pieces the brazen serpent that Moses had made; for unto those days the children of Israel did burn incense to it; and he called it Nehushtan. ^5He trusted in Jehovah, the God of Israel; so that after him was none like him among all the kings of Judah, nor among them that were before him. ^6For he clave to Jehovah; he departed not from following him, but kept his commandments, which Jehovah commanded Moses. ^7And Jehovah was with him; whithersoever he went forth he prospered: and he rebelled against the king of Assyria, and served him not. ^8He smote the Philistines unto Gaza and the borders thereof, from the tower of the watchmen to the fortified city.

^9And it came to pass in the fourth year of king Hezekiah, which was the seventh year of Hoshea son of Elah king of Israel, that Shalmaneser king of Assyria came up against Samaria, and besieged it. ^10And at the end of three years they took it: in the sixth year of Hezekiah, which was the ninth year of Hoshea king of Israel, Samaria was taken. ^11And the king of Assyria carried Israel away unto Assyria, and put them in Halah, and on the Habor, the river of Gozan, and in the cities of the Medes, ^12because they obeyed not the voice of Jehovah their God, but transgressed his covenant, even all that Moses the servant of Jehovah commanded, and would not hear it, nor do it.

^13Now in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah did Sennacherib king of Assyria come up against all the fortified cities of Judah, and took them. ^14And Hezekiah king of Judah sent to the king of Assyria to Lachish, saying, I have offended; return from me: that which thou puttest on me will I bear. And the king of Assyria appointed unto Hezekiah king of Judah three hundred talents of silver and thirty talents of gold. ^15And Hezekiah gave him all the silver that was found in the house of Jehovah, and in the treasures of the king's house. ^16At that time did Hezekiah cut off the gold from the doors of the temple of Jehovah, and from the pillars which Hezekiah king of Judah had overlaid, and gave it to the king of Assyria. ^17And the king of Assyria sent Tartan and Rab-saris and Rabshakeh from Lachish to king Hezekiah with a great army unto Jerusalem. And they went up and came to Jerusalem. And when they were come up, they came and stood by the conduit of the upper pool, which is in the highway of the fuller's field. ^18And when they had called to the king, there came out to them Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, and Shebnah the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph the recorder.

^19And Rabshakeh said unto them, Say ye now to Hezekiah, Thus saith the great king, the king of Assyria, What confidence is this wherein thou trustest? ^20Thou sayest (but they are but vain words), There is counsel and strength for the war. Now on whom dost thou trust, that thou hast rebelled against me? ^21Now, behold, thou trustest upon the staff of this bruised reed, even upon Egypt; whereon if a man lean, it will go into his hand, and pierce it: so is Pharaoh king of Egypt unto all that trust on him. ^22But if ye say unto me, We trust in Jehovah our God; is not that he, whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah hath taken away, and hath said to Judah and to Jerusalem, Ye shall worship before this altar in Jerusalem? ^23Now therefore, I pray thee, give pledges to my master the king of Assyria, and I will give thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to set riders upon them. ^24How then canst thou turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master's servants, and put thy trust on Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? ^25Am I now come up without Jehovah against this place to destroy it? Jehovah said unto me, Go up against this land, and destroy it.

^26Then said Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, and Shebnah, and Joah, unto Rabshakeh, Speak, I pray thee, to thy servants in the Syrian language; for we understand it: and speak not with us in the Jews' language, in the ears of the people that are on the wall. ^27But Rabshakeh said unto them, Hath my master sent me to thy master, and to thee, to speak these words? hath he not sent me to the men that sit on the wall, to eat their own dung, and to drink their own water with you? ^28Then Rabshakeh stood, and cried with a loud voice in the Jews' language, and spake, saying, Hear ye the word of the great king, the king of Assyria. ^29Thus saith the king, Let not Hezekiah deceive you; for he will not be able to deliver you out of his hand: ^30neither let Hezekiah make you trust in Jehovah, saying, Jehovah will surely deliver us, and this city shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria. ^31Hearken not to Hezekiah: for thus saith the king of Assyria, Make your peace with me, and come out to me; and eat ye every one of his vine, and every one of his fig-tree, and drink ye every one the waters of his own cistern; ^32Until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards, a land of olive-trees and of honey, that ye may live, and not die: and hearken not unto Hezekiah, when he persuadeth you, saying, Jehovah will deliver us. ^33Hath any of the gods of the nations ever delivered his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria? ^34Where are the gods of Hamath, and of Arpad? where are the gods of Sepharvaim, of Hena, and Ivvah? have they delivered Samaria out of my hand? ^35Who are they among all the gods of the countries, that have delivered their country out of my hand, that Jehovah should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand?

^36But the people held their peace, and answered him not a word; for the king's commandment was, saying, Answer him not. ^37Then came Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah the son of Asaph the recorder, to Hezekiah with their clothes rent, and told him the words of Rabshakeh.

2 Kings 20

20

^1In those days was Hezekiah sick unto death. And Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz came to him, and said unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, Set thy house in order: for thou shalt die, and not live. ^2Then he turned his face to the wall, and prayed unto Jehovah, saying, ^3Remember now, O Jehovah, I beseech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight. And Hezekiah wept sore. ^4And it came to pass, before Isaiah was gone out into the middle part of the city, that the word of Jehovah came to him, saying, ^5Turn back, and say to Hezekiah the prince of my people, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of David thy father, I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears: behold, I will heal thee; on the third day thou shalt go up unto the house of Jehovah. ^6And I will add unto thy days fifteen years; and I will deliver thee and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria; and I will defend this city for mine own sake, and for my servant David's sake. ^7And Isaiah said, Take a cake of figs. And they took and laid it on the boil, and he recovered.

^8And Hezekiah said unto Isaiah, What shall be the sign that Jehovah will heal me, and that I shall go up unto the house of Jehovah the third day? ^9And Isaiah said, This shall be the sign unto thee from Jehovah, that Jehovah will do the thing that he hath spoken: shall the shadow go forward ten steps, or go back ten steps? ^10And Hezekiah answered, It is a light thing for the shadow to decline ten steps: nay, but let the shadow return backward ten steps. ^11And Isaiah the prophet cried unto Jehovah; and he brought the shadow ten steps backward, by which it had gone down on the dial of Ahaz.

^12At that time Berodach-baladan the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent letters and a present unto Hezekiah; for he had heard that Hezekiah had been sick. ^13And Hezekiah hearkened unto them, and showed them all the house of his precious things, the silver, and the gold, and the spices, and the precious oil, and the house of his armor, and all that was found in his treasures: there was nothing in his house, nor in all his dominion, that Hezekiah showed them not. ^14Then came Isaiah the prophet unto king Hezekiah, and said unto him, What said these men? and from whence came they unto thee? And Hezekiah said, They are come from a far country, even from Babylon. ^15And he said, What have they seen in thy house? And Hezekiah answered, All that is in my house have they seen: there is nothing among my treasures that I have not showed them.

^16And Isaiah said unto Hezekiah, Hear the word of Jehovah. ^17Behold, the days come, that all that is in thy house, and that which thy fathers have laid up in store unto this day, shall be carried to Babylon: nothing shall be left, saith Jehovah. ^18And of thy sons that shall issue from thee, whom thou shalt beget, shall they take away; and they shall be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon. ^19Then said Hezekiah unto Isaiah, Good is the word of Jehovah which thou hast spoken. He said moreover, Is it not so, if peace and truth shall be in my days? ^20Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and all his might, and how he made the pool, and the conduit, and brought water into the city, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^21And Hezekiah slept with his fathers; and Manasseh his son reigned in his stead.

2 Kings 21

21

^1Manasseh was twelve years old when he began to reign; and he reigned five and fifty years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Hephzibah. ^2And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, after the abominations of the nations whom Jehovah cast out before the children of Israel. ^3For he built again the high places which Hezekiah his father had destroyed; and he reared up altars for Baal, and made an Asherah, as did Ahab king of Israel, and worshipped all the host of heaven, and served them. ^4And he built altars in the house of Jehovah, whereof Jehovah said, In Jerusalem will I put my name. ^5And he built altars for all the host of heaven in the two courts of the house of Jehovah. ^6And he made his son to pass through the fire, and practised augury, and used enchantments, and dealt with them that had familiar spirits, and with wizards: he wrought much evil in the sight of Jehovah, to provoke him to anger. ^7And he set the graven image of Asherah, that he had made, in the house of which Jehovah said to David and to Solomon his son, In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, will I put my name for ever; ^8neither will I cause the feet of Israel to wander any more out of the land which I gave their fathers, if only they will observe to do according to all that I have commanded them, and according to all the law that my servant Moses commanded them. ^9But they hearkened not: and Manasseh seduced them to do that which is evil more than did the nations whom Jehovah destroyed before the children of Israel.

^10And Jehovah spake by his servants the prophets, saying, ^11Because Manasseh king of Judah hath done these abominations, and hath done wickedly above all that the Amorites did, that were before him, and hath made Judah also to sin with his idols; ^12therefore thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Behold, I bring such evil upon Jerusalem and Judah, that whosoever heareth of it, both his ears shall tingle. ^13And I will stretch over Jerusalem the line of Samaria, and the plummet of the house of Ahab; and I will wipe Jerusalem as a man wipeth a dish, wiping it and turning it upside down. ^14And I will cast off the remnant of mine inheritance, and deliver them into the hand of their enemies; and they shall become a prey and a spoil to all their enemies; ^15because they have done that which is evil in my sight, and have provoked me to anger, since the day their fathers came forth out of Egypt, even unto this day.

^16Moreover Manasseh shed innocent blood very much, till he had filled Jerusalem from one end to another; besides his sin wherewith he made Judah to sin, in doing that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah. ^17Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and all that he did, and his sin that he sinned, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^18And Manasseh slept with his fathers, and was buried in the garden of his own house, in the garden of Uzza: and Amon his son reigned in his stead.

^19Amon was twenty and two years old when he began to reign; and he reigned two years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Meshullemeth the daughter of Haruz of Jotbah. ^20And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, as did Manasseh his father. ^21And he walked in all the way that his father walked in, and served the idols that his father served, and worshipped them: ^22and he forsook Jehovah, the God of his fathers, and walked not in the way of Jehovah. ^23And the servants of Amon conspired against him, and put the king to death in his own house. ^24But the people of the land slew all them that had conspired against king Amon; and the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his stead. ^25Now the rest of the acts of Amon which he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^26And he was buried in his sepulchre in the garden of Uzza: and Josiah his son reigned in his stead.

2 Kings 22

22

^1Josiah was eight years old when he began to reign; and he reigned thirty and one years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Jedidah the daughter of Adaiah of Bozkath. ^2And he did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, and walked in all the way of David his father, and turned not aside to the right hand or to the left.

^3And it came to pass in the eighteenth year of king Josiah, that the king sent Shaphan, the son of Azaliah the son of Meshullam, the scribe, to the house of Jehovah, saying, ^4Go up to Hilkiah the high priest, that he may sum the money which is brought into the house of Jehovah, which the keepers of the threshold have gathered of the people: ^5and let them deliver it into the hand of the workmen that have the oversight of the house of Jehovah; and let them give it to the workmen that are in the house of Jehovah, to repair the breaches of the house, ^6unto the carpenters, and to the builders, and to the masons, and for buying timber and hewn stone to repair the house. ^7Howbeit there was no reckoning made with them of the money that was delivered into their hand; for they dealt faithfully.

^8And Hilkiah the high priest said unto Shaphan the scribe, I have found the book of the law in the house of Jehovah. And Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan, and he read it. ^9And Shaphan the scribe came to the king, and brought the king word again, and said, Thy servants have emptied out the money that was found in the house, and have delivered it into the hand of the workmen that have the oversight of the house of Jehovah. ^10And Shaphan the scribe told the king, saying, Hilkiah the priest hath delivered me a book. And Shaphan read it before the king. ^11And it came to pass, when the king had heard the words of the book of the law, that he rent his clothes. ^12And the king commanded Hilkiah the priest, and Ahikam the son of Shaphan, and Achbor the son of Micaiah, and Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah the king's servant, saying, ^13Go ye, inquire of Jehovah for me, and for the people, and for all Judah, concerning the words of this book that is found; for great is the wrath of Jehovah that is kindled against us, because our fathers have not hearkened unto the words of this book, to do according unto all that which is written concerning us.

^14So Hilkiah the priest, and Ahikam, and Achbor, and Shaphan, and Asaiah, went unto Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tikvah, the son of Harhas, keeper of the wardrobe (now she dwelt in Jerusalem in the second quarter); and they communed with her. ^15And she said unto them, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel: Tell ye the man that sent you unto me, ^16Thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will bring evil upon this place, and upon the inhabitants thereof, even all the words of the book which the king of Judah hath read. ^17Because they have forsaken me, and have burned incense unto other gods, that they might provoke me to anger with all the work of their hands, therefore my wrath shall be kindled against this place, and it shall not be quenched. ^18But unto the king of Judah, who sent you to inquire of Jehovah, thus shall ye say to him, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel: As touching the words which thou hast heard, ^19because thy heart was tender, and thou didst humble thyself before Jehovah, when thou heardest what I spake against this place, and against the inhabitants thereof, that they should become a desolation and a curse, and hast rent thy clothes, and wept before me; I also have heard thee, saith Jehovah. ^20Therefore, behold, I will gather thee to thy fathers, and thou shalt be gathered to thy grave in peace, neither shall thine eyes see all the evil which I will bring upon this place. And they brought the king word again.

2 Kings 23

23

^1And the king sent, and they gathered unto him all the elders of Judah and of Jerusalem. ^2And the king went up to the house of Jehovah, and all the men of Judah and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem with him, and the priests, and the prophets, and all the people, both small and great: and he read in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant which was found in the house of Jehovah. ^3And the king stood by the pillar, and made a covenant before Jehovah, to walk after Jehovah, and to keep his commandments, and his testimonies, and his statutes, with all his heart, and all his soul, to confirm the words of this covenant that were written in this book: and all the people stood to the covenant.

^4And the king commanded Hilkiah the high priest, and the priests of the second order, and the keepers of the threshold, to bring forth out of the temple of Jehovah all the vessels that were made for Baal, and for the Asherah, and for all the host of heaven, and he burned them without Jerusalem in the fields of the Kidron, and carried the ashes of them unto Beth-el. ^5And he put down the idolatrous priests, whom the kings of Judah had ordained to burn incense in the high places in the cities of Judah, and in the places round about Jerusalem; them also that burned incense unto Baal, to the sun, and to the moon, and to the planets, and to all the host of heaven. ^6And he brought out the Asherah from the house of Jehovah, without Jerusalem, unto the brook Kidron, and burned it at the brook Kidron, and beat it to dust, and cast the dust thereof upon the graves of the common people. ^7And he brake down the houses of the sodomites, that were in the house of Jehovah, where the women wove hangings for the Asherah. ^8And he brought all the priests out of the cities of Judah, and defiled the high places where the priests had burned incense, from Geba to Beer-sheba; and he brake down the high places of the gates that were at the entrance of the gate of Joshua the governor of the city, which were on a man's left hand at the gate of the city. ^9Nevertheless the priests of the high places came not up to the altar of Jehovah in Jerusalem, but they did eat unleavened bread among their brethren. ^10And he defiled Topheth, which is in the valley of the children of Hinnom, that no man might make his son or his daughter to pass through the fire to Molech. ^11And he took away the horses that the kings of Judah had given to the sun, at the entrance of the house of Jehovah, by the chamber of Nathan-melech the chamberlain, which was in the precincts; and he burned the chariots of the sun with fire. ^12And the altars that were on the roof of the upper chamber of Ahaz, which the kings of Judah had made, and the altars which Manasseh had made in the two courts of the house of Jehovah, did the king break down, and beat them down from thence, and cast the dust of them into the brook Kidron. ^13And the high places that were before Jerusalem, which were on the right hand of the mount of corruption, which Solomon the king of Israel had builded for Ashtoreth the abomination of the Sidonians, and for Chemosh the abomination of Moab, and for Milcom the abomination of the children of Ammon, did the king defile. ^14And he brake in pieces the pillars, and cut down the Asherim, and filled their places with the bones of men.

^15Moreover the altar that was at Beth-el, and the high place which Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who made Israel to sin, had made, even that altar and the high place he brake down; and he burned the high place and beat it to dust, and burned the Asherah. ^16And as Josiah turned himself, he spied the sepulchres that were there in the mount; and he sent, and took the bones out of the sepulchres, and burned them upon the altar, and defiled it, according to the word of Jehovah which the man of God proclaimed, who proclaimed these things. ^17Then he said, What monument is that which I see? And the men of the city told him, It is the sepulchre of the man of God, who came from Judah, and proclaimed these things that thou hast done against the altar of Beth-el. ^18And he said, Let him be; let no man move his bones. So they let his bones alone, with the bones of the prophet that came out of Samaria. ^19And all the houses also of the high places that were in the cities of Samaria, which the kings of Israel had made to provoke Jehovah to anger, Josiah took away, and did to them according to all the acts that he had done in Beth-el. ^20And he slew all the priests of the high places that were there, upon the altars, and burned men's bones upon them; and he returned to Jerusalem.

^21And the king commanded all the people, saying, Keep the passover unto Jehovah your God, as it is written in this book of the covenant. ^22Surely there was not kept such a passover from the days of the judges that judged Israel, nor in all the days of the kings of Israel, nor of the kings of Judah; ^23but in the eighteenth year of king Josiah was this passover kept to Jehovah in Jerusalem.

^24Moreover them that had familiar spirits, and the wizards, and the teraphim, and the idols, and all the abominations that were seen in the land of Judah and in Jerusalem, did Josiah put away, that he might confirm the words of the law which were written in the book that Hilkiah the priest found in the house of Jehovah. ^25And like unto him was there no king before him, that turned to Jehovah with all his heart, and with all his soul, and with all his might, according to all the law of Moses; neither after him arose there any like him.

^26Notwithstanding, Jehovah turned not from the fierceness of his great wrath, wherewith his anger was kindled against Judah, because of all the provocations wherewith Manasseh had provoked him. ^27And Jehovah said, I will remove Judah also out of my sight, as I have removed Israel, and I will cast off this city which I have chosen, even Jerusalem, and the house of which I said, My name shall be there.

^28Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^29In his days Pharaoh-necoh king of Egypt went up against the king of Assyria to the river Euphrates: and king Josiah went against him; and Pharaoh-necoh slew him at Megiddo, when he had seen him. ^30And his servants carried him in a chariot dead from Megiddo, and brought him to Jerusalem, and buried him in his own sepulchre. And the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and anointed him, and made him king in his father's stead.

^31Jehoahaz was twenty and three years old when he began to reign; and he reigned three months in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. ^32And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, according to all that his fathers had done. ^33And Pharaoh-necoh put him in bonds at Riblah in the land of Hamath, that he might not reign in Jerusalem; and put the land to a tribute of a hundred talents of silver, and a talent of gold. ^34And Pharaoh-necoh made Eliakim the son of Josiah king in the room of Josiah his father, and changed his name to Jehoiakim: but he took Jehoahaz away; and he came to Egypt, and died there. ^35And Jehoiakim gave the silver and the gold to Pharaoh; but he taxed the land to give the money according to the commandment of Pharaoh: he exacted the silver and the gold of the people of the land, of every one according to his taxation, to give it unto Pharaoh-necoh.

^36Jehoiakim was twenty and five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Zebidah the daughter of Pedaiah of Rumah. ^37And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, according to all that his fathers had done.

2 Kings 24

24

^1In his days Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up, and Jehoiakim became his servant three years: then he turned and rebelled against him. ^2And Jehovah sent against him bands of the Chaldeans, and bands of the Syrians, and bands of the Moabites, and bands of the children of Ammon, and sent them against Judah to destroy it, according to the word of Jehovah, which he spake by his servants the prophets. ^3Surely at the commandment of Jehovah came this upon Judah, to remove them out of his sight, for the sins of Manasseh, according to all that he did, ^4and also for the innocent blood that he shed; for he filled Jerusalem with innocent blood: and Jehovah would not pardon. ^5Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^6So Jehoiakim slept with his fathers; and Jehoiachin his son reigned in his stead. ^7And the king of Egypt came not again any more out of his land; for the king of Babylon had taken, from the brook of Egypt unto the river Euphrates, all that pertained to the king of Egypt.

^8Jehoiachin was eighteen years old when he began to reign; and he reigned in Jerusalem three months: and his mother's name was Nehushta the daughter of Elnathan of Jerusalem. ^9And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, according to all that his father had done.

^10At that time the servants of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came up to Jerusalem, and the city was besieged. ^11And Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came unto the city, while his servants were besieging it; ^12and Jehoiachin the king of Judah went out to the king of Babylon, he, and his mother, and his servants, and his princes, and his officers: and the king of Babylon took him in the eighth year of his reign. ^13And he carried out thence all the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and the treasures of the king's house, and cut in pieces all the vessels of gold, which Solomon king of Israel had made in the temple of Jehovah, as Jehovah had said. ^14And he carried away all Jerusalem, and all the princes, and all the mighty men of valor, even ten thousand captives, and all the craftsmen and the smiths; none remained, save the poorest sort of the people of the land. ^15And he carried away Jehoiachin to Babylon; and the king's mother, and the king's wives, and his officers, and the chief men of the land, carried he into captivity from Jerusalem to Babylon. ^16And all the men of might, even seven thousand, and the craftsmen and the smiths a thousand, all of them strong and apt for war, even them the king of Babylon brought captive to Babylon. ^17And the king of Babylon made Mattaniah, Jehoiachin's father's brother, king is his stead, and changed his name to Zedekiah.

^18Zedekiah was twenty and one years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Hamutal the daughter of Jeremiah of Libnah. ^19And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, according to all that Jehoiakim had done. ^20For through the anger of Jehovah did it come to pass in Jerusalem and Judah, until he had cast them out from his presence. And Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylon.

2 Kings 25

25

^1And it came to pass in the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, in the tenth day of the month, that Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon came, he and all his army, against Jerusalem, and encamped against it; and they built forts against it round about. ^2So the city was besieged unto the eleventh year of king Zedekiah. ^3On the ninth day of the fourth month the famine was sore in the city, so that there was no bread for the people of the land. ^4Then a breach was made in the city, and all the men of war fled by night by the way of the gate between the two walls, which was by the king's garden (now the Chaldeans were against the city round about); and the king went by the way of the Arabah. ^5But the army of the Chaldeans pursued after the king, and overtook him in the plains of Jericho; and all his army was scattered from him. ^6Then they took the king, and carried him up unto the king of Babylon to Riblah; and they gave judgment upon him. ^7And they slew the sons of Zedekiah before his eyes, and put out the eyes of Zedekiah, and bound him in fetters, and carried him to Babylon.

^8Now in the fifth month, on the seventh day of the month, which was the nineteenth year of king Nebuchadnezzar, king of Babylon, came Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard, a servant of the king of Babylon, unto Jerusalem. ^9And he burnt the house of Jehovah, and the king's house; and all the houses of Jerusalem, even every great house, burnt he with fire. ^10And all the army of the Chaldeans, that were with the captain of the guard, brake down the walls of Jerusalem round about. ^11And the residue of the people that were left in the city, and those that fell away, that fell to the king of Babylon, and the residue of the multitude, did Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard carry away captive. ^12But the captain of the guard left of the poorest of the land to be vinedressers and husbandmen.

^13And the pillars of brass that were in the house of Jehovah, and the bases and the brazen sea that were in the house of Jehovah, did the Chaldeans break in pieces, and carried the brass of them to Babylon. ^14And the pots, and the shovels, and the snuffers, and the spoons, and all the vessels of brass wherewith they ministered, took they away. ^15And the firepans, and the basins, that which was of gold, in gold, and that which was of silver, in silver, the captain of the guard took away. ^16The two pillars, the one sea, and the bases, which Solomon had made for the house of Jehovah, the brass of all these vessels was without weight. ^17The height of the one pillar was eighteen cubits, and a capital of brass was upon it; and the height of the capital was three cubits, with network and pomegranates upon the capital round about, all of brass: and like unto these had the second pillar with network.

^18And the captain of the guard took Seraiah the chief priest, and Zephaniah the second priest, and the three keepers of the threshold: ^19and out of the city he took an officer that was set over the men of war; and five men of them that saw the king's face, who were found in the city; and the scribe, the captain of the host, who mustered the people of the land; and threescore men of the people of the land, that were found in the city. ^20And Nebuzaradan the captain of the guard took them, and brought them to the king of Babylon to Riblah. ^21And the king of Babylon smote them, and put them to death at Riblah in the land of Hamath. So Judah was carried away captive out of his land.

^22And as for the people that were left in the land of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon had left, even over them he made Gedaliah the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, governor. ^23Now when all the captains of the forces, they and their men, heard that the king of Babylon had made Gedaliah governor, they came to Gedaliah to Mizpah, even Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, and Johanan the son of Kareah, and Seraiah the son of Tanhumeth the Netophathite, and Jaazaniah the son of the Maacathite, they and their men. ^24And Gedaliah sware to them and to their men, and said unto them, Fear not because of the servants of the Chaldeans: dwell in the land, and serve the king of Babylon, and it shall be well with you. ^25But it came to pass in the seventh month, that Ishmael the son of Nethaniah, the son of Elishama, of the seed royal, came, and ten men with him, and smote Gedaliah, so that he died, and the Jews and the Chaldeans that were with him at Mizpah. ^26And all the people, both small and great, and the captains of the forces, arose, and came to Egypt; for they were afraid of the Chaldeans.

^27And it came to pass in the seven and thirtieth year of the captivity of Jehoiachin king of Judah, in the twelfth month, on the seven and twentieth day of the month, that Evil-merodach king of Babylon, in the year that he began to reign, did lift up the head of Jehoiachin king of Judah out of prison; ^28and he spake kindly to him, and set his throne above the throne of the kings that were with him in Babylon, ^29and changed his prison garments. And Jehoiachin did eat bread before him continually all the days of his life: ^30and for his allowance, there was a continual allowance given him of the king, every day a portion, all the days of his life.

2 Peter 2

2

^1But there arose false prophets also among the people, as among you also there shall be false teachers, who shall privily bring in destructive heresies, denying even the Master that bought them, bringing upon themselves swift destruction. ^2And many shall follow their lascivious doings; by reason of whom the way of the truth shall be evil spoken of. ^3And in covetousness shall they with feigned words make merchandise of you: whose sentence now from of old lingereth not, and their destruction slumbereth not. ^4For if God spared not angels when they sinned, but cast them down to hell, and committed them to pits of darkness, to be reserved unto judgment; ^5and spared not the ancient world, but preserved Noah with seven others, a preacher of righteousness, when he brought a flood upon the world of the ungodly; ^6and turning the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah into ashes condemned them with an overthrow, having made them an example unto those that should live ungodly; ^7and delivered righteous Lot, sore distressed by the lascivious life of the wicked ^8(for that righteous man dwelling among them, in seeing and hearing, vexed his righteous soul from day to day with their lawless deeds): ^9the Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptation, and to keep the unrighteous under punishment unto the day of judgment; ^10but chiefly them that walk after the flesh in the lust of defilement, and despise dominion. Daring, self-willed, they tremble not to rail at dignities: ^11whereas angels, though greater in might and power, bring not a railing judgment against them before the Lord. ^12But these, as creatures without reason, born mere animals to be taken and destroyed, railing in matters whereof they are ignorant, shall in their destroying surely be destroyed, ^13suffering wrong as the hire of wrong-doing; men that count it pleasure to revel in the day-time, spots and blemishes, revelling in their deceivings while they feast with you; ^14having eyes full of adultery, and that cannot cease from sin; enticing unstedfast souls; having a heart exercised in covetousness; children of cursing; ^15forsaking the right way, they went astray, having followed the way of Balaam the son of Beor, who loved the hire of wrong-doing; ^16but he was rebuked for his own transgression: a dumb ass spake with man's voice and stayed the madness of the prophet. ^17These are springs without water, and mists driven by a storm; for whom the blackness of darkness hath been reserved. ^18For, uttering great swelling words of vanity, they entice in the lusts of the flesh, by lasciviousness, those who are just escaping from them that live in error; ^19promising them liberty, while they themselves are bondservants of corruption; for of whom a man is overcome, of the same is he also brought into bondage. ^20For if, after they have escaped the defilements of the world through the knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, they are again entangled therein and overcome, the last state is become worse with them than the first. ^21For it were better for them not to have known the way of righteousness, than, after knowing it, to turn back from the holy commandment delivered unto them. ^22It has happened unto them according to the true proverb, The dog turning to his own vomit again, and the sow that had washed to wallowing in the mire.

2 Peter 3

3

^1This is now, beloved, the second epistle that I write unto you; and in both of them I stir up your sincere mind by putting you in remembrance; ^2that ye should remember the words which were spoken before by the holy prophets, and the commandments of the Lord and Saviour through your apostles: ^3knowing this first, that in the last days mockers shall come with mockery, walking after their own lusts, ^4and saying, Where is the promise of his coming? for, from the day that the fathers fell asleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the creation. ^5For this they willfully forget, that there were heavens from of old, and an earth compacted out of water and amidst water, by the word of God; ^6by which means the world that then was, being overflowed with water, perished: ^7but the heavens that now are, and the earth, by the same word have been stored up for fire, being reserved against the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men. ^8But forget not this one thing, beloved, that one day is with the Lord as a thousand years, and a thousand years as one day. ^9The Lord is not slack concerning his promise, as some count slackness; but is longsuffering to you-ward, not wishing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance. ^10But the day of the Lord will come as a thief; in the which the heavens shall pass away with a great noise, and the elements shall be dissolved with fervent heat, and the earth and the works that are therein shall be burned up. ^11Seeing that these things are thus all to be dissolved, what manner of persons ought ye to be in all holy living and godliness, ^12looking for and earnestly desiring the coming of the day of God, by reason of which the heavens being on fire shall be dissolved, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat? ^13But, according to his promise, we look for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteousness. ^14Wherefore, beloved, seeing that ye look for these things, give diligence that ye may be found in peace, without spot and blameless in his sight. ^15And account that the longsuffering of our Lord is salvation; even as our beloved brother Paul also, according to the wisdom given to him, wrote unto you; ^16as also in all his epistles, speaking in them of these things; wherein are some things hard to be understood, which the ignorant and unstedfast wrest, as they do also the other spans, unto their own destruction. ^17Ye therefore, beloved, knowing these things beforehand, beware lest, being carried away with the error of the wicked, ye fall from your own stedfastness. ^18But grow in the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. To him be the glory both now and for ever. Amen.

2 Samuel 2

2

^1And it came to pass after this, that David inquired of Jehovah, saying, Shall I go up into any of the cities of Judah? And Jehovah said unto him, Go up. And David said, Whither shall I go up? And he said, Unto Hebron. ^2So David went up thither, and his two wives also, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite. ^3And his men that were with him did David bring up, every man with his household: and they dwelt in the cities of Hebron. ^4And the men of Judah came, and there they anointed David king over the house of Judah.

And they told David, saying, The men of Jabesh-gilead were they that buried Saul. ^5And David sent messengers unto the men of Jabesh-gilead, and said unto them, Blessed be ye of Jehovah, that ye have showed this kindness unto your lord, even unto Saul, and have buried him. ^6And now Jehovah show lovingkindness and truth unto you: and I also will requite you this kindness, because ye have done this thing. ^7Now therefore let your hands be strong, and be ye valiant; for Saul your lord is dead, and also the house of Judah have anointed me king over them.

^8Now Abner the son of Ner, captain of Saul's host, had taken Ish-bosheth the son of Saul, and brought him over to Mahanaim; ^9and he made him king over Gilead, and over the Ashurites, and over Jezreel, and over Ephraim, and over Benjamin, and over all Israel. ^10Ish-bosheth, Saul's son, was forty years old when he began to reign over Israel, and he reigned two years. But the house of Judah followed David. ^11And the time that David was king in Hebron over the house of Judah was seven years and six months.

^12And Abner the son of Ner, and the servants of Ish-bosheth the son of Saul, went out from Mahanaim to Gibeon. ^13And Joab the son of Zeruiah, and the servants of David, went out, and met them by the pool of Gibeon; and they sat down, the one on the one side of the pool, and the other on the other side of the pool. ^14And Abner said to Joab, Let the young men, I pray thee, arise and play before us. And Joab said, Let them arise. ^15Then they arose and went over by number: twelve for Benjamin, and for Ish-bosheth the son of Saul, and twelve of the servants of David. ^16And they caught every one his fellow by the head, and thrust his sword in his fellow's side; so they fell down together: wherefore that place was called Helkath-hazzurim, which is in Gibeon. ^17And the battle was very sore that day: and Abner was beaten, and the men of Israel, before the servants of David.

^18And the three sons of Zeruiah were there, Joab, and Abishai, and Asahel: and Asahel was as light of foot as a wild roe. ^19And Asahel pursued after Abner; and in going he turned not to the right hand nor to the left from following Abner. ^20Then Abner looked behind him, and said, Is it thou, Asahel? And he answered, It is I. ^21And Abner said to him, Turn thee aside to thy right hand or to thy left, and lay thee hold on one of the young men, and take thee his armor. But Asahel would not turn aside from following him. ^22And Abner said again to Asahel, Turn thee aside from following me: wherefore should I smite thee to the ground? how then should I hold up my face to Joab thy brother? ^23Howbeit he refused to turn aside: wherefore Abner with the hinder end of the spear smote him in the body, so that the spear came out behind him; and he fell down there, and died in the same place: and it came to pass, that as many as came to the place where Asahel fell down and died stood still.

^24But Joab and Abishai pursued after Abner: and the sun went down when they were come to the hill of Ammah, that lieth before Giah by the way of the wilderness of Gibeon. ^25And the children of Benjamin gathered themselves together after Abner, and became one band, and stood on the top of a hill. ^26Then Abner called to Joab, and said, Shall the sword devour for ever? knowest thou not that it will be bitterness in the latter end? how long shall it be then, ere thou bid the people return from following their brethren? ^27And Joab said, As God liveth, if thou hadst not spoken, surely then in the morning the people had gone away, nor followed every one his brother. ^28So Joab blew the trumpet; and all the people stood still, and pursued after Israel no more, neither fought they any more. ^29And Abner and his men went all that night through the Arabah; and they passed over the Jordan, and went through all Bithron, and came to Mahanaim.

^30And Joab returned from following Abner: and when he had gathered all the people together, there lacked of David's servants nineteen men and Asahel. ^31But the servants of David had smitten of Benjamin, and of Abner's men, so that three hundred and threescore men died. ^32And they took up Asahel, and buried him in the sepulchre of his father, which was in Beth-lehem. And Joab and his men went all night, and the day brake upon them at Hebron.

2 Samuel 3

3

^1Now there was long war between the house of Saul and the house of David: and David waxed stronger and stronger, but the house of Saul waxed weaker and weaker.

^2And unto David were sons born in Hebron: and his first-born was Amnon, of Ahinoam the Jezreelitess; ^3and his second, Chileab, of Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite; and the third, Absalom the son of Maacah the daughter of Talmai king of Geshur; ^4and the fourth, Adonijah the son of Haggith; and the fifth, Shephatiah the son of Abital; ^5and the sixth, Ithream, of Eglah, David's wife. These were born to David in Hebron.

^6And it came to pass, while there was war between the house of Saul and the house of David, that Abner made himself strong in the house of Saul. ^7Now Saul had a concubine, whose name was Rizpah, the daughter of Aiah: and Ish-bosheth said to Abner, Wherefore hast thou gone in unto my father's concubine? ^8Then was Abner very wroth for the words of Ish-bosheth, and said, Am I a dog's head that belongeth to Judah? This day do I show kindness unto the house of Saul thy father, to his brethren, and to his friends, and have not delivered thee into the hand of David; and yet thou chargest me this day with a fault concerning this woman. ^9God do so to Abner, and more also, if, as Jehovah hath sworn to David, I do not even so to him; ^10to transfer the kingdom from the house of Saul, and to set up the throne of David over Israel and over Judah, from Dan even to Beer-sheba. ^11And he could not answer Abner another word, because he feared him.

^12And Abner sent messengers to David on his behalf, saying, Whose is the land? saying also, Make thy league with me, and, behold, my hand shall be with thee, to bring about all Israel unto thee. ^13And he said, Well; I will make a league with thee; but one thing I require of thee: that is, thou shalt not see my face, except thou first bring Michal, Saul's daughter, when thou comest to see my face. ^14And David sent messengers to Ish-bosheth, Saul's son, saying, Deliver me my wife Michal, whom I betrothed to me for a hundred foreskins of the Philistines. ^15And Ish-bosheth sent, and took her from her husband, even from Paltiel the son of Laish. ^16And her husband went with her, weeping as he went, and followed her to Bahurim. Then said Abner unto him, Go, return: and he returned.

^17And Abner had communication with the elders of Israel, saying, In times past ye sought for David to be king over you: ^18now then do it; for Jehovah hath spoken of David, saying, By the hand of my servant David I will save my people Israel out of the hand of the Philistines, and out of the hand of all their enemies. ^19And Abner also spake in the ears of Benjamin: and Abner went also to speak in the ears of David in Hebron all that seemed good to Israel, and to the whole house of Benjamin. ^20So Abner came to David to Hebron, and twenty men with him. And David made Abner and the men that were with him a feast. ^21And Abner said unto David, I will arise and go, and will gather all Israel unto my lord the king, that they may make a covenant with thee, and that thou mayest reign over all that thy soul desireth. And David sent Abner away; and he went in peace.

^22And, behold, the servants of David and Joab came from a foray, and brought in a great spoil with them: but Abner was not with David in Hebron; for he had sent him away, and he was gone in peace. ^23When Joab and all the host that was with him were come, they told Joab, saying, Abner the son of Ner came to the king, and he hath sent him away, and he is gone in peace. ^24Then Joab came to the king, and said, What hast thou done? behold, Abner came unto thee; why is it that thou hast sent him away, and he is quite gone? ^25Thou knowest Abner the son of Ner, that he came to deceive thee, and to know thy going out and thy coming in, and to know all that thou doest. ^26And when Joab was come out from David, he sent messengers after Abner, and they brought him back from the well of Sirah: but David knew it not.

^27And when Abner was returned to Hebron, Joab took him aside into the midst of the gate to speak with him quietly, and smote him there in the body, so that he died, for the blood of Asahel his brother. ^28And afterward, when David heard it, he said, I and my kingdom are guiltless before Jehovah for ever of the blood of Abner the son of Ner: ^29let it fall upon the head of Joab, and upon all his father's house; and let there not fail from the house of Joab one that hath an issue, or that is a leper, or that leaneth on a staff, or that falleth by the sword, or that lacketh bread. ^30So Joab and Abishai his brother slew Abner, because he had killed their brother Asahel at Gibeon in the battle.

^31And David said to Joab, and to all the people that were with him, Rend your clothes, and gird you with sackcloth, and mourn before Abner. And king David followed the bier. ^32And they buried Abner in Hebron: and the king lifted up his voice, and wept at the grave of Abner; and all the people wept. ^33And the king lamented for Abner, and said,

Should Abner die as a fool dieth?

^34Thy hands were not bound, nor thy feet put into fetters:

As a man falleth before the children of iniquity, so didst thou fall.

And all the people wept again over him. ^35And all the people came to cause David to eat bread while it was yet day; but David sware, saying, God do so to me, and more also, if I taste bread, or aught else, till the sun be down. ^36And all the people took notice of it, and it pleased them; as whatsoever the king did pleased all the people. ^37So all the people and all Israel understood that day that it was not of the king to slay Abner the son of Ner. ^38And the king said unto his servants, Know ye not that there is a prince and a great man fallen this day in Israel? ^39And I am this day weak, though anointed king; and these men the sons of Zeruiah are too hard for me: Jehovah reward the evil-doer according to his wickedness.

2 Samuel 4

4

^1And when Ish-bosheth, Saul's son, heard that Abner was dead in Hebron, his hands became feeble, and all the Israelites were troubled. ^2And Ish-bosheth, Saul's son, had two men that were captains of bands: the name of the one was Baanah, and the name of the other Rechab, the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, of the children of Benjamin (for Beeroth also is reckoned to Benjamin: ^3and the Beerothites fled to Gittaim, and have been sojourners there until this day).

^4Now Jonathan, Saul's son, had a son that was lame of his feet. He was five years old when the tidings came of Saul and Jonathan out of Jezreel; and his nurse took him up, and fled: and it came to pass, as she made haste to flee, that he fell, and became lame. And his name was Mephibosheth.

^5And the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, Rechab and Baanah, went, and came about the heat of the day to the house of Ish-bosheth, as he took his rest at noon. ^6And they came thither into the midst of the house, as though they would have fetched wheat; and they smote him in the body: and Rechab and Baanah his brother escaped. ^7Now when they came into the house, as he lay on his bed in his bedchamber, they smote him, and slew him, and beheaded him, and took his head, and went by the way of the Arabah all night. ^8And they brought the head of Ish-bosheth unto David to Hebron, and said to the king, Behold, the head of Ish-bosheth, the son of Saul, thine enemy, who sought thy life; and Jehovah hath avenged my lord the king this day of Saul, and of his seed. ^9And David answered Rechab and Baanah his brother, the sons of Rimmon the Beerothite, and said unto them, As Jehovah liveth, who hath redeemed my soul out of all adversity, ^10when one told me, saying, Behold, Saul is dead, thinking to have brought good tidings, I took hold of him, and slew him in Ziklag, which was the reward I gave him for his tidings. ^11How much more, when wicked men have slain a righteous person in his own house upon his bed, shall I not now require his blood of your hand, and take you away from the earth? ^12And David commanded his young men, and they slew them, and cut off their hands and their feet, and hanged them up beside the pool in Hebron. But they took the head of Ish-bosheth, and buried it in the grave of Abner in Hebron.

2 Samuel 5

5

^1Then came all the tribes of Israel to David unto Hebron, and spake, saying, Behold, we are thy bone and thy flesh. ^2In times past, when Saul was king over us, it was thou that leddest out and broughtest in Israel: and Jehovah said to thee, Thou shalt be shepherd of my people Israel, and thou shalt be prince over Israel. ^3So all the elders of Israel came to the king to Hebron; and king David made a covenant with them in Hebron before Jehovah: and they anointed David king over Israel. ^4David was thirty years old when he began to reign, and he reigned forty years. ^5In Hebron he reigned over Judah seven years and six months; and in Jerusalem he reigned thirty and three years over all Israel and Judah.

^6And the king and his men went to Jerusalem against the Jebusites, the inhabitants of the land, who spake unto David, saying, Except thou take away the blind and the lame, thou shalt not come in hither; thinking, David cannot come in hither. ^7Nevertheless David took the stronghold of Zion; the same is the city of David. ^8And David said on that day, Whosoever smiteth the Jebusites, let him get up to the watercourse, and smite the lame and the blind, that are hated of David's soul. Wherefore they say, There are the blind and the lame; he cannot come into the house. ^9And David dwelt in the stronghold, and called it the city of David. And David built round about from Millo and inward. ^10And David waxed greater and greater; for Jehovah, the God of hosts, was with him.

^11And Hiram king of Tyre sent messengers to David, and cedar-trees, and carpenters, and masons; and they built David a house. ^12And David perceived that Jehovah had established him king over Israel, and that he had exalted his kingdom for his people Israel's sake.

^13And David took him more concubines and wives out of Jerusalem, after he was come from Hebron; and there were yet sons and daughters born to David. ^14And these are the names of those that were born unto him in Jerusalem: Shammua, and Shobab, and Nathan, and Solomon, ^15and Ibhar, and Elishua, and Nepheg, and Japhia, ^16and Elishama, and Eliada, and Eliphelet.

^17And when the Philistines heard that they had anointed David king over Israel, all the Philistines went up to seek David; and David heard of it, and went down to the stronghold. ^18Now the Philistines had come and spread themselves in the valley of Rephaim. ^19And David inquired of Jehovah, saying, Shall I go up against the Philistines? wilt thou deliver them into my hand? And Jehovah said unto David, Go up; for I will certainly deliver the Philistines into thy hand. ^20And David came to Baal-perazim, and David smote them there; and he said, Jehovah hath broken mine enemies before me, like the breach of waters. Therefore he called the name of that place Baal-perazim. ^21And they left their images there; and David and his men took them away.

^22And the Philistines came up yet again, and spread themselves in the valley of Rephaim. ^23And when David inquired of Jehovah, he said, Thou shalt not go up: make a circuit behind them, and come upon them over against the mulberry-trees. ^24And it shall be, when thou hearest the sound of marching in the tops of the mulberry-trees, that then thou shalt bestir thyself; for then is Jehovah gone out before thee to smite the host of the Philistines. ^25And David did so, as Jehovah commanded him, and smote the Philistines from Geba until thou come to Gezer.

2 Samuel 6

6

^1And David again gathered together all the chosen men of Israel, thirty thousand. ^2And David arose, and went with all the people that were with him, from Baale-judah, to bring up from thence the ark of God, which is called by the Name, even the name of Jehovah of hosts that sitteth above the cherubim. ^3And they set the ark of God upon a new cart, and brought it out of the house of Abinadab that was in the hill: and Uzzah and Ahio, the sons of Abinadab, drove the new cart. ^4And they brought it out of the house of Abinadab, which was in the hill, with the ark of God: and Ahio went before the ark. ^5And David and all the house of Israel played before Jehovah with all manner of instruments made of fir-wood, and with harps, and with psalteries, and with timbrels, and with castanets, and with cymbals.

^6And when they came to the threshing-floor of Nacon, Uzzah put forth his hand to the ark of God, and took hold of it; for the oxen stumbled. ^7And the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Uzzah; and God smote him there for his error; and there he died by the ark of God. ^8And David was displeased, because Jehovah had broken forth upon Uzzah; and he called that place Perez-uzzah, unto this day. ^9And David was afraid of Jehovah that day; and he said, How shall the ark of Jehovah come unto me? ^10So David would not remove the ark of Jehovah unto him into the city of David; but David carried it aside into the house of Obed-edom the Gittite. ^11And the ark of Jehovah remained in the house of Obed-edom the Gittite three months: and Jehovah blessed Obed-edom, and all his house.

^12And it was told king David, saying, Jehovah hath blessed the house of Obed-edom, and all that pertaineth unto him, because of the ark of God. And David went and brought up the ark of God from the house of Obed-edom into the city of David with joy. ^13And it was so, that, when they that bare the ark of Jehovah had gone six paces, he sacrificed an ox and a fatling. ^14And David danced before Jehovah with all his might; and David was girded with a linen ephod. ^15So David and all the house of Israel brought up the ark of Jehovah with shouting, and with the sound of the trumpet.

^16And it was so, as the ark of Jehovah came into the city of David, that Michal the daughter of Saul looked out at the window, and saw king David leaping and dancing before Jehovah; and she despised him in her heart. ^17And they brought in the ark of Jehovah, and set it in its place, in the midst of the tent that David had pitched for it; and David offered burnt-offerings and peace-offerings before Jehovah. ^18And when David had made an end of offering the burnt-offering and the peace-offerings, he blessed the people in the name of Jehovah of hosts. ^19And he dealt among all the people, even among the whole multitude of Israel, both to men and women, to every one a cake of bread, and a portion of flesh, and a cake of raisins. So all the people departed every one to his house.

^20Then David returned to bless his household. And Michal the daughter of Saul came out to meet David, and said, How glorious was the king of Israel to-day, who uncovered himself to-day in the eyes of the handmaids of his servants, as one of the vain fellows shamelessly uncovereth himself! ^21And David said unto Michal, It was before Jehovah, who chose me above thy father, and above all his house, to appoint me prince over the people of Jehovah, over Israel: therefore will I play before Jehovah. ^22And I will be yet more vile than this, and will be base in mine own sight: but of the handmaids of whom thou hast spoken, of them shall I be had in honor. ^23And Michal the daughter of Saul had no child unto the day of her death.

2 Samuel 7

7

^1And it came to pass, when the king dwelt in his house, and Jehovah had given him rest from all his enemies round about, ^2that the king said unto Nathan the prophet, See now, I dwell in a house of cedar, but the ark of God dwelleth within curtains. ^3And Nathan said to the king, Go, do all that is in thy heart; for Jehovah is with thee. ^4And it came to pass the same night, that the word of Jehovah came unto Nathan, saying, ^5Go and tell my servant David, Thus saith Jehovah, Shalt thou build me a house for me to dwell in? ^6for I have not dwelt in a house since the day that I brought up the children of Israel out of Egypt, even to this day, but have walked in a tent and in a tabernacle. ^7In all places wherein I have walked with all the children of Israel, spake I a word with any of the tribes of Israel, whom I commanded to be shepherd of my people Israel, saying, Why have ye not built me a house of cedar? ^8Now therefore thus shalt thou say unto my servant David, Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, I took thee from the sheepcote, from following the sheep, that thou shouldest be prince over my people, over Israel; ^9and I have been with thee whithersoever thou wentest, and have cut off all thine enemies from before thee; and I will make thee a great name, like unto the name of the great ones that are in the earth. ^10And I will appoint a place for my people Israel, and will plant them, that they may dwell in their own place, and be moved no more; neither shall the children of wickedness afflict them any more, as at the first, ^11and as from the day that I commanded judges to be over my people Israel; and I will cause thee to rest from all thine enemies. Moreover Jehovah telleth thee that Jehovah will make thee a house. ^12When thy days are fulfilled, and thou shalt sleep with thy fathers, I will set up thy seed after thee, that shall proceed out of thy bowels, and I will establish his kingdom. ^13He shall build a house for my name, and I will establish the throne of his kingdom for ever. ^14I will be his father, and he shall be my son: if he commit iniquity, I will chasten him with the rod of men, and with the stripes of the children of men; ^15but my lovingkindness shall not depart from him, as I took it from Saul, whom I put away before thee. ^16And thy house and thy kingdom shall be made sure for ever before thee: thy throne shall be established for ever. ^17According to all these words, and according to all this vision, so did Nathan speak unto David.

^18Then David the king went in, and sat before Jehovah; and he said, Who am I, O Lord Jehovah, and what is my house, that thou hast brought me thus far? ^19And this was yet a small thing in thine eyes, O Lord Jehovah; but thou hast spoken also of thy servant's house for a great while to come; and this too after the manner of men, O Lord Jehovah! ^20And what can David say more unto thee? for thou knowest thy servant, O Lord Jehovah. ^21For thy word's sake, and according to thine own heart, hast thou wrought all this greatness, to make thy servant know it. ^22Wherefore thou art great, O Jehovah God: for there is none like thee, neither is there any God besides thee, according to all that we have heard with our ears. ^23And what one nation in the earth is like thy people, even like Israel, whom God went to redeem unto himself for a people, and to make him a name, and to do great things for you, and terrible things for thy land, before thy people, whom thou redeemest to thee out of Egypt, from the nations and their gods? ^24And thou didst establish to thyself thy people Israel to be a people unto thee for ever; and thou, Jehovah, becamest their God. ^25And now, O Jehovah God, the word that thou hast spoken concerning thy servant, and concerning his house, confirm thou it for ever, and do as thou hast spoken. ^26And let thy name be magnified for ever, saying, Jehovah of hosts is God over Israel; and the house of thy servant David shall be established before thee. ^27For thou, O Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, hast revealed to thy servant, saying, I will build thee a house: therefore hath thy servant found in his heart to pray this prayer unto thee. ^28And now, O Lord Jehovah, thou art God, and thy words are truth, and thou hast promised this good thing unto thy servant: ^29now therefore let it please thee to bless the house of thy servant, that it may continue for ever before thee; for thou, O Lord Jehovah, hast spoken it: and with thy blessing let the house of thy servant be blessed for ever.

2 Samuel 8

8

^1And after this it came to pass, that David smote the Philistines, and subdued them: and David took the bridle of the mother city out of the hand of the Philistines.

^2And he smote Moab, and measured them with the line, making them to lie down on the ground; and he measured two lines to put to death, and one full line to keep alive. And the Moabites became servants to David, and brought tribute.

^3David smote also Hadadezer the son of Rehob, king of Zobah, as he went to recover his dominion at the River. ^4And David took from him a thousand and seven hundred horsemen, and twenty thousand footmen: and David hocked all the chariot horses, but reserved of them for a hundred chariots. ^5And when the Syrians of Damascus came to succor Hadadezer king of Zobah, David smote of the Syrians two and twenty thousand men. ^6Then David put garrisons in Syria of Damascus; and the Syrians became servants to David, and brought tribute. And Jehovah gave victory to David whithersoever he went. ^7And David took the shields of gold that were on the servants of Hadadezer, and brought them to Jerusalem. ^8And from Betah and from Berothai, cities of Hadadezer, king David took exceeding much brass. ^9And when Toi king of Hamath heard that David had smitten all the host of Hadadezer, ^10then Toi sent Joram his son unto king David, to salute him, and to bless him, because he had fought against Hadadezer and smitten him: for Hadadezer had wars with Toi. And Joram brought with him vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and vessels of brass: ^11These also did king David dedicate unto Jehovah, with the silver and gold that he dedicated of all the nations which he subdued; ^12of Syria, and of Moab, and of the children of Ammon, and of the Philistines, and of Amalek, and of the spoil of Hadadezer, son of Rehob, king of Zobah.

^13And David gat him a name when he returned from smiting the Syrians in the Valley of Salt, even eighteen thousand men. ^14And he put garrisons in Edom; throughout all Edom put he garrisons, and all the Edomites became servants to David. And Jehovah gave victory to David whithersoever he went.

^15And David reigned over all Israel; and David executed justice and righteousness unto all his people. ^16And Joab the son of Zeruiah was over the host; and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was recorder; ^17and Zadok the son of Ahitub, and Ahimelech the son of Abiathar, were priests; and Seraiah was scribe; ^18and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and the Pelethites; and David's sons were chief ministers.

2 Samuel 9

9

^1And David said, Is there yet any that is left of the house of Saul, that I may show him kindness for Jonathan's sake? ^2And there was of the house of Saul a servant whose name was Ziba, and they called him unto David; and the king said unto him, Art thou Ziba? And he said, Thy servant is he. ^3And the king said, Is there not yet any of the house of Saul, that I may show the kindness of God unto him? And Ziba said unto the king, Jonathan hath yet a son, who is lame of his feet. ^4And the king said unto him, Where is he? And Ziba said unto the king, Behold, he is in the house of Machir the son of Ammiel, in Lo-debar. ^5Then king David sent, and fetched him out of the house of Machir the son of Ammiel, from Lo-debar. ^6And Mephibosheth, the son of Jonathan, the son of Saul, came unto David, and fell on his face, and did obeisance. And David said, Mephibosheth. And he answered, Behold, thy servant! ^7And David said unto him, Fear not; for I will surely show thee kindness for Jonathan thy father's sake, and will restore thee all the land of Saul thy father; and thou shalt eat bread at my table continually. ^8And he did obeisance, and said, What is thy servant, that thou shouldest look upon such a dead dog as I am?

^9Then the king called to Ziba, Saul's servant, and said unto him, All that pertained to Saul and to all his house have I given unto thy master's son. ^10And thou shalt till the land for him, thou, and thy sons, and thy servants; and thou shalt bring in the fruits, that thy master's son may have bread to eat: but Mephibosheth thy master's son shall eat bread alway at my table. Now Ziba had fifteen sons and twenty servants. ^11Then said Ziba unto the king, According to all that my lord the king commandeth his servant, so shall thy servant do. As for Mephibosheth, said the king, he shall eat at my table, as one of the king's sons. ^12And Mephibosheth had a young son, whose name was Mica. And all that dwelt in the house of Ziba were servants unto Mephibosheth. ^13So Mephibosheth dwelt in Jerusalem; for he did eat continually at the king's table. And he was lame in both his feet.

2 Samuel 10

10

^1And it came to pass after this, that the king of the children of Ammon died, and Hanun his son reigned in his stead. ^2And David said, I will show kindness unto Hanun the son of Nahash, as his father showed kindness unto me. So David sent by his servants to comfort him concerning his father. And David's servants came into the land of the children of Ammon. ^3But the princes of the children of Ammon said unto Hanun their lord, Thinkest thou that David doth honor thy father, in that he hath sent comforters unto thee? hath not David sent his servants unto thee to search the city, and to spy it out, and to overthrow it? ^4So Hanun took David's servants, and shaved off the one half of their beards, and cut off their garments in the middle, even to their buttocks, and sent them away. ^5When they told it unto David, he sent to meet them; for the men were greatly ashamed. And the king said, Tarry at Jericho until your beards be grown, and then return.

^6And when the children of Ammon saw that they were become odious to David, the children of Ammon sent and hired the Syrians of Beth-rehob, and the Syrians of Zobah, twenty thousand footmen, and the king of Maacah with a thousand men, and the men of Tob twelve thousand men. ^7And when David heard of it, he sent Joab, and all the host of the mighty men. ^8And the children of Ammon came out, and put the battle in array at the entrance of the gate: and the Syrians of Zobah and of Rehob, and the men of Tob and Maacah, were by themselves in the field.

^9Now when Joab saw that the battle was set against him before and behind, he chose of all the choice men of Israel, and put them in array against the Syrians: ^10And the rest of the people he committed into the hand of Abishai his brother; and he put them in array against the children of Ammon. ^11And he said, If the Syrians be too strong for me, then thou shalt help me; but if the children of Ammon be too strong for thee, then I will come and help thee. ^12Be of good courage, and let us play the man for our people, and for the cities of our God: and Jehovah do that which seemeth him good. ^13So Joab and the people that were with him drew nigh unto the battle against the Syrians: and they fled before him. ^14And when the children of Ammon saw that the Syrians were fled, they likewise fled before Abishai, and entered into the city. Then Joab returned from the children of Ammon, and came to Jerusalem.

^15And when the Syrians saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they gathered themselves together. ^16And Hadarezer sent, and brought out the Syrians that were beyond the River: and they came to Helam, with Shobach the captain of the host of Hadarezer at their head. ^17And it was told David; and he gathered all Israel together, and passed over the Jordan, and came to Helam. And the Syrians set themselves in array against David, and fought with him. ^18And the Syrians fled before Israel; and David slew of the Syrians the men of seven hundred chariots, and forty thousand horsemen, and smote Shobach the captain of their host, so that he died there. ^19And when all the kings that were servants to Hadarezer saw that they were put to the worse before Israel, they made peace with Israel, and served them. So the Syrians feared to help the children of Ammon any more.

2 Samuel 11

11

^1And it came to pass, at the return of the year, at the time when kings go out to battle, that David sent Joab, and his servants with him, and all Israel; and they destroyed the children of Ammon, and besieged Rabbah. But David tarried at Jerusalem.

^2And it came to pass at eventide, that David arose from off his bed, and walked upon the roof of the king's house: and from the roof he saw a woman bathing; and the woman was very beautiful to look upon. ^3And David send and inquired after the woman. And one said, Is not this Bath-sheba, the daughter of Eliam, the wife of Uriah the Hittite? ^4And David sent messengers, and took her; and she came in unto him, and he lay with her (for she was purified from her uncleanness); and she returned unto her house. ^5And the woman conceived; and she sent and told David, and said, I am with child.

^6And David sent to Joab, saying, Send me Uriah the Hittite. And Joab sent Uriah to David. ^7And when Uriah was come unto him, David asked of him how Joab did, and how the people fared, and how the war prospered. ^8And David said to Uriah, Go down to thy house, and wash thy feet. And Uriah departed out of the king's house, and there followed him a mess of food from the king. ^9But Uriah slept at the door of the king's house with all the servants of his lord, and went not down to his house. ^10And when they had told David, saying, Uriah went not down unto his house, David said unto Uriah, Art thou not come from a journey? wherefore didst thou not go down unto thy house? ^11And Uriah said unto David, The ark, and Israel, and Judah, abide in booths; and my lord Joab, and the servants of my lord, are encamped in the open field; shall I then go into my house, to eat and to drink, and to lie with my wife? as thou livest, and as thy soul liveth, I will not do this thing. ^12And David said to Uriah, Tarry here to-day also, and to-morrow I will let thee depart. So Uriah abode in Jerusalem that day, and the morrow. ^13And when David had called him, he did eat and drink before him; and he made him drunk: and at even he went out to lie on his bed with the servants of his lord, but went not down to his house.

^14And it came to pass in the morning, that David wrote a letter to Joab, and sent it by the hand of Uriah. ^15And he wrote in the letter, saying, Set ye Uriah in the forefront of the hottest battle, and retire ye from him, that he may be smitten, and die. ^16And it came to pass, when Joab kept watch upon the city, that he assigned Uriah unto the place where he knew that valiant men were. ^17And the men of the city went out, and fought with Joab: and there fell some of the people, even of the servants of David; and Uriah the Hittite died also. ^18Then Joab sent and told David all the things concerning the war; ^19and he charged the messenger, saying, When thou hast made an end of telling all the things concerning the war unto the king, ^20it shall be that, if the king's wrath arise, and he say unto thee, Wherefore went ye so nigh unto the city to fight? knew ye not that they would shoot from the wall? ^21who smote Abimelech the son of Jerubbesheth? did not a woman cast an upper millstone upon him from the wall, so that he died at Thebez? why went ye so nigh the wall? then shalt thou say, Thy servant Uriah the Hittite is dead also.

^22So the messenger went, and came and showed David all that Joab had sent him for. ^23And the messenger said unto David, The men prevailed against us, and came out unto us into the field, and we were upon them even unto the entrance of the gate. ^24And the shooters shot at thy servants from off the wall; and some of the king's servants are dead, and thy servant Uriah the Hittite is dead also. ^25Then David said unto the messenger, Thus shalt thou say unto Joab, Let not this thing displease thee, for the sword devoureth one as well as another; make thy battle more strong against the city, and overthrow it: and encourage thou him.

^26And when the wife of Uriah heard that Uriah her husband was dead, she made lamentation for her husband. ^27And when the mourning was past, David sent and took her home to his house, and she became his wife, and bare him a son. But the thing that David had done displeased Jehovah.

2 Samuel 12

12

^1And Jehovah sent Nathan unto David. And he came unto him, and said unto him, There were two men in one city; the one rich, and the other poor. ^2The rich man had exceeding many flocks and herds; ^3but the poor man had nothing, save one little ewe lamb, which he had bought and nourished up: and it grew up together with him, and with his children; it did eat of his own morsel, and drank of his own cup, and lay in his bosom, and was unto him as a daughter. ^4And there came a traveller unto the rich man, and he spared to take of his own flock and of his own herd, to dress for the wayfaring man that was come unto him, but took the poor man's lamb, and dressed it for the man that was come to him. ^5And David's anger was greatly kindled against the man; and he said to Nathan, As Jehovah liveth, the man that hath done this is worthy to die: ^6and he shall restore the lamb fourfold, because he did this thing, and because he had no pity. ^7And Nathan said to David, Thou art the man. Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, I anointed thee king over Israel, and I delivered thee out of the hand of Saul; ^8and I gave thee thy master's house, and thy master's wives into thy bosom, and gave thee the house of Israel and of Judah; and if that had been too little, I would have added unto thee such and such things. ^9Wherefore hast thou despised the word of Jehovah, to do that which is evil in his sight? thou hast smitten Uriah the Hittite with the sword, and hast taken his wife to be thy wife, and hast slain him with the sword of the children of Ammon. ^10Now therefore the sword shall never depart from thy house, because thou hast despised me, and hast taken the wife of Uriah the Hittite to be thy wife. ^11Thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will raise up evil against thee out of thine own house; and I will take thy wives before thine eyes, and give them unto thy neighbor, and he shall lie with thy wives in the sight of this sun. ^12For thou didst it secretly: but I will do this thing before all Israel, and before the sun. ^13And David said unto Nathan, I have sinned against Jehovah. And Nathan said unto David, Jehovah also hath put away thy sin; thou shalt not die. ^14Howbeit, because by this deed thou hast given great occasion to the enemies of Jehovah to blaspheme, the child also that is born unto thee shall surely die. ^15And Nathan departed unto his house.

And Jehovah struck the child that Uriah's wife bare unto David, and it was very sick. ^16David therefore besought God for the child; and David fasted, and went in, and lay all night upon the earth. ^17And the elders of his house arose, and stood beside him, to raise him up from the earth: but he would not, neither did he eat bread with them. ^18And it came to pass on the seventh day, that the child died. And the servants of David feared to tell him that the child was dead; for they said, Behold, while the child was yet alive, we spake unto him, and he hearkened not unto our voice: how will he then vex himself, if we tell him that the child is dead! ^19But when David saw that his servants were whispering together, David perceived that the child was dead; and David said unto his servants, Is the child dead? And they said, He is dead. ^20Then David arose from the earth, and washed, and anointed himself, and changed his apparel; and he came into the house of Jehovah, and worshipped: then he came to his own house; and when he required, they set bread before him, and he did eat. ^21Then said his servants unto him, What thing is this that thou hast done? thou didst fast and weep for the child, while it was alive; but when the child was dead, thou didst rise and eat bread. ^22And he said, While the child was yet alive, I fasted and wept: for I said, Who knoweth whether Jehovah will not be gracious to me, that the child may live? ^23But now he is dead, wherefore should I fast? can I bring him back again? I shall go to him, but he will not return to me.

^24And David comforted Bath-sheba his wife, and went in unto her, and lay with her: and she bare a son, and he called his name Solomon. And Jehovah loved him; ^25and he sent by the hand of Nathan the prophet; and he called his name Jedidiah, for Jehovah's sake.

^26Now Joab fought against Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and took the royal city. ^27And Joab sent messengers to David, and said, I have fought against Rabbah; yea, I have taken the city of waters. ^28Now therefore gather the rest of the people together, and encamp against the city, and take it; lest I take the city, and it be called after my name. ^29And David gathered all the people together, and went to Rabbah, and fought against it, and took it. ^30And he took the crown of their king from off his head; and the weight thereof was a talent of gold, and in it were precious stones; and it was set on David's head. And he brought forth the spoil of the city, exceeding much. ^31And he brought forth the people that were therein, and put them under saws, and under harrows of iron, and under axes of iron, and made them pass through the brickkiln: and thus did he unto all the cities of the children of Ammon. And David and all the people returned unto Jerusalem.

2 Samuel 13

13

^1And it came to pass after this, that Absalom the son of David had a fair sister, whose name was Tamar; and Amnon the son of David loved her. ^2And Amnon was so vexed that he fell sick because of his sister Tamar; for she was a virgin; and it seemed hard to Amnon to do anything unto her. ^3But Amnon had a friend, whose name was Jonadab, the son of Shimeah, David's brother; and Jonadab was a very subtle man. ^4And he said unto him, Why, O son of the king, art thou thus lean from day to day? wilt thou not tell me? And Amnon said unto him, I love Tamar, my brother Absalom's sister. ^5And Jonadab said unto him, Lay thee down on thy bed, and feign thyself sick: and when thy father cometh to see thee, say unto him, Let my sister Tamar come, I pray thee, and give me bread to eat, and dress the food in my sight, that I may see it, and eat it from her hand. ^6So Amnon lay down, and feigned himself sick: and when the king was come to see him, Amnon said unto the king, Let her sister Tamar come, I pray thee, and make me a couple of cakes in my sight, that I may eat from her hand.

^7Then David sent home to Tamar, saying, Go now to thy brother Amnon's house, and dress him food. ^8So Tamar went to her brother Amnon's house; and he was laid down. And she took dough, and kneaded it, and made cakes in his sight, and did bake the cakes. ^9And she took the pan, and poured them out before him; but he refused to eat. And Amnon said, Have out all men from me. And they went out every man from him. ^10And Amnon said unto Tamar, Bring the food into the chamber, that I may eat from thy hand. And Tamar took the cakes which she had made, and brought them into the chamber to Amnon her brother. ^11And when she had brought them near unto him to eat, he took hold of her, and said unto her, Come, lie with me, my sister. ^12And she answered him, Nay, my brother, do not force me; for no such thing ought to be done in Israel: do not thou this folly. ^13And I, whither shall I carry my shame? and as for thee, thou wilt be as one of the fools in Israel. Now therefore, I pray thee, speak unto the king; for he will not withhold me from thee. ^14Howbeit he would not hearken unto her voice; but being stronger than she, he forced her, and lay with her.

^15Then Amnon hated her with exceeding great hatred; for the hatred wherewith he hated her was greater than the love wherewith he had loved her. And Amnon said unto her, Arise, be gone. ^16And she said unto him, Not so, because this great wrong in putting me forth is worse than the other that thou didst unto me. But he would not hearken unto her. ^17Then he called his servant that ministered unto him, and said, Put now this woman out from me, and bolt the door after her. ^18And she had a garment of divers colors upon her; for with such robes were the king's daughters that were virgins apparelled. Then his servant brought her out, and bolted the door after her. ^19And Tamar put ashes on her head, and rent her garment of divers colors that was on her; and she laid her hand on her head, and went her way, crying aloud as she went.

^20And Absalom her brother said unto her, Hath Amnon thy brother been with thee? but now hold thy peace, my sister: he is thy brother; take not this thing to heart. So Tamar remained desolate in her brother Absalom's house. ^21But when king David heard of all these things, he was very wroth. ^22And Absalom spake unto Amnon neither good nor bad; for Absalom hated Amnon, because he had forced his sister Tamar.

^23And it came to pass after two full years, that Absalom had sheep-shearers in Baal-hazor, which is beside Ephraim: and Absalom invited all the king's sons. ^24And Absalom came to the king, and said, Behold now, thy servant hath sheep-shearers; let the king, I pray thee, and his servants go with thy servant. ^25And the king said to Absalom, Nay, my son, let us not all go, lest we be burdensome unto thee. And he pressed him: howbeit he would not go, but blessed him. ^26Then said Absalom, If not, I pray thee, let my brother Amnon go with us. And the king said unto him, Why should he go with thee? ^27But Absalom pressed him, and he let Amnon and all the king's sons go with him. ^28And Absalom commanded his servants, saying, Mark ye now, when Amnon's heart is merry with wine; and when I say unto you, Smite Amnon, then kill him; fear not; have not I commanded you? be courageous, and be valiant. ^29And the servants of Absalom did unto Amnon as Absalom had commanded. Then all the king's sons arose, and every man gat him up upon his mule, and fled.

^30And it came to pass, while they were in the way, that the tidings came to David, saying, Absalom hath slain all the king's sons, and there is not one of them left. ^31Then the king arose, and rent his garments, and lay on the earth; and all his servants stood by with their clothes rent. ^32And Jonadab, the son of Shimeah, David's brother, answered and said, Let not my lord suppose that they have killed all the young men the king's sons; for Amnon only is dead; for by the appointment of Absalom this hath been determined from the day that he forced his sister Tamar. ^33Now therefore let not my lord the king take the thing to his heart, to think that all the king's sons are dead; for Amnon only is dead.

^34But Absalom fled. And the young man that kept the watch lifted up his eyes, and looked, and, behold, there came much people by the way of the hill-side behind him. ^35And Jonadab said unto the king, Behold, the king's sons are come: as thy servant said, so it is. ^36And it came to pass, as soon as he had made an end of speaking, that, behold, the king's sons came, and lifted up their voice, and wept: and the king also and all his servants wept very sore.

^37But Absalom fled, and went to Talmai the son of Ammihur, king of Geshur. And David mourned for his son every day. ^38So Absalom fled, and went to Geshur, and was there three years. ^39And the soul of king David longed to go forth unto Absalom: for he was comforted concerning Amnon, seeing he was dead.

2 Samuel 14

14

^1Now Joab the son of Zeruiah perceived that the king's heart was toward Absalom. ^2And Joab sent to Tekoa, and fetched thence a wise woman, and said unto her, I pray thee, feign thyself to be a mourner, and put on mourning apparel, I pray thee, and anoint not thyself with oil, but be as a woman that hath a long time mourned for the dead: ^3and go in to the king, and speak on this manner unto him. So Joab put the words in her mouth.

^4And when the woman of Tekoa spake to the king, she fell on her face to the ground, and did obeisance, and said, Help, O king. ^5And the king said unto her, What aileth thee? And she answered, Of a truth I am a widow, and my husband is dead. ^6And thy handmaid had two sons, and they two strove together in the field, and there was none to part them, but the one smote the other, and killed him. ^7And, behold, the whole family is risen against thy handmaid, and they say, Deliver him that smote his brother, that we may kill him for the life of his brother whom he slew, and so destroy the heir also. Thus will they quench my coal which is left, and will leave to my husband neither name nor remainder upon the face of the earth.

^8And the king said unto the woman, Go to thy house, and I will give charge concerning thee. ^9And the woman of Tekoa said unto the king, My lord, O king, the iniquity be on me, and on my father's house; and the king and his throne be guiltless. ^10And the king said, Whosoever saith aught unto thee, bring him to me, and he shall not touch thee any more. ^11Then said she, I pray thee, let the king remember Jehovah thy God, that the avenger of blood destroy not any more, lest they destroy my son. And he said, As Jehovah liveth, there shall not one hair of thy son fall to the earth.

^12Then the woman said, Let thy handmaid, I pray thee, speak a word unto my lord the king. And he said, Say on. ^13And the woman said, Wherefore then hast thou devised such a thing against the people of God? for in speaking this word the king is as one that is guilty, in that the king doth not fetch home again his banished one. ^14For we must needs die, and are as water split on the ground, which cannot be gathered up again; neither doth God take away life, but deviseth means, that he that is banished be not an outcast from him. ^15Now therefore seeing that I am come to speak this word unto my lord the king, it is because the people have made me afraid: and thy handmaid said, I will now speak unto the king; it may be that the king will perform the request of his servant. ^16For the king will hear, to deliver his servant out of the hand of the man that would destroy me and my son together out of the inheritance of God. ^17Then thy handmaid said, Let, I pray thee, the word of my lord the king be comfortable; for as an angel of God, so is my lord the king to discern good and bad: and Jehovah thy God be with thee.

^18Then the king answered and said unto the woman, Hide not from me, I pray thee, aught that I shall ask thee. And the woman said, Let my lord the king now speak. ^19And the king said, Is the hand of Joab with thee in all this? And the woman answered and said, As thy soul liveth, my lord the king, none can turn to the right hand or to the left from aught that my lord the king hath spoken; for thy servant Joab, he bade me, and he put all these words in the mouth of thy handmaid; ^20to change the face of the matter hath thy servant Joab done this thing: and my lord is wise, according to the wisdom of an angel of God, to know all things that are in the earth.

^21And the king said unto Joab, Behold now, I have done this thing: go therefore, bring the young man Absalom back. ^22And Joab fell to the ground on his face, and did obeisance, and blessed the king: and Joab said, To-day thy servant knoweth that I have found favor in thy sight, my lord, O king, in that the king hath performed the request of his servant. ^23So Joab arose and went to Geshur, and brought Absalom to Jerusalem. ^24And the king said, Let him turn to his own house, but let him not see my face. So Absalom turned to his own house, and saw not the king's face.

^25Now in all Israel there was none to be so much praised as Absalom for his beauty: from the sole of his foot even to the crown of his head there was no blemish in him. ^26And when he cut the hair of his head (now it was at every year's end that he cut it; because it was heavy on him, therefore he cut it); he weighed the hair of his head at two hundred shekels, after the king's weight. ^27And unto Absalom there were born three sons, and one daughter, whose name was Tamar: she was a woman of a fair countenance.

^28And Absalom dwelt two full years in Jerusalem; and he saw not the king's face. ^29Then Absalom sent for Joab, to send him to the king; but he would not come to him: and he sent again a second time, but he would not come. ^30Therefore he said unto his servants, See, Joab's field is near mine, and he hath barley there; go and set it on fire. And Absalom's servants set the field on fire. ^31Then Joab arose, and came to Absalom unto his house, and said unto him, Wherefore have thy servants set my field on fire? ^32And Absalom answered Joab, Behold, I sent unto thee, saying, Come hither, that I may send thee to the king, to say, Wherefore am I come from Geshur? it were better for me to be there still. Now therefore let me see the king's face; and if there be iniquity in me, let him kill me. ^33So Joab came to the king, and told him; and when he had called for Absalom, he came to the king, and bowed himself on his face to the ground before the king: and the king kissed Absalom.

2 Samuel 15

15

^1And it came to pass after this, that Absalom prepared him a chariot and horses, and fifty men to run before him. ^2And Absalom rose up early, and stood beside the way of the gate: and it was so, that, when any man had a suit which should come to the king for judgment, then Absalom called unto him, and said, Of what city art thou? And he said, Thy servant is of one of the tribes of Israel. ^3And Absalom said unto him, See, thy matters are good and right; but there is no man deputed of the king to hear thee. ^4Absalom said moreover, Oh that I were made judge in the land, that every man who hath any suit or cause might come unto me, and I would do him justice! ^5And it was so, that, when any man came nigh to do him obeisance, he put forth his hand, and took hold of him, and kissed him. ^6And on this manner did Absalom to all Israel that came to the king for judgment: so Absalom stole the hearts of the men of Israel.

^7And it came to pass at the end of forty years, that Absalom said unto the king, I pray thee, let me go and pay my vow, which I have vowed unto Jehovah, in Hebron. ^8For thy servant vowed a vow while I abode at Geshur in Syria, saying, If Jehovah shall indeed bring me again to Jerusalem, then I will serve Jehovah. ^9And the king said unto him, Go in peace. So he arose, and went to Hebron. ^10But Absalom sent spies throughout all the tribes of Israel, saying, As soon as ye hear the sound of the trumpet, then ye shall say, Absalom is king in Hebron. ^11And with Absalom went two hundred men out of Jerusalem, that were invited, and went in their simplicity; and they knew not anything. ^12And Absalom sent for Ahithophel the Gilonite, David's counsellor, from his city, even from Giloh, while he was offering the sacrifices. And the conspiracy was strong; for the people increased continually with Absalom.

^13And there came a messenger to David, saying, The hearts of the men of Israel are after Absalom. ^14And David said unto all his servants that were with him at Jerusalem, Arise, and let us flee; for else none of us shall escape from Absalom: make speed to depart, lest he overtake us quickly, and bring down evil upon us, and smite the city with the edge of the sword. ^15And the king's servants said unto the king, Behold, thy servants are ready to do whatsoever my lord the king shall choose. ^16And the king went forth, and all his household after him. And the king left ten women, that were concubines, to keep the house. ^17And the king went forth, and all the people after him; and they tarried in Beth-merhak. ^18And all his servants passed on beside him; and all the Cherethites, and all the Pelethites, and all the Gittites, six hundred men that came after him from Gath, passed on before the king.

^19Then said the king to Ittai the Gittite, Wherefore goest thou also with us? return, and abide with the king: for thou art a foreigner, and also an exile; return to thine own place. ^20Whereas thou camest but yesterday, should I this day make thee go up and down with us, seeing I go whither I may? return thou, and take back thy brethren; mercy and truth be with thee. ^21And Ittai answered the king, and said, As Jehovah liveth, and as my lord the king liveth, surely in what place my lord the king shall be, whether for death or for life, even there also will thy servant be. ^22And David said to Ittai, Go and pass over. And Ittai the Gittite passed over, and all his men, and all the little ones that were with him. ^23And all the country wept with a loud voice, and all the people passed over: the king also himself passed over the brook Kidron, and all the people passed over, toward the way of the wilderness.

^24And, lo, Zadok also came, and all the Levites with him, bearing the ark of the covenant of God; and they set down the ark of God; and Abiathar went up, until all the people had done passing out of the city. ^25And the king said unto Zadok, Carry back the ark of God into the city: if I shall find favor in the eyes of Jehovah, he will bring me again, and show me both it, and his habitation: ^26but if he say thus, I have no delight in thee; behold, here am I, let him do to me as seemeth good unto him. ^27The king said also unto Zadok the priest, Art thou not a seer? return into the city in peace, and your two sons with you, Ahimaaz thy son, and Jonathan the son of Abiathar. ^28See, I will tarry at the fords of the wilderness, until there come word from you to certify me. ^29Zadok therefore and Abiathar carried the ark of God again to Jerusalem: and they abode there.

^30And David went up by the ascent of the mount of Olives, and wept as he went up; and he had his head covered, and went barefoot: and all the people that were with him covered every man his head, and they went up, weeping as they went up. ^31And one told David, saying, Ahithophel is among the conspirators with Absalom. And David said, O Jehovah, I pray thee, turn the counsel of Ahithophel into foolishness. ^32And it came to pass, that, when David was come to the top of the ascent, where God was worshipped, behold, Hushai the Archite came to meet him with his coat rent, and earth upon his head. ^33And David said unto him, If thou passest on with me, then thou wilt be a burden unto me: ^34but if thou return to the city, and say unto Absalom, I will be thy servant, O king; as I have been thy father's servant in time past, so will I now be thy servant; then wilt thou defeat for me the counsel of Ahithophel. ^35And hast thou not there with thee Zadok and Abiathar the priests? therefore it shall be, that what thing soever thou shalt hear out of the king's house, thou shalt tell it to Zadok and Abiathar the priests. ^36Behold, they have there with them their two sons, Ahimaaz, Zadok's son, and Jonathan, Abiathar's son; and by them ye shall send unto me everything that ye shall hear. ^37So Hushai, David's friend, came into the city; and Absalom came into Jerusalem.

2 Samuel 16

16

^1And when David was a little past the top of the ascent, behold, Ziba the servant of Mephibosheth met him, with a couple of asses saddled, and upon them two hundred loaves of bread, and a hundred clusters of raisins, and a hundred of summer fruits, and a bottle of wine. ^2And the king said unto Ziba, What meanest thou by these? And Ziba said, The asses are for the king's household to ride on; and the bread and summer fruit for the young men to eat; and the wine, that such as are faint in the wilderness may drink. ^3And the king said, And where is thy master's son? And Ziba said unto the king, Behold, he abideth at Jerusalem; for he said, To-day will the house of Israel restore me the kingdom of my father. ^4Then said the king to Ziba, Behold, thine is all that pertaineth unto Mephibosheth. And Ziba said, I do obeisance; let me find favor in thy sight, my lord, O king.

^5And when king David came to Bahurim, behold, there came out thence a man of the family of the house of Saul, whose name was Shimei, the son of Gera; he came out, and cursed still as he came. ^6And he cast stones at David, and at all the servants of king David: and all the people and all the mighty men were on his right hand and on his left. ^7And thus said Shimei when he cursed, Begone, begone, thou man of blood, and base fellow: ^8Jehovah hath returned upon thee all the blood of the house of Saul, in whose stead thou hast reigned; and Jehovah hath delivered the kingdom into the hand of Absalom thy son; and, behold, thou art taken in thine own mischief, because thou art a man of blood.

^9Then said Abishai the son of Zeruiah unto the king, Why should this dead dog curse my lord the king? let me go over, I pray thee, and take off his head. ^10And the king said, What have I to do with you, ye sons of Zeruiah? Because he curseth, and because Jehovah hath said unto him, Curse David; who then shall say, Wherefore hast thou done so? ^11And David said to Abishai, and to all his servants, Behold, my son, who came forth from my bowels, seeketh my life: how much more may this Benjamite now do it? let him alone, and let him curse; for Jehovah hath bidden him. ^12It may be that Jehovah will look on the wrong done unto me, and that Jehovah will requite me good for his cursing of me this day. ^13So David and his men went by the way; and Shimei went along on the hill-side over against him, and cursed as he went, and threw stones at him, and cast dust. ^14And the king, and all the people that were with him, came weary; and he refreshed himself there.

^15And Absalom, and all the people, the men of Israel, came to Jerusalem, and Ahithophel with him. ^16And it came to pass, when Hushai the Archite, David's friend, was come unto Absalom, that Hushai said unto Absalom, Long live the king, Long live the king. ^17And Absalom said to Hushai, Is this thy kindness to thy friend? why wentest thou not with thy friend? ^18And Hushai said unto Absalom, Nay; but whom Jehovah, and this people, and all the men of Israel have chosen, his will I be, and with him will I abide. ^19And again, whom should I serve? should I not serve in the presence of his son? as I have served in thy father's presence, so will I be in thy presence.

^20Then said Absalom to Ahithophel, Give your counsel what we shall do. ^21And Ahithophel said unto Absalom, Go in unto thy father's concubines, that he hath left to keep the house; and all Israel will hear that thou art abhorred of thy father: then will the hands of all that are with thee be strong. ^22So they spread Absalom a tent upon the top of the house; and Absalom went in unto his father's concubines in the sight of all Israel. ^23And the counsel of Ahithophel, which he gave in those days, was as if a man inquired at the oracle of God: so was all the counsel of Ahithophel both with David and with Absalom.

2 Samuel 17

17

^1Moreover Ahithophel said unto Absalom, Let me now choose out twelve thousand men, and I will arise and pursue after David this night: ^2and I will come upon him while he is weary and weak-handed, and will make him afraid; and all the people that are with him shall flee; and I will smite the king only; ^3and I will bring back all the people unto thee: the man whom thou seekest is as if all returned: so all the people shall be in peace. ^4And the saying pleased Absalom well, and all the elders of Israel.

^5Then said Absalom, Call now Hushai the Archite also, and let us hear likewise what he saith. ^6And when Hushai was come to Absalom, Absalom spake unto him, saying, Ahithophel hath spoken after this manner: shall we do after his saying? if not, speak thou. ^7And Hushai said unto Absalom, The counsel that Ahithophel hath given this time is not good. ^8Hushai said moreover, Thou knowest thy father and his men, that they are mighty men, and they are chafed in their minds, as a bear robbed of her whelps in the field; and thy father is a man of war, and will not lodge with the people. ^9Behold, he is hid now in some pit, or in some other place: and it will come to pass, when some of them are fallen at the first, that whosoever heareth it will say, There is a slaughter among the people that follow Absalom. ^10And even he that is valiant, whose heart is as the heart of a lion, will utterly melt; for all Israel knoweth that thy father is a mighty man, and they that are with him are valiant men. ^11But I counsel that all Israel be gathered together unto thee, from Dan even to Beer-sheba, as the sand that is by the sea for multitude; and that thou go to battle in thine own person. ^12So shall we come upon him in some place where he shall be found, and we will light upon him as the dew falleth on the ground; and of him and of all the men that are with him we will not leave so much as one. ^13Moreover, if he be gotten into a city, then shall all Israel bring ropes to that city, and we will draw it into the river, until there be not one small stone found there. ^14And Absalom and all the men of Israel said, The counsel of Hushai the Archite is better than the counsel of Ahithophel. For Jehovah had ordained to defeat the good counsel of Ahithophel, to the intent that Jehovah might bring evil upon Absalom.

^15Then said Hushai unto Zadok and to Abiathar the priests, Thus and thus did Ahithophel counsel Absalom and the elders of Israel; and thus and thus have I counselled. ^16Now therefore send quickly, and tell David, saying, Lodge not this night at the fords of the wilderness, but by all means pass over; lest the king be swallowed up, and all the people that are with him. ^17Now Jonathan and Ahimaaz were staying by En-rogel; and a maid-servant used to go and tell them; and they went and told king David: for they might not be seen to come into the city. ^18But a lad saw them, and told Absalom: and they went both of them away quickly, and came to the house of a man in Bahurim, who had a well in his court; and they went down thither. ^19And the woman took and spread the covering over the well's mouth, and strewed bruised grain thereon; and nothing was known. ^20And Absalom's servants came to the woman to the house; and they said, Where are Ahimaaz and Jonathan? And the woman said unto them, They are gone over the brook of water. And when they had sought and could not find them, they returned to Jerusalem.

^21And it came to pass, after they were departed, that they came up out of the well, and went and told king David; and they said unto David, Arise ye, and pass quickly over the water; for thus hath Ahithophel counselled against you. ^22Then David arose, and all the people that were with him, and they passed over the Jordan: by the morning light there lacked not one of them that was not gone over the Jordan. ^23And when Ahithophel saw that his counsel was not followed, he saddled his ass, and arose, and gat him home, unto his city, and set his house in order, and hanged himself; and he died, and was buried in the sepulchre of his father.

^24Then David came to Mahanaim. And Absalom passed over the Jordan, he and all the men of Israel with him. ^25And Absalom set Amasa over the host instead of Joab. Now Amasa was the son of a man, whose name was Ithra the Israelite, that went in to Abigal the daughter of Nahash, sister to Zeruiah, Joab's mother. ^26And Israel and Absalom encamped in the land of Gilead.

^27And it came to pass, when David was come to Mahanaim, that Shobi the son of Nahash of Rabbah of the children of Ammon, and Machir the son of Ammiel of Lodebar, and Barzillai the Gileadite of Rogelim, ^28brought beds, and basins, and earthen vessels, and wheat, and barley, and meal, and parched grain, and beans, and lentils, and parched pulse, ^29and honey, and butter, and sheep, and cheese of the herd, for David, and for the people that were with him, to eat: for they said, The people are hungry, and weary, and thirsty, in the wilderness.

2 Samuel 18

18

^1And David numbered the people that were with him, and set captains of thousands and captains of hundreds over them. ^2And David sent forth the people, a third part under the hand of Joab, and a third part under the hand of Abishai the son of Zeruiah, Joab's brother, and a third part under the hand of Ittai the Gittite. And the king said unto the people, I will surely go forth with you myself also. ^3But the people said, Thou shalt not go forth: for if we flee away, they will not care for us; neither if half of us die, will they care for us: but thou art worth ten thousand of us; therefore now it is better that thou be ready to succor us out of the city. ^4And the king said unto them, What seemeth you best I will do. And the king stood by the gate-side, and all the people went out by hundreds and by thousands. ^5And the king commanded Joab and Abishai and Ittai, saying, Deal gently for my sake with the young man, even with Absalom. And all the people heard when the king gave all the captains charge concerning Absalom.

^6So the people went out into the field against Israel: and the battle was in the forest of Ephraim. ^7And the people of Israel were smitten there before the servants of David, and there was a great slaughter there that day of twenty thousand men. ^8For the battle was there spread over the face of all the country; and the forest devoured more people that day than the sword devoured.

^9And Absalom chanced to meet the servants of David. And Absalom was riding upon his mule, and the mule went under the thick boughs of a great oak, and his head caught hold of the oak, and he was taken up between heaven and earth; and the mule that was under him went on. ^10And a certain man saw it, and told Joab, and said, Behold, I saw Absalom hanging in an oak. ^11And Joab said unto the man that told him, And, behold, thou sawest it, and why didst thou not smite him there to the ground? and I would have given thee ten pieces of silver, and a girdle. ^12And the man said unto Joab, Though I should receive a thousand pieces of silver in my hand, yet would I not put forth my hand against the king's son; for in our hearing the king charged thee and Abishai and Ittai, saying, Beware that none touch the young man Absalom. ^13Otherwise if I had dealt falsely against his life (and there is no matter hid from the king), then thou thyself wouldest have set thyself against me. ^14Then said Joab, I may not tarry thus with thee. And he took three darts in his hand, and thrust them through the heart of Absalom, while he was yet alive in the midst of the oak. ^15And ten young men that bare Joab's armor compassed about and smote Absalom, and slew him.

^16And Joab blew the trumpet, and the people returned from pursuing after Israel; for Joab held back the people. ^17And they took Absalom, and cast him into the great pit in the forest, and raised over him a very great heap of stones: and all Israel fled every one to his tent. ^18Now Absalom in his lifetime had taken and reared up for himself the pillar, which is in the king's dale; for he said, I have no son to keep my name in remembrance: and he called the pillar after his own name; and it is called Absalom's monument, unto this day.

^19Then said Ahimaaz the son of Zadok, Let me now run, and bear the king tidings, how that Jehovah hath avenged him of his enemies. ^20And Joab said unto him, Thou shalt not be the bearer of tidings this day, but thou shalt bear tidings another day; but this day thou shalt bear no tidings, because the king's son is dead. ^21Then said Joab to the Cushite, Go, tell the king what thou hast seen. And the Cushite bowed himself unto Joab, and ran. ^22Then said Ahimaaz the son of Zadok yet again to Joab, But come what may, let me, I pray thee, also run after the Cushite. And Joab said, Wherefore wilt thou run, my son, seeing that thou wilt have no reward for the tidings? ^23But come what may, said he, I will run. And he said unto him, Run. Then Ahimaaz ran by the way of the Plain, and outran the Cushite.

^24Now David was sitting between the two gates: and the watchman went up to the roof of the gate unto the wall, and lifted up his eyes, and looked, and, behold, a man running alone. ^25And the watchman cried, and told the king. And the king said, If he be alone, there is tidings in his mouth. And he came apace, and drew near. ^26And the watchman saw another man running; and the watchman called unto the porter, and said, Behold, another man running alone. And the king said, He also bringeth tidings. ^27And the watchman said, I think the running of the foremost is like the running of Ahimaaz the son of Zadok. And the king said, He is a good man, and cometh with good tidings.

^28And Ahimaaz called, and said unto the king, All is well. And he bowed himself before the king with his face to the earth, and said, Blessed be Jehovah thy God, who hath delivered up the men that lifted up their hand against my lord the king. ^29And the king said, Is it well with the young man Absalom? And Ahimaaz answered, When Joab sent the king's servant, even me thy servant, I saw a great tumult, but I knew not what it was. ^30And the king said, Turn aside, and stand here. And he turned aside, and stood still.

^31And, behold, the Cushite came; and the Cushite said, Tidings for my lord the king; for Jehovah hath avenged thee this day of all them that rose up against thee. ^32And the king said unto the Cushite, Is it well with the young man Absalom? And the Cushite answered, The enemies of my lord the king, and all that rise up against thee to do thee hurt, be as that young man is. ^33And the king was much moved, and went up to the chamber over the gate, and wept: and as he went, thus he said, O my son Absalom, my son, my son Absalom! would I had died for thee, O Absalom, my son, my son!

2 Samuel 19

19

^1And it was told Joab, Behold, the king weepeth and mourneth for Absalom. ^2And the victory that day was turned into mourning unto all the people; for the people heard say that day, The king grieveth for his son. ^3And the people gat them by stealth that day into the city, as people that are ashamed steal away when they flee in battle. ^4And the king covered his face, and the king cried with a loud voice, O my son Absalom, O Absalom, my son, my son! ^5And Joab came into the house to the king, and said, Thou hast shamed this day the faces of all thy servants, who this day have saved thy life, and the lives of thy sons and of thy daughters, and the lives of thy wives, and the lives of thy concubines; ^6in that thou lovest them that hate thee, and hatest them that love thee. For thou hast declared this day, that princes and servants are nought unto thee: for this day I perceive, that if Absalom had lived, and all we had died this day, then it had pleased thee well. ^7Now therefore arise, go forth, and speak comfortably unto thy servants; for I swear by Jehovah, if thou go not forth, there will not tarry a man with thee this night: and that will be worse unto thee than all the evil that hath befallen thee from thy youth until now. ^8Then the king arose, and sat in the gate. And they told unto all the people, saying, Behold, the king is sitting in the gate: and all the people came before the king.

Now Israel had fled every man to his tent. ^9And all the people were at strife throughout all the tribes of Israel, saying, The king delivered us out of the hand of our enemies, and he saved us out of the hand of the Philistines; and now he is fled out of the land from Absalom. ^10And Absalom, whom we anointed over us, is dead in battle. Now therefore why speak ye not a word of bringing the king back?

^11And king David sent to Zadok and to Abiathar the priests, saying, Speak unto the elders of Judah, saying, Why are ye the last to bring the king back to his house? seeing the speech of all Israel is come to the king, to bring him to his house. ^12Ye are my brethren, ye are my bone and my flesh: wherefore then are ye the last to bring back the king? ^13And say ye to Amasa, Art thou not my bone and my flesh? God do so to me, and more also, if thou be not captain of the host before me continually in the room of Joab. ^14And he bowed the heart of all the men of Judah, even as the heart of one man; so that they sent unto the king, saying, Return thou, and all thy servants. ^15So the king returned, and came to the Jordan. And Judah came to Gilgal, to go to meet the king, to bring the king over the Jordan.

^16And Shimei the son of Gera, the Benjamite, who was of Bahurim, hasted and came down with the men of Judah to meet king David. ^17And there were a thousand men of Benjamin with him, and Ziba the servant of the house of Saul, and his fifteen sons and his twenty servants with him; and they went through the Jordan in the presence of the king. ^18And there went over a ferry-boat to bring over the king's household, and to do what he thought good. And Shimei the son of Gera fell down before the king, when he was come over the Jordan. ^19And he said unto the king, Let not my lord impute iniquity unto me, neither do thou remember that which thy servant did perversely the day that my lord the king went out of Jerusalem, that the king should take it to his heart. ^20For thy servant doth know that I have sinned: therefore, behold, I am come this day the first of all the house of Joseph to go down to meet my lord the king.

^21But Abishai the son of Zeruiah answered and said, Shall not Shimei be put to death for this, because he cursed Jehovah's anointed? ^22And David said, What have I to do with you, ye sons of Zeruiah, that ye should this day be adversaries unto me? shall there any man be put to death this day in Israel? for do not I know that I am this day king over Israel? ^23And the king said unto Shimei, Thou shalt not die. And the king sware unto him.

^24And Mephibosheth the son of Saul came down to meet the king; and he had neither dressed his feet, nor trimmed his beard, nor washed his clothes, from the day the king departed until the day he came home in peace. ^25And it came to pass, when he was come to Jerusalem to meet the king, that the king said unto him, Wherefore wentest not thou with me, Mephibosheth? ^26And he answered, My lord, O king, my servant deceived me: for thy servant said, I will saddle me an ass, that I may ride thereon, and go with the king; because thy servant is lame. ^27And he hath slandered thy servant unto my lord the king; but my lord the king is as an angel of God: do therefore what is good in thine eyes. ^28For all my father's house were but dead men before my lord the king; yet didst thou set thy servant among them that did eat at thine own table. What right therefore have I yet that I should cry any more unto the king? ^29And the king said unto him, Why speakest thou any more of thy matters? I say, Thou and Ziba divide the land. ^30And Mephibosheth said unto the king, yea, let him take all, forasmuch as my lord the king is come in peace unto his own house.

^31And Barzillai the Gileadite came down from Rogelim; and he went over the Jordan with the king, to conduct him over the Jordan. ^32Now Barzillai was a very aged man, even fourscore years old: and he had provided the king with sustenance while he lay at Mahanaim; for he was a very great man. ^33And the king said unto Barzillai, Come thou over with me, and I will sustain thee with me in Jerusalem. ^34And Barzillai said unto the king, How many are the days of the years of my life, that I should go up with the king unto Jerusalem? ^35I am this day fourscore years old: can I discern between good and bad? can thy servant taste what I eat or what I drink? can I hear any more the voice of singing men and singing women? wherefore then should thy servant be yet a burden unto my lord the king? ^36Thy servant would but just go over the Jordan with the king: and why should the king recompense it me with such a reward? ^37Let thy servant, I pray thee, turn back again, that I may die in mine own city, by the grave of my father and my mother. But behold, thy servant Chimham; let him go over with my lord the king; and do to him what shall seem good unto thee. ^38And the king answered, Chimham shall go over with me, and I will do to him that which shall seem good unto thee: and whatsoever thou shalt require of me, that will I do for thee. ^39And all the people went over the Jordan, and the king went over: and the king kissed Barzillai, and blessed him; and he returned unto his own place.

^40So the king went over to Gilgal, and Chimham went over with him: and all the people of Judah brought the king over, and also half the people of Israel. ^41And, behold, all the men of Israel came to the king, and said unto the king, Why have our brethren the men of Judah stolen thee away, and brought the king, and his household, over the Jordan, and all David's men with him? ^42And all the men of Judah answered the men of Israel, Because the king is near of kin to us: wherefore then are ye angry for this matter? have we eaten at all at the king's cost? or hath he given us any gift? ^43And the men of Israel answered the men of Judah, and said, We have ten parts in the king, and we have also more right in David than ye: why then did ye despise us, that our advice should not be first had in bringing back our king? And the words of the men of Judah were fiercer than the words of the men of Israel.

2 Samuel 20

20

^1And there happened to be there a base fellow, whose name was Sheba, the son of Bichri, a Benjamite: and he blew the trumpet, and said, We have no portion in David, neither have we inheritance in the son of Jesse: every man to his tents, O Israel. ^2So all the men of Israel went up from following David, and followed Sheba the son of Bichri; but the men of Judah clave unto their king, from the Jordan even to Jerusalem.

^3And David came to his house at Jerusalem; and the king took the ten women his concubines, whom he had left to keep the house, and put them in ward, and provided them with sustenance, but went not in unto them. So they were shut up unto the day of their death, living in widowhood.

^4Then said the king to Amasa, Call me the men of Judah together within three days, and be thou here present. ^5So Amasa went to call the men of Judah together; but he tarried longer than the set time which he had appointed him. ^6And David said to Abishai, Now will Sheba the son of Bichri do us more harm than did Absalom: take thou thy lord's servants, and pursue after him, lest he get him fortified cities, and escape out of our sight. ^7And there went out after him Joab's men, and the Cherethites and the Pelethites, and all the mighty men; and they went out of Jerusalem, to pursue after Sheba the son of Bichri. ^8When they were at the great stone which is in Gibeon, Amasa came to meet them. And Joab was girded with his apparel of war that he had put on, and thereon was a girdle with a sword fastened upon his loins in the sheath thereof; and as he went forth it fell out. ^9And Joab said to Amasa, Is it well with thee, my brother? And Joab took Amasa by the beard with his right hand to kiss him. ^10But Amasa took no heed to the sword that was in Joab's hand: so he smote him therewith in the body, and shed out his bowels to the ground, and struck him not again; and he died.

And Joab and Abishai his brother pursued after Sheba the son of Bichri. ^11And there stood by him one of Joab's young men, and said, He that favoreth Joab, and he that is for David, let him follow Joab. ^12And Amasa lay wallowing in his blood in the midst of the highway. And when the man saw that all the people stood still, he carried Amasa out of the highway into the field, and cast a garment over him, when he saw that every one that came by him stood still. ^13When he was removed out of the highway, all the people went on after Joab, to pursue after Sheba the son of Bichri.

^14And he went through all the tribes of Israel unto Abel, and to Beth-maacah, and all the Berites: and they were gathered together, and went also after him. ^15And they came and besieged him in Abel of Beth-maacah, and they cast up a mound against the city, and it stood against the rampart; and all the people that were with Joab battered the wall, to throw it down. ^16Then cried a wise woman out of the city, Hear, hear; say, I pray you, unto Joab, Come near hither, that I may speak with thee. ^17And he came near unto her; and the woman said, Art thou Joab? And he answered, I am. Then she said unto him, Hear the words of thy handmaid. And he answered, I do hear. ^18Then she spake, saying, They were wont to speak in old time, saying, They shall surely ask counsel at Abel: and so they ended the matter. ^19I am of them that are peaceable and faithful in Israel: thou seekest to destroy a city and a mother in Israel: why wilt thou swallow up the inheritance of Jehovah? ^20And Joab answered and said, Far be it, far be it from me, that I should swallow up or destroy. ^21The matter is not so: but a man of the hill-country of Ephraim, Sheba the son of Bichri by name, hath lifted up his hand against the king, even against David; deliver him only, and I will depart from the city. And the woman said unto Joab, Behold, his head shall be thrown to thee over the wall. ^22Then the woman went unto all the people in her wisdom. And they cut off the head of Sheba the son of Bichri, and threw it out to Joab. And he blew the trumpet, and they were dispersed from the city, every man to his tent. And Joab returned to Jerusalem unto the king.

^23Now Joab was over all the host of Israel; and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the Cherethites and over the Pelethites; ^24and Adoram was over the men subject to taskwork; and Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud was the recorder; ^25and Sheva was scribe; and Zadok and Abiathar were priests; ^26and also Ira the Jairite was chief minister unto David.

2 Samuel 21

21

^1And there was a famine in the days of David three years, year after year; and David sought the face of Jehovah. And Jehovah said, It is for Saul, and for his bloody house, because he put to death the Gibeonites. ^2And the king called the Gibeonites, and said unto them (now the Gibeonites were not of the children of Israel, but of the remnant of the Amorites; and the children of Israel had sworn unto them: and Saul sought to slay them in his zeal for the children of Israel and Judah); ^3and David said unto the Gibeonites, What shall I do for you? and wherewith shall I make atonement, that ye may bless the inheritance of Jehovah? ^4And the Gibeonites said unto him, It is no matter of silver or gold between us and Saul, or his house; neither is it for us to put any man to death in Israel. And he said, What ye shall say, that will I do for you. ^5And they said unto the king, The man that consumed us, and that devised against us, that we should be destroyed from remaining in any of the borders of Israel, ^6let seven men of his sons be delivered unto us, and we will hang them up unto Jehovah in Gibeah of Saul, the chosen of Jehovah. And the king said, I will give them.

^7But the king spared Mephibosheth, the son of Jonathan the son of Saul, because of Jehovah's oath that was between them, between David and Jonathan the son of Saul. ^8But the king took the two sons of Rizpah the daughter of Aiah, whom she bare unto Saul, Armoni and Mephibosheth; and the five sons of Michal the daughter of Saul, whom she bare to Adriel the son of Barzillai the Meholathite: ^9And he delivered them into the hands of the Gibeonites, and they hanged them in the mountain before Jehovah, and they fell all seven together. And they were put to death in the days of harvest, in the first days, at the beginning of barley harvest.

^10And Rizpah the daughter of Aiah took sackcloth, and spread it for her upon the rock, from the beginning of harvest until water was poured upon them from heaven; and she suffered neither the birds of the heavens to rest on them by day, nor the beasts of the field by night. ^11And it was told David what Rizpah the daughter of Aiah, the concubine of Saul, had done.

^12And David went and took the bones of Saul and the bones of Jonathan his son from the men of Jabesh-gilead, who had stolen them from the street of Beth-shan, where the Philistines had hanged them, in the day that the Philistines slew Saul in Gilboa; ^13and he brought up from thence the bones of Saul and the bones of Jonathan his son: and they gathered the bones of them that were hanged. ^14And they buried the bones of Saul and Jonathan his son in the country of Benjamin in Zela, in the sepulchre of Kish his father: and they performed all that the king commanded. And after that God was entreated for the land.

^15And the Philistines had war again with Israel; and David went down, and his servants with him, and fought against the Philistines. And David waxed faint; ^16and Ishbibenob, who was of the sons of the giant, the weight of whose spear was three hundred shekels of brass in weight, he being girded with a new sword, thought to have slain David. ^17But Abishai the son of Zeruiah succored him, and smote the Philistine, and killed him. Then the men of David sware unto him, saying, Thou shalt go no more out with us to battle, that thou quench not the lamp of Israel.

^18And it came to pass after this, that there was again war with the Philistines at Gob: then Sibbecai the Hushathite slew Saph, who was of the sons of the giant. ^19And there was again war with the Philistines at Gob; and Elhanan the son of Jaareoregim the Beth-lehemite slew Goliath the Gittite, the staff of whose spear was like a weaver's beam. ^20And there was again war at Gath, where was a man of great stature, that had on every hand six fingers, and on every foot six toes, four and twenty in number; and he also was born to the giant. ^21And when he defied Israel, Jonathan the son of Shimei, David's brother, slew him. ^22These four were born to the giant in Gath; and they fell by the hand of David, and by the hand of his servants.

2 Samuel 23

23

^1Now these are the last words of David.

David the son of Jesse saith,

And the man who was raised on high saith,

The anointed of the God of Jacob,

And the sweet psalmist of Israel:

^2The Spirit of Jehovah spake by me,

And his word was upon my tongue.

^3The God of Israel said,

The Rock of Israel spake to me:

One that ruleth over men righteously,

That ruleth in the fear of God,

^4He shall be as the light of the morning, when the sun riseth,

A morning without clouds,

When the tender grass springeth out of the earth,

Through clear shining after rain.

^5Verily my house is not so with God;

Yet he hath made with me an everlasting covenant,

Ordered in all things, and sure:

For it is all my salvation, and all my desire,

Although he maketh it not to grow.

^6But the ungodly shall be all of them as thorns to be thrust away,

Because they cannot be taken with the hand

^7But the man that toucheth them

Must be armed with iron and the staff of a spear:

And they shall be utterly burned with fire in their place

^8These are the names of the mighty men whom David had: Josheb-basshebeth a Tahchemonite, chief of the captains; the same was Adino the Eznite, against eight hundred slain at one time.

^9And after him was Eleazar the son of Dodai the son of an Ahohite, one of the three mighty men with David, when they defied the Philistines that were there gathered together to battle, and the men of Israel were gone away. ^10He arose, and smote the Philistines until his hand was weary, and his hand clave unto the sword; and Jehovah wrought a great victory that day; and the people returned after him only to take spoil.

^11And after him was Shammah the son of Agee a Hararite. And the Philistines were gathered together into a troop, where was a plot of ground full of lentils; and the people fled from the Philistines. ^12But he stood in the midst of the plot, and defended it, and slew the Philistines; and Jehovah wrought a great victory.

^13And three of the thirty chief men went down, and came to David in the harvest time unto the cave of Adullam; and the troop of the Philistines was encamped in the valley of Rephaim. ^14And David was then in the stronghold; and the garrison of the Philistines was then in Beth-lehem. ^15And David longed, and said, Oh that one would give me water to drink of the well of Beth-lehem, which is by the gate! ^16And the three mighty men brake through the host of the Philistines, and drew water out of the well of Beth-lehem, that was by the gate, and took it, and brought it to David: but he would not drink thereof, but poured it out unto Jehovah. ^17And he said, Be it far from me, O Jehovah, that I should do this: shall I drink the blood of the men that went in jeopardy of their lives? therefore he would not drink it. These things did the three mighty men.

^18And Abishai, the brother of Joab, the son of Zeruiah, was chief of the three. And he lifted up his spear against three hundred and slew them, and had a name among the three. ^19Was he not most honorable of the three? therefore he was made their captain: howbeit he attained not unto the first three.

^20And Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, the son of a valiant man of Kabzeel, who had done mighty deeds, he slew the two sons of Ariel of Moab: he went down also and slew a lion in the midst of a pit in time of snow. ^21And he slew an Egyptian, a goodly man: and the Egyptian had a spear in his hand; but he went down to him with a staff, and plucked the spear out of the Egyptian's hand, and slew him with his own spear. ^22These things did Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and had a name among the three mighty men. ^23He was more honorable than the thirty, but he attained not to the first three. And David set him over his guard.

^24Asahel the brother of Joab was one of the thirty; Elhanan the son of Dodo of Beth-lehem, ^25Shammah the Harodite, Elika the Harodite, ^26Helez the Paltite, Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite, ^27Abiezer the Anathothite, Mebunnai the Hushathite, ^28Zalmon the Ahohite, Maharai the Netophathite, ^29Heleb the son of Baanah the Netophathite, Ittai the son of Ribai of Gibeah of the children of Benjamin, ^30Benaiah a Pirathonite, Hiddai of the brooks of Gaash. ^31Abialbon the Arbathite, Azmaveth the Barhumite, ^32Eliahba the Shaalbonite, the sons of Jashen, Jonathan, ^33Shammah the Hararite, Ahiam the son of Sharar the Ararite, ^34Eliphelet the son of Ahasbai, the son of the Maacathite, Eliam the son of Ahithophel the Gilonite, ^35Hezro the Carmelite, Paarai the Arbite, ^36Igal the son of Nathan of Zobah, Bani the Gadite, ^37Zelek the Ammonite, Naharai the Beerothite, armorbearers to Joab the son of Zeruiah, ^38Ira the Ithrite, Gareb the Ithrite, ^39Uriah the Hittite: thirty and seven in all.

2 Samuel 24

24

^1And again the anger of Jehovah was kindled against Israel, and he moved David against them, saying, Go, number Israel and Judah. ^2And the king said to Joab the captain of the host, who was with him, Go now to and fro through all the tribes of Israel, from Dan even to Beer-sheba, and number ye the people, that I may know the sum of the people. ^3And Joab said unto the king, Now Jehovah thy God add unto the people, how many soever they may be, a hundredfold; and may the eyes of my lord the king see it: but why doth my lord the king delight in this thing? ^4Notwithstanding, the king's word prevailed against Joab, and against the captains of the host. And Joab and the captains of the host went out from the presence of the king, to number the people of Israel. ^5And they passed over the Jordan, and encamped in Aroer, on the right side of the city that is in the middle of the valley of Gad, and unto Jazer: ^6then they came to Gilead, and to the land of Tahtim-hodshi; and they came to Dan-jaan, and round about to Sidon, ^7and came to the stronghold of Tyre, and to all the cities of the Hivites, and of the Canaanites; and they went out to the south of Judah, at Beer-sheba. ^8So when they had gone to and from through all the land, they came to Jerusalem at the end of nine months and twenty days. ^9And Joab gave up the sum of the numbering of the people unto the king: and there were in Israel eight hundred thousand valiant men that drew the sword; and the men of Judah were five hundred thousand men.

^10And David's heart smote him after that he had numbered the people. And David said unto Jehovah, I have sinned greatly in that which I have done: but now, O Jehovah, put away, I beseech thee, the iniquity of thy servant; for I have done very foolishly. ^11And when David rose up in the morning, the word of Jehovah came unto the prophet Gad, David's seer, saying, ^12Go and speak unto David, Thus saith Jehovah, I offer thee three things: choose thee one of them, that I may do it unto thee. ^13So Gad came to David, and told him, and said unto him, Shall seven years of famine come unto thee in thy land? or wilt thou flee three months before thy foes while they pursue thee? or shall there be three days' pestilence in thy land? now advise thee, and consider what answer I shall return to him that sent me. ^14And David said unto Gad, I am in a great strait: let us fall now into the hand of Jehovah; for his mercies are great; and let me not fall into the hand of man. ^15So Jehovah sent a pestilence upon Israel from the morning even to the time appointed; and there died of the people from Dan even to Beer-sheba seventy thousand men. ^16And when the angel stretched out his hand toward Jerusalem to destroy it, Jehovah repented him of the evil, and said to the angel that destroyed the people, It is enough; now stay thy hand. And the angel of Jehovah was by the threshing-floor of Araunah the Jebusite. ^17And David spake unto Jehovah when he saw the angel that smote the people, and said, Lo, I have sinned, and I have done perversely; but these sheep, what have they done? let thy hand, I pray thee, be against me, and against my father's house.

^18And Gad came that day to David, and said unto him, Go up, rear an altar unto Jehovah in the threshing-floor of Araunah the Jebusite. ^19And David went up according to the saying of Gad, as Jehovah commanded. ^20And Araunah looked forth, and saw the king and his servants coming on toward him: and Araunah went out, and bowed himself before the king with his face to the ground. ^21And Araunah said, Wherefore is my lord the king come to his servant? And David said, To buy the threshing-floor of thee, to build an altar unto Jehovah, that the plague may be stayed from the people. ^22And Araunah said unto David, Let my lord the king take and offer up what seemeth good unto him: behold, the oxen for the burnt-offering, and the threshing instruments and the yokes of the oxen for the wood: ^23all this, O king, doth Araunah give unto the king. And Araunah said unto the king, Jehovah thy God accept thee. ^24And the king said unto Araunah, Nay; but I will verily buy it of thee at a price. Neither will I offer burnt-offerings unto Jehovah my God which cost me nothing. So David bought the threshing-floor and the oxen for fifty shekels of silver. ^25And David built there an altar unto Jehovah, and offered burnt-offerings and peace-offerings. So Jehovah was entreated for the land, and the plague was stayed from Israel.

2 Thessalonians 2

2

^1Now we beseech you, brethren, touching the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, and our gathering together unto him; ^2to the end that ye be not quickly shaken from your mind, nor yet be troubled, either by spirit, or by word, or by epistle as from us, as that the day of the Lord is just at hand; ^3let no man beguile you in any wise: for it will not be, except the falling away come first, and the man of sin be revealed, the son of perdition, ^4he that opposeth and exalteth himself against all that is called God or that is worshipped; so that he sitteth in the temple of God, setting himself forth as God. ^5Remember ye not, that, when I was yet with you, I told you these things? ^6And now ye know that which restraineth, to the end that he may be revealed in his own season. ^7For the mystery of lawlessness doth already work: only there is one that restraineth now, until he be taken out of the way. ^8And then shall be revealed the lawless one, whom the Lord Jesus shall slay with the breath of his mouth, and bring to nought by the manifestation of his coming; ^9even he, whose coming is according to the working of Satan with all power and signs and lying wonders, ^10and with all deceit of unrighteousness for them that perish; because they received not the love of the truth, that they might be saved. ^11And for this cause God sendeth them a working of error, that they should believe a lie: ^12that they all might be judged who believed not the truth, but had pleasure in unrighteousness. ^13But we are bound to give thanks to God always for you, brethren beloved of the Lord, for that God chose you from the beginning unto salvation in sanctification of the Spirit and belief of the truth: ^14whereunto he called you through our gospel, to the obtaining of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ. ^15So then, brethren, stand fast, and hold the traditions which ye were taught, whether by word, or by epistle of ours. ^16Now our Lord Jesus Christ himself, and God our Father who loved us and gave us eternal comfort and good hope through grace, ^17comfort your hearts and establish them in every good work and word.

2 Timothy 2

2

^1Thou therefore, my child, be strengthened in the grace that is in Christ Jesus. ^2And the things which thou hast heard from me among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithful men, who shall be able to teach others also. ^3Suffer hardship with me, as a good soldier of Christ Jesus. ^4No soldier on service entangleth himself in the affairs of this life; that he may please him who enrolled him as a soldier. ^5And if also a man contend in the games, he is not crowded, except he have contended lawfully. ^6The husbandmen that laboreth must be the first to partake of the fruits. ^7Consider what I say; for the Lord shall give thee understanding in all things. ^8Remember Jesus Christ, risen from the dead, of the seed of David, according to my gospel: ^9wherein I suffer hardship unto bonds, as a malefactor; but the word of God is not bound. ^10Therefore I endure all things for the elect's sake, that they also may obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory. ^11Faithful is the saying: For if we died with him, we shall also live with him: ^12if we endure, we shall also reign with him: if we shall deny him, he also will deny us: ^13if we are faithless, he abideth faithful; for he cannot deny himself. ^14Of these things put them in remembrance, charging them in the sight of the Lord, that they strive not about words, to no profit, to the subverting of them that hear. ^15Give diligence to present thyself approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed, handling aright the word of truth. ^16But shun profane babblings: for they will proceed further in ungodliness, ^17and their word will eat as doth a gangrene: or whom is Hymenaeus an Philetus; ^18men who concerning the truth have erred, saying that the resurrection is past already, and overthrow the faith of some. ^19Howbeit the firm foundation of God standeth, having this seal, The Lord knoweth them that are his: and, Let every one that nameth the name of the Lord depart from unrighteousness. ^20Now in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of wood and of earth; and some unto honor, and some unto dishonor. ^21If a man therefore purge himself from these, he shall be a vessel unto honor, sanctified, meet for the master's use, prepared unto every good work. ^22after righteousness, faith, love, pace, with them that call on the Lord out of a pure heart. ^23But foolish and ignorant questionings refuse, knowing that they gender strifes. ^24And the Lord's servant must not strive, but be gentle towards all, apt to teach, forbearing, ^25in meekness correcting them that oppose themselves; if peradventure God may give them repentance unto the knowledge of the truth, ^26and they may recover themselves out of the snare of the devil, having been taken captive by him unto his will.

2 Timothy 3

3

^1But know this, that in the last days grievous times shall come. ^2For men shall be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful, haughty, railers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy, ^3without natural affection, implacable, slanderers, without self-control, fierce, no lovers of good, ^4traitors, headstrong, puffed up, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God; ^5holding a form of godliness, but having denied the power therefore. From these also turn away. ^6For of these are they that creep into houses, and take captive silly women laden with sins, led away by divers lusts, ^7ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth. ^8And even as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so do these also withstand the truth. Men corrupted in mind, reprobate concerning the faith. ^9But they shall proceed no further. For their folly shall be evident unto all men, as theirs also came to be. ^10But thou didst follow my teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, longsuffering, love, patience, ^11persecutions, sufferings. What things befell me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra; what persecutions I endured. And out of them all the Lord delivered me. ^12Yea, and all that would live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution. ^13But evil men and impostors shall wax worse and worse, deceiving and being deceived. ^14But abide thou in the things which thou hast learned and hast been assured of, knowing of whom thou hast learned them. ^15And that from a babe thou hast known the sacred writings which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus. ^16Every span inspired of God is also profitable for teaching, for reproof, for correction, for instruction which is in righteousness. ^17That the man of God may be complete, furnished completely unto every good work.

2 Timothy 4

4

^1I charge thee in the sight of God, and of Christ Jesus, who shall judge the living and the dead, and by his appearing and his kingdom: ^2preach the word; be urgent in season, out of season; reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all longsuffering and teaching. ^3For the time will come when they will not endure the sound doctrine; but, having itching ears, will heap to themselves teachers after their own lusts; ^4and will turn away their ears from the truth, and turn aside unto fables. ^5But be thou sober in all things, suffer hardship, do the work of an evangelist, fulfil thy ministry. ^6For I am already being offered, and the time of my departure is come. ^7I have fought the good fight, I have finished the course, I have kept the faith: ^8henceforth there is laid up for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give to me at that day; and not to me only, but also to all them that have loved his appearing. ^9Give diligence to come shortly unto me: ^10for Demas forsook me, having loved this present world, and went to Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, Titus to Dalmatia. ^11Only Luke is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with thee; for he is useful to me for ministering. ^12But Tychicus I sent to Ephesus. ^13The cloak that I left at Troas with Carpus, bring when thou comest, and the books, especially the parchments. ^14Alexander the coppersmith did me much evil: the Lord will render to him according to his works: ^15of whom do thou also beware; for he greatly withstood our words. ^16At my first defence no one took my part, but all forsook me: may it not be laid to their account. ^17But the Lord stood by me, and strengthened me; that through me the message might be fully proclaimed, and that all the Gentiles might hear: and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion. ^18The Lord will deliver me from every evil work, and will save me unto his heavenly kingdom: to whom be the glory forever and ever. Amen. ^19Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus. ^20Erastus remained at Corinth: but Trophimus I left at Miletus sick. ^21Give diligence to come before winter. Eubulus saluteth thee, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren. ^22The Lord be with thy spirit. Grace be with you.

1 John 2

2

^1My little children, these things write I unto you that ye may not sin. And if any man sin, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous: ^2and he is the propitiation for our sins; and not for ours only, but also for the whole world. ^3And hereby we know that we know him, if we keep his commandments. ^4He that saith, I know him, and keepeth not his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him; ^5but whoso keepeth his word, in him verily hath the love of God been perfected. Hereby we know that we are in him: ^6he that saith he abideth in him ought himself also to walk even as he walked. ^7Beloved, no new commandment write I unto you, but an old commandment which ye had from the beginning: the old commandment is the word which ye heard. ^8Again, a new commandment write I unto you, which thing is true in him and in you; because the darkness is passing away, and the true light already shineth. ^9He that saith he is in the light and hateth his brother, is in the darkness even until now. ^10He that loveth his brother abideth in the light, and there is no occasion of stumbling in him. ^11But he that hateth his brother is in the darkness, and walketh in the darkness, and knoweth not whither he goeth, because the darkness hath blinded his eyes. ^12I write unto you, my little children, because your sins are forgiven you for his name's sake. ^13I write unto you, fathers, because ye know him who is from the beginning. I write unto you, young men, because ye have overcome the evil one. I have written unto you, little children, because ye know the Father. ^14I have written unto you, fathers, because ye know him who is from the beginning. I have written unto you, young men, because ye are strong, and the word of God abideth in you, and ye have overcome the evil one. ^15Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world. If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him. ^16For all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh and the lust of the eyes and the vain glory of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world. ^17And the world passeth away, and the lust thereof: but he that doeth the will of God abideth for ever. ^18Little children, it is the last hour: and as ye heard that antichrist cometh, even now have there arisen many antichrists; whereby we know that it is the last hour. ^19They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would have continued with us: but they went out, that they might be made manifest that they all are not of us. ^20And ye have an anointing from the Holy One, and ye know all the things. ^21I have not written unto you because ye know not the truth, but because ye know it, and because no lie is of the truth. ^22Who is the liar but he that denieth that Jesus is the Christ? This is the antichrist, even he that denieth the Father and the Son. ^23Whosoever denieth the Son, the same hath not the Father: he that confesseth the Son hath the Father also. ^24As for you, let that abide in you which ye heard from the beginning. If that which ye heard from the beginning abide in you, ye also shall abide in the Son, and in the Father. ^25And this is the promise which he promised us, even the life eternal. ^26These things have I written unto you concerning them that would lead you astray. ^27And as for you, the anointing which ye received of him abideth in you, and ye need not that any one teach you; but as his anointing teacheth you; concerning all things, and is true, and is no lie, and even as it taught you, ye abide in him. ^28And now, my little children, abide in him; that, if he shall be manifested, we may have boldness, and not be ashamed before him at his coming. ^29If ye know that he is righteous, ye know that every one also that doeth righteousness is begotten of him.

1 John 3

3

^1Behold what manner of love the Father hath bestowed upon us, that we should be called children of God; and such we are. For this cause the world knoweth us not, because it knew him not. ^2Beloved, now are we children of God, and it is not yet made manifest what we shall be. We know that, if he shall be manifested, we shall be like him; for we shall see him even as he is. ^3And every one that hath this hope set on him purifieth himself, even as he is pure. ^4Every one that doeth sin doeth also lawlessness; and sin is lawlessness. ^5And ye know that he was manifested to take away sins; and in him is no sin. ^6Whosoever abideth in him sinneth not: whosoever sinneth hath not seen him, neither knoweth him. ^7My little children, let no man lead you astray: he that doeth righteousness is righteous, even as he is righteous: ^8he that doeth sin is of the devil; for the devil sinneth from the beginning. To this end was the Son of God manifested, that he might destroy the works of the devil. ^9Whosoever is begotten of God doeth no sin, because his seed abideth in him: and he cannot sin, because he is begotten of God. ^10In this the children of God are manifest, and the children of the devil: whosoever doeth not righteousness is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother. ^11For this is the message which ye heard from the beginning, that we should love one another: ^12not as Cain was of the evil one, and slew his brother. And wherefore slew he him? Because his works were evil, and his brother's righteous. ^13Marvel not, brethren, if the world hateth you. ^14We know that we have passed out of death into life, because we love the brethren. He that loveth not abideth in death. ^15Whosoever hateth his brother is a murderer: and ye know that no murderer hath eternal life abiding in him. ^16Hereby know we love, because he laid down his life for us: and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren. ^17But whoso hath the world's goods, and beholdeth his brother in need, and shutteth up his compassion from him, how doth the love of God abide in him? ^18My Little children, let us not love in word, neither with the tongue; but in deed and truth. ^19Hereby shall we know that we are of the truth, and shall assure our heart before him: ^20because if our heart condemn us, God is greater than our heart, and knoweth all things. ^21Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, we have boldness toward God; ^22and whatsoever we ask we receive of him, because we keep his commandments and do the things that are pleasing in his sight. ^23And this is his commandment, that we should believe in the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and love one another, even as he gave us commandment. ^24And he that keepeth his commandments abideth in him, and he in him. And hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he gave us.

1 John 4

4

^1Beloved, believe not every spirit, but prove the spirits, whether they are of God; because many false prophets are gone out into the world. ^2Hereby know ye the Spirit of God: every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is of God: ^3and every spirit that confesseth not Jesus is not of God: and this is the spirit of the antichrist, whereof ye have heard that it cometh; and now it is in the world already. ^4Ye are of God, my little children, and have overcome them: because greater is he that is in you than he that is in the world. ^5They are of the world: therefore speak they as of the world, and the world heareth them. ^6We are of God: he that knoweth God heareth us; he who is not of God heareth us not. By this we know the spirit of truth, and the spirit of error. ^7Beloved, let us love one another: for love is of God; and every one that loveth is begotten of God, and knoweth God. ^8He that loveth not knoweth not God; for God is love. ^9Herein was the love of God manifested in us, that God hath sent his only begotten Son into the world that we might live through him. ^10Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his Son to be the propitiation for our sins. ^11Beloved, if God so loved us, we also ought to love one another. ^12No man hath beheld God at any time: if we love one another, God abideth in us, and his love is perfected in us: ^13hereby we know that we abide in him and he in us, because he hath given us of his Spirit. ^14And we have beheld and bear witness that the Father hath sent the Son to be the Saviour of the world. ^15Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God abideth in him, and he in God. ^16And we know and have believed the love which God hath in us. God is love; and he that abideth in love abideth in God, and God abideth in him. ^17Herein is love made perfect with us, that we may have boldness in the day of judgment; because as he is, even so are we in this world. ^18There is no fear in love: but perfect love casteth out fear, because fear hath punishment; and he that feareth is not made perfect in love. ^19We love, because he first loved us. ^20If a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar: for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen, cannot love God whom he hath not seen. ^21And this commandment have we from him, that he who loveth God love his brother also.

1 John 5

5

^1Whosoever believeth that Jesus is the Christ is begotten of God: and whosoever loveth him that begat loveth him also that is begotten of him. ^2Hereby we know that we love the children of God, when we love God and do his commandments. ^3For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments: and his commandments are not grievous. ^4For whatsoever is begotten of God overcometh the world: and this is the victory that hath overcome the world, even our faith. ^5And who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jesus is the Son of God? ^6This is he that came by water and blood, even Jesus Christ; not with the water only, but with the water and with the blood. ^7And it is the Spirit that beareth witness, because the Spirit is the truth. ^8For there are three who bear witness, the Spirit, and the water, and the blood: and the three agree in one. ^9If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater: for the witness of God is this, that he hath borne witness concerning his Son. ^10He that believeth on the Son of God hath the witness in him: he that believeth not God hath made him a liar; because he hath not believed in the witness that God hath borne concerning his Son. ^11And the witness is this, that God gave unto us eternal life, and this life is in his Son. ^12He that hath the Son hath the life; he that hath not the Son of God hath not the life. ^13These things have I written unto you, that ye may know that ye have eternal life, even unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God. ^14And this is the boldness which we have toward him, that, if we ask anything according to his will, he heareth us: ^15and if we know that he heareth us whatsoever we ask, we know that we have the petitions which we have asked of him. ^16If any man see his brother sinning a sin not unto death, he shall ask, and God will give him life for them that sin not unto death. There is a sin unto death: not concerning this do I say that he should make request. ^17All unrighteousness is sin: and there is a sin not unto death. ^18We know that whosoever is begotten of God sinneth not; but he that was begotten of God keepeth himself, and the evil one toucheth him not. ^19We know that we are of God, and the whole world lieth in the evil one. ^20And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an understanding, that we know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God, and eternal life. ^21My little children, guard yourselves from idols.

1 Kings 2

2

^1Now the days of David drew nigh that he should die; and he charged Solomon his son, saying, ^2I am going the way of all the earth: be thou strong therefore, and show thyself a man; ^3and keep the charge of Jehovah thy God, to walk in his ways, to keep his statutes, and his commandments, and his ordinances, and his testimonies, according to that which is written in the law of Moses, that thou mayest prosper in all that thou doest, and whithersoever thou turnest thyself. ^4That Jehovah may establish his word which he spake concerning me, saying, If thy children take heed to their way, to walk before me in truth with all their heart and with all their soul, there shall not fail thee (said he) a man on the throne of Israel. ^5Moreover thou knowest also what Joab the son of Zeruiah did unto me, even what he did to the two captains of the hosts of Israel, unto Abner the son of Ner, and unto Amasa the son of Jether, whom he slew, and shed the blood of war in peace, and put the blood of war upon his girdle that was about his loins, and in his shoes that were on his feet. ^6Do therefore according to thy wisdom, and let not his hoar head go down to Sheol in peace. ^7But show kindness unto the sons of Barzillai the Gileadite, and let them be of those that eat at thy table; for so they came to me when I fled from Absalom thy brother. ^8And, behold, there is with thee Shimei the son of Gera, the Benjamite, of Bahurim, who cursed me with a grievous curse in the day when I went to Mahanaim; but he came down to meet me at the Jordan, and I sware to him by Jehovah, saying, I will not put thee to death with the sword. ^9Now therefore hold him not guiltless, for thou art a wise man; and thou wilt know what thou oughtest to do unto him, and thou shalt bring his hoar head down to Sheol with blood.

^10And David slept with his fathers, and was buried in the city of David. ^11And the days that David reigned over Israel were forty years; seven years reigned he in Hebron, and thirty and three years reigned he in Jerusalem. ^12And Solomon sat upon the throne of David his father; and his kingdom was established greatly.

^13Then Adonijah the son of Haggith came to Bath-sheba the mother of Solomon. And she said, Comest thou peaceably? And he said, Peaceably. ^14He said moreover, I have somewhat to say unto thee. And she said, Say on. ^15And he said, Thou knowest that the kingdom was mine, and that all Israel set their faces on me, that I should reign: howbeit the kingdom is turned about, and is become my brother's; for it was his from Jehovah. ^16And now I ask one petition of thee; deny me not. And she said unto him, Say on. ^17And he said, Speak, I pray thee, unto Solomon the king (for he will not say thee nay), that he give me Abishag the Shunammite to wife. ^18And Bath-sheba said, Well; I will speak for thee unto the king.

^19Bath-sheba therefore went unto king Solomon, to speak unto him for Adonijah. And the king rose up to meet her, and bowed himself unto her, and sat down on his throne, and caused a throne to be set for the king's mother; and she sat on his right hand. ^20Then she said, I ask one small petition of thee; deny me not. And the king said unto her, Ask on, my mother; for I will not deny thee. ^21And she said, Let Abishag the Shunammite be given to Adonijah thy brother to wife. ^22And king Solomon answered and said unto his mother, And why dost thou ask Abishag the Shunammite for Adonijah? ask for him the kingdom also; for he is mine elder brother; even for him, and for Abiathar the priest, and for Joab the son of Zeruiah. ^23Then king Solomon sware by Jehovah, saying, God do so to me, and more also, if Adonijah hath not spoken this word against his own life. ^24Now therefore as Jehovah liveth, who hath established me, and set me on the throne of David my father, and who hath made me a house, as he promised, surely Adonijah shall be put to death this day. ^25And king Solomon sent by Benaiah the son of Jehoiada; and he fell upon him, so that he died.

^26And unto Abiathar the priest said the king, Get thee to Anathoth, unto thine own fields; for thou art worthy of death: but I will not at this time put thee to death, because thou barest the ark of the Lord Jehovah before David my father, and because thou wast afflicted in all wherein my father was afflicted. ^27So Solomon thrust out Abiathar from being priest unto Jehovah, that he might fulfil the word of Jehovah, which he spake concerning the house of Eli in Shiloh.

^28And the tidings came to Joab; for Joab had turned after Adonijah, though he turned not after Absalom. And Joab fled unto the Tent of Jehovah, and caught hold on the horns of the altar. ^29And it was told king Solomon, Joab is fled unto the Tent of Jehovah, and, behold, he is by the altar. Then Solomon sent Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, saying, Go, fall upon him. ^30And Benaiah came to the Tent of Jehovah, and said unto him, Thus saith the king, Come forth. And he said, Nay; but I will die here. And Benaiah brought the king word again, saying, Thus said Joab, and thus he answered me. ^31And the king said unto him, Do as he hath said, and fall upon him, and bury him; that thou mayest take away the blood, which Joab shed without cause, from me and from my father's house. ^32And Jehovah will return his blood upon his own head, because he fell upon two men more righteous and better than he, and slew them with the sword, and my father David knew it not, to wit, Abner the son of Ner, captain of the host of Israel, and Amasa the son of Jether, captain of the host of Judah. ^33So shall their blood return upon the head of Joab, and upon the head of his seed for ever: but unto David, and unto his seed, and unto his house, and unto his throne, shall there be peace for ever from Jehovah. ^34Then Benaiah the son of Jehoiada went up, and fell upon him, and slew him; and he was buried in his own house in the wilderness. ^35And the king put Benaiah the son of Jehoiada in his room over the host; and Zadok the priest did the king put in the room of Abiathar.

^36And the king sent and called for Shimei, and said unto him, Build thee a house in Jerusalem, and dwell there, and go not forth thence any whither. ^37For on the day thou goest out, and passest over the brook Kidron, know thou for certain that thou shalt surely die: thy blood shall be upon thine own head. ^38And Shimei said unto the king, The saying is good: as my lord the king hath said, so will thy servant do. And Shimei dwelt in Jerusalem many days.

^39And it came to pass at the end of three years, that two of the servants of Shimei ran away unto Achish, son of Maacah, king of Gath. And they told Shimei, saying, Behold, thy servants are in Gath. ^40And Shimei arose, and saddled his ass, and went to Gath to Achish, to seek his servants; and Shimei went, and brought his servants from Gath. ^41And it was told Solomon that Shimei had gone from Jerusalem to Gath, and was come again. ^42And the king sent and called for Shimei, and said unto him, Did I not adjure thee by Jehovah, and protest unto thee, saying, Know for certain, that on the day thou goest out, and walkest abroad any whither, thou shalt surely die? and thou saidst unto me, The saying that I have heard is good. ^43Why then hast thou not kept the oath of Jehovah, and the commandment that I have charged thee with? ^44The king said moreover to Shimei, Thou knowest all the wickedness which thy heart is privy to, that thou didst to David my father: therefore Jehovah shall return thy wickedness upon thine own head. ^45But king Solomon shall be blessed, and the throne of David shall be established before Jehovah for ever. ^46So the king commanded Benaiah the son of Jehoiada; and he went out, and fell upon him, so that he died. And the kingdom was established in the hand of Solomon.

1 Kings 3

3

^1And Solomon made affinity with Pharaoh king of Egypt, and took Pharaoh's daughter, and brought her into the city of David, until he had made an end of building his own house, and the house of Jehovah, and the wall of Jerusalem round about. ^2Only the people sacrificed in the high places, because there was no house built for the name of Jehovah until those days. ^3And Solomon loved Jehovah, walking in the statutes of David his father: only he sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places.

^4And the king went to Gibeon to sacrifice there; for that was the great high place: a thousand burnt-offerings did Solomon offer upon that altar. ^5In Gibeon Jehovah appeared to Solomon in a dream by night; and God said, Ask what I shall give thee. ^6And Solomon said, Thou hast showed unto thy servant David my father great lovingkindness, according as he walked before thee in truth, and in righteousness, and in uprightness of heart with thee; and thou hast kept for him this great lovingkindness, that thou hast given him a son to sit on his throne, as it is this day. ^7And now, O Jehovah my God, thou hast made thy servant king instead of David my father: and I am but a little child; I know not how to go out or come in. ^8And thy servant is in the midst of thy people which thou hast chosen, a great people, that cannot be numbered nor counted for multitude. ^9Give thy servant therefore an understanding heart to judge thy people, that I may discern between good and evil; for who is able to judge this thy great people?

^10And the speech pleased the Lord, that Solomon had asked this thing. ^11And God said unto him, Because thou hast asked this thing, and hast not asked for thyself long life, neither hast asked riches for thyself, nor hast asked the life of thine enemies, but hast asked for thyself understanding to discern justice; ^12behold, I have done according to thy word: lo, I have given thee a wise and an understanding heart; so that there hath been none like thee before thee, neither after thee shall any arise like unto thee. ^13And I have also given thee that which thou hast not asked, both riches and honor, so that there shall not be any among the kings like unto thee, all thy days. ^14And if thou wilt walk in my ways, to keep my statutes and my commandments, as thy father David did walk, then I will lengthen thy days. ^15And Solomon awoke; and, behold, it was a dream: and he came to Jerusalem, and stood before the ark of the covenant of Jehovah, and offered up burnt-offerings, and offered peace-offerings, and made a feast to all his servants.

^16Then there came two women that were harlots, unto the king, and stood before him. ^17And the one woman said, Oh, my lord, I and this woman dwell in one house; and I was delivered of a child with her in the house. ^18And it came to pass the third day after I was delivered, that this woman was delivered also; and we were together; there was no stranger with us in the house, save we two in the house. ^19And this woman's child died in the night, because she lay upon it. ^20And she arose at midnight, and took my son from beside me, while thy handmaid slept, and laid it in her bosom, and laid her dead child in my bosom. ^21And when I rose in the morning to give my child suck, behold, it was dead; but when I had looked at it in the morning, behold, it was not my son, whom I did bear. ^22And the other woman said, Nay; but the living is my son, and the dead is thy son. And this said, No; but the dead is thy son, and the living is my son. Thus they spake before the king.

^23Then said the king, The one saith, This is my son that liveth, and thy son is the dead: and the other saith, Nay; but thy son is the dead, and my son is the living. ^24And the king said, Fetch me a sword. And they brought a sword before the king. ^25And the king said, Divide the living child in two, and give half to the one, and half to the other. ^26Then spake the woman whose the living child was unto the king, for her heart yearned over her son, and she said, Oh, my lord, give her the living child, and in no wise slay it. But the other said, It shall be neither mine nor thine; divide it. ^27Then the king answered and said, Give her the living child, and in no wise slay it: she is the mother thereof. ^28And all Israel heard of the judgment which the king had judged; and they feared the king: for they saw that the wisdom of God was in him, to do justice.

1 Kings 4

4

^1And king Solomon was king over all Israel. ^2And these were the princes whom he had: Azariah the son of Zadok, the priest; ^3Elihoreph and Ahijah, the sons of Shisha, scribes; Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud, the recorder; ^4and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the host; and Zadok and Abiathar were priests; ^5and Azariah the son of Nathan was over the officers; and Zabud the son of Nathan was chief minister, and the king's friend; ^6and Ahishar was over the household; and Adoniram the son of Abda was over the men subject to taskwork.

^7And Solomon had twelve officers over all Israel, who provided victuals for the king and his household: each man had to make provision for a month in the year. ^8And these are their names: Ben-hur, in the hill-country of Ephraim; ^9Ben-deker, in Makaz, and in Shaalbim, and Beth-shemesh, and Elon-beth-hanan; ^10Ben-hesed, in Arubboth (to him pertained Socoh, and all the land of Hepher); ^11Ben-abinadab, in all the height of Dor (he had Taphath the daughter of Solomon to wife); ^12Baana the son of Ahilud, in Taanach and Megiddo, and all Beth-shean which is beside Zarethan, beneath Jezreel, from Beth-shean to Abel-meholah, as far as beyond Jokmeam; ^13Ben-geber, in Ramoth-gilead (to him pertained the towns of Jair the son of Manasseh, which are in Gilead; even to him pertained the region of Argob, which is in Bashan, threescore great cities with walls and brazen bars); ^14Ahinadab the son of Iddo, in Mahanaim; ^15Ahimaaz, in Naphtali (he also took Basemath the daughter of Solomon to wife); ^16Baana the son of Hushai, in Asher and Bealoth; ^17Jehoshaphat the son of Paruah, in Issachar; ^18Shimei the son of Ela, in Benjamin; ^19Geber the son of Uri, in the land of Gilead, the country of Sihon king of the Amorites and of Og king of Bashan; and he was the only officer that was in the land.

^20Judah and Israel were many as the sand which is by the sea in multitude, eating and drinking and making merry. ^21And Solomon ruled over all the kingdoms from the River unto the land of the Philistines, and unto the border of Egypt: they brought tribute, and served Solomon all the days of his life. ^22And Solomon's provision for one day was thirty measures of fine flour, and threescore measures of meal, ^23ten fat oxen, and twenty oxen out of the pastures, and a hundred sheep, besides harts, and gazelles, and roebucks, and fatted fowl. ^24For he had dominion over all the region on this side the River, from Tiphsah even to Gaza, over all the kings on this side the River: and he had peace on all sides round about him. ^25And Judah and Israel dwelt safely, every man under his vine and under his fig-tree, from Dan even to Beer-sheba, all the days of Solomon. ^26And Solomon had forty thousand stalls of horses for his chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen. ^27And those officers provided victuals for king Solomon, and for all that came unto king Solomon's table, every man in his month; they let nothing be lacking. ^28Barley also and straw for the horses and swift steeds brought they unto the place where the officers were, every man according to his charge.

^29And God gave Solomon wisdom and understanding exceeding much, and largeness of heart, even as the sand that is on the sea-shore. ^30And Solomon's wisdom excelled the wisdom of all the children of the east, and all the wisdom of Egypt. ^31For he was wiser than all men; than Ethan the Ezrahite, and Heman, and Calcol, and Darda, the sons of Mahol: and his fame was in all the nations round about. ^32And he spake three thousand proverbs; and his songs were a thousand and five. ^33And he spake of trees, from the cedar that is in Lebanon even unto the hyssop that springeth out of the wall; he spake also of beasts, and of birds, and of creeping things, and of fishes. ^34And there came of all peoples to hear the wisdom of Solomon, from all kings of the earth, who had heard of his wisdom.

1 Kings 5

5

^1And Hiram king of Tyre sent his servants unto Solomon; for he had heard that they had anointed him king in the room of his father: for Hiram was ever a lover of David. ^2And Solomon sent to Hiram, saying, ^3Thou knowest how that David my father could not build a house for the name of Jehovah his God for the wars which were about him on every side, until Jehovah put them under the soles of his feet. ^4But now Jehovah my God hath given me rest on every side; there is neither adversary, nor evil occurrence. ^5And, behold, I purpose to build a house for the name of Jehovah my God, as Jehovah spake unto David my father, saying, Thy son, whom I will set upon thy throne in thy room, he shall build the house for my name. ^6Now therefore command thou that they cut me cedar-trees out of Lebanon; and my servants shall be with thy servants; and I will give thee hire for thy servants according to all that thou shalt say: for thou knowest that there is not among us any that knoweth how to cut timber like unto the Sidonians.

^7And it came to pass, when Hiram heard the words of Solomon, that he rejoiced greatly, and said, Blessed be Jehovah this day, who hath given unto David a wise son over this great people. ^8And Hiram sent to Solomon, saying, I have heard the message which thou hast sent unto me: I will do all thy desire concerning timber of cedar, and concerning timber of fir. ^9My servants shall bring them down from Lebanon unto the sea; and I will make them into rafts to go by sea unto the place that thou shalt appoint me, and will cause them to be broken up there, and thou shalt receive them; and thou shalt accomplish my desire, in giving food for my household. ^10So Hiram gave Solomon timber of cedar and timber of fir according to all his desire. ^11And Solomon gave Hiram twenty thousand measures of wheat for food to his household, and twenty measures of pure oil: thus gave Solomon to Hiram year by year. ^12And Jehovah gave Solomon wisdom, as he promised him; and there was peace between Hiram and Solomon; and they two made a league together.

^13And king Solomon raised a levy out of all Israel; and the levy was thirty thousand men. ^14And he sent them to Lebanon, ten thousand a month by courses; a month they were in Lebanon, and two months at home; and Adoniram was over the men subject to taskwork. ^15And Solomon had threescore and ten thousand that bare burdens, and fourscore thousand that were hewers in the mountains; ^16besides Solomon's chief officers that were over the work, three thousand and three hundred, who bare rule over the people that wrought in the work. ^17And the king commanded, and they hewed out great stones, costly stones, to lay the foundation of the house with wrought stone. ^18And Solomon's builders and Hiram's builders and the Gebalites did fashion them, and prepared the timber and the stones to build the house.

1 Kings 6

6

^1And it came to pass in the four hundred and eightieth year after the children of Israel were come out of the land of Egypt, in the fourth year of Solomon's reign over Israel, in the month Ziv, which is the second month, that he began to build the house of Jehovah. ^2And the house which king Solomon built for Jehovah, the length thereof was threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof twenty cubits, and the height thereof thirty cubits. ^3And the porch before the temple of the house, twenty cubits was the length thereof, according to the breadth of the house; and ten cubits was the breadth thereof before the house. ^4And for the house he made windows of fixed lattice-work. ^5And against the wall of the house he built stories round about, against the walls of the house round about, both of the temple and of the oracle; and he made side-chambers round about. ^6The nethermost story was five cubits broad, and the middle was six cubits broad, and the third was seven cubits broad; for on the outside he made offsets in the wall of the house round about, that the beams should not have hold in the walls of the house. ^7And the house, when it was in building, was built of stone made ready at the quarry; and there was neither hammer nor axe nor any tool of iron heard in the house, while it was in building. ^8The door for the middle side-chambers was in the right side of the house: and they went up by winding stairs into the middle story, and out of the middle into the third. ^9So he built the house, and finished it; and he covered the house with beams and planks of cedar. ^10And he built the stories against all the house, each five cubits high: and they rested on the house with timber of cedar.

^11And the word of Jehovah came to Solomon, saying, ^12Concerning this house which thou art building, if thou wilt walk in my statutes, and execute mine ordinances, and keep all my commandments to walk in them; then will I establish my word with thee, which I spake unto David thy father. ^13And I will dwell among the children of Israel, and will not forsake my people Israel.

^14So Solomon built the house, and finished it. ^15And he built the walls of the house within with boards of cedar: from the floor of the house unto the walls of the ceiling, he covered them on the inside with wood; and he covered the floor of the house with boards of fir. ^16And he built twenty cubits on the hinder part of the house with boards of cedar from the floor unto the walls of the ceiling: he built them for it within, for an oracle, even for the most holy place. ^17And the house, that is, the temple before the oracle, was forty cubits long. ^18And there was cedar on the house within, carved with knops and open flowers: all was cedar; there was no stone seen. ^19And he prepared an oracle in the midst of the house within, to set there the ark of the covenant of Jehovah. ^20And within the oracle was a space of twenty cubits in length, and twenty cubits in breadth, and twenty cubits in the height thereof; and he overlaid it with pure gold: and he covered the altar with cedar. ^21So Solomon overlaid the house within with pure gold: and he drew chains of gold across before the oracle; and he overlaid it with gold. ^22And the whole house he overlaid with gold, until all the house was finished: also the whole altar that belonged to the oracle he overlaid with gold.

^23And in the oracle he made two cherubim of olive-wood, each ten cubits high. ^24And five cubits was the one wing of the cherub, and five cubits the other wing of the cherub: from the uttermost part of the one wing unto the uttermost part of the other were ten cubits. ^25And the other cherub was ten cubits: both the cherubim were of one measure and one form. ^26The height of the one cherub was ten cubits, and so was it of the other cherub. ^27And he set the cherubim within the inner house; and the wings of the cherubim were stretched forth, so that the wing of the one touched the one wall, and the wing of the other cherub touched the other wall; and their wings touched one another in the midst of the house. ^28And he overlaid the cherubim with gold.

^29And he carved all the walls of the house round about with carved figures of cherubim and palm-trees and open flowers, within and without. ^30And the floor of the house he overlaid with gold, within and without. ^31And for the entrance of the oracle he made doors of olive-wood: the lintel and door-posts were a fifth part of the wall. ^32So he made two doors of olive-wood; and he carved upon them carvings of cherubim and palm-trees and open flowers, and overlaid them with gold; and he spread the gold upon the cherubim, and upon the palm-trees. ^33So also made he for the entrance of the temple door-posts of olive-wood, out of a fourth part of the wall; ^34and two doors of fir-wood: the two leaves of the one door were folding, and the two leaves of the other door were folding. ^35And he carved thereon cherubim and palm-trees and open flowers; and he overlaid them with gold fitted upon the graven work. ^36And he built the inner court with three courses of hewn stone, and a course of cedar beams.

^37In the fourth year was the foundation of the house of Jehovah laid, in the month Ziv. ^38And in the eleventh year, in the month Bul, which is the eighth month, was the house finished throughout all the parts thereof, and according to all the fashion of it. So was he seven years in building it.

1 Kings 7

7

^1And Solomon was building his own house thirteen years, and he finished all his house. ^2For he built the house of the forest of Lebanon; the length thereof was a hundred cubits, and the breadth thereof fifty cubits, and the height thereof thirty cubits, upon four rows of cedar pillars, with cedar beams upon the pillars. ^3And it was covered with cedar above over the forty and five beams, that were upon the pillars; fifteen in a row. ^4And there were beams in three rows, and window was over against window in three ranks. ^5And all the doors and posts were made square with beams: and window was over against window in three ranks. ^6And he made the porch of pillars; the length thereof was fifty cubits, and the breadth thereof thirty cubits; and a porch before them; and pillars and a threshold before them. ^7And he made the porch of the throne where he was to judge, even the porch of judgment: and it was covered with cedar from floor to floor. ^8And his house where he was to dwell, the other court within the porch, was of the like work. He made also a house for Pharaoh's daughter (whom Solomon had taken to wife), like unto this porch.

^9All these were of costly stones, even of hewn stone, according to measure, sawed with saws, within and without, even from the foundation unto the coping, and so on the outside unto the great court. ^10And the foundation was of costly stones, even great stones, stones of ten cubits, and stones of eight cubits. ^11And above were costly stones, even hewn stone, according to measure, and cedar-wood. ^12And the great court round about had three courses of hewn stone, and a course of cedar beams; like as the inner court of the house of Jehovah, and the porch of the house.

^13And king Solomon sent and fetched Hiram out of Tyre. ^14He was the son of a widow of the tribe of Naphtali, and his father was a man of Tyre, a worker in brass; and he was filled with wisdom and understanding and skill, to work all works in brass. And he came to king Solomon, and wrought all his work. ^15For he fashioned the two pillars of brass, eighteen cubits high apiece: and a line of twelve cubits compassed either of them about. ^16And he made two capitals of molten brass, to set upon the tops of the pillars: the height of the one capital was five cubits, and the height of the other capital was five cubits. ^17There were nets of checker-work, and wreaths of chain-work, for the capitals which were upon the top of the pillars; seven for the one capital, and seven for the other capital. ^18So he made the pillars; and there were two rows round about upon the one network, to cover the capitals that were upon the top of the pillars: and so did he for the other capital. ^19And the capitals that were upon the top of the pillars in the porch were of lily-work, four cubits. ^20And there were capitals above also upon the two pillars, close by the belly which was beside the network: and the pomegranates were two hundred, in rows round about upon the other capital. ^21And he set up the pillars at the porch of the temple: and he set up the right pillar, and called the name thereof Jachin; and he set up the left pillar, and called the name thereof Boaz. ^22And upon the top of the pillars was lily-work: so was the work of the pillars finished.

^23And he made the molten sea of ten cubits from brim to brim, round in compass, and the height thereof was five cubits; and a line of thirty cubits compassed it round about. ^24And under the brim of it round about there were knops which did compass it, for ten cubits, compassing the sea round about: the knops were in two rows, cast when it was cast. ^25It stood upon twelve oxen, three looking toward the north, and three looking toward the west, and three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east; and the sea was set upon them above, and all their hinder parts were inward. ^26And it was a handbreadth thick: and the brim thereof was wrought like the brim of a cup, like the flower of a lily: it held two thousand baths.

^27And he made the ten bases of brass; four cubits was the length of one base, and four cubits the breadth thereof, and three cubits the height of it. ^28And the work of the bases was on this manner: they had panels; and there were panels between the ledges; ^29and on the panels that were between the ledges were lions, oxen, and cherubim; and upon the ledges there was a pedestal above; and beneath the lions and oxen were wreaths of hanging work. ^30And every base had four brazen wheels, and axles of brass; and the four feet thereof had undersetters: beneath the laver were the undersetters molten, with wreaths at the side of each. ^31And the mouth of it within the capital and above was a cubit: and the mouth thereof was round after the work of a pedestal, a cubit and a half; and also upon the mouth of it were gravings, and their panels were foursquare, not round. ^32And the four wheels were underneath the panels; and the axletrees of the wheels were in the base: and the height of a wheel was a cubit and half a cubit. ^33And the work of the wheels was like the work of a chariot wheel: their axletrees, and their felloes, and their spokes, and their naves, were all molten. ^34And there were four undersetters at the four corners of each base: the undersetters thereof were of the base itself. ^35And in the top of the base was there a round compass half a cubit high; and on the top of the base the stays thereof and the panels thereof were of the same. ^36And on the plates of the stays thereof, and on the panels thereof, he graved cherubim, lions, and palm-trees, according to the space of each, with wreaths round about. ^37After this manner he made the ten bases: all of them had one casting, one measure, and one form.

^38And he made ten lavers of brass: one laver contained forty baths; and every laver was four cubits; and upon very one of the ten bases one laver. ^39And he set the bases, five on the right side of the house, and five on the left side of the house: and he set the sea on the right side of the house eastward, toward the south.

^40And Hiram made the lavers, and the shovels, and the basins. So Hiram made an end of doing all the work that he wrought for king Solomon in the house of Jehovah: ^41the two pillars, and the two bowls of the capitals that were on the top of the pillars; and the two networks to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the top of the pillars; ^42and the four hundred pomegranates for the two networks; two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were upon the pillars; ^43and the ten bases, and the ten lavers on the bases; ^44and the one sea, and the twelve oxen under the sea; ^45and the pots, and the shovels, and the basins: even all these vessels, which Hiram made for king Solomon, in the house of Jehovah, were of burnished brass. ^46In the plain of the Jordan did the king cast them, in the clay ground between Succoth and Zarethan. ^47And Solomon left all the vessels unweighed, because they were exceeding many: the weight of the brass could not be found out.

^48And Solomon made all the vessels that were in the house of Jehovah: the golden altar, and the table whereupon the showbread was, of gold; ^49and the candlesticks, five on the right side, and five on the left, before the oracle, of pure gold; and the flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs, of gold; ^50and the cups, and the snuffers, and the basins, and the spoons, and the firepans, of pure gold; and the hinges, both for the doors of the inner house, the most holy place, and for the doors of the house, to wit, of the temple, of gold.

^51Thus all the work that king Solomon wrought in the house of Jehovah was finished. And Solomon brought in the things which David his father had dedicated, even the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, and put them in the treasuries of the house of Jehovah.

1 Kings 8

8

^1Then Solomon assembled the elders of Israel, and all the heads of the tribes, the princes of the fathers' houses of the children of Israel, unto king Solomon in Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the covenant of Jehovah out of the city of David, which is Zion. ^2And all the men of Israel assembled themselves unto king Solomon at the feast, in the month Ethanim, which is the seventh month. ^3And all the elders of Israel came, and the priests took up the ark. ^4And they brought up the ark of Jehovah, and the tent of meeting, and all the holy vessels that were in the Tent; even these did the priests and the Levites bring up. ^5And king Solomon and all the congregation of Israel, that were assembled unto him, were with him before the ark, sacrificing sheep and oxen, that could not be counted nor numbered for multitude. ^6And the priests brought in the ark of the covenant of Jehovah unto its place, into the oracle of the house, to the most holy place, even under the wings of the cherubim. ^7For the cherubim spread forth their wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubim covered the ark and the staves thereof above. ^8And the staves were so long that the ends of the staves were seen from the holy place before the oracle; but they were not seen without: and there they are unto this day. ^9There was nothing in the ark save the two tables of stone which Moses put there at Horeb, when Jehovah made a covenant with the children of Israel, when they came out of the land of Egypt. ^10And it came to pass, when the priests were come out of the holy place, that the cloud filled the house of Jehovah, ^11so that the priests could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud; for the glory of Jehovah filled the house of Jehovah.

^12Then spake Solomon, Jehovah hath said that he would dwell in the thick darkness. ^13I have surely built thee a house of habitation, a place for thee to dwell in for ever. ^14And the king turned his face about, and blessed all the assembly of Israel: and all the assembly of Israel stood. ^15And he said, Blessed be Jehovah, the God of Israel, who spake with his mouth unto David thy father, and hath with his hand fulfilled it, saying, ^16Since the day that I brought forth my people Israel out of Egypt, I chose no city out of all the tribes of Israel to build a house, that my name might be there; but I chose David to be over my people Israel. ^17Now it was in the heart of David my father to build a house for the name of Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^18But Jehovah said unto David my father, Whereas it was in thy heart to build a house for my name, thou didst well that it was in thy heart: ^19nevertheless thou shalt not build the house; but thy son that shall come forth out of thy loins, he shall build the house for my name. ^20And Jehovah hath established his word that he spake; for I am risen up in the room of David my father, and sit on the throne of Israel, as Jehovah promised, and have built the house for the name of Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^21And there have I set a place for the ark, wherein is the covenant of Jehovah, which he made with our fathers, when he brought them out of the land of Egypt.

^22And Solomon stood before the altar of Jehovah in the presence of all the assembly of Israel, and spread forth his hands toward heaven; ^23and he said, O Jehovah, the God of Israel, there is no God like thee, in heaven above, or on earth beneath; who keepest covenant and lovingkindness with thy servants, that walk before thee with all their heart; ^24who hast kept with thy servant David my father that which thou didst promise him: yea, thou spakest with thy mouth, and hast fulfilled it with thy hand, as it is this day. ^25Now therefore, O Jehovah, the God of Israel, keep with thy servant David my father that which thou hast promised him, saying, There shall not fail thee a man in my sight to sit on the throne of Israel, if only thy children take heed to their way, to walk before me as thou hast walked before me. ^26Now therefore, O God of Israel, let thy word, I pray thee, be verified, which thou spakest unto thy servant David my father.

^27But will God in very deed dwell on the earth? behold, heaven and the heaven of heavens cannot contain thee; how much less this house that I have builded! ^28Yet have thou respect unto the prayer of thy servant, and to his supplication, O Jehovah my God, to hearken unto the cry and to the prayer which thy servant prayeth before thee this day; ^29that thine eyes may be open toward this house night and day, even toward the place whereof thou hast said, My name shall be there; to hearken unto the prayer which thy servant shall pray toward this place. ^30And hearken thou to the supplication of thy servant, and of thy people Israel, when they shall pray toward this place: yea, hear thou in heaven thy dwelling-place; and when thou hearest, forgive.

^31If a man sin against his neighbor, and an oath be laid upon him to cause him to swear, and he come and swear before thine altar in this house; ^32then hear thou in heaven, and do, and judge thy servants, condemning the wicked, to bring his way upon his own head, and justifying the righteous, to give him according to his righteousness.

^33When thy people Israel are smitten down before the enemy, because they have sinned against thee; if they turn again to thee, and confess thy name, and pray and make supplication unto thee in this house: ^34then hear thou in heaven, and forgive the sin of thy people Israel, and bring them again unto the land which thou gavest unto their fathers.

^35When heaven is shut up, and there is no rain, because they have sinned against thee; if they pray toward this place, and confess thy name, and turn from their sin, when thou dost afflict them: ^36then hear thou in heaven, and forgive the sin of thy servants, and of thy people Israel, when thou teachest them the good way wherein they should walk; and send rain upon thy land, which thou hast given to thy people for an inheritance.

^37If there be in the land famine, if there be pestilence, if there be blasting or mildew, locust or caterpillar; if their enemy besiege them in the land of their cities; whatsoever plague, whatsoever sickness there be; ^38what prayer and supplication soever be made by any man, or by all thy people Israel, who shall know every man the plague of his own heart, and spread forth his hands toward this house: ^39then hear thou in heaven thy dwelling-place, and forgive, and do, and render unto every man according to all his ways, whose heart thou knowest; (for thou, even thou only, knowest the hearts of all the children of men;) ^40that they may fear thee all the days that they live in the land which thou gavest unto our fathers.

^41Moreover concerning the foreigner, that is not of thy people Israel, when he shall come out of a far country for thy name's sake ^42(for they shall hear of thy great name, and of thy mighty hand, and of thine outstretched arm); when he shall come and pray toward this house; ^43hear thou in heaven thy dwelling-place, and do according to all that the foreigner calleth to thee for; that all the peoples of the earth may know thy name, to fear thee, as doth thy people Israel, and that they may know that this house which I have built is called by my name.

^44If thy people go out to battle against their enemy, by whatsoever way thou shalt send them, and they pray unto Jehovah toward the city which thou hast chosen, and toward the house which I have built for thy name; ^45then hear thou in heaven their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause.

^46If they sin against thee (for there is no man that sinneth not), and thou be angry with them, and deliver them to the enemy, so that they carry them away captive unto the land of the enemy, far off or near; ^47yet if they shall bethink themselves in the land whither they are carried captive, and turn again, and make supplication unto thee in the land of them that carried them captive, saying, We have sinned, and have done perversely, we have dealt wickedly; ^48if they return unto thee with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their enemies, who carried them captive, and pray unto thee toward their land, which thou gavest unto their fathers, the city which thou hast chosen, and the house which I have built for thy name: ^49then hear thou their prayer and their supplication in heaven thy dwelling-place, and maintain their cause; ^50and forgive thy people who have sinned against thee, and all their transgressions wherein they have transgressed against thee; and give them compassion before those who carried them captive, that they may have compassion on them ^51(for they are thy people, and thine inheritance, which thou broughtest forth out of Egypt, from the midst of the furnace of iron); ^52that thine eyes may be open unto the supplication of thy servant, and unto the supplication of thy people Israel, to hearken unto them whensoever they cry unto thee. ^53For thou didst separate them from among all the peoples of the earth, to be thine inheritance, as thou spakest by Moses thy servant, when thou broughtest our fathers out of Egypt, O Lord Jehovah.

^54And it was so, that, when Solomon had made an end of praying all this prayer and supplication unto Jehovah, he arose from before the altar of Jehovah, from kneeling on his knees with his hands spread forth toward heaven. ^55And he stood, and blessed all the assembly of Israel with a loud voice, saying, ^56Blessed be Jehovah, that hath given rest unto his people Israel, according to all that he promised: there hath not failed one word of all his good promise, which he promised by Moses his servant. ^57Jehovah our God be with us, as he was with our fathers: let him not leave us, nor forsake us; ^58that he may incline our hearts unto him, to walk in all his ways, and to keep his commandments, and his statutes, and his ordinances, which he commanded our fathers. ^59And let these my words, wherewith I have made supplication before Jehovah, be nigh unto Jehovah our God day and night, that he maintain the cause of his servant, and the cause of his people Israel, as every day shall require; ^60that all the peoples of the earth may know that Jehovah, he is God; there is none else. ^61Let your heart therefore be perfect with Jehovah our God, to walk in his statutes, and to keep his commandments, as at this day.

^62And the king, and all Israel with him, offered sacrifice before Jehovah. ^63And Solomon offered for the sacrifice of peace-offerings, which he offered unto Jehovah, two and twenty thousand oxen, and a hundred and twenty thousand sheep. So the king and all the children of Israel dedicated the house of Jehovah. ^64The same day did the king hallow the middle of the court that was before the house of Jehovah; for there he offered the burnt-offering, and the meal-offering, and the fat of the peace-offerings, because the brazen altar that was before Jehovah was too little to receive the burnt-offering, and the meal-offering, and the fat of the peace-offerings. ^65So Solomon held the feast at that time, and all Israel with him, a great assembly, from the entrance of Hamath unto the brook of Egypt, before Jehovah our God, seven days and seven days, even fourteen days. ^66On the eighth day he sent the people away; and they blessed the king, and went unto their tents joyful and glad of heart for all the goodness that Jehovah had showed unto David his servant, and to Israel his people.

1 Kings 9

9

^1And it came to pass, when Solomon had finished the building of the house of Jehovah, and the king's house, and all Solomon's desire which he was pleased to do, ^2that Jehovah appeared to Solomon the second time, as he had appeared unto him at Gibeon. ^3And Jehovah said unto him, I have heard thy prayer and thy supplication, that thou hast made before me: I have hallowed this house, which thou hast built, to put my name there for ever; and mine eyes and my heart shall be there perpetually. ^4And as for thee, if thou wilt walk before me, as David thy father walked, in integrity of heart, and in uprightness, to do according to all that I have commanded thee, and wilt keep my statutes and mine ordinances; ^5then I will establish the throne of thy kingdom over Israel for ever, according as I promised to David thy father, saying, There shall not fail thee a man upon the throne of Israel. ^6But if ye shall turn away from following me, ye or your children, and not keep my commandments and my statutes which I have set before you, but shall go and serve other gods, and worship them; ^7then will I cut off Israel out of the land which I have given them; and this house, which I have hallowed for my name, will I cast out of my sight; and Israel shall be a proverb and a byword among all peoples. ^8And though this house is so high, yet shall every one that passeth by it be astonished, and shall hiss; and they shall say, Why hath Jehovah done thus unto this land, and to this house? ^9and they shall answer, Because they forsook Jehovah their God, who brought forth their fathers out of the land of Egypt, and laid hold on other gods, and worshipped them, and served them: therefore hath Jehovah brought all this evil upon them.

^10And it came to pass at the end of twenty years, wherein Solomon had built the two houses, the house of Jehovah and the king's house ^11(now Hiram the king of Tyre had furnished Solomon with cedar-trees and fir-trees, and with gold, according to all his desire), that then king Solomon gave Hiram twenty cities in the land of Galilee. ^12And Hiram came out from Tyre to see the cities which Solomon had given him; and they pleased him not. ^13And he said, What cities are these which thou hast given me, my brother? And he called them the land of Cabul unto this day. ^14And Hiram sent to the king sixscore talents of gold.

^15And this is the reason of the levy which king Solomon raised, to build the house of Jehovah, and his own house, and Millo, and the wall of Jerusalem, and Hazor, and Megiddo, and Gezer. ^16Pharaoh king of Egypt had gone up, and taken Gezer, and burnt it with fire, and slain the Canaanites that dwelt in the city, and given it for a portion unto his daughter, Solomon's wife. ^17And Solomon built Gezer, and Beth-horon the nether, ^18and Baalath, and Tamar in the wilderness, in the land, ^19and all the store-cities that Solomon had, and the cities for his chariots, and the cities for his horsemen, and that which Solomon desired to build for his pleasure in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion. ^20As for all the people that were left of the Amorites, the Hittites, the Perizzites, the Hivites, and the Jebusites, who were not of the children of Israel; ^21their children that were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel were not able utterly to destroy, of them did Solomon raise a levy of bondservants unto this day. ^22But of the children of Israel did Solomon make no bondservants; but they were the men of war, and his servants, and his princes, and his captains, and rulers of his chariots and of his horsemen.

^23These were the chief officers that were over Solomon's work, five hundred and fifty, who bare rule over the people that wrought in the work.

^24But Pharaoh's daughter came up out of the city of David unto her house which Solomon had built for her: then did he build Millo.

^25And three times a year did Solomon offer burnt-offerings and peace-offerings upon the altar which he built unto Jehovah, burning incense therewith, upon the altar that was before Jehovah. So he finished the house.

^26And king Solomon made a navy of ships in Ezion-geber, which is beside Eloth, on the shore of the Red Sea, in the land of Edom. ^27And Hiram sent in the navy his servants, shipmen that had knowledge of the sea, with the servants of Solomon. ^28And they came to Ophir, and fetched from thence gold, four hundred and twenty talents, and brought it to king Solomon.

1 Kings 10

10

^1And when the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon concerning the name of Jehovah, she came to prove him with hard questions. ^2And she came to Jerusalem with a very great train, with camels that bare spices, and very much gold, and precious stones; and when she was come to Solomon, she communed with him of all that was in her heart. ^3And Solomon told her all her questions: there was not anything hid from the king which he told her not. ^4And when the queen of Sheba had seen all the wisdom of Solomon, and the house that he had built, ^5and the food of his table, and the sitting of his servants, and the attendance of his ministers, and their apparel, and his cupbearers, and his ascent by which he went up unto the house of Jehovah; there was no more spirit in her. ^6And she said to the king, It was a true report that I heard in mine own land of thine acts, and of thy wisdom. ^7Howbeit I believed not the words, until I came, and mine eyes had seen it: and, behold, the half was not told me; thy wisdom and prosperity exceed the fame which I heard. ^8Happy are thy men, happy are these thy servants, that stand continually before thee, and that hear thy wisdom. ^9Blessed be Jehovah thy God, who delighted in thee, to set thee on the throne of Israel: because Jehovah loved Israel for ever, therefore made he thee king, to do justice and righteousness. ^10And she gave the king a hundred and twenty talents of gold, and of spices very great store, and precious stones: there came no more such abundance of spices as these which the queen of Sheba gave to king Solomon.

^11And the navy also of Hiram, that brought gold from Ophir, brought in from Ophir great plenty of almug-trees and precious stones. ^12And the king made of the almug-trees pillars for the house of Jehovah, and for the king's house, harps also and psalteries for the singers: there came no such almug-trees, nor were seen, unto this day.

^13And king Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all her desire, whatsoever she asked, besides that which Solomon gave her of his royal bounty. So she turned, and went to her own land, she and her servants.

^14Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was six hundred threescore and six talents of gold, ^15besides that which the traders brought, and the traffic of the merchants, and of all the kings of the mingled people, and of the governors of the country. ^16And king Solomon made two hundred bucklers of beaten gold; six hundred shekels of gold went to one buckler. ^17And he made three hundred shields of beaten gold; three pounds of gold went to one shield: and the king put them in the house of the forest of Lebanon. ^18Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with the finest gold. ^19There were six steps to the throne, and the top of the throne was round behind; and there were stays on either side by the place of the seat, and two lions standing beside the stays. ^20And twelve lions stood there on the one side and on the other upon the six steps: there was not the like made in any kingdom. ^21And all king Solomon's drinking vessels were of gold, and all the vessels of the house of the forest of Lebanon were of pure gold: none were of silver; it was nothing accounted of in the days of Solomon. ^22For the king had at sea a navy of Tarshish with the navy of Hiram: once every three years came the navy of Tarshish, bringing gold, and silver, ivory, and apes, and peacocks.

^23So king Solomon exceeded all the kings of the earth in riches and in wisdom. ^24And all the earth sought the presence of Solomon, to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart. ^25And they brought every man his tribute, vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and raiment, and armor, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate year by year.

^26And Solomon gathered together chariots and horsemen: and he had a thousand and four hundred chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, that he bestowed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem. ^27And the king made silver to be in Jerusalem as stones, and cedars made he to be as the sycomore-trees that are in the lowland, for abundance. ^28And the horses which Solomon had were brought out of Egypt; and the king's merchants received them in droves, each drove at a price. ^29And a chariot came up and went out of Egypt for six hundred shekels of silver, and a horse for a hundred and fifty; and so for all the kings of the Hittites, and for the kings of Syria, did they bring them out by their means.

1 Kings 11

11

^1Now king Solomon loved many foreign women, together with the daughter of Pharaoh, women of the Moabites, Ammonites, Edomites, Sidonians, and Hittites; ^2of the nations concerning which Jehovah said unto the children of Israel, Ye shall not go among them, neither shall they come among you; for surely they will turn away your heart after their gods: Solomon clave unto these in love. ^3And he had seven hundred wives, princesses, and three hundred concubines; and his wives turned away his heart. ^4For it came to pass, when Solomon was old, that his wives turned away his heart after other gods; and his heart was not perfect with Jehovah his God, as was the heart of David his father. ^5For Solomon went after Ashtoreth the goddess of the Sidonians, and after Milcom the abomination of the Ammonites. ^6And Solomon did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and went not fully after Jehovah, as did David his father. ^7Then did Solomon build a high place for Chemosh the abomination of Moab, in the mount that is before Jerusalem, and for Molech the abomination of the children of Ammon. ^8And so did he for all his foreign wives, who burnt incense and sacrificed unto their gods.

^9And Jehovah was angry with Solomon, because his heart was turned away from Jehovah, the God of Israel, who had appeared unto him twice, ^10and had commanded him concerning this thing, that he should not go after other gods: but he kept not that which Jehovah commanded. ^11Wherefore Jehovah said unto Solomon, Forasmuch as this is done of thee, and thou hast not kept my covenant and my statutes, which I have commanded thee, I will surely rend the kingdom from thee, and will give it to thy servant. ^12Notwithstanding in thy days I will not do it, for David thy father's sake: but I will rend it out of the hand of thy son. ^13Howbeit I will not rend away all the kingdom; but I will give one tribe to thy son, for David my servant's sake, and for Jerusalem's sake which I have chosen.

^14And Jehovah raised up an adversary unto Solomon, Hadad the Edomite: he was of the king's seed in Edom. ^15For it came to pass, when David was in Edom, and Joab the captain of the host was gone up to bury the slain, and had smitten every male in Edom ^16(for Joab and all Israel remained there six months, until he had cut off every male in Edom); ^17that Hadad fled, he and certain Edomites of his father's servants with him, to go into Egypt, Hadad being yet a little child. ^18And they arose out of Midian, and came to Paran; and they took men with them out of Paran, and they came to Egypt, unto Pharaoh king of Egypt, who gave him a house, and appointed him victuals, and gave him land. ^19And Hadad found great favor in the sight of Pharaoh, so that he gave him to wife the sister of his own wife, the sister of Tahpenes the queen. ^20And the sister of Tahpenes bare him Genubath his son, whom Tahpenes weaned in Pharaoh's house; and Genubath was in Pharaoh's house among the sons of Pharaoh. ^21And when Hadad heard in Egypt that David slept with his fathers, and that Joab the captain of the host was dead, Hadad said to Pharaoh, Let me depart, that I may go to mine own country. ^22Then Pharaoh said unto him, But what hast thou lacked with me, that, behold, thou seekest to go to thine own country? And he answered, Nothing: howbeit only let me depart.

^23And God raised up another adversary unto him, Rezon the son of Eliada, who had fled from his lord Hadadezer king of Zobah. ^24And he gathered men unto him, and became captain over a troop, when David slew them of Zobah: and they went to Damascus, and dwelt therein, and reigned in Damascus. ^25And he was an adversary to Israel all the days of Solomon, besides the mischief that Hadad did: and he abhorred Israel, and reigned over Syria.

^26And Jeroboam the son of Nebat, an Ephraimite of Zeredah, a servant of Solomon, whose mother's name was Zeruah, a widow, he also lifted up his hand against the king. ^27And this was the reason why he lifted up his hand against the king: Solomon built Millo, and repaired the breach of the city of David his father. ^28And the man Jeroboam was a mighty man of valor; and Solomon saw the young man that he was industrious, and he gave him charge over all the labor of the house of Joseph. ^29And it came to pass at that time, when Jeroboam went out of Jerusalem, that the prophet Ahijah the Shilonite found him in the way; now Ahijah had clad himself with a new garment; and they two were alone in the field. ^30And Ahijah laid hold of the new garment that was on him, and rent it in twelve pieces. ^31And he said to Jeroboam, Take thee ten pieces; for thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Behold, I will rend the kingdom out of the hand of Solomon, and will give ten tribes to thee ^32(but he shall have one tribe, for my servant David's sake and for Jerusalem's sake, the city which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel); ^33because that they have forsaken me, and have worshipped Ashtoreth the goddess of the Sidonians, Chemosh the god of Moab, and Milcom the god of the children of Ammon; and they have not walked in my ways, to do that which is right in mine eyes, and to keep my statutes and mine ordinances, as did David his father. ^34Howbeit I will not take the whole kingdom out of his hand; but I will make him prince all the days of his life, for David my servant's sake whom I chose, who kept my commandments and my statutes; ^35but I will take the kingdom out of his son's hand, and will give it unto thee, even ten tribes. ^36And unto his son will I give one tribe, that David my servant may have a lamp alway before me in Jerusalem, the city which I have chosen me to put my name there. ^37And I will take thee, and thou shalt reign according to all that thy soul desireth, and shalt be king over Israel. ^38And it shall be, if thou wilt hearken unto all that I command thee, and wilt walk in my ways, and do that which is right in mine eyes, to keep my statutes and my commandments, as David my servant did; that I will be with thee, and will build thee a sure house, as I built for David, and will give Israel unto thee. ^39And I will for this afflict the seed of David, but not for ever. ^40Solomon sought therefore to kill Jeroboam; but Jeroboam arose, and fled into Egypt, unto Shishak king of Egypt, and was in Egypt until the death of Solomon.

^41Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, and all that he did, and his wisdom, are they not written in the book of the acts of Solomon? ^42And the time that Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel was forty years. ^43And Solomon slept with his fathers, and was buried in the city of David his father: and Rehoboam his son reigned in his stead.

1 Kings 12

12

^1And Rehoboam went to Shechem: for all Israel were come to Shechem to make him king. ^2And it came to pass, when Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard of it (for he was yet in Egypt, whither he had fled from the presence of king Solomon, and Jeroboam dwelt in Egypt, ^3and they sent and called him), that Jeroboam and all the assembly of Israel came, and spake unto Rehoboam, saying, ^4Thy father made our yoke grievous: now therefore make thou the grievous service of thy father, and his heavy yoke which he put upon us, lighter, and we will serve thee. ^5And he said unto them, Depart yet for three days, then come again to me. And the people departed.

^6And king Rehoboam took counsel with the old men, that had stood before Solomon his father while he yet lived, saying, What counsel give ye me to return answer to this people? ^7And they spake unto him, saying, If thou wilt be a servant unto this people this day, and wilt serve them, and answer them, and speak good words to them, then they will be thy servants for ever. ^8But he forsook the counsel of the old men which they had given him, and took counsel with the young men that were grown up with him, that stood before him. ^9And he said unto them, What counsel give ye, that we may return answer to this people, who have spoken to me, saying, Make the yoke that thy father did put upon us lighter? ^10And the young men that were grown up with him spake unto him, saying, Thus shalt thou say unto this people that spake unto thee, saying, Thy father made our yoke heavy, but make thou it lighter unto us; thus shalt thou speak unto them, My little finger is thicker than my father's loins. ^11And now whereas my father did lade you with a heavy yoke, I will add to your yoke: my father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions.

^12So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the king bade, saying, Come to me again the third day. ^13And the king answered the people roughly, and forsook the counsel of the old men which they had given him, ^14and spake to them after the counsel of the young men, saying, My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add to your yoke: my father chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions. ^15So the king hearkened not unto the people; for it was a thing brought about of Jehovah, that he might establish his word, which Jehovah spake by Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat.

^16And when all Israel saw that the king hearkened not unto them, the people answered the king, saying, What portion have we in David? neither have we inheritance in the son of Jesse: to your tents, O Israel: now see to thine own house, David. So Israel departed unto their tents. ^17But as for the children of Israel that dwelt in the cities of Judah, Rehoboam reigned over them. ^18Then king Rehoboam sent Adoram, who was over the men subject to taskwork; and all Israel stoned him to death with stones. And king Rehoboam made speed to get him up to his chariot, to flee to Jerusalem. ^19So Israel rebelled against the house of David unto this day. ^20And it came to pass, when all Israel heard that Jeroboam was returned, that they sent and called him unto the congregation, and made him king over all Israel: there was none that followed the house of David, but the tribe of Judah only.

^21And when Rehoboam was come to Jerusalem, he assembled all the house of Judah, and the tribe of Benjamin, a hundred and fourscore thousand chosen men, that were warriors, to fight against the house of Israel, to bring the kingdom again to Rehoboam the son of Solomon. ^22But the word of God came unto Shemaiah the man of God, saying, ^23Speak unto Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and unto all the house of Judah and Benjamin, and to the rest of the people, saying, ^24Thus saith Jehovah, Ye shall not go up, nor fight against your brethren the children of Israel: return every man to his house; for this thing is of me. So they hearkened unto the word of Jehovah, and returned and went their way, according to the word of Jehovah.

^25Then Jeroboam built Shechem in the hill-country of Ephraim, and dwelt therein; and he went out from thence, and built Penuel. ^26And Jeroboam said in his heart, Now will the kingdom return to the house of David: ^27if this people go up to offer sacrifices in the house of Jehovah at Jerusalem, then will the heart of this people turn again unto their lord, even unto Rehoboam king of Judah; and they will kill me, and return to Rehoboam king of Judah. ^28Whereupon the king took counsel, and made two calves of gold; and he said unto them, It is too much for you to go up to Jerusalem: behold thy gods, O Israel, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. ^29And he set the one in Beth-el, and the other put he in Dan. ^30And this thing became a sin; for the people went to worship before the one, even unto Dan. ^31And he made houses of high places, and made priests from among all the people, that were not of the sons of Levi. ^32And Jeroboam ordained a feast in the eighth month, on the fifteenth day of the month, like unto the feast that is in Judah, and he went up unto the altar; so did he in Beth-el, sacrificing unto the calves that he had made: and he placed in Beth-el the priests of the high places that he had made. ^33And he went up unto the altar which he had made in Beth-el on the fifteenth day in the eighth month, even in the month which he had devised of his own heart: and he ordained a feast for the children of Israel, and went up unto the altar, to burn incense.

1 Kings 13

13

^1And, behold, there came a man of God out of Judah by the word of Jehovah unto Beth-el: and Jeroboam was standing by the altar to burn incense. ^2And he cried against the altar by the word of Jehovah, and said, O altar, altar, thus saith Jehovah: Behold, a son shall be born unto the house of David, Josiah by name; and upon thee shall he sacrifice the priests of the high places that burn incense upon thee, and men's bones shall they burn upon thee. ^3And he gave a sign the same day, saying, This is the sign which Jehovah hath spoken: Behold, the altar shall be rent, and the ashes that are upon it shall be poured out. ^4And it came to pass, when the king heard the saying of the man of God, which he cried against the altar in Beth-el, that Jeroboam put forth his hand from the altar, saying, Lay hold on him. And his hand, which he put forth against him, dried up, so that he could not draw it back again to him. ^5The altar also was rent, and the ashes poured out from the altar, according to the sign which the man of God had given by the word of Jehovah. ^6And the king answered and said unto the man of God, Entreat now the favor of Jehovah thy God, and pray for me, that my hand may be restored me again. And the man of God entreated Jehovah, and the king's hand was restored him again, and became as it was before. ^7And the king said unto the man of God, Come home with me, and refresh thyself, and I will give thee a reward. ^8And the man of God said unto the king, If thou wilt give me half thy house, I will not go in with thee, neither will I eat bread nor drink water in this place; ^9for so was it charged me by the word of Jehovah, saying, Thou shalt eat no bread, nor drink water, neither return by the way that thou camest. ^10So he went another way, and returned not by the way that he came to Beth-el.

^11Now there dwelt an old prophet in Beth-el; and one of his sons came and told him all the works that the man of God had done that day in Beth-el: the words which he had spoken unto the king, them also they told unto their father. ^12And their father said unto them, What way went he? Now his sons had seen what way the man of God went, that came from Judah. ^13And he said unto his sons, Saddle me the ass. So they saddled him the ass; and he rode thereon. ^14And he went after the man of God, and found him sitting under an oak; and he said unto him, Art thou the man of God that camest from Judah? And he said, I am. ^15Then he said unto him, Come home with me, and eat bread. ^16And he said, I may not return with thee, nor go in with thee; neither will I eat bread nor drink water with thee in this place: ^17for it was said to me by the word of Jehovah, Thou shalt eat no bread nor drink water there, nor turn again to go by the way that thou camest. ^18And he said unto him, I also am a prophet as thou art; and an angel spake unto me by the word of Jehovah, saying, Bring him back with thee into thy house, that he may eat bread and drink water. But he lied unto him. ^19So he went back with him, and did eat bread in his house, and drank water.

^20And it came to pass, as they sat at the table, that the word of Jehovah came unto the prophet that brought him back; ^21and he cried unto the man of God that came from Judah, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, Forasmuch as thou hast been disobedient unto the mouth of Jehovah, and hast not kept the commandment which Jehovah thy God commanded thee, ^22but camest back, and hast eaten bread and drunk water in the place of which he said to thee, Eat no bread, and drink no water; thy body shall not come unto the sepulchre of thy fathers. ^23And it came to pass, after he had eaten bread, and after he had drunk, that he saddled for him the ass, to wit, for the prophet whom he had brought back. ^24And when he was gone, a lion met him by the way, and slew him: and his body was cast in the way, and the ass stood by it; the lion also stood by the body. ^25And, behold, men passed by, and saw the body cast in the way, and the lion standing by the body; and they came and told it in the city where the old prophet dwelt.

^26And when the prophet that brought him back from the way heard thereof, he said, It is the man of God, who was disobedient unto the mouth of Jehovah: therefore Jehovah hath delivered him unto the lion, which hath torn him, and slain him, according to the word of Jehovah, which he spake unto him. ^27And he spake to his sons, saying, Saddle me the ass. And they saddled it. ^28And he went and found his body cast in the way, and the ass and the lion standing by the body: the lion had not eaten the body, nor torn the ass. ^29And the prophet took up the body of the man of God, and laid it upon the ass, and brought it back; and he came to the city of the old prophet, to mourn, and to bury him. ^30And he laid his body in his own grave; and they mourned over him, saying, Alas, my brother! ^31And it came to pass, after he had buried him, that he spake to his sons, saying, When I am dead, then bury me in the sepulchre wherein the man of God is buried; lay my bones beside his bones. ^32For the saying which he cried by the word of Jehovah against the altar in Beth-el, and against all the houses of the high places which are in the cities of Samaria, shall surely come to pass.

^33After this thing Jeroboam returned not from his evil way, but made again from among all the people priests of the high places: whosoever would, he consecrated him, that there might be priests of the high places. ^34And this thing became sin unto the house of Jeroboam, even to cut it off, and to destroy it from off the face of the earth.

1 Kings 14

14

^1At that time Abijah the son of Jeroboam fell sick. ^2And Jeroboam said to his wife, Arise, I pray thee, and disguise thyself, that thou be not known to be the wife of Jeroboam; and get thee to Shiloh: behold, there is Ahijah the prophet, who spake concerning me that I should be king over this people. ^3And take with thee ten loaves, and cakes, and a cruse of honey, and go to him: he will tell thee what shall become of the child. ^4And Jeroboam's wife did so, and arose, and went to Shiloh, and came to the house of Ahijah. Now Ahijah could not see; for his eyes were set by reason of his age. ^5And Jehovah said unto Ahijah, Behold, the wife of Jeroboam cometh to inquire of thee concerning her son; for he is sick: thus and thus shalt thou say unto her; for it will be, when she cometh in, that she will feign herself to be another woman.

^6And it was so, when Ahijah heard the sound of her feet, as she came in at the door, that he said, Come in, thou wife of Jeroboam; why feignest thou thyself to be another? for I am sent to thee with heavy tidings. ^7Go, tell Jeroboam, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel: Forasmuch as I exalted thee from among the people, and made thee prince over my people Israel, ^8and rent the kingdom away from the house of David, and gave it thee; and yet thou hast not been as my servant David, who kept my commandments, and who followed me with all his heart, to do that only which was right in mine eyes, ^9but hast done evil above all that were before thee, and hast gone and made thee other gods, and molten images, to provoke me to anger, and hast cast me behind thy back: ^10therefore, behold, I will bring evil upon the house of Jeroboam, and will cut off from Jeroboam every man-child, him that is shut up and him that is left at large in Israel, and will utterly sweep away the house of Jeroboam, as a man sweepeth away dung, till it be all gone. ^11Him that dieth of Jeroboam in the city shall the dogs eat; and him that dieth in the field shall the birds of the heavens eat: for Jehovah hath spoken it. ^12Arise thou therefore, get thee to thy house: and when thy feet enter into the city, the child shall die. ^13And all Israel shall mourn for him, and bury him; for he only of Jeroboam shall come to the grave, because in him there is found some good thing toward Jehovah, the God of Israel, in the house of Jeroboam. ^14Moreover Jehovah will raise him up a king over Israel, who shall cut off the house of Jeroboam that day: but what? even now. ^15For Jehovah will smite Israel, as a reed is shaken in the water; and he will root up Israel out of this good land which he gave to their fathers, and will scatter them beyond the River, because they have made their Asherim, provoking Jehovah to anger. ^16And he will give Israel up because of the sins of Jeroboam, which he hath sinned, and wherewith he hath made Israel to sin.

^17And Jeroboam's wife arose, and departed, and came to Tirzah: and as she came to the threshold of the house, the child died. ^18And all Israel buried him, and mourned for him, according to the word of Jehovah, which he spake by his servant Ahijah the prophet.

^19And the rest of the acts of Jeroboam, how he warred, and how he reigned, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel. ^20And the days which Jeroboam reigned were two and twenty years: and he slept with his fathers, and Nadab his son reigned in his stead.

^21And Rehoboam the son of Solomon reigned in Judah. Rehoboam was forty and one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city which Jehovah had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, to put his name there: and his mother's name was Naamah the Ammonitess. ^22And Judah did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and they provoked him to jealousy with their sins which they committed, above all that their fathers had done. ^23For they also built them high places, and pillars, and Asherim, on every high hill, and under every green tree; ^24and there were also sodomites in the land: they did according to all the abominations of the nations which Jehovah drove out before the children of Israel.

^25And it came to pass in the fifth year of king Rehoboam, that Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem; ^26and he took away the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and the treasures of the king's house; he even took away all: and he took away all the shields of gold which Solomon had made. ^27And king Rehoboam made in their stead shields of brass, and committed them to the hands of the captains of the guard, who kept the door of the king's house. ^28And it was so, that, as oft as the king went into the house of Jehovah, the guard bare them, and brought them back into the guard-chamber.

^29Now the rest of the acts of Rehoboam, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^30And there was war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam continually. ^31And Rehoboam slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David: and his mother's name was Naamah the Ammonitess. And Abijam his son reigned in his stead.

1 Kings 15

15

^1Now in the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam the son of Nebat began Abijam to reign over Judah. ^2Three years reigned he in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Maacah the daughter of Abishalom. ^3And he walked in all the sins of his father, which he had done before him; and his heart was not perfect with Jehovah his God, as the heart of David his father. ^4Nevertheless for David's sake did Jehovah his God give him a lamp in Jerusalem, to set up his son after him, and to establish Jerusalem; ^5because David did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, and turned not aside from anything that he commanded him all the days of his life, save only in the matter of Uriah the Hittite. ^6Now there was war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam all the days of his life.

^7And the rest of the acts of Abijam, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? And there was war between Abijam and Jeroboam. ^8And Abijam slept with his fathers; and they buried him in the city of David: and Asa his son reigned in his stead.

^9And in the twentieth year of Jeroboam king of Israel began Asa to reign over Judah. ^10And forty and one years reigned he in Jerusalem: and his mother's name was Maacah the daughter of Abishalom. ^11And Asa did that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah, as did David his father. ^12And he put away the sodomites out of the land, and removed all the idols that his fathers had made. ^13And also Maacah his mother he removed from being queen, because she had made an abominable image for an Asherah; and Asa cut down her image, and burnt it at the brook Kidron. ^14But the high places were not taken away: nevertheless the heart of Asa was perfect with Jehovah all his days. ^15And he brought into the house of Jehovah the things that his father had dedicated, and the things that himself had dedicated, silver, and gold, and vessels.

^16And there was war between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days. ^17And Baasha king of Israel went up against Judah, and built Ramah, that he might not suffer any one to go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. ^18Then Asa took all the silver and the gold that were left in the treasures of the house of Jehovah, and the treasures of the king's house, and delivered them into the hand of his servants; and king Asa sent them to Ben-hadad, the son of Tabrimmon, the son of Hezion, king of Syria, that dwelt at Damascus, saying, ^19There is a league between me and thee, between my father and thy father: behold, I have sent unto thee a present of silver and gold; go, break thy league with Baasha king of Israel, that he may depart from me. ^20And Ben-hadad hearkened unto king Asa, and sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel, and smote Ijon, and Dan, and Abel-beth-maacah, and all Chinneroth, with all the land of Naphtali. ^21And it came to pass, when Baasha heard thereof, that he left off building Ramah, and dwelt in Tirzah. ^22Then king Asa made a proclamation unto all Judah; none was exempted: and they carried away the stones of Ramah, and the timber thereof, wherewith Baasha had builded; and king Asa built therewith Geba of Benjamin, and Mizpah.

^23Now the rest of all the acts of Asa, and all his might, and all that he did, and the cities which he built, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? But in the time of his old age he was diseased in his feet. ^24And Asa slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David his father; and Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his stead.

^25And Nadab the son of Jeroboam began to reign over Israel in the second year of Asa king of Judah; and he reigned over Israel two years. ^26And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and walked in the way of his father, and in his sin wherewith he made Israel to sin. ^27And Baasha the son of Ahijah, of the house of Issachar, conspired against him; and Baasha smote him at Gibbethon, which belonged to the Philistines; for Nadab and all Israel were laying siege to Gibbethon. ^28Even in the third year of Asa king of Judah did Baasha slay him, and reigned in his stead. ^29And it came to pass that, as soon as he was king, he smote all the house of Jeroboam: he left not to Jeroboam any that breathed, until he had destroyed him; according unto the saying of Jehovah, which he spake by his servant Ahijah the Shilonite; ^30for the sins of Jeroboam which he sinned, and wherewith he made Israel to sin, because of his provocation wherewith he provoked Jehovah, the God of Israel, to anger.

^31Now the rest of the acts of Nadab, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^32And there was war between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days.

^33In the third year of Asa king of Judah began Baasha the son of Ahijah to reign over all Israel in Tirzah, and reigned twenty and four years. ^34And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and walked in the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin wherewith he made Israel to sin.

1 Kings 16

16

^1And the word of Jehovah came to Jehu the son of Hanani against Baasha, saying, ^2Forasmuch as I exalted thee out of the dust, and made thee prince over my people Israel, and thou hast walked in the way of Jeroboam, and hast made my people Israel to sin, to provoke me to anger with their sins; ^3behold, I will utterly sweep away Baasha and his house; and I will make thy house like the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat. ^4Him that dieth of Baasha in the city shall the dogs eat; and him that dieth of his in the field shall the birds of the heavens eat.

^5Now the rest of the acts of Baasha, and what he did, and his might, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^6And Baasha slept with his fathers, and was buried in Tirzah; and Elah his son reigned in his stead. ^7And moreover by the prophet Jehu the son of Hanani came the word of Jehovah against Baasha, and against his house, both because of all the evil that he did in the sight of Jehovah, to provoke him to anger with the work of his hands, in being like the house of Jeroboam, and because he smote him.

^8In the twenty and sixth year of Asa king of Judah began Elah the son of Baasha to reign over Israel in Tirzah, and reigned two years. ^9And his servant Zimri, captain of half his chariots, conspired against him. Now he was in Tirzah, drinking himself drunk in the house of Arza, who was over the household in Tirzah: ^10and Zimri went in and smote him, and killed him, in the twenty and seventh year of Asa king of Judah, and reigned in his stead. ^11And it came to pass, when he began to reign, as soon as he sat on his throne, that he smote all the house of Baasha: he left him not a single man-child, neither of his kinsfolks, nor of his friends. ^12Thus did Zimri destroy all the house of Baasha, according to the word of Jehovah, which he spake against Baasha by Jehu the prophet, ^13for all the sins of Baasha, and the sins of Elah his son, which they sinned, and wherewith they made Israel to sin, to provoke Jehovah, the God of Israel, to anger with their vanities. ^14Now the rest of the acts of Elah, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?

^15In the twenty and seventh year of Asa king of Judah did Zimri reign seven days in Tirzah. Now the people were encamped against Gibbethon, which belonged to the Philistines. ^16And the people that were encamped heard say, Zimri hath conspired, and hath also smitten the king: wherefore all Israel made Omri, the captain of the host, king over Israel that day in the camp. ^17And Omri went up from Gibbethon, and all Israel with him, and they besieged Tirzah. ^18And it came to pass, when Zimri saw that the city was taken, that he went into the castle of the king's house, and burnt the king's house over him with fire, and died, ^19for his sins which he sinned in doing that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, in walking in the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin which he did, to make Israel to sin. ^20Now the rest of the acts of Zimri, and his treason that he wrought, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?

^21Then were the people of Israel divided into two parts: half of the people followed Tibni the son of Ginath, to make him king; and half followed Omri. ^22But the people that followed Omri prevailed against the people that followed Tibni the son of Ginath: so Tibni died, and Omri reigned. ^23In the thirty and first year of Asa king of Judah began Omri to reign over Israel, and reigned twelve years: six years reigned he in Tirzah. ^24And he bought the hill Samaria of Shemer for two talents of silver; and he built on the hill, and called the name of the city which he built, after the name of Shemer, the owner of the hill, Samaria. ^25And Omri did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and dealt wickedly above all that were before him. ^26For he walked in all the way of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and in his sins wherewith he made Israel to sin, to provoke Jehovah, the God of Israel, to anger with their vanities. ^27Now the rest of the acts of Omri which he did, and his might that he showed, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^28So Omri slept with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria; and Ahab his son reigned in his stead.

^29And in the thirty and eighth year of Asa king of Judah began Ahab the son of Omri to reign over Israel: and Ahab the son of Omri reigned over Israel in Samaria twenty and two years. ^30And Ahab the son of Omri did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah above all that were before him. ^31And it came to pass, as if it had been a light thing for him to walk in the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, that he took to wife Jezebel the daughter of Ethbaal king of the Sidonians, and went and served Baal, and worshipped him. ^32And he reared up an altar for Baal in the house of Baal, which he had built in Samaria. ^33And Ahab made the Asherah; and Ahab did yet more to provoke Jehovah, the God of Israel, to anger than all the kings of Israel that were before him. ^34In his days did Hiel the Beth-elite build Jericho: he laid the foundation thereof with the loss of Abiram his first-born, and set up the gates thereof with the loss of his youngest son Segub, according to the word of Jehovah, which he spake by Joshua the son of Nun.

1 Kings 17

17

^1And Elijah the Tishbite, who was of the sojourners of Gilead, said unto Ahab, As Jehovah, the God of Israel, liveth, before whom I stand, there shall not be dew nor rain these years, but according to my word. ^2And the word of Jehovah came unto him, saying, ^3Get thee hence, and turn thee eastward, and hide thyself by the brook Cherith, that is before the Jordan. ^4And it shall be, that thou shalt drink of the brook; and I have commanded the ravens to feed thee there. ^5So he went and did according unto the word of Jehovah; for he went and dwelt by the brook Cherith, that is before the Jordan. ^6And the ravens brought him bread and flesh in the morning, and bread and flesh in the evening; and he drank of the brook. ^7And it came to pass after a while, that the brook dried up, because there was no rain in the land.

^8And the word of Jehovah came unto him, saying, ^9Arise, get thee to Zarephath, which belongeth to Sidon, and dwell there: behold, I have commanded a widow there to sustain thee. ^10So he arose and went to Zarephath; and when he came to the gate of the city, behold, a widow was there gathering sticks: and he called to her, and said, Fetch me, I pray thee, a little water in a vessel, that I may drink. ^11And as she was going to fetch it, he called to her, and said, Bring me, I pray thee, a morsel of bread in thy hand. ^12And she said, As Jehovah thy God liveth, I have not a cake, but a handful of meal in the jar, and a little oil in the cruse: and, behold, I am gathering two sticks, that I may go in and dress it for me and my son, that we may eat it, and die. ^13And Elijah said unto her, Fear not; go and do as thou hast said; but make me thereof a little cake first, and bring it forth unto me, and afterward make for thee and for thy son. ^14For thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, The jar of meal shall not waste, neither shall the cruse of oil fail, until the day that Jehovah sendeth rain upon the earth. ^15And she went and did according to the saying of Elijah: and she, and he, and her house, did eat many days. ^16The jar of meal wasted not, neither did the cruse of oil fail, according to the word of Jehovah, which he spake by Elijah.

^17And it came to pass after these things, that the son of the woman, the mistress of the house, fell sick; and his sickness was so sore, that there was no breath left in him. ^18And she said unto Elijah, What have I to do with thee, O thou man of God? thou art come unto me to bring my sin to remembrance, and to slay my son! ^19And he said unto her, Give me thy son. And he took him out of her bosom, and carried him up into the chamber, where he abode, and laid him upon his own bed. ^20And he cried unto Jehovah, and said, O Jehovah my God, hast thou also brought evil upon the widow with whom I sojourn, by slaying her son? ^21And he stretched himself upon the child three times, and cried unto Jehovah, and said, O Jehovah my God, I pray thee, let this child's soul come into him again. ^22And Jehovah hearkened unto the voice of Elijah; and the soul of the child came into him again, and he revived. ^23And Elijah took the child, and brought him down out of the chamber into the house, and delivered him unto his mother; and Elijah said, See, thy son liveth. ^24And the woman said to Elijah, Now I know that thou art a man of God, and that the word of Jehovah in thy mouth is truth.

1 Kings 18

18

^1And it came to pass after many days, that the word of Jehovah came to Elijah, in the third year, saying, Go, show thyself unto Ahab; and I will send rain upon the earth. ^2And Elijah went to show himself unto Ahab. And the famine was sore in Samaria. ^3And Ahab called Obadiah, who was over the household. (Now Obadiah feared Jehovah greatly: ^4for it was so, when Jezebel cut off the prophets of Jehovah, that Obadiah took a hundred prophets, and hid them by fifty in a cave, and fed them with bread and water.) ^5And Ahab said unto Obadiah, Go through the land, unto all the fountains of water, and unto all the brooks: peradventure we may find grass and save the horses and mules alive, that we lose not all the beasts. ^6So they divided the land between them to pass throughout it: Ahab went one way by himself, and Obadiah went another way by himself.

^7And as Obadiah was in the way, behold, Elijah met him: and he knew him, and fell on his face, and said, Is it thou, my lord Elijah? ^8And he answered him, It is I: go, tell thy lord, Behold, Elijah is here. ^9And he said, Wherein have I sinned, that thou wouldest deliver thy servant into the hand of Ahab, to slay me? ^10As Jehovah thy God liveth, there is no nation or kingdom, whither my lord hath not sent to seek thee: and when they said, He is not here, he took an oath of the kingdom and nation, that they found thee not. ^11And now thou sayest, Go, tell thy lord, Behold, Elijah is here. ^12And it will come to pass, as soon as I am gone from thee, that the Spirit of Jehovah will carry thee whither I know not; and so when I come and tell Ahab, and he cannot find thee, he will slay me: but I thy servant fear Jehovah from my youth. ^13Was it not told my lord what I did when Jezebel slew the prophets of Jehovah, how I hid a hundred men of Jehovah's prophets by fifty in a cave, and fed them with bread and water? ^14And now thou sayest, Go, tell thy lord, Behold, Elijah is here; and he will slay me. ^15And Elijah said, As Jehovah of hosts liveth, before whom I stand, I will surely show myself unto him to-day.

^16So Obadiah went to meet Ahab, and told him; and Ahab went to meet Elijah. ^17And it came to pass, when Ahab saw Elijah, that Ahab said unto him, Is it thou, thou troubler of Israel? ^18And he answered, I have not troubled Israel; but thou, and thy father's house, in that ye have forsaken the commandments of Jehovah, and thou hast followed the Baalim. ^19Now therefore send, and gather to me all Israel unto mount Carmel, and the prophets of Baal four hundred and fifty, and the prophets of the Asherah four hundred, that eat at Jezebel's table.

^20So Ahab sent unto all the children of Israel, and gathered the prophets together unto mount Carmel. ^21And Elijah came near unto all the people, and said, How long go ye limping between the two sides? if Jehovah be God, follow him; but if Baal, then follow him. And the people answered him not a word. ^22Then said Elijah unto the people, I, even I only, am left a prophet of Jehovah; but Baal's prophets are four hundred and fifty men. ^23Let them therefore give us two bullocks; and let them choose one bullock for themselves, and cut it in pieces, and lay it on the wood, and put no fire under; and I will dress the other bullock, and lay it on the wood, and put no fire under. ^24And call ye on the name of your god, and I will call on the name of Jehovah; and the God that answereth by fire, let him be God. And all the people answered and said, It is well spoken.

^25And Elijah said unto the prophets of Baal, Choose you one bullock for yourselves, and dress it first; for ye are many; and call on the name of your god, but put no fire under. ^26And they took the bullock which was given them, and they dressed it, and called on the name of Baal from morning even until noon, saying, O Baal, hear us. But there was no voice, nor any that answered. And they leaped about the altar which was made. ^27And it came to pass at noon, that Elijah mocked them, and said, Cry aloud; for he is a god: either he is musing, or he is gone aside, or he is on a journey, or peradventure he sleepeth and must be awaked. ^28And they cried aloud, and cut themselves after their manner with knives and lances, till the blood gushed out upon them. ^29And it was so, when midday was past, that they prophesied until the time of the offering of the evening oblation; but there was neither voice, nor any to answer, nor any that regarded.

^30And Elijah said unto all the people, Come near unto me; and all the people came near unto him. And he repaired the altar of Jehovah that was thrown down. ^31And Elijah took twelve stones, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob, unto whom the word of Jehovah came, saying, Israel shall be thy name. ^32And with the stones he built an altar in the name of Jehovah; and he made a trench about the altar, as great as would contain two measures of seed. ^33And he put the wood in order, and cut the bullock in pieces, and laid it on the wood. And he said, Fill four jars with water, and pour it on the burnt-offering, and on the wood. ^34And he said, Do it the second time; and they did it the second time. And he said, Do it the third time; and they did it the third time. ^35And the water ran round about the altar; and he filled the trench also with water. ^36And it came to pass at the time of the offering of the evening oblation, that Elijah the prophet came near, and said, O Jehovah, the God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Israel, let it be known this day that thou art God in Israel, and that I am thy servant, and that I have done all these things at thy word. ^37Hear me, O Jehovah, hear me, that this people may know that thou, Jehovah, art God, and that thou hast turned their heart back again. ^38Then the fire of Jehovah fell, and consumed the burnt-offering, and the wood, and the stones, and the dust, and licked up the water that was in the trench. ^39And when all the people saw it, they fell on their faces: and they said, Jehovah, he is God; Jehovah, he is God. ^40and Elijah said unto them, Take the prophets of Baal; let not one of them escape. And they took them; and Elijah brought them down to the brook Kishon, and slew them there.

^41And Elijah said unto Ahab, Get thee up, eat and drink; for there is the sound of abundance of rain. ^42So Ahab went up to eat and to drink. And Elijah went up to the top of Carmel; and he bowed himself down upon the earth, and put his face between his knees. ^43And he said to his servant, Go up now, look toward the sea. And he went up, and looked, and said, There is nothing. And he said, Go again seven times. ^44And it came to pass at the seventh time, that he said, Behold, there ariseth a cloud out of the sea, as small as a man's hand. And he said, Go up, say unto Ahab, Make ready thy chariot, and get thee down, that the rain stop thee not. ^45And it came to pass in a little while, that the heavens grew black with clouds and wind, and there was a great rain. And Ahab rode, and went to Jezreel: ^46and the hand of Jehovah was on Elijah; and he girded up his loins, and ran before Ahab to the entrance of Jezreel.

1 Kings 19

19

^1And Ahab told Jezebel all that Elijah had done, and withal how he had slain all the prophets with the sword. ^2Then Jezebel send a messenger unto Elijah, saying, So let the gods do to me, and more also, if I make not thy life as the life of one of them by to-morrow about this time. ^3And when he saw that, he arose, and went for his life, and came to Beer-sheba, which belongeth to Judah, and left his servant there. ^4But he himself went a day's journey into the wilderness, and came and sat down under a juniper-tree: and he requested for himself that he might die, and said, It is enough; now, O Jehovah, take away my life; for I am not better than my fathers. ^5And he lay down and slept under a juniper-tree; and, behold, an angel touched him, and said unto him, Arise and eat. ^6And he looked, and, behold, there was at his head a cake baken on the coals, and a cruse of water. And he did eat and drink, and laid him down again. ^7And the angel of Jehovah came again the second time, and touched him, and said, Arise and eat, because the journey is too great for thee. ^8And he arose, and did eat and drink, and went in the strength of that food forty days and forty nights unto Horeb the mount of God.

^9And he came thither unto a cave, and lodged there; and, behold, the word of Jehovah came to him, and he said unto him, What doest thou here, Elijah? ^10And he said, I have been very jealous for Jehovah, the God of hosts; for the children of Israel have forsaken thy covenant, thrown down thine altars, and slain thy prophets with the sword: and I, even I only, am left; and they seek my life, to take it away. ^11And he said, Go forth, and stand upon the mount before Jehovah. And, behold, Jehovah passed by, and a great and strong wind rent the mountains, and brake in pieces the rocks before Jehovah; but Jehovah was not in the wind: and after the wind an earthquake; but Jehovah was not in the earthquake: ^12and after the earthquake a fire; but Jehovah was not in the fire: and after the fire a still small voice. ^13And it was so, when Elijah heard it, that he wrapped his face in his mantle, and went out, and stood in the entrance of the cave. And, behold, there came a voice unto him, and said, What doest thou here, Elijah? ^14And he said, I have been very jealous for Jehovah, the God of hosts; for the children of Israel have forsaken thy covenant, thrown down thine altars, and slain thy prophets with the sword; and I, even I only, am left; and they seek my life, to take it away.

^15And Jehovah said unto him, Go, return on thy way to the wilderness of Damascus: and when thou comest, thou shalt anoint Hazael to be king over Syria; ^16and Jehu the son of Nimshi shalt thou anoint to be king over Israel; and Elisha the son of Shaphat of Abel-meholah shalt thou anoint to be prophet in thy room. ^17And it shall come to pass, that him that escapeth from the sword of Hazael shall Jehu slay; and him that escapeth from the sword of Jehu shall Elisha slay. ^18Yet will I leave me seven thousand in Israel, all the knees which have not bowed unto Baal, and every mouth which hath not kissed him. ^19So he departed thence, and found Elisha the son of Shaphat, who was plowing, with twelve yoke of oxen before him, and he with the twelfth: and Elijah passed over unto him, and cast his mantle upon him. ^20And he left the oxen, and ran after Elijah, and said, Let me, I pray thee, kiss my father and my mother, and then I will follow thee. And he said unto him, Go back again; for what have I done to thee? ^21And he returned from following him, and took the yoke of oxen, and slew them, and boiled their flesh with the instruments of the oxen, and gave unto the people, and they did eat. Then he arose, and went after Elijah, and ministered unto him.

1 Kings 20

20

^1And Ben-hadad the king of Syria gathered all his host together; and there were thirty and two kings with him, and horses and chariots: and he went up and besieged Samaria, and fought against it. ^2And he sent messengers to Ahab king of Israel, into the city, and said unto him, Thus saith Ben-hadad, ^3Thy silver and thy gold is mine; thy wives also and thy children, even the goodliest, are mine. ^4And the king of Israel answered and said, It is according to thy saying, my lord, O king; I am thine, and all that I have. ^5And the messengers came again, and said, Thus speaketh Ben-hadad, saying, I sent indeed unto thee, saying, Thou shalt deliver me thy silver, and thy gold, and thy wives, and thy children; ^6but I will send my servants unto thee to-morrow about this time, and they shall search thy house, and the houses of thy servants; and it shall be, that whatsoever is pleasant in thine eyes, they shall put it in their hand, and take it away.

^7Then the king of Israel called all the elders of the land, and said, Mark, I pray you, and see how this man seeketh mischief: for he sent unto me for my wives, and for my children, and for my silver, and for my gold; and I denied him not. ^8And all the elders and all the people said unto him, Hearken thou not, neither consent. ^9Wherefore he said unto the messengers of Ben-hadad, Tell my lord the king, All that thou didst send for to thy servant at the first I will do; but this thing I may not do. And the messengers departed, and brought him word again. ^10And Ben-hadad sent unto him, and said, The gods do so unto me, and more also, if the dust of Samaria shall suffice for handfuls for all the people that follow me. ^11And the king of Israel answered and said, Tell him, Let not him that girdeth on his armor boast himself as he that putteth it off. ^12And it came to pass, when Ben-hadad heard this message, as he was drinking, he and the kings, in the pavilions, that he said unto his servants, Set yourselves in array. And they set themselves in array against the city.

^13And, behold, a prophet came near unto Ahab king of Israel, and said, Thus saith Jehovah, Hast thou seen all this great multitude? behold, I will deliver it into thy hand this day; and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah. ^14And Ahab said, By whom? And he said, Thus saith Jehovah, By the young men of the princes of the provinces. Then he said, Who shall begin the battle? And he answered, Thou. ^15Then he mustered the young men of the princes of the provinces, and they were two hundred and thirty-two: and after them he mustered all the people, even all the children of Israel, being seven thousand.

^16And they went out at noon. But Ben-hadad was drinking himself drunk in the pavilions, he and the kings, the thirty and two kings that helped him. ^17And the young men of the princes of the provinces went out first; and Ben-hadad sent out, and they told him, saying, There are men come out from Samaria. ^18And he said, Whether they are come out for peace, take them alive, or whether they are come out for war, taken them alive. ^19So these went out of the city, the young men of the princes of the provinces, and the army which followed them. ^20And they slew every one his man; and the Syrians fled, and Israel pursued them: and Ben-hadad the king of Syria escaped on a horse with horsemen. ^21And the king of Israel went out, and smote the horses and chariots, and slew the Syrians with a great slaughter.

^22And the prophet came near to the king of Israel, and said unto him, Go, strengthen thyself, and mark, and see what thou doest; for at the return of the year the king of Syria will come up against thee. ^23And the servants of the king of Syria said unto him, Their god is a god of the hills; therefore they were stronger than we: but let us fight against them in the plain, and surely we shall be stronger than they. ^24And do this thing: take the kings away, every man out of his place, and put captains in their room; ^25and number thee an army, like the army that thou hast lost, horse for horse, and chariot for chariot; and we will fight against them in the plain, and surely we shall be stronger than they. And he hearkened unto their voice, and did so.

^26And it came to pass at the return of the year, that Ben-hadad mustered the Syrians, and went up to Aphek, to fight against Israel. ^27And the children of Israel were mustered, and were victualled, and went against them: and the children of Israel encamped before them like two little flocks of kids; but the Syrians filled the country. ^28And a man of God came near and spake unto the king of Israel, and said, Thus saith Jehovah, Because the Syrians have said, Jehovah is a god of the hills, but he is not a god of the valleys; therefore will I deliver all this great multitude into thy hand, and ye shall know that I am Jehovah. ^29And they encamped one over against the other seven days. And so it was, that in the seventh day the battle was joined; and the children of Israel slew of the Syrians a hundred thousand footmen in one day. ^30But the rest fled to Aphek, into the city; and the wall fell upon twenty and seven thousand men that were left. And Ben-hadad fled, and came into the city, into an inner chamber.

^31And his servants said unto him, Behold now, we have heard that the kings of the house of Israel are merciful kings: let us, we pray thee, put sackcloth on our loins, and ropes upon our heads, and go out to the king of Israel: peradventure he will save thy life. ^32So they girded sackcloth on their loins, and put ropes on their heads, and came to the king of Israel, and said, Thy servant Ben-hadad saith, I pray thee, let me live. And he said, Is he yet alive? he is my brother. ^33Now the men observed diligently, and hasted to catch whether it were his mind; and they said, Thy brother Ben-hadad. Then he said, Go ye, bring him. Then Ben-hadad came forth to him; and he caused him to come up into the chariot. ^34And Ben-hadad said unto him, The cities which my father took from thy father I will restore; and thou shalt make streets for thee in Damascus, as my father made in Samaria. And I, said Ahab, will let thee go with this covenant. So he made a covenant with him, and let him go.

^35And a certain man of the sons of the prophets said unto his fellow by the word of Jehovah, Smite me, I pray thee. And the man refused to smite him. ^36Then said he unto him, Because thou hast not obeyed the voice of Jehovah, behold, as soon as thou art departed from me, a lion shall slay thee. And as soon as he was departed from him, a lion found him, and slew him. ^37Then he found another man, and said, Smite me, I pray thee. And the man smote him, smiting and wounding him. ^38So the prophet departed, and waited for the king by the way, and disguised himself with his headband over his eyes. ^39And as the king passed by, he cried unto the king; and he said, Thy servant went out into the midst of the battle; and, behold, a man turned aside, and brought a man unto me, and said, Keep this man: if by any means he be missing, then shall thy life be for his life, or else thou shalt pay a talent of silver. ^40And as thy servant was busy here and there, he was gone. And the king of Israel said unto him, So shall thy judgment be; thyself hast decided it. ^41And he hasted, and took the headband away from his eyes; and the king of Israel discerned him that he was of the prophets. ^42And he said unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, Because thou hast let go out of thy hand the man whom I had devoted to destruction, therefore thy life shall go for his life, and thy people for his people. ^43And the king of Israel went to his house heavy and displeased, and came to Samaria.

1 Kings 21

21

^1And it came to pass after these things, that Naboth the Jezreelite had a vineyard, which was in Jezreel, hard by the palace of Ahab king of Samaria. ^2And Ahab spake unto Naboth, saying, Give me thy vineyard, that I may have it for a garden of herbs, because it is near unto my house; and I will give thee for it a better vineyard than it: or, if it seem good to thee, I will give thee the worth of it in money. ^3And Naboth said to Ahab, Jehovah forbid it me, that I should give the inheritance of my fathers unto thee. ^4And Ahab came into his house heavy and displeased because of the word which Naboth the Jezreelite had spoken to him; for he had said, I will not give thee the inheritance of my fathers. And he laid him down upon his bed, and turned away his face, and would eat no bread.

^5But Jezebel his wife came to him, and said unto him, Why is thy spirit so sad, that thou eatest no bread? ^6And he said unto her, Because I spake unto Naboth the Jezreelite, and said unto him, Give me thy vineyard for money; or else, if it please thee, I will give thee another vineyard for it: and he answered, I will not give thee my vineyard. ^7And Jezebel his wife said unto him, Dost thou now govern the kingdom of Israel? arise, and eat bread, and let thy heart be merry: I will give thee the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite. ^8So she wrote letters in Ahab's name, and sealed them with his seal, and sent the letters unto the elders and to the nobles that were in his city, and that dwelt with Naboth. ^9And she wrote in the letters, saying, Proclaim a fast, and set Naboth on high among the people: ^10and set two men, base fellows, before him, and let them bear witness against him, saying, Thou didst curse God and the king. And then carry him out, and stone him to death.

^11And the men of his city, even the elders and the nobles who dwelt in his city, did as Jezebel had sent unto them, according as it was written in the letters which she had sent unto them. ^12They proclaimed a fast, and set Naboth on high among the people. ^13And the two men, the base fellows, came in and sat before him: and the base fellows bare witness against him, even against Naboth, in the presence of the people, saying, Naboth did curse God and the king. Then they carried him forth out of the city, and stoned him to death with stones. ^14Then they sent to Jezebel, saying, Naboth is stoned, and is dead. ^15And it came to pass, when Jezebel heard that Naboth was stoned, and was dead, that Jezebel said to Ahab, Arise, take possession of the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite, which he refused to give thee for money; for Naboth is not alive, but dead. ^16And it came to pass, when Ahab heard that Naboth was dead, that Ahab rose up to go down to the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite, to take possession of it.

^17And the word of Jehovah came to Elijah the Tishbite, saying, ^18Arise, go down to meet Ahab king of Israel, who dwelleth in Samaria: behold, he is in the vineyard of Naboth, whither he is gone down to take possession of it. ^19And thou shalt speak unto him, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, Hast thou killed and also taken possession? And thou shalt speak unto him, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, In the place where dogs licked the blood of Naboth shall dogs lick thy blood, even thine. ^20And Ahab said to Elijah, Hast thou found me, O mine enemy? And he answered, I have found thee, because thou hast sold thyself to do that which is evil in the sight of Jehovah. ^21Behold, I will bring evil upon thee, and will utterly sweep thee away and will cut off from Ahab every man-child, and him that is shut up and him that is left at large in Israel: ^22and I will make thy house like the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and like the house of Baasha the son of Ahijah for the provocation wherewith thou hast provoked me to anger, and hast made Israel to sin. ^23And of Jezebel also spake Jehovah, saying, The dogs shall eat Jezebel by the rampart of Jezreel. ^24Him that dieth of Ahab in the city the dogs shall eat; and him that dieth in the field shall the birds of the heavens eat. ^25(But there was none like unto Ahab, who did sell himself to do that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, whom Jezebel his wife stirred up. ^26And he did very abominably in following idols, according to all that the Amorites did, whom Jehovah cast out before the children of Israel.)

^27And it came to pass, when Ahab heard those words, that he rent his clothes, and put sackcloth upon his flesh, and fasted, and lay in sackcloth, and went softly. ^28And the word of Jehovah came to Elijah the Tishbite, saying, ^29Seest thou how Ahab humbleth himself before me? because he humbleth himself before me, I will not bring the evil in his days; but in his son's days will I bring the evil upon his house.

1 Kings 22

22

^1And they continued three years without war between Syria and Israel. ^2And it came to pass in the third year, that Jehoshaphat the king of Judah came down to the king of Israel. ^3And the king of Israel said unto his servants, Know ye that Ramoth-gilead is ours, and we are still, and take it not out of the hand of the king of Syria? ^4And he said unto Jehoshaphat, Wilt thou go with me to battle to Ramoth-gilead? And Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, I am as thou art, my people as thy people, my horses as thy horses.

^5And Jehoshaphat said unto the king of Israel, Inquire first, I pray thee, for the word of Jehovah. ^6Then the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, about four hundred men, and said unto them, Shall I go against Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I forbear? And they said, Go up; for the Lord will deliver it into the hand of the king. ^7But Jehoshaphat said, Is there not here a prophet of Jehovah besides, that we may inquire of him? ^8And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, there is yet one man by whom we may inquire of Jehovah, Micaiah the son of Imlah: but I hate him; for he doth not prophesy good concerning me, but evil. And Jehoshaphat said, Let not the king say so. ^9Then the king of Israel called an officer, and said, Fetch quickly Micaiah the son of Imlah. ^10Now the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah were sitting each on his throne, arrayed in their robes, in an open place at the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets were prophesying before them. ^11And Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah made him horns of iron, and said, Thus saith Jehovah, With these shalt thou push the Syrians, until they be consumed. ^12And all the prophets prophesied so, saying, Go up to Ramoth-gilead, and prosper; for Jehovah will deliver it into the hand of the king.

^13And the messenger that went to call Micaiah spake unto him, saying, Behold now, the words of the prophets declare good unto the king with one mouth: let thy word, I pray thee, be like the word of one of them, and speak thou good. ^14And Micaiah said, As Jehovah liveth, what Jehovah saith unto me, that will I speak. ^15And when he was come to the king, the king said unto him, Micaiah, shall we go to Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall we forbear? And he answered him, Go up and prosper; and Jehovah will deliver it into the hand of the king. ^16And the king said unto him, How many times shall I adjure thee that thou speak unto me nothing but the truth in the name of Jehovah? ^17And he said, I saw all Israel scattered upon the mountains, as sheep that have no shepherd: and Jehovah said, These have no master; let them return every man to his house in peace. ^18And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, Did I not tell thee that he would not prophesy good concerning me, but evil? ^19And Micaiah said, Therefore hear thou the word of Jehovah: I saw Jehovah sitting on his throne, and all the host of heaven standing by him on his right hand and on his left. ^20And Jehovah said, Who shall entice Ahab, that he may go up and fall at Ramoth-gilead? And one said on this manner; and another said on that manner. ^21And there came forth a spirit, and stood before Jehovah, and said, I will entice him. ^22And Jehovah said unto him, Wherewith? And he said, I will go forth, and will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets. And he said, Thou shalt entice him, and shalt prevail also: go forth, and do so. ^23Now therefore, behold, Jehovah hath put a lying spirit in the mouth of all these thy prophets; and Jehovah hath spoken evil concerning thee.

^24Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah came near, and smote Micaiah on the cheek, and said, Which way went the Spirit of Jehovah from me to speak unto thee? ^25And Micaiah said, Behold, thou shalt see on that day, when thou shalt go into an inner chamber to hide thyself. ^26And the king of Israel said, Take Micaiah, and carry him back unto Amon the governor of the city, and to Joash the king's son; ^27and say, Thus saith the king, Put this fellow in the prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction, until I come in peace. ^28And Micaiah said, If thou return at all in peace, Jehovah hath not spoken by me. And he said, Hear, ye peoples, all of you.

^29So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth-gilead. ^30And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, I will disguise myself, and go into the battle; but put thou on thy robes. And the king of Israel disguised himself, and went into the battle. ^31Now the king of Syria had commanded the thirty and two captains of his chariots, saying, Fight neither with small nor great, save only with the king of Israel. ^32And it came to pass, when the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, that they said, Surely it is the king of Israel; and they turned aside to fight against him: and Jehoshaphat cried out. ^33And it came to pass, when the captains of the chariots saw that it was not the king of Israel, that they turned back from pursuing him. ^34And a certain man drew his bow at a venture, and smote the king of Israel between the joints of the armor: wherefore he said unto the driver of his chariot, Turn thy hand, and carry me out of the host; for I am sore wounded. ^35And the battle increased that day: and the king was stayed up in his chariot against the Syrians, and died at even; and the blood ran out of the wound into the bottom of the chariot. ^36And there went a cry throughout the host about the going down of the sun, saying, Every man to his city, and every man to his country.

^37So the king died, and was brought to Samaria; and they buried the king in Samaria. ^38And they washed the chariot by the pool of Samaria; and the dogs licked up his blood (now the harlots washed themselves there); according unto the word of Jehovah which he spake. ^39Now the rest of the acts of Ahab, and all that he did, and the ivory house which he built, and all the cities that he built, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? ^40So Ahab slept with his fathers; and Ahaziah his son reigned in his stead.

^41And Jehoshaphat the son of Asa began to reign over Judah in the fourth year of Ahab king of Israel. ^42Jehoshaphat was thirty and five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty and five years in Jerusalem. And his mother's name was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. ^43And he walked in all the way of Asa his father; He turned not aside from it, doing that which was right in the eyes of Jehovah: howbeit the high places were not taken away; the people still sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places. ^44And Jehoshaphat made peace with the king of Israel.

^45Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, and his might that he showed, and how he warred, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? ^46And the remnant of the sodomites, that remained in the days of his father Asa, he put away out of the land. ^47And there was no king in Edom: a deputy was king. ^48Jehoshaphat made ships of Tarshish to go to Ophir for gold: but they went not; for the ships were broken at Ezion-geber. ^49Then said Ahaziah the son of Ahab unto Jehoshaphat, Let my servants go with thy servants in the ships. But Jehoshaphat would not. ^50And Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David his father; And Jehoram his son reigned in his stead.

^51Ahaziah the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria in the seventeenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and he reigned two years over Israel. ^52And he did that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah, and walked in the way of his father, and in the way of his mother, and in the way of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, wherein he made Israel to sin. ^53And he served Baal, and worshipped him, and provoked to anger Jehovah, the God of Israel, according to all that his father had done.

1 Peter 2

2

^1Putting away therefore all wickedness, and all guile, and hypocrisies, and envies, and all evil speakings, ^2as newborn babes, long for the spiritual milk which is without guile, that ye may grow thereby unto salvation; ^3if ye have tasted that the Lord is gracious: ^4unto whom coming, a living stone, rejected indeed of men, but with God elect, precious, ^5ye also, as living stones, are built up a spiritual house, to be a holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual sacrifices, acceptable to God through Jesus Christ. ^6Because it is contained in span,

Behold, I lay in Zion a chief corner stone, elect, precious:

And he that believeth on him shall not be put to shame.

^7For you therefore that believe is the preciousness: but for such as disbelieve,

The stone which the builders rejected,

The same was made the head of the corner;

^8and,

A stone of stumbling, and a rock of offence;

for they stumble at the word, being disobedient: whereunto also they were appointed. ^9But ye are a elect race, a royal priesthood, a holy nation, a people for God's own possession, that ye may show forth the excellencies of him who called you out of darkness into his marvellous light: ^10who in time past were no people, but now are the people of God: who had not obtained mercy, but now have obtained mercy. ^11Beloved, I beseech you as sojourners and pilgrims, to abstain from fleshly lust, which war against the soul; ^12having your behavior seemly among the Gentiles; that, wherein they speak against you as evil-doers, they may by your good works, which they behold, glorify God in the day of visitation. ^13Be subject to every ordinance of man for the Lord's sake: whether to the king, as supreme; ^14or unto governors, as sent by him for vengeance on evil-doers and for praise to them that do well. ^15For so is the will of God, that by well-doing ye should put to silence the ignorance of foolish men: ^16as free, and not using your freedom for a cloak of wickedness, but as bondservants of God. ^17Honor all men. Love the brotherhood. Fear God. Honor the king. ^18Servants, be in subjection to your masters with all fear; not only to the good and gentle, but also to the froward. ^19For this is acceptable, if for conscience toward God a man endureth griefs, suffering wrongfully. ^20For what glory is it, if, when ye sin, and are buffeted for it, ye shall take it patiently? but if, when ye do well, and suffer for it, ye shall take it patiently, this is acceptable with God. ^21For hereunto were ye called: because Christ also suffered for you, leaving you an example, that ye should follow his steps: ^22who did no sin, neither was guile found in his mouth: ^23who, when he was reviled, reviled not again; when he suffered threatened not; but committed himself to him that judgeth righteously: ^24who his own self bare our sins in his body upon the tree, that we, having died unto sins, might live unto righteousness; by whose stripes ye were healed. ^25For ye were going astray like sheep; but are now returned unto the Shepherd and Bishop of your souls.

1 Peter 3

3

^1In like manner, ye wives, be in subjection to your own husbands; that, even if any obey not the word, they may without the word be gained by the behavior of their wives; ^2beholding your chaste behavior coupled with fear. ^3Whose adorning let it not be the outward adorning of braiding the hair, and of wearing jewels of gold, or of putting on apparel; ^4but let it be the hidden man of the heart, in the incorruptible apparel of a meek and quiet spirit, which is in the sight of God of great price. ^5For after this manner aforetime the holy women also, who hoped in God, adorned themselves, being in subjection to their own husbands: ^6as Sarah obeyed Abraham, calling him lord: whose children ye now are, if ye do well, and are not put in fear by any terror. ^7Ye husbands, in like manner, dwell with your wives according to knowledge, giving honor unto the woman, as unto the weaker vessel, as being also joint-heirs of the grace of life; to the end that your prayers be not hindered. ^8Finally, be ye all likeminded, compassionate, loving as brethren, tenderhearted, humbleminded: ^9not rendering evil for evil, or reviling for reviling; but contrariwise blessing; for hereunto were ye called, that ye should inherit a blessing. ^10For,

He that would love life,

And see good days,

Let him refrain his tongue from evil,

And his lips that they speak no guile:

^11And let him turn away from evil, and do good;

Let him seek peace, and pursue it.

^12For the eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous,

And his ears unto their supplication:

But the face of the Lord is upon them that do evil.

^13And who is he that will harm you, if ye be zealous of that which is good? ^14But even if ye should suffer for righteousness' sake, blessed are ye: and fear not their fear, neither be troubled; ^15but sanctify in your hearts Christ as Lord: being ready always to give answer to every man that asketh you a reason concerning the hope that is in you, yet with meekness and fear: ^16having a good conscience; that, wherein ye are spoken against, they may be put to shame who revile your good manner of life in Christ. ^17For it is better, if the will of God should so will, that ye suffer for well-doing than for evil-doing. ^18Because Christ also suffered for sins once, the righteous for the unrighteous, that he might bring us to God; being put to death in the flesh, but made alive in the spirit; ^19in which also he went and preached unto the spirits in prison, ^20that aforetime were disobedient, when the longsuffering of God waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was a preparing, wherein few, that is, eight souls, were saved through water: ^21which also after a true likeness doth now save you, even baptism, not the putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the interrogation of a good conscience toward God, through the resurrection of Jesus Christ; ^22who is one the right hand of God, having gone into heaven; angels and authorities and powers being made subject unto him.

1 Peter 4

4

^1Forasmuch then as Christ suffered in the flesh, arm ye yourselves also with the same mind; for he that hath suffered in the flesh hath ceased from sin; ^2that ye no longer should live the rest of your time in flesh to the lusts of men, but to the will of God. ^3For the time past may suffice to have wrought the desire of the Gentiles, and to have walked in lasciviousness, lusts, winebibbings, revellings, carousings, and abominable idolatries: ^4wherein they think strange that ye run not with them into the same excess of riot, speaking evil of you: ^5who shall give account to him that is ready to judge the living and the dead. ^6For unto this end was the gospel preached even to the dead, that they might be judged indeed according to men in the flesh, but live according to God in the spirit. ^7But the end of all things is at hand: be ye therefore of sound mind, and be sober unto prayer: ^8above all things being fervent in your love among yourselves; for love covereth a multitude of sins: ^9using hospitality one to another without murmuring: ^10according as each hath received a gift, ministering it among yourselves, as good stewards of the manifold grace of God; ^11if any man speaketh, speaking as it were oracles of God; is any man ministereth, ministering as of the strength which God supplieth: that in all things God may be glorified through Jesus Christ, whose is the glory and the dominion for ever and ever. Amen. ^12Beloved, think it not strange concerning the fiery trial among you, which cometh upon you to prove you, as though a strange thing happened unto you: ^13but insomuch as ye are partakers of Christ's sufferings, rejoice; that at the revelation of his glory also ye may rejoice with exceeding joy. ^14If ye are reproached for the name of Christ, blessed are ye; because the Spirit of glory and the Spirit of God resteth upon you. ^15For let none of you suffer as a murderer, or a thief, or an evil-doer, or as a meddler in other men's matters: ^16but if a man suffer as a Christian, let him not be ashamed; but let him glorify God in this name. ^17For the time is come for judgment to begin at the house of God: and if it begin first at us, what shall be the end of them that obey not the gospel of God? ^18And if the righteous is scarcely saved, where shall the ungodly and sinner appear? ^19Wherefore let them also that suffer according to the will of God commit their souls in well-doing unto a faithful Creator.

1 Peter 5

5

^1The elders among you I exhort, who am a fellow-elder, and a witness of the sufferings of Christ, who am also a partaker of the glory that shall be revealed: ^2Tend the flock of God which is among you, exercising the oversight, not of constraint, but willingly, according to the will of God; nor yet for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind; ^3neither as lording it over the charge allotted to you, but making yourselves ensamples to the flock. ^4And when the chief Shepherd shall be manifested, ye shall receive the crown of glory that fadeth not away. ^5Likewise, ye younger, be subject unto the elder. Yea, all of you gird yourselves with humility, to serve one another: for God resisteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble. ^6Humble yourselves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time; ^7casting all your anxiety upon him, because he careth for you. ^8Be sober, be watchful: your adversary the devil, as a roaring lion, walketh about, seeking whom he may devour, ^9whom withstand stedfast in your faith, knowing that the same sufferings are accomplished in your brethren who are in the world. ^10And the God of all grace, who called you unto his eternal glory in Christ, after that ye have suffered a little while, shall himself perfect, establish, strengthen you. ^11To him be the dominion for ever and ever. Amen. ^12By Silvanus, our faithful brother, as I account him, I have written unto you briefly, exhorting, and testifying that this is the true grace of God. Stand ye fast therein. ^13She that is in Babylon, elect together with you, saluteth you; and so doth Mark my son. ^14Salute one another with a kiss of love. Peace be unto you all that are in Christ.

Isaiah 2

2

^1The word that Isaiah the son of Amoz saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem. ^2And it shall come to pass in the latter days, that the mountain of Jehovah's house shall be established on the top of the mountains, and shall be exalted above the hills; and all nations shall flow unto it. ^3And many peoples shall go and say, Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of Jehovah, to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths: for out of Zion shall go forth the law, and the word of Jehovah from Jerusalem. ^4And he will judge between the nations, and will decide concerning many peoples; and they shall beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruning-hooks; nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any more. ^5O house of Jacob, come ye, and let us walk in the light of Jehovah. ^6For thou hast forsaken thy people the house of Jacob, because they are filled with customs from the east, and are soothsayers like the Philistines, and they strike hands with the children of foreigners. ^7And their land is full of silver and gold, neither is there any end of their treasures; their land also is full of horses, neither is there any end of their chariots. ^8Their land also is full of idols; they worship the work of their own hands, that which their own fingers have made. ^9And the mean man is bowed down, and the great man is brought low: therefore forgive them not. ^10Enter into the rock, and hide thee in the dust, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty. ^11The lofty looks of man shall be brought low, and the haughtiness of men shall be bowed down, and Jehovah alone shall be exalted in that day. ^12For there shall be a day of Jehovah of hosts upon all that is proud and haughty, and upon all that is lifted up; and it shall be brought low; ^13and upon all the cedars of Lebanon, that are high and lifted up, and upon all the oaks of Bashan, ^14and upon all the high mountains, and upon all the hills that are lifted up, ^15and upon every lofty tower, and upon every fortified wall, ^16and upon all the ships of Tarshish, and upon all pleasant imagery. ^17And the loftiness of man shall be bowed down, and the haughtiness of men shall be brought low; and Jehovah alone shall be exalted in that day. ^18And the idols shall utterly pass away. ^19And men shall go into the caves of the rocks, and into the holes of the earth, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty, when he ariseth to shake mightily the earth. ^20In that day men shall cast away their idols of silver, and their idols of gold, which have been made for them to worship, to the moles and to the bats; ^21to go into the caverns of the rocks, and into the clefts of the ragged rocks, from before the terror of Jehovah, and from the glory of his majesty, when he ariseth to shake mightily the earth. ^22Cease ye from man, whose breath is in his nostrils; for wherein is he to be accounted of?

Isaiah 3

3

^1For, behold, the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, doth take away from Jerusalem and from Judah stay and staff, the whole stay of bread, and the whole stay of water; ^2the mighty man, and the man of war; the judge, and the prophet, and the diviner, and the elder; ^3the captain of fifty, and the honorable man, and the counsellor, and the expert artificer, and the skilful enchanter. ^4And I will give children to be their princes, and babes shall rule over them. ^5And the people shall be oppressed, every one by another, and every one by his neighbor: the child shall behave himself proudly against the old man, and the base against the honorable. ^6When a man shall take hold of his brother in the house of his father, saying, Thou hast clothing, be thou our ruler, and let this ruin be under thy hand; ^7in that day shall he lift up his voice, saying, I will not be a healer; for in my house is neither bread nor clothing: ye shall not make me ruler of the people. ^8For Jerusalem is ruined, and Judah is fallen; because their tongue and their doings are against Jehovah, to provoke the eyes of his glory. ^9The show of their countenance doth witness against them; and they declare their sin as Sodom, they hide it not. Woe unto their soul! for they have done evil unto themselves. ^10Say ye of the righteous, that it shall be well with him; for they shall eat the fruit of their doings. ^11Woe unto the wicked! it shall be ill with him; for what his hands have done shall be done unto him. ^12As for my people, children are their oppressors, and women rule over them. O my people, they that lead thee cause thee to err, and destroy the way of thy paths. ^13Jehovah standeth up to contend, and standeth to judge the peoples. ^14Jehovah will enter into judgment with the elders of his people, and the princes thereof: It is ye that have eaten up the vineyard; the spoil of the poor is in your houses: ^15what mean ye that ye crush my people, and grind the face of the poor? saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts. ^16Moreover Jehovah said, Because the daughters of Zion are haughty, and walk with outstretched necks and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as they go, and making a tinkling with their feet; ^17therefore the Lord will smite with a scab the crown of the head of the daughters of Zion, and Jehovah will lay bare their secret parts. ^18In that day the Lord will take away the beauty of their anklets, and the cauls, and the crescents; ^19the pendants, and the bracelets, and the mufflers; ^20the headtires, and the ankle chains, and the sashes, and the perfume-boxes, and the amulets; ^21the rings, and the nose-jewels; ^22the festival robes, and the mantles, and the shawls, and the satchels; ^23the hand-mirrors, and the fine linen, and the turbans, and the veils. ^24And it shall come to pass, that instead of sweet spices there shall be rottenness; and instead of a girdle, a rope; and instead of well set hair, baldness; and instead of a robe, a girding of sackcloth; branding instead of beauty. ^25Thy men shall fall by the sword, and thy mighty in the war. ^26And her gates shall lament and mourn; and she shall be desolate and sit upon the ground.

Isaiah 5

5

^1Let me sing for my wellbeloved a song of my beloved touching his vineyard. My wellbeloved had a vineyard in a very fruitful hill: ^2and he digged it, and gathered out the stones thereof, and planted it with the choicest vine, and built a tower in the midst of it, and also hewed out a winepress therein: and he looked that it should bring forth grapes, and it brought forth wild grapes. ^3And now, O inhabitants of Jerusalem and men of Judah, judge, I pray you, betwixt me and my vineyard. ^4What could have been done more to my vineyard, that I have not done in it? wherefore, when I looked that it should bring forth grapes, brought it forth wild grapes? ^5And now I will tell you what I will do to my vineyard: I will take away the hedge thereof, and it shall be eaten up; I will break down the wall thereof, and it shall be trodden down: ^6and I will lay it waste; it shall not be pruned nor hoed; but there shall come up briers and thorns: I will also command the clouds that they rain no rain upon it. ^7For the vineyard of Jehovah of hosts is the house of Israel, and the men of Judah his pleasant plant: and he looked for justice, but, behold, oppression; for righteousness, but, behold, a cry. ^8Woe unto them that join house to house, that lay field to field, till there be no room, and ye be made to dwell alone in the midst of the land! ^9In mine ears saith Jehovah of hosts, Of a truth many houses shall be desolate, even great and fair, without inhabitant. ^10For ten acres of vineyard shall yield one bath, and a homer of seed shall yield but an ephah. ^11Woe unto them that rise up early in the morning, that they may follow strong drink; that tarry late into the night, till wine inflame them! ^12And the harp and the lute, the tabret and the pipe, and wine, are in their feasts; but they regard not the work of Jehovah, neither have they considered the operation of his hands. ^13Therefore my people are gone into captivity for lack of knowledge; and their honorable men are famished, and their multitude are parched with thirst. ^14Therefore Sheol hath enlarged its desire, and opened its mouth without measure; and their glory, and their multitude, and their pomp, and he that rejoiceth among them, descend into it. ^15And the mean man is bowed down, and the great man is humbled, and the eyes of the lofty are humbled: ^16but Jehovah of hosts is exalted in justice, and God the Holy One is sanctified in righteousness. ^17Then shall the lambs feed as in their pasture, and the waste places of the fat ones shall wanderers eat. ^18Woe unto them that draw iniquity with cords of falsehood, and sin as it were with a cart rope; ^19that say, Let him make speed, let him hasten his work, that we may see it; and let the counsel of the Holy One of Israel draw nigh and come, that we may know it! ^20Woe unto them that call evil good, and good evil; that put darkness for light, and light for darkness; that put bitter for sweet, and sweet for bitter! ^21Woe unto them that are wise in their own eyes, and prudent in their own sight! ^22Woe unto them that are mighty to drink wine, and men of strength to mingle strong drink; ^23that justify the wicked for a bribe, and take away the righteousness of the righteous from him! ^24Therefore as the tongue of fire devoureth the stubble, and as the dry grass sinketh down in the flame, so their root shall be as rottenness, and their blossom shall go up as dust; because they have rejected the law of Jehovah of hosts, and despised the word of the Holy One of Israel. ^25Therefore is the anger of Jehovah kindled against his people, and he hath stretched forth his hand against them, and hath smitten them; and the mountains tremble, and their dead bodies are as refuse in the midst of the streets. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still. ^26And he will lift up an ensign to the nations from far, and will hiss for them from the end of the earth; and, behold, they shall come with speed swiftly. ^27None shall be weary nor stumble among them; none shall slumber nor sleep; neither shall the girdle of their loins be loosed, nor the latchet of their shoes be broken: ^28whose arrows are sharp, and all their bows bent; their horses' hoofs shall be accounted as flint, and their wheels as a whirlwind: ^29their roaring shall be like a lioness, they shall roar like young lions; yea, they shall roar, and lay hold of the prey, and carry it away safe, and there shall be none to deliver. ^30And they shall roar against them in that day like the roaring of the sea: and if one look unto the land, behold, darkness and distress; and the light is darkened in the clouds thereof.

Isaiah 6

6

^1In the year that king Uzziah died I saw the Lord sitting upon a throne, high and lifted up; and his train filled the temple. ^2Above him stood the seraphim: each one had six wings; with twain he covered his face, and with twain he covered his feet, and with twain he did fly. ^3And one cried unto another, and said, Holy, holy, holy, is Jehovah of hosts: the whole earth is full of his glory. ^4And the foundations of the thresholds shook at the voice of him that cried, and the house was filled with smoke. ^5Then said I, Woe is me! for I am undone; because I am a man of unclean lips, and I dwell in the midst of a people of unclean lips: for mine eyes have seen the King, Jehovah of hosts. ^6Then flew one of the seraphim unto me, having a live coal in his hand, which he had taken with the tongs from off the altar: ^7and he touched my mouth with it, and said, Lo, this hath touched thy lips; and thine iniquity is taken away, and thy sin forgiven. ^8And I heard the voice of the Lord, saying, Whom shall I send, and who will go for us? Then I said, Here am I; send me. ^9And he said, Go, and tell this people, Hear ye indeed, but understand not; and see ye indeed, but perceive not. ^10Make the heart of this people fat, and make their ears heavy, and shut their eyes; lest they sea with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and turn again, and be healed. ^11Then said I, Lord, how long? And he answered, Until cities be waste without inhabitant, and houses without man, and the land become utterly waste, ^12and Jehovah have removed men far away, and the forsaken places be many in the midst of the land. ^13And if there be yet a tenth in it, it also shall in turn be eaten up: as a terebinth, and as an oak, whose stock remaineth, when they are felled; so the holy seed is the stock thereof.

Isaiah 7

7

^1And it came to pass in the days of Ahaz the son of Jotham, the son of Uzziah, king of Judah, that Rezin the king of Syria, and Pekah the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, went up to Jerusalem to war against it, but could not prevail against it. ^2And it was told the house of David, saying, Syria is confederate with Ephraim. And his heart trembled, and the heart of his people, as the trees of the forest tremble with the wind. ^3Then said Jehovah unto Isaiah, Go forth now to meet Ahaz, thou, and Shear-jashub thy son, at the end of the conduit of the upper pool, in the highway of the fuller's field; ^4and say unto him, Take heed, and be quiet; fear not, neither let thy heart be faint, because of these two tails of smoking firebrands, for the fierce anger of Rezin and Syria, and of the son of Remaliah. ^5Because Syria, Ephraim, and the son of Remaliah, have purposed evil against thee, saying, ^6Let us go up against Judah, and vex it, and let us make a breach therein for us, and set up a king in the midst of it, even the son of Tabeel; ^7thus saith the Lord Jehovah, It shall not stand, neither shall it come to pass. ^8For the head of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Rezin; and within threescore and five years shall Ephraim be broken in pieces, so that is shall not be a people: ^9and the head of Ephraim is Samaria, and the head of Samaria is Remaliah's son. If ye will not believe, surely ye shall not be established. ^10And Jehovah spake again unto Ahaz, saying, ^11Ask thee a sign of Jehovah thy God; ask it either in the depth, or in the height above. ^12But Ahaz said, I will not ask, neither will I tempt Jehovah. ^13And he said, Hear ye now, O house of David: Is it a small thing for you to weary men, that ye will weary my God also? ^14Therefore the Lord himself will give you a sign: behold, a virgin shall conceive, and bear a son, and shall call his name Immanuel. ^15Butter and honey shall he eat, when he knoweth to refuse the evil, and choose the good. ^16For before the child shall know to refuse the evil, and choose the good, the land whose two kings thou abhorrest shall be forsaken. ^17Jehovah will bring upon thee, and upon thy people, and upon thy father's house, days that have not come, from the day that Ephraim departed from Judah-even the king of Assyria. ^18And it shall come to pass in that day, that Jehovah will hiss for the fly that is in the uttermost part of the rivers of Egypt, and for the bee that is in the land of Assyria. ^19And they shall come, and shall rest all of them in the desolate valleys, and in the clefts of the rocks, and upon all thorn-hedges, and upon all pastures. ^20In that day will the Lord shave with a razor that is hired in the parts beyond the River, even with the king of Assyria, the head and the hair of the feet; and it shall also consume the beard. ^21And it shall come to pass in that day, that a man shall keep alive a young cow, and two sheep; ^22and it shall come to pass, that because of the abundance of milk which they shall give he shall eat butter: for butter and honey shall every one eat that is left in the midst of the land. ^23And it shall come to pass in that day, that every place, where there were a thousand vines at a thousand silverlings, shall be for briers and thorns. ^24With arrows and with bow shall one come thither, because all the land shall be briers and thorns. ^25And all the hills that were digged with the mattock, thou shalt not come thither for fear of briers and thorns; but it shall be for the sending forth of oxen, and for the treading of sheep.

Isaiah 8

8

^1And Jehovah said unto me, Take thee a great tablet, and write upon it with the pen of a man, For Maher-shalal-hash-baz; ^2and I will take unto me faithful witnesses to record, Uriah the priest, and Zechariah the son of Jeberechiah. ^3And I went unto the prophetess; and she conceived, and bare a son. Then said Jehovah unto me, Call his name Maher-shalal-hash-baz. ^4For before the child shall have knowledge to cry, My father, and, My mother, the riches of Damascus and the spoil of Samaria shall be carried away before the king of Assyria. ^5And Jehovah spake unto me yet again, saying, ^6Forasmuch as this people have refused the waters of Shiloah that go softly, and rejoice in Rezin and Remaliah's son; ^7now therefore, behold, the Lord bringeth up upon them the waters of the River, strong and many, even the king of Assyria and all his glory: and it shall come up over all its channels, and go over all its banks; ^8and it shall sweep onward into Judah; it shall overflow and pass through; it shall reach even to the neck; and the stretching out of its wings shall fill the breadth of thy land, O Immanuel. ^9Make an uproar, O ye peoples, and be broken in pieces; and give ear, all ye of far countries: gird yourselves, and be broken in pieces; gird yourselves, and be broken in pieces. ^10Take counsel together, and it shall be brought to nought; speak the word, and it shall not stand: for God is with us. ^11For Jehovah spake thus to me with a strong hand, and instructed me not to walk in the way of this people, saying, ^12Say ye not, A conspiracy, concerning all whereof this people shall say, A conspiracy; neither fear ye their fear, nor be in dread thereof. ^13Jehovah of hosts, him shall ye sanctify; and let him be your fear, and let him be your dread. ^14And he shall be for a sanctuary; but for a stone of stumbling and for a rock of offence to both the houses of Israel, for a gin and for a snare to the inhabitants of Jerusalem. ^15And many shall stumble thereon, and fall, and be broken, and be snared, and be taken. ^16Bind thou up the testimony, seal the law among my disciples. ^17And I will wait for Jehovah, that hideth his face from the house of Jacob, and I will look for him. ^18Behold, I and the children whom Jehovah hath given me are for signs and for wonders in Israel from Jehovah of hosts, who dwelleth in mount Zion. ^19And when they shall say unto you, Seek unto them that have familiar spirits and unto the wizards, that chirp and that mutter: should not a people seek unto their God? on behalf of the living should they seek unto the dead? ^20To the law and to the testimony! if they speak not according to this word, surely there is no morning for them. ^21And they shall pass through it, sore distressed and hungry; and it shall come to pass that, when they shall be hungry, they shall fret themselves, and curse by their king and by their God, and turn their faces upward: ^22and they shall look unto the earth, and behold, distress and darkness, the gloom of anguish; and into thick darkness they shall be driven away.

Isaiah 9

9

^1But there shall be no gloom to her that was in anguish. In the former time he brought into contempt the land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali; but in the latter time hath he made it glorious, by the way of the sea, beyond the Jordan, Galilee of the nations. ^2The people that walked in darkness have seen a great light: they that dwelt in the land of the shadow of death, upon them hath the light shined. ^3Thou hast multiplied the nation, thou hast increased their joy: they joy before thee according to the joy in harvest, as men rejoice when they divide the spoil. ^4For the yoke of his burden, and the staff of his shoulder, the rod of his oppressor, thou hast broken as in the day of Midian. ^5For all the armor of the armed man in the tumult, and the garments rolled in blood, shall be for burning, for fuel of fire. ^6For unto us a child is born, unto us a son is given; and the government shall be upon his shoulder: and his name shall be called Wonderful, Counsellor, Mighty God, Everlasting Father, Prince of Peace. ^7Of the increase of his government and of peace there shall be no end, upon the throne of David, and upon his kingdom, to establish it, and to uphold it with justice and with righteousness from henceforth even for ever. The zeal of Jehovah of hosts will perform this. ^8The Lord sent a word into Jacob, and it hath lighted upon Israel. ^9And all the people shall know, even Ephraim and the inhabitant of Samaria, that say in pride and in stoutness of heart, ^10The bricks are fallen, but we will build with hewn stone; the sycomores are cut down, but we will put cedars in their place. ^11Therefore Jehovah will set up on high against him the adversaries of Rezin, and will stir up his enemies, ^12the Syrians before, and the Philistines behind; and they shall devour Israel with open mouth. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still. ^13Yet the people have not turned unto him that smote them, neither have they sought Jehovah of hosts. ^14Therefore Jehovah will cut off from Israel head and tail, palm-branch and rush, in one day. ^15The elder and the honorable man, he is the head; and the prophet that teacheth lies, he is the tail. ^16For they that lead this people cause them to err; and they that are led of them are destroyed. ^17Therefore the Lord will not rejoice over their young men, neither will he have compassion on their fatherless and widows; for every one is profane and an evil-doer, and every mouth speaketh folly. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still. ^18For wickedness burneth as the fire; it devoureth the briers and thorns; yea, it kindleth in the thickets of the forest, and they roll upward in a column of smoke. ^19Through the wrath of Jehovah of hosts is the land burnt up; and the people are as the fuel of fire: no man spareth his brother. ^20And one shall snatch on the right hand, and be hungry; and he shall eat on the left hand, and they shall not be satisfied: they shall eat every man the flesh of his own arm: ^21Manasseh, Ephraim; and Ephraim, Manasseh; and they together shall be against Judah. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still.

Isaiah 10

10

^1Woe unto them that decree unrighteous decrees, and to the writers that write perverseness; ^2to turn aside the needy from justice, and to rob the poor of my people of their right, that widows may be their spoil, and that they may make the fatherless their prey! ^3And what will ye do in the day of visitation, and in the desolation which shall come from far? to whom will ye flee for help? and where will ye leave your glory? ^4They shall only bow down under the prisoners, and shall fall under the slain. For all this his anger is not turned away, but his hand is stretched out still. ^5Ho Assyrian, the rod of mine anger, the staff in whose hand is mine indignation! ^6I will send him against a profane nation, and against the people of my wrath will I give him a charge, to take the spoil, and to take the prey, and to tread them down like the mire of the streets. ^7Howbeit he meaneth not so, neither doth his heart think so; but it is in his heart to destroy, and to cut off nations not a few. ^8For he saith, Are not my princes all of them kings? ^9Is not Calno as Carchemish? is not Hamath as Arpad? is not Samaria as Damascus? ^10As my hand hath found the kingdoms of the idols, whose graven images did excel them of Jerusalem and of Samaria; ^11shall I not, as I have done unto Samaria and her idols, so do to Jerusalem and her idols? ^12Wherefore it shall come to pass, that, when the Lord hath performed his whole work upon mount Zion and on Jerusalem, I will punish the fruit of the stout heart of the king of Assyria, and the glory of his high looks. ^13For he hath said, By the strength of my hand I have done it, and by my wisdom; for I have understanding: and I have removed the bounds of the peoples, and have robbed their treasures, and like a valiant man I have brought down them that sit on thrones: ^14and my hand hath found as a nest the riches of the peoples; and as one gathereth eggs that are forsaken, have I gathered all the earth: and there was none that moved the wing, or that opened the mouth, or chirped. ^15Shall the axe boast itself against him that heweth therewith? shall the saw magnify itself against him that wieldeth it? as if a rod should wield them that lift it up, or as if a staff should lift up him that is not wood. ^16Therefore will the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, send among his fat ones leanness; and under his glory there shall be kindled a burning like the burning of fire. ^17And the light of Israel will be for a fire, and his Holy One for a flame; and it will burn and devour his thorns and his briers in one day. ^18And he will consume the glory of his forest, and of his fruitful field, both soul and body: and it shall be as when a standard-bearer fainteth. ^19And the remnant of the trees of his forest shall be few, so that a child may write them. ^20And it shall come to pass in that day, that the remnant of Israel, and they that are escaped of the house of Jacob, shall no more again lean upon him that smote them, but shall lean upon Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel, in truth. ^21A remnant shall return, even the remnant of Jacob, unto the mighty God. ^22For though thy people, Israel, be as the sand of the sea, only a remnant of them shall return: a destruction is determined, overflowing with righteousness. ^23For a full end, and that determined, will the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, make in the midst of all the earth. ^24Therefore thus saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, O my people that dwellest in Zion, be not afraid of the Assyrian, though he smite thee with the rod, and lift up his staff against thee, after the manner of Egypt. ^25For yet a very little while, and the indignation against thee shall be accomplished, and mine anger shall be directed to his destruction. ^26And Jehovah of hosts will stir up against him a scourge, as in the slaughter of Midian at the rock of Oreb: and his rod will be over the sea, and he will lift it up after the manner of Egypt. ^27And it shall come to pass in that day, that his burden shall depart from off thy shoulder, and his yoke from off thy neck, and the yoke shall be destroyed by reason of fatness. ^28He is come to Aiath, he is passed through Migron; at Michmash he layeth up his baggage; ^29they are gone over the pass; they have taken up their lodging at Geba; Ramah trembleth; Gibeah of Saul is fled. ^30Cry aloud with thy voice, O daughter of Gallim! hearken, O Laishah! O thou poor Anathoth! ^31Madmenah is a fugitive; the inhabitants of Gebim flee for safety. ^32This very day shall he halt at Nob: he shaketh his hand at the mount of the daughter of Zion, the hill of Jerusalem. ^33Behold, the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, will lop the boughs with terror: and the high of stature shall be hewn down, and the lofty shall be brought low. ^34And he will cut down the thickets of the forest with iron, and Lebanon shall fall by a mighty one.

Isaiah 11

11

^1And there shall come forth a shoot out of the stock of Jesse, and a branch out of his roots shall bear fruit. ^2And the Spirit of Jehovah shall rest upon him, the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and might, the spirit of knowledge and of the fear of Jehovah. ^3And his delight shall be in the fear of Jehovah; and he shall not judge after the sight of his eyes, neither decide after the hearing of his ears; ^4but with righteousness shall he judge the poor, and decide with equity for the meek of the earth; and he shall smite the earth with the rod of his mouth; and with the breath of his lips shall he slay the wicked. ^5And righteousness shall be the girdle of his waist, and faithfulness the girdle of his loins. ^6And the wolf shall dwell with the lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid; and the calf and the young lion and the fatling together; and a little child shall lead them. ^7And the cow and the bear shall feed; their young ones shall lie down together; and the lion shall eat straw like the ox. ^8And the sucking child shall play on the hole of the asp, and the weaned child shall put his hand on the adder's den. ^9They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain; for the earth shall be full of the knowledge of Jehovah, as the waters cover the sea. ^10And it shall come to pass in that day, that the root of Jesse, that standeth for an ensign of the peoples, unto him shall the nations seek; and his resting-place shall be glorious. ^11And it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord will set his hand again the second time to recover the remnant of his people, that shall remain, from Assyria, and from Egypt, and from Pathros, and from Cush, and from Elam, and from Shinar, and from Hamath, and from the islands of the sea. ^12And he will set up an ensign for the nations, and will assemble the outcasts of Israel, and gather together the dispersed of Judah from the four corners of the earth. ^13The envy also of Ephraim shall depart, and they that vex Judah shall be cut off: Ephraim shall not envy Judah, and Judah shall not vex Ephraim. ^14And they shall fly down upon the shoulder of the Philistines on the west; together shall they despoil the children of the east: they shall put forth their hand upon Edom and Moab; and the children of Ammon shall obey them. ^15And Jehovah will utterly destroy the tongue of the Egyptian sea; and with his scorching wind will he wave his hand over the River, and will smite it into seven streams, and cause men to march over dryshod. ^16And there shall be a highway for the remnant of his people, that shall remain, from Assyria; like as there was for Israel in the day that he came up out of the land of Egypt.

Isaiah 13

13

^1The burden of Babylon, which Isaiah the son of Amoz did see. ^2Set ye up an ensign upon the bare mountain, lift up the voice unto them, wave the hand, that they may go into the gates of the nobles. ^3I have commanded my consecrated ones, yea, I have called my mighty men for mine anger, even my proudly exulting ones. ^4The noise of a multitude in the mountains, as of a great people! the noise of a tumult of the kingdoms of the nations gathered together! Jehovah of hosts is mustering the host for the battle. ^5They come from a far country, from the uttermost part of heaven, even Jehovah, and the weapons of his indignation, to destroy the whole land. ^6Wail ye; for the day of Jehovah is at hand; as destruction from the Almighty shall it come. ^7Therefore shall all hands be feeble, and every heart of man shall melt: ^8and they shall be dismayed; pangs and sorrows shall take hold of them; they shall be in pain as a woman in travail: they shall look in amazement one at another; their faces shall be faces of flame. ^9Behold, the day of Jehovah cometh, cruel, with wrath and fierce anger; to make the land a desolation, and to destroy the sinners thereof out of it. ^10For the stars of heaven and the constellations thereof shall not give their light; the sun shall be darkened in its going forth, and the moon shall not cause its light to shine. ^11And I will punish the world for their evil, and the wicked for their iniquity: and I will cause the arrogancy of the proud to cease, and will lay low the haughtiness of the terrible. ^12I will make a man more rare than fine gold, even a man than the pure gold of Ophir. ^13Therefore I will make the heavens to tremble, and the earth shall be shaken out of its place, in the wrath of Jehovah of hosts, and in the day of his fierce anger. ^14And it shall come to pass, that as the chased roe, and as sheep that no man gathereth, they shall turn every man to his own people, and shall flee every man to his own land. ^15Every one that is found shall be thrust through; and every one that is taken shall fall by the sword. ^16Their infants also shall be dashed in pieces before their eyes; their houses shall be rifled, and their wives ravished. ^17Behold, I will stir up the Medes against them, who shall not regard silver, and as for gold, they shall not delight in it. ^18And their bows shall dash the young men in pieces; and they shall have no pity on the fruit of the womb; their eye shall not spare children. ^19And Babylon, the glory of kingdoms, the beauty of the Chaldeans' pride, shall be as when God overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah. ^20It shall never be inhabited, neither shall it be dwelt in from generation to generation: neither shall the Arabian pitch tent there; neither shall shepherds make their flocks to lie down there. ^21But wild beasts of the desert shall lie there; and their houses shall be full of doleful creatures; and ostriches shall dwell there, and wild goats shall dance there. ^22And wolves shall cry in their castles, and jackals in the pleasant palaces: and her time is near to come, and her days shall not be prolonged.

Isaiah 14

14

^1For Jehovah will have compassion on Jacob, and will yet choose Israel, and set them in their own land: and the sojourner shall join himself with them, and they shall cleave to the house of Jacob. ^2And the peoples shall take them, and bring them to their place; and the house of Israel shall possess them in the land of Jehovah for servants and for handmaids: and they shall take them captive whose captives they were; and they shall rule over their oppressors. ^3And it shall come to pass in the day that Jehovah shall give thee rest from thy sorrow, and from thy trouble, and from the hard service wherein thou wast made to serve, ^4that thou shalt take up this parable against the king of Babylon, and say, How hath the oppressor ceased! the golden city ceased! ^5Jehovah hath broken the staff of the wicked, the sceptre of the rulers; ^6that smote the peoples in wrath with a continual stroke, that ruled the nations in anger, with a persecution that none restrained. ^7The whole earth is at rest, and is quiet: they break forth into singing. ^8Yea, the fir-trees rejoice at thee, and the cedars of Lebanon, saying, Since thou art laid low, no hewer is come up against us. ^9Sheol from beneath is moved for thee to meet thee at thy coming; it stirreth up the dead for thee, even all the chief ones of the earth; it hath raised up from their thrones all the kings of the nations. ^10All they shall answer and say unto thee, Art thou also become weak as we? art thou become like unto us? ^11Thy pomp is brought down to Sheol, and the noise of thy viols: the worm is spread under thee, and worms cover thee. ^12How art thou fallen from heaven, O day-star, son of the morning! how art thou cut down to the ground, that didst lay low the nations! ^13And thou saidst in thy heart, I will ascend into heaven, I will exalt my throne above the stars of God; and I will sit upon the mount of congregation, in the uttermost parts of the north; ^14I will ascend above the heights of the clouds; I will make myself like the Most High. ^15Yet thou shalt be brought down to Sheol, to the uttermost parts of the pit. ^16They that see thee shall gaze at thee, they shall consider thee, saying, Is this the man that made the earth to tremble, that did shake kingdoms; ^17that made the world as a wilderness, and overthrew the cities thereof; that let not loose his prisoners to their home? ^18All the kings of the nations, all of them, sleep in glory, every one in his own house. ^19But thou art cast forth away from thy sepulchre like an abominable branch, clothed with the slain, that are thrust through with the sword, that go down to the stones of the pit; as a dead body trodden under foot. ^20Thou shalt not be joined with them in burial, because thou hast destroyed thy land, thou hast slain thy people; the seed of evil-doers shall not be named for ever. ^21Prepare ye slaughter for his children for the iniquity of their fathers, that they rise not up, and possess the earth, and fill the face of the world with cities. ^22And I will rise up against them, saith Jehovah of hosts, and cut off from Babylon name and remnant, and son and son's son, saith Jehovah. ^23I will also make it a possession for the porcupine, and pools of water: and I will sweep it with the besom of destruction, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^24Jehovah of hosts hath sworn, saying, Surely, as I have thought, so shall it come to pass; and as I have purposed, so shall it stand: ^25that I will break the Assyrian in my land, and upon my mountains tread him under foot: then shall his yoke depart from off them, and his burden depart from off their shoulder. ^26This is the purpose that is purposed upon the whole earth; and this is the hand that is stretched out upon all the nations. ^27For Jehovah of hosts hath purposed, and who shall annul it? and his hand is stretched out, and who shall turn it back? ^28In the year that king Ahaz died was this burden. ^29Rejoice not, O Philistia, all of thee, because the rod that smote thee is broken; for out of the serpent's root shall come forth an adder, and his fruit shall be a fiery flying serpent. ^30And the first-born of the poor shall feed, and the needy shall lie down in safety; and I will kill thy root with famine, and thy remnant shall be slain. ^31Howl, O gate; cry, O city; thou art melted away, O Philistia, all of thee; for there cometh a smoke out of the north, and there is no straggler in his ranks. ^32What then shall one answer the messengers of the nation? That Jehovah hath founded Zion, and in her shall the afflicted of his people take refuge.

Isaiah 15

15

^1The burden of Moab. For in a night Ar of Moab is laid waste, and brought to nought; for in a night Kir of Moab is laid waste, and brought to nought. ^2They are gone up to Bayith, and to Dibon, to the high places, to weep: Moab waileth over Nebo, and over Medeba; on all their heads is baldness, every beard is cut off. ^3In their streets they gird themselves with sackcloth; on their housetops, and in their broad places, every one waileth, weeping abundantly. ^4And Heshbon crieth out, and Elealeh; their voice is heard even unto Jahaz: therefore the armed men of Moab cry aloud; his soul trembleth within him. ^5My heart crieth out for Moab; her nobles flee unto Zoar, to Eglath-shelishi-yah: for by the ascent of Luhith with weeping they go up; for in the way of Horonaim they raise up a cry of destruction. ^6For the waters of Nimrim shall be desolate; for the grass is withered away, the tender grass faileth, there is no green thing. ^7Therefore the abundance they have gotten, and that which they have laid up, shall they carry away over the brook of the willows. ^8For the cry is gone round about the borders of Moab; the wailing thereof unto Eglaim, and the wailing thereof unto Beer-elim. ^9For the waters of Dimon are full of blood; for I will bring yet more upon Dimon, a lion upon them of Moab that escape, and upon the remnant of the land.

Isaiah 16

16

^1Send ye the lambs for the ruler of the land from Selah to the wilderness, unto the mount of the daughter of Zion. ^2For it shall be that, as wandering birds, as a scattered nest, so shall the daughters of Moab be at the fords of the Arnon. ^3Give counsel, execute justice; make thy shade as the night in the midst of the noonday; hide the outcasts; betray not the fugitive. ^4Let mine outcasts dwell with thee; as for Moab, be thou a covert to him from the face of the destroyer. For the extortioner is brought to nought, destruction ceaseth, the oppressors are consumed out of the land. ^5And a throne shall be established in lovingkindness; and one shall sit thereon in truth, in the tent of David, judging, and seeking justice, and swift to do righteousness. ^6We have heard of the pride of Moab, that he is very proud; even of his arrogancy, and his pride, and his wrath; his boastings are nought. ^7Therefore shall Moab wail for Moab, every one shall wail: for the raisin-cakes of Kir-hareseth shall ye mourn, utterly stricken. ^8For the fields of Heshbon languish, and the vine of Sibmah; the lords of the nations have broken down the choice branches thereof, which reached even unto Jazer, which wandered into the wilderness; its shoots were spread abroad, they passed over the sea. ^9Therefore I will weep with the weeping of Jazer for the vine of Sibmah; I will water thee with my tears, O Heshbon, and Elealeh: for upon thy summer fruits and upon thy harvest the battle shout is fallen. ^10And gladness is taken away, and joy out of the fruitful field; and in the vineyards there shall be no singing, neither joyful noise: no treader shall tread out wine in the presses; I have made the vintage shout to cease. ^11Wherefore my heart soundeth like a harp for Moab, and mine inward parts for Kir-heres. ^12And it shall come to pass, when Moab presenteth himself, when he wearieth himself upon the high place, and shall come to his sanctuary to pray, that he shall not prevail. ^13This is the word that Jehovah spake concerning Moab in time past. ^14But now Jehovah hath spoken, saying, Within three years, as the years of a hireling, the glory of Moab shall be brought into contempt, with all his great multitude; and the remnant shall be very small and of no account.

Isaiah 17

17

^1The burden of Damascus. Behold, Damascus is taken away from being a city, and it shall be a ruinous heap. ^2The cities of Aroer are forsaken; they shall be for flocks, which shall lie down, and none shall make them afraid. ^3And the fortress shall cease from Ephraim, and the kingdom from Damascus, and the remnant of Syria; they shall be as the glory of the children of Israel, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^4And it shall come to pass in that day, that the glory of Jacob shall be made thin, and the fatness of his flesh shall wax lean. ^5And it shall be as when the harvestman gathereth the standing grain, and his arm reapeth the ears; yea, it shall be as when one gleaneth ears in the valley of Rephaim. ^6Yet there shall be left therein gleanings, as the shaking of an olive-tree, two or three berries in the top of the uppermost bough, four or five in the outmost branches of a fruitful tree, saith Jehovah, the God of Israel. ^7In that day shall men look unto their Maker, and their eyes shall have respect to the Holy One of Israel. ^8And they shall not look to the altars, the work of their hands; neither shall they have respect to that which their fingers have made, either the Asherim, or the sun-images. ^9In that day shall their strong cities be as the forsaken places in the wood and on the mountain top, which were forsaken from before the children of Israel; and it shall be a desolation. ^10For thou hast forgotten the God of thy salvation, and hast not been mindful of the rock of thy strength; therefore thou plantest pleasant plants, and settest it with strange slips. ^11In the day of thy planting thou hedgest it in, and in the morning thou makest thy seed to blossom; but the harvest fleeth away in the day of grief and of desperate sorrow. ^12Ah, the uproar of many peoples, that roar like the roaring of the seas; and the rushing of nations, that rush like the rushing of mighty waters! ^13The nations shall rush like the rushing of many waters: but he shall rebuke them, and they shall flee far off, and shall be chased as the chaff of the mountains before the wind, and like the whirling dust before the storm. ^14At eventide, behold, terror; and before the morning they are not. This is the portion of them that despoil us, and the lot of them that rob us.

Isaiah 19

19

^1The burden of Egypt. Behold, Jehovah rideth upon a swift cloud, and cometh unto Egypt: and the idols of Egypt shall tremble at his presence; and the heart of Egypt shall melt in the midst of it. ^2And I will stir up the Egyptians against the Egyptians: and they shall fight every one against his brother, and every one against his neighbor; city against city, and kingdom against kingdom. ^3And the spirit of Egypt shall fail in the midst of it; and I will destroy the counsel thereof: and they shall seek unto the idols, and to the charmers, and to them that have familiar spirits, and to the wizards. ^4And I will give over the Egyptians into the hand of a cruel lord; and a fierce king shall rule over them, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts. ^5And the waters shall fail from the sea, and the river shall be wasted and become dry. ^6And the rivers shall become foul; the streams of Egypt shall be diminished and dried up; the reeds and flags shall wither away. ^7The meadows by the Nile, by the brink of the Nile, and all the sown fields of the Nile, shall become dry, be driven away, and be no more. ^8And the fishers shall lament, and all they that cast angle into the Nile shall mourn, and they that spread nets upon the waters shall languish. ^9Moreover they that work in combed flax, and they that weave white cloth, shall be confounded. ^10And the pillars of Egypt shall be broken in pieces; all they that work for hire shall be grieved in soul. ^11The princes of Zoan are utterly foolish; the counsel of the wisest counsellors of Pharaoh is become brutish: how say ye unto Pharaoh, I am the son of the wise, the son of ancient kings? ^12Where then are thy wise men? and let them tell thee now; and let them know what Jehovah of hosts hath purposed concerning Egypt. ^13The princes of Zoan are become fools, the princes of Memphis are deceived; they have caused Egypt to go astray, that are the corner-stone of her tribes. ^14Jehovah hath mingled a spirit of perverseness in the midst of her; and they have caused Egypt to go astray in every work thereof, as a drunken man staggereth in his vomit. ^15Neither shall there be for Egypt any work, which head or tail, palm-branch or rush, may do. ^16In that day shall the Egyptians be like unto women; and they shall tremble and fear because of the shaking of the hand of Jehovah of hosts, which he shaketh over them. ^17And the land of Judah shall become a terror unto Egypt; every one to whom mention is made thereof shall be afraid, because of the purpose of Jehovah of hosts, which he purposeth against it. ^18In that day there shall be five cities in the land of Egypt that speak the language of Canaan, and swear to Jehovah of hosts; one shall be called The city of destruction. ^19In that day shall there be an altar to Jehovah in the midst of the land of Egypt, and a pillar at the border thereof to Jehovah. ^20And it shall be for a sign and for a witness unto Jehovah of hosts in the land of Egypt; for they shall cry unto Jehovah because of oppressors, and he will send them a saviour, and a defender, and he will deliver them. ^21And Jehovah shall be known to Egypt, and the Egyptians shall know Jehovah in that day; yea, they shall worship with sacrifice and oblation, and shall vow a vow unto Jehovah, and shall perform it. ^22And Jehovah will smite Egypt, smiting and healing; and they shall return unto Jehovah, and he will be entreated of them, and will heal them. ^23In that day shall there be a highway out of Egypt to Assyria, and the Assyrian shall come into Egypt, and the Egyptian into Assyria; and the Egyptians shall worship with the Assyrians. ^24In that day shall Israel be the third with Egypt and with Assyria, a blessing in the midst of the earth; ^25for that Jehovah of hosts hath blessed them, saying, Blessed be Egypt my people, and Assyria the work of my hands, and Israel mine inheritance.

Isaiah 21

21

^1The burden of the wilderness of the sea. As whirlwinds in the South sweep through, it cometh from the wilderness, from a terrible land. ^2A grievous vision is declared unto me; the treacherous man dealeth treacherously, and the destroyer destroyeth. Go up, O Elam; besiege, O Media; all the sighing thereof have I made to cease. ^3Therefore are my loins filled with anguish; pangs have taken hold upon me, as the pangs of a woman in travail: I am pained so that I cannot hear; I am dismayed so that I cannot see. ^4My heart fluttereth, horror hath affrighted me; the twilight that I desired hath been turned into trembling unto me. ^5They prepare the table, they set the watch, they eat, they drink: rise up, ye princes, anoint the shield. ^6For thus hath the Lord said unto me, Go, set a watchman: let him declare what he seeth: ^7and when he seeth a troop, horsemen in pairs, a troop of asses, a troop of camels, he shall hearken diligently with much heed. ^8And he cried as a lion: O Lord, I stand continually upon the watch-tower in the day-time, and am set in my ward whole nights; ^9and, behold, here cometh a troop of men, horsemen in pairs. And he answered and said, Fallen, fallen is Babylon; and all the graven images of her gods are broken unto the ground. ^10O thou my threshing, and the grain of my floor! that which I have heard from Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, have I declared unto you. ^11The burden of Dumah. One calleth unto me out of Seir, Watchman, what of the night? Watchman, what of the night? ^12The watchman said, The morning cometh, and also the night: if ye will inquire, inquire ye: turn ye, come. ^13The burden upon Arabia. In the forest in Arabia shall ye lodge, O ye caravans of Dedanites. ^14Unto him that was thirsty they brought water; the inhabitants of the land of Tema did meet the fugitives with their bread. ^15For they fled away from the swords, from the drawn sword, and from the bent bow, and from the grievousness of war. ^16For thus hath the Lord said unto me, Within a year, according to the years of a hireling, all the glory of Kedar shall fail; ^17and the residue of the number of the archers, the mighty men of the children of Kedar, shall be few; for Jehovah, the God of Israel, hath spoken it.

Isaiah 22

22

^1The burden of the valley of vision. What aileth thee now, that thou art wholly gone up to the housetops? ^2O thou that art full of shoutings, a tumultuous city, a joyous town; thy slain are not slain with the sword, neither are they dead in battle. ^3All thy rulers fled away together, they were bound by the archers; all that were found of thee were bound together; they fled afar off. ^4Therefore said I, Look away from me, I will weep bitterly; labor not to comfort me for the destruction of the daughter of my people. ^5For it is a day of discomfiture, and of treading down, and of perplexity, from the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, in the valley of vision; a breaking down of the walls, and a crying to the mountains. ^6And Elam bare the quiver, with chariots of men and horsemen; and Kir uncovered the shield. ^7And it came to pass, that thy choicest valleys were full of chariots, and the horsemen set themselves in array at the gate. ^8And he took away the covering of Judah; and thou didst look in that day to the armor in the house of the forest. ^9And ye saw the breaches of the city of David, that they were many; and ye gathered together the waters of the lower pool; ^10and ye numbered the houses of Jerusalem, and ye brake down the houses to fortify the wall; ^11ye made also a reservoir between the two walls for the water of the old pool. But ye looked not unto him that had done this, neither had ye respect unto him that purposed it long ago. ^12And in that day did the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, call to weeping, and to mourning, and to baldness, and to girding with sackcloth: ^13and behold, joy and gladness, slaying oxen and killing sheep, eating flesh and drinking wine: let us eat and drink, for to-morrow we shall die. ^14And Jehovah of hosts revealed himself in mine ears, Surely this iniquity shall not be forgiven you till ye die, saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts. ^15Thus saith the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, Go, get thee unto this treasurer, even unto Shebna, who is over the house, and say, ^16What doest thou here? and whom has thou here, that thou hast hewed thee out here a sepulchre? hewing him out a sepulchre on high, graving a habitation for himself in the rock! ^17Behold, Jehovah, like a strong man, will hurl thee away violently; yea, he will wrap thee up closely. ^18He will surely wind thee round and round, and toss thee like a ball into a large country; there shalt thou die, and there shall be the chariots of thy glory, thou shame of thy lord's house. ^19And I will thrust thee from thine office; and from thy station shalt thou be pulled down. ^20And it shall come to pass in that day, that I will call my servant Eliakim the son of Hilkiah: ^21and I will cloth him with thy robe, and strengthen him with thy girdle, and I will commit thy government into his hand; and he shall be a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and to the house of Judah. ^22And the key of the house of David will I lay upon his shoulder; and he shall open, and none shall shut; and he shall shut, and none shall open. ^23And I will fasten him as a nail in a sure place; and he shall be for a throne of glory to his father's house. ^24And they shall hang upon him all the glory of his father's house, the offspring and the issue, every small vessel, from the cups even to all the flagons. ^25In that day, saith Jehovah of hosts, shall the nail that was fastened in a sure place give way; and it shall be hewn down, and fall; and the burden that was upon it shall be cut off; for Jehovah hath spoken it.

Isaiah 23

23

^1The burden of Tyre. Howl, ye ships of Tarshish; for it is laid waste, so that there is no house, no entering in: from the land of Kittim it is revealed to them. ^2Be still, ye inhabitants of the coast, thou whom the merchants of Sidon, that pass over the sea, have replenished. ^3And on great waters the seed of the Shihor, the harvest of the Nile, was her revenue; and she was the mart of nations. ^4Be thou ashamed, O Sidon; for the sea hath spoken, the stronghold of the sea, saying, I have not travailed, nor brought forth, neither have I nourished young men, nor brought up virgins. ^5When the report cometh to Egypt, they shall be sorely pained at the report of Tyre. ^6Pass ye over to Tarshish; wail, ye inhabitants of the coast. ^7Is this your joyous city, whose antiquity is of ancient days, whose feet carried her afar off to sojourn? ^8Who hath purposed this against Tyre, the bestower of crowns, whose merchants are princes, whose traffickers are the honorable of the earth? ^9Jehovah of hosts hath purposed it, to stain the pride of all glory, to bring into contempt all the honorable of the earth. ^10Pass through thy land as the Nile, O daughter of Tarshish; there is no restraint any more. ^11He hath stretched out his hand over the sea, he hath shaken the kingdoms: Jehovah hath given commandment concerning Canaan, to destroy the strongholds thereof. ^12And he said, Thou shalt no more rejoice, O thou oppressed virgin daughter of Sidon: arise, pass over to Kittim; even there shalt thou have no rest. ^13Behold, the land of the Chaldeans: this people was not; the Assyrian founded it for them that dwell in the wilderness; they set up their towers; they overthrew the palaces thereof; they made it a ruin. ^14Howl, ye ships of Tarshish; for your stronghold is laid waste. ^15And it shall come to pass in that day, that Tyre shall be forgotten seventy years, according to the days of one king: after the end of seventy years it shall be unto Tyre as in the song of the harlot. ^16Take a harp, go about the city, thou harlot that hast been forgotten; make sweet melody, sing many songs, that thou mayest be remembered. ^17And it shall come to pass after the end of seventy years, that Jehovah will visit Tyre, and she shall return to her hire, and shall play the harlot with all the kingdoms of the world upon the face of the earth. ^18And her merchandise and her hire shall be holiness to Jehovah: it shall not be treasured nor laid up; for her merchandise shall be for them that dwell before Jehovah, to eat sufficiently, and for durable clothing.

Isaiah 24

24

^1Behold, Jehovah maketh the earth empty, and maketh it waste, and turneth it upside down, and scattereth abroad the inhabitants thereof. ^2And it shall be, as with the people, so with the priest; as with the servant, so with his master; as with the maid, so with her mistress; as with the buyer, so with the seller; as with the creditor, so with the debtor; as with the taker of interest, so with the giver of interest to him. ^3The earth shall be utterly emptied, and utterly laid waste; for Jehovah hath spoken this word. ^4The earth mourneth and fadeth away, the world languisheth and fadeth away, the lofty people of the earth do languish. ^5The earth also is polluted under the inhabitants thereof; because they have transgressed the laws, violated the statutes, broken the everlasting covenant. ^6Therefore hath the curse devoured the earth, and they that dwell therein are found guilty: therefore the inhabitants of the earth are burned, and few men left. ^7The new wine mourneth, the vine languisheth, all the merry-hearted do sigh. ^8The mirth of tabrets ceaseth, the noise of them that rejoice endeth, the joy of the harp ceaseth. ^9They shall not drink wine with a song; strong drink shall be bitter to them that drink it. ^10The waste city is broken down; every house is shut up, that no man may come in. ^11There is a crying in the streets because of the wine; all joy is darkened, the mirth of the land is gone. ^12In the city is left desolation, and the gate is smitten with destruction. ^13For thus shall it be in the midst of the earth among the peoples, as the shaking of an olive-tree, as the gleanings when the vintage is done. ^14These shall lift up their voice, they shall shout; for the majesty of Jehovah they cry aloud from the sea. ^15Wherefore glorify ye Jehovah in the east, even the name of Jehovah, the God of Israel, in the isles of the sea. ^16From the uttermost part of the earth have we heard songs: Glory to the righteous. But I said, I pine away, I pine away, woe is me! the treacherous have dealt treacherously; yea, the treacherous have dealt very treacherously. ^17Fear, and the pit, and the snare, are upon thee, O inhabitant of the earth. ^18And it shall come to pass, that he who fleeth from the noise of the fear shall fall into the pit; and he that cometh up out of the midst of the pit shall be taken in the snare: for the windows on high are opened, and the foundations of the earth tremble. ^19The earth is utterly broken, the earth is rent asunder, the earth is shaken violently. ^20The earth shall stagger like a drunken man, and shall sway to and fro like a hammock; and the transgression thereof shall be heavy upon it, and it shall fall, and not rise again. ^21And it shall come to pass in that day, that Jehovah will punish the host of the high ones on high, and the kings of the earth upon the earth. ^22And they shall be gathered together, as prisoners are gathered in the pit, and shall be shut up in the prison; and after many days shall they be visited. ^23Then the moon shall be confounded, and the sun ashamed; for Jehovah of hosts will reign in mount Zion, and in Jerusalem; and before his elders shall be glory.

Isaiah 25

25

^1O Jehovah, thou art my God; I will exalt thee, I will praise thy name; for thou hast done wonderful things, even counsels of old, in faithfulness and truth. ^2For thou hast made of a city a heap, of a fortified city a ruin, a palace of strangers to be no city; it shall never be built. ^3Therefore shall a strong people glorify thee; a city of terrible nations shall fear thee. ^4For thou hast been a stronghold to the poor, a stronghold to the needy in his distress, a refuge from the storm, a shade from the heat, when the blast of the terrible ones is as a storm against the wall. ^5As the heat in a dry place wilt thou bring down the noise of strangers; as the heat by the shade of a cloud, the song of the terrible ones shall be brought low. ^6And in this mountain will Jehovah of hosts make unto all peoples a feast of fat things, a feast of wines on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of wines on the lees well refined. ^7And he will destroy in this mountain the face of the covering that covereth all peoples, and the veil that is spread over all nations. ^8He hath swallowed up death for ever; and the Lord Jehovah will wipe away tears from off all faces; and the reproach of his people will he take away from off all the earth: for Jehovah hath spoken it. ^9And it shall be said in that day, Lo, this is our God; we have waited for him, and he will save us: this is Jehovah; we have waited for him, we will be glad and rejoice in his salvation. ^10For in this mountain will the hand of Jehovah rest; and Moab shall be trodden down in his place, even as straw is trodden down in the water of the dung-hill. ^11And he shall spread forth his hands in the midst thereof, as he that swimmeth spreadeth forth his hands to swim; but Jehovah will lay low his pride together with the craft of his hands. ^12And the high fortress of thy walls hath he brought down, laid low, and brought to the ground, even to the dust.

Isaiah 26

26

^1In that day shall this song be sung in the land of Judah: we have a strong city; salvation will he appoint for walls and bulwarks. ^2Open ye the gates, that the righteous nation which keepeth faith may enter in. ^3Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace, whose mind is stayed on thee; because he trusteth in thee. ^4Trust ye in Jehovah for ever; for in Jehovah, even Jehovah, is an everlasting rock. ^5For he hath brought down them that dwell on high, the lofty city: he layeth it low, he layeth it low even to the ground; he bringeth it even to the dust. ^6The foot shall tread it down; even the feet of the poor, and the steps of the needy. ^7The way of the just is uprightness: thou that art upright dost direct the path of the just. ^8Yea, in the way of thy judgments, O Jehovah, have we waited for thee; to thy name, even to thy memorial name, is the desire of our soul. ^9With my soul have I desired thee in the night; yea, with my spirit within me will I seek thee earnestly: for when thy judgments are in the earth, the inhabitants of the world learn righteousness. ^10Let favor be showed to the wicked, yet will he not learn righteousness; in the land of uprightness will he deal wrongfully, and will not behold the majesty of Jehovah. ^11Jehovah, thy hand is lifted up, yet they see not: but they shall see thy zeal for the people, and be put to shame; yea, fire shall devour thine adversaries. ^12Jehovah, thou wilt ordain peace for us; for thou hast also wrought all our works for us. ^13O Jehovah our God, other lords besides thee have had dominion over us; but by thee only will we make mention of thy name. ^14They are dead, they shall not live; they are deceased, they shall not rise: therefore hast thou visited and destroyed them, and made all remembrance of them to perish. ^15Thou hast increased the nation, O Jehovah, thou hast increased the nation; thou art glorified; thou hast enlarged all the borders of the land. ^16Jehovah, in trouble have they visited thee; they poured out a prayer when thy chastening was upon them. ^17Like as a woman with child, that draweth near the time of her delivery, is in pain and crieth out in her pangs; so we have been before thee, O Jehovah. ^18We have been with child, we have been in pain, we have as it were brought forth wind; we have not wrought any deliverance in the earth; neither have the inhabitants of the world fallen. ^19Thy dead shall live; my dead bodies shall arise. Awake and sing, ye that dwell in the dust; for thy dew is as the dew of herbs, and the earth shall cast forth the dead. ^20Come, my people, enter thou into thy chambers, and shut thy doors about thee: hide thyself for a little moment, until the indignation be overpast. ^21For, behold, Jehovah cometh forth out of his place to punish the inhabitants of the earth for their iniquity: the earth also shall disclose her blood, and shall no more cover her slain.

Isaiah 28

28

^1Woe to the crown of pride of the drunkards of Ephraim, and to the fading flower of his glorious beauty, which is on the head of the fat valley of them that are overcome with wine! ^2Behold, the Lord hath a mighty and strong one; as a tempest of hail, a destroying storm, as a tempest of mighty waters overflowing, will he cast down to the earth with the hand. ^3The crown of pride of the drunkards of Ephraim shall be trodden under foot: ^4and the fading flower of his glorious beauty, which is on the head of the fat valley, shall be as the first-ripe fig before the summer; which when he that looketh upon it seeth, while it is yet in his hand he eateth it up. ^5In that day will Jehovah of hosts become a crown of glory, and a diadem of beauty, unto the residue of his people; ^6and a spirit of justice to him that sitteth in judgment, and strength to them that turn back the battle at the gate. ^7And even these reel with wine, and stagger with strong drink; the priest and the prophet reel with strong drink, they are swallowed up of wine, they stagger with strong drink; they err in vision, they stumble in judgment. ^8For all tables are full of vomit and filthiness, so that there is no place clean. ^9Whom will he teach knowledge? and whom will he make to understand the message? them that are weaned from the milk, and drawn from the breasts? ^10For it is precept upon precept, precept upon precept; line upon line, line upon line; here a little, there a little. ^11Nay, but by men of strange lips and with another tongue will he speak to this people; ^12to whom he said, This is the rest, give ye rest to him that is weary; and this is the refreshing: yet they would not hear. ^13Therefore shall the word of Jehovah be unto them precept upon precept, precept upon precept; line upon line, line upon line; here a little, there a little; that they may go, and fall backward, and be broken, and snared, and taken. ^14Wherefore hear the word of Jehovah, ye scoffers, that rule this people that is in Jerusalem: ^15Because ye have said, We have made a covenant with death, and with Sheol are we at agreement; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, it shall not come unto us; for we have made lies our refuge, and under falsehood have we hid ourselves: ^16therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Behold, I lay in Zion for a foundation a stone, a tried stone, a precious corner -stone of sure foundation: he that believeth shall not be in haste. ^17And I will make justice the line, and righteousness the plummet; and the hail shall sweep away the refuge of lies, and the waters shall overflow the hiding-place. ^18And your covenant with death shall be annulled, and your agreement with Sheol shall not stand; when the overflowing scourge shall pass through, then ye shall be trodden down by it. ^19As often as it passeth through, it shall take you; for morning by morning shall it pass through, by day and by night: and it shall be nought but terror to understand the message. ^20For the bed is shorter than that a man can stretch himself on it; and the covering narrower than that he can wrap himself in it. ^21For Jehovah will rise up as in mount Perazim, he will be wroth as in the valley of Gibeon; that he may do his work, his strange work, and bring to pass his act, his strange act. ^22Now therefore be ye not scoffers, lest your bonds be made strong; for a decree of destruction have I heard from the Lord, Jehovah of hosts, upon the whole earth. ^23Give ye ear, and hear my voice; hearken, and hear my speech. ^24Doth he that ploweth to sow plow continually? doth he continually open and harrow his ground? ^25When he hath levelled the face thereof, doth he not cast abroad the fitches, and scatter the cummin, and put in the wheat in rows, and the barley in the appointed place, and the spelt in the border thereof? ^26For his God doth instruct him aright, and doth teach him. ^27For the fitches are not threshed with a sharp threshing instrument, neither is a cart wheel turned about upon the cummin; but the fitches are beaten out with a staff, and the cummin with a rod. ^28Bread grain is ground; for he will not be always threshing it: and though the wheel of his cart and his horses scatter it, he doth not grind it. ^29This also cometh forth from Jehovah of hosts, who is wonderful in counsel, and excellent in wisdom.

Isaiah 29

29

^1Ho Ariel, Ariel, the city where David encamped! add ye year to year; let the feasts come round: ^2then will I distress Ariel, and there shall be mourning and lamentation; and she shall be unto me as Ariel. ^3And I will encamp against thee round about, and will lay siege against thee with posted troops, and I will raise siege works against thee. ^4And thou shalt be brought down, and shalt speak out of the ground, and thy speech shall be low out of the dust; and thy voice shall be as of one that hath a familiar spirit, out of the ground, and thy speech shall whisper out of the dust. ^5But the multitude of thy foes shall be like small dust, and the multitude of the terrible ones as chaff that passeth away: yea, it shall be in an instant suddenly. ^6She shall be visited of Jehovah of hosts with thunder, and with earthquake, and great noise, with whirlwind and tempest, and the flame of a devouring fire. ^7And the multitude of all the nations that fight against Ariel, even all that fight against her and her stronghold, and that distress her, shall be as a dream, a vision of the night. ^8And it shall be as when a hungry man dreameth, and, behold, he eateth; but he awaketh, and his soul is empty: or as when a thirsty man dreameth, and, behold, he drinketh; but he awaketh, and, behold, he is faint, and his soul hath appetite: so shall the multitude of all the nations be, that fight against mount Zion. ^9Tarry ye and wonder; take your pleasure and be blind: they are drunken, but not with wine; they stagger, but not with strong drink. ^10For Jehovah hath poured out upon you the spirit of deep sleep, and hath closed your eyes, the prophets; and your heads, the seers, hath he covered. ^11And all vision is become unto you as the words of a book that is sealed, which men deliver to one that is learned, saying, Read this, I pray thee; and he saith, I cannot, for it is sealed: ^12and the book is delivered to him that is not learned, saying, Read this, I pray thee; and he saith, I am not learned. ^13And the Lord said, Forasmuch as this people draw nigh unto me, and with their mouth and with their lips to honor me, but have removed their heart far from me, and their fear of me is a commandment of men which hath been taught them; ^14therefore, behold, I will proceed to do a marvellous work among this people, even a marvellous work and a wonder; and the wisdom of their wise men shall perish, and the understanding of their prudent men shall be hid. ^15Woe unto them that hide deep their counsel from Jehovah, and whose works are in the dark, and that say, Who seeth us? and who knoweth us? ^16Ye turn things upside down! Shall the potter be esteemed as clay; that the thing made should say of him that made it, He made me not; or the thing formed say of him that formed it, He hath no understanding? ^17Is it not yet a very little while, and Lebanon shall be turned into a fruitful field, and the fruitful field shall be esteemed as a forest? ^18And in that day shall the deaf hear the words of the book, and the eyes of the blind shall see out of obscurity and out of darkness. ^19The meek also shall increase their joy in Jehovah, and the poor among men shall rejoice in the Holy One of Israel. ^20For the terrible one is brought to nought, and the scoffer ceaseth, and all they that watch for iniquity are cut off; ^21that make a man an offender in his cause, and lay a snare for him that reproveth in the gate, and turn aside the just with a thing of nought. ^22Therefore thus saith Jehovah, who redeemed Abraham, concerning the house of Jacob: Jacob shall not now be ashamed, neither shall his face now wax pale. ^23But when he seeth his children, the work of my hands, in the midst of him, they shall sanctify my name; yea, they shall sanctify the Holy One of Jacob, and shall stand in awe of the God of Israel. ^24They also that err in spirit shall come to understanding, and they that murmur shall receive instruction.

Isaiah 30

30

^1Woe to the rebellious children, saith Jehovah, that take counsel, but not of me; and that make a league, but not of my Spirit, that they may add sin to sin, ^2that set out to go down into Egypt, and have not asked at my mouth; to strengthen themselves in the strength of Pharaoh, and to take refuge in the shadow of Egypt! ^3Therefore shall the strength of Pharaoh be your shame, and the refuge in the shadow of Egypt your confusion. ^4For their princes are at Zoan, and their ambassadors are come to Hanes. ^5They shall all be ashamed because of a people that cannot profit them, that are not a help nor profit, but a shame, and also a reproach. ^6The burden of the beasts of the South. Through the land of trouble and anguish, from whence come the lioness and the lion, the viper and fiery flying serpent, they carry their riches upon the shoulders of young asses, and their treasures upon the humps of camels, to a people that shall not profit them. ^7For Egypt helpeth in vain, and to no purpose: therefore have I called her Rahab that sitteth still. ^8Now go, write it before them on a tablet, and inscribe it in a book, that it may be for the time to come for ever and ever. ^9For it is a rebellious people, lying children, children that will not hear the law of Jehovah; ^10that say to the seers, See not; and to the prophets, Prophesy not unto us right things, speak unto us smooth things, prophesy deceits, ^11get you out of the way, turn aside out of the path, cause the Holy One of Israel to cease from before us. ^12Wherefore thus saith the Holy One of Israel, Because ye despise this word, and trust in oppression and perverseness, and rely thereon; ^13therefore this iniquity shall be to you as a breach ready to fall, swelling out in a high wall, whose breaking cometh suddenly in an instant. ^14And he shall break it as a potter's vessel is broken, breaking it in pieces without sparing; so that there shall not be found among the pieces thereof a sherd wherewith to take fire from the hearth, or to dip up water out of the cistern. ^15For thus said the Lord Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel, In returning and rest shall ye be saved; in quietness and in confidence shall be your strength. And ye would not: ^16but ye said, No, for we will flee upon horses; therefore shall ye flee: and, We will ride upon the swift; therefore shall they that pursue you be swift. ^17One thousand shall flee at the threat of one; at the threat of five shall ye flee: till ye be left as a beacon upon the top of a mountain, and as an ensign on a hill. ^18And therefore will Jehovah wait, that he may be gracious unto you; and therefore will he be exalted, that he may have mercy upon you: for Jehovah is a God of justice; blessed are all they that wait for him. ^19For the people shall dwell in Zion at Jerusalem; thou shalt weep no more; he will surely be gracious unto thee at the voice of thy cry; when he shall hear, he will answer thee. ^20And though the Lord give you the bread of adversity and the water of affliction, yet shall not thy teachers be hidden anymore, but thine eyes shall see thy teachers; ^21and thine ears shall hear a word behind thee, saying, This is the way, walk ye in it; when ye turn to the right hand, and when ye turn to the left. ^22And ye shall defile the overlaying of thy graven images of silver, and the plating of thy molten images of gold: thou shalt cast them away as an unclean thing; thou shalt say unto it, Get thee hence. ^23And he will give the rain for thy seed, wherewith thou shalt sow the ground; and bread of the increase of the ground, and it shall be fat and plenteous. In that day shall thy cattle feed in large pastures; ^24the oxen likewise and the young asses that till the ground shall eat savory provender, which hath been winnowed with the shovel and with the fork. ^25And there shall be upon every lofty mountain, and upon every high hill, brooks and streams of waters, in the day of the great slaughter, when the towers fall. ^26Moreover the light of the moon shall be as the light of the sun, and the light of the sun shall be sevenfold, as the light of seven days, in the day that Jehovah bindeth up the hurt of his people, and healeth the stroke of their wound. ^27Behold, the name of Jehovah cometh from far, burning with his anger, and in thick rising smoke: his lips are full of indignation, and his tongue is as a devouring fire; ^28and his breath is as an overflowing stream, that reacheth even unto the neck, to sift the nations with the sieve of destruction: and a bridle that causeth to err shall be in the jaws of the peoples. ^29Ye shall have a song as in the night when a holy feast is kept; and gladness of heart, as when one goeth with a pipe to come unto the mountain of Jehovah, to the Rock of Israel. ^30And Jehovah will cause his glorious voice to be heard, and will show the lighting down of his arm, with the indignation of his anger, and the flame of a devouring fire, with a blast, and tempest, and hailstones. ^31For through the voice of Jehovah shall the Assyrian be dismayed; with his rod will he smite him. ^32And every stroke of the appointed staff, which Jehovah shall lay upon him, shall be with the sound of tabrets and harps; and in battles with the brandishing of his arm will he fight with them. ^33For a Topheth is prepared of old; yea, for the king it is made ready; he hath made it deep and large; the pile thereof is fire and much wood; the breath of Jehovah, like a stream of brimstone, doth kindle it.

Isaiah 31

31

^1Woe to them that go down to Egypt for help, and rely on horses, and trust in chariots because they are many, and in horsemen because they are very strong, but they look not unto the Holy One of Israel, neither seek Jehovah! ^2Yet he also is wise, and will bring evil, and will not call back his words, but will arise against the house of the evil-doers, and against the help of them that work iniquity. ^3Now the Egyptians are men, and not God; and their horses flesh, and not spirit: and when Jehovah shall stretch out his hand, both he that helpeth shall stumble, and he that is helped shall fall, and they all shall be consumed together. ^4For thus saith Jehovah unto me, As the lion and the young lion growling over his prey, if a multitude of shepherds be called forth against him, will not be dismayed at their voice, nor abase himself for the noise of them: so will Jehovah of hosts come down to fight upon mount Zion, and upon the hill thereof. ^5As birds hovering, so will Jehovah of hosts protect Jerusalem; he will protect and deliver it, he will pass over and preserve it. ^6Turn ye unto him from whom ye have deeply revolted, O children of Israel. ^7For in that day they shall cast away every man his idols of silver, and his idols of gold, which your own hands have made unto you for a sin. ^8And the Assyrian shall fall by the sword, not of man; and the sword, not of men, shall devour him; and he shall flee from the sword, and his young men shall become subject to taskwork. ^9And his rock shall pass away by reason of terror, and his princes shall be dismayed at the ensign, saith Jehovah, whose fire is in Zion, and his furnace in Jerusalem.

Isaiah 32

32

^1Behold, a king shall reign in righteousness, and princes shall rule in justice. ^2And a man shall be as a hiding-place from the wind, and a covert from the tempest, as streams of water in a dry place, as the shade of a great rock in a weary land. ^3And the eyes of them that see shall not be dim, and the ears of them that hear shall hearken. ^4And the heart of the rash shall understand knowledge, and the tongue of the stammerers shall be ready to speak plainly. ^5The fool shall be no more called noble, nor the churl said to be bountiful. ^6For the fool will speak folly, and his heart will work iniquity, to practise profaneness, and to utter error against Jehovah, to make empty the soul of the hungry, and to cause the drink of the thirsty to fail. ^7And the instruments of the churl are evil: he deviseth wicked devices to destroy the meek with lying words, even when the needy speaketh right. ^8But the noble deviseth noble things; and in noble things shall he continue. ^9Rise up, ye women that are at ease, and hear my voice; ye careless daughters, give ear unto my speech. ^10For days beyond a year shall ye be troubled, ye careless women; for the vintage shall fail, the ingathering shall not come. ^11Tremble, ye women that are at ease; be troubled, ye careless ones; strip you, and make you bare, and gird sackcloth upon your loins. ^12They shall smite upon the breasts for the pleasant fields, for the fruitful vine. ^13Upon the land of my people shall come up thorns and briers; yea, upon all the houses of joy in the joyous city. ^14For the palace shall be forsaken; the populous city shall be deserted; the hill and the watch-tower shall be for dens for ever, a joy of wild asses, a pasture of flocks; ^15until the Spirit be poured upon us from on high, and the wilderness become a fruitful field, and the fruitful field be esteemed as a forest. ^16Then justice shall dwell in the wilderness; and righteousness shall abide in the fruitful field. ^17And the work of righteousness shall be peace; and the effect of righteousness, quietness and confidence for ever. ^18And my people shall abide in a peaceable habitation, and in safe dwellings, and in quiet resting-places. ^19But it shall hail in the downfall of the forest; and the city shall be utterly laid low. ^20Blessed are yet that sow beside all waters, that send forth the feet of the ox and the ass.

Isaiah 33

33

^1Woe to thee that destroyest, and thou wast not destroyed; and dealest treacherously, and they dealt not treacherously with thee! When thou hast ceased to destroy, thou shalt be destroyed; and when thou hast made an end of dealing treacherously, they shall deal treacherously with thee. ^2O Jehovah, be gracious unto us; we have waited for thee: be thou our arm every morning, our salvation also in the time of trouble. ^3At the noise of the tumult the peoples are fled; at the lifting up of thyself the nations are scattered. ^4And your spoil shall be gathered as the caterpillar gathereth: as locusts leap shall men leap upon it. ^5Jehovah is exalted; for he dwelleth on high: he hath filled Zion with justice and righteousness. ^6And there shall be stability in thy times, abundance of salvation, wisdom, and knowledge: the fear of Jehovah is thy treasure. ^7Behold, their valiant ones cry without; the ambassadors of peace weep bitterly. ^8The highways lie waste, the wayfaring man ceaseth: the enemy hath broken the covenant, he hath despised the cities, he regardeth not man. ^9The land mourneth and languisheth; Lebanon is confounded and withereth away; Sharon is like a desert; and Bashan and Carmel shake off their leaves. ^10Now will I arise, saith Jehovah; now will I lift up myself; now will I be exalted. ^11Ye shall conceive chaff, ye shall bring forth stubble: your breath is a fire that shall devour you. ^12And the peoples shall be as the burnings of lime, as thorns cut down, that are burned in the fire. ^13Hear, ye that are far off, what I have done; and, ye that are near, acknowledge my might. ^14The sinners in Zion are afraid; trembling hath seized the godless ones: Who among us can dwell with the devouring fire? who among us can dwell with everlasting burnings? ^15He that walketh righteously, and speaketh uprightly; he that despiseth the gain of oppressions, that shaketh his hands from taking a bribe, that stoppeth his ears from hearing of blood, and shutteth his eyes from looking upon evil: ^16He shall dwell on high; his place of defence shall be the munitions of rocks; his bread shall be given him; his waters shall be sure. ^17Thine eyes shall see the king in his beauty: they shall behold a land that reacheth afar. ^18Thy heart shall muse on the terror: Where is he that counted, where is he that weighed the tribute? where is he that counted the towers? ^19Thou shalt not see the fierce people, a people of a deep speech that thou canst not comprehend, of a strange tongue that thou canst not understand. ^20Look upon Zion, the city of our solemnities: thine eyes shall see Jerusalem a quiet habitation, a tent that shall not be removed, the stakes whereof shall never be plucked up, neither shall any of the cords thereof be broken. ^21But there Jehovah will be with us in majesty, a place of broad rivers and streams, wherein shall go no galley with oars, neither shall gallant ship pass thereby. ^22For Jehovah is our judge, Jehovah is our lawgiver, Jehovah is our king; he will save us. ^23Thy tacklings are loosed; they could not strengthen the foot of their mast, they could not spread the sail: then was the prey of a great spoil divided; the lame took the prey. ^24And the inhabitant shall not say, I am sick: the people that dwell therein shall be forgiven their iniquity.

Isaiah 34

34

^1Come near, ye nations, to hear; and hearken, ye peoples: let the earth hear, and the fulness thereof; the world, and all things that come forth from it. ^2For Jehovah hath indignation against all the nations, and wrath against all their host: he hath utterly destroyed them, he hath delivered them to the slaughter. ^3Their slain also shall be cast out, and the stench of their dead bodies shall come up; and the mountains shall be melted with their blood. ^4And all the host of heaven shall be dissolved, and the heavens shall be rolled together as a scroll; and all their host shall fade away, as the leaf fadeth from off the vine, and as a fading leaf from the fig-tree. ^5For my sword hath drunk its fill in heaven: behold, it shall come down upon Edom, and upon the people of my curse, to judgment. ^6The sword of Jehovah is filled with blood, it is made fat with fatness, with the blood of lambs and goats, with the fat of the kidneys of rams; for Jehovah hath a sacrifice in Bozrah, and a great slaughter in the land of Edom. ^7And the wild-oxen shall come down with them, and the bullocks with the bulls: and their land shall be drunken with blood, and their dust made fat with fatness. ^8For Jehovah hath a day of vengeance, a year of recompense for the cause of Zion. ^9And the streams of Edom shall be turned into pitch, and the dust thereof into brimstone, and the land thereof shall become burning pitch. ^10It shall not be quenched night nor day; the smoke thereof shall go up for ever; from generation to generation it shall lie waste; none shall pass through it for ever and ever. ^11But the pelican and the porcupine shall possess it; and the owl and the raven shall dwell therein: and he will stretch over it the line of confusion, and the plummet of emptiness. ^12They shall call the nobles thereof to the kingdom, but none shall be there; and all its princes shall be nothing. ^13And thorns shall come up in its palaces, nettles and thistles in the fortresses thereof; and it shall be a habitation of jackals, a court for ostriches. ^14And the wild beasts of the desert shall meet with the wolves, and the wild goat shall cry to his fellow; yea, the night-monster shall settle there, and shall find her a place of rest. ^15There shall the dart-snake make her nest, and lay, and hatch, and gather under her shade; yea, there shall the kites be gathered, every one with her mate. ^16Seek ye out of the book of Jehovah, and read: no one of these shall be missing, none shall want her mate; for my mouth, it hath commanded, and his Spirit, it hath gathered them. ^17And he hath cast the lot for them, and his hand hath divided it unto them by line: they shall possess it for ever; from generation to generation shall they dwell therein.

Isaiah 35

35

^1The wilderness and the dry land shall be glad; and the desert shall rejoice, and blossom as the rose. ^2It shall blossom abundantly, and rejoice even with joy and singing; the glory of Lebanon shall be given unto it, the excellency of Carmel and Sharon: they shall see the glory of Jehovah, the excellency of our God. ^3Strengthen ye the weak hands, and confirm the feeble knees. ^4Say to them that are of a fearful heart, Be strong, fear not: behold, your God will come with vengeance, with the recompense of God; he will come and save you. ^5Then the eyes of the blind shall be opened, and the ears of the deaf shall be unstopped. ^6Then shall the lame man leap as a hart, and the tongue of the dumb shall sing; for in the wilderness shall waters break out, and streams in the desert. ^7And the glowing sand shall become a pool, and the thirsty ground springs of water: in the habitation of jackals, where they lay, shall be grass with reeds and rushes. ^8And a highway shall be there, and a way, and it shall be called The way of holiness; the unclean shall not pass over it; but it shall be for the redeemed: the wayfaring men, yea fools, shall not err therein. ^9No lion shall be there, nor shall any ravenous beast go up thereon; they shall not be found there; but the redeemed shall walk there: ^10and the ransomed of Jehovah shall return, and come with singing unto Zion; and everlasting joy shall be upon their heads: they shall obtain gladness and joy, and sorrow and sighing shall flee away.

Isaiah 36

36

^1Now it came to pass in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, that Sennacherib king of Assyria came up against all the fortified cities of Judah, and took them. ^2And the king of Assyria sent Rabshakeh from Lachish to Jerusalem unto king Hezekiah with a great army. And he stood by the conduit of the upper pool in the highway of the fuller's field. ^3Then came forth unto him Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah, the son of Asaph, the recorder. ^4And Rabshakeh said unto them, Say ye now to Hezekiah, Thus saith the great king, the king of Assyria, What confidence is this wherein thou trustest? ^5I say, thy counsel and strength for the war are but vain words: now on whom dost thou trust, that thou hast rebelled against me? ^6Behold, thou trustest upon the staff of this bruised reed, even upon Egypt, whereon if a man lean, it will go into his hand, and pierce it: so is Pharaoh king of Egypt to all that trust on him. ^7But if thou say unto me, We trust in Jehovah our God: is not that he, whose high places and whose altars Hezekiah hath taken away, and hath said to Judah and to Jerusalem, Ye shall worship before this altar? ^8Now therefore, I pray thee, give pledges to my master the king of Assyria, and I will give thee two thousand horses, if thou be able on thy part to set riders upon them. ^9How then canst thou turn away the face of one captain of the least of my master's servants, and put thy trust on Egypt for chariots and for horsemen? ^10And am I now come up without Jehovah against this land to destroy it? Jehovah said unto me, Go up against this land, and destroy it. ^11Then said Eliakim and Shebna and Joah unto Rabshakeh, Speak, I pray thee, unto thy servants in the Syrian language; for we understand it: and speak not to us in the Jews' language, in the ears of the people that are on the wall. ^12But Rabshakeh said, Hath my master sent me to thy master, and to thee, to speak these words? hath he not sent me to the men that sit upon the wall, to eat their own dung, and to drink their own water with you? ^13Then Rabshakeh stood, and cried with a loud voice in the Jews' language, and said, Hear ye the words of the great king, the king of Assyria. ^14Thus saith the king, Let not Hezekiah deceive you; for he will not be able to deliver you: ^15neither let Hezekiah make you trust in Jehovah, saying, Jehovah will surely deliver us; this city shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria. ^16Hearken not to Hezekiah: for thus saith the king of Assyria, Make your peace with me, and come out to me; and eat ye every one of his vine, and every one of his fig-tree, and drink ye every one the waters of his own cistern; ^17until I come and take you away to a land like your own land, a land of grain and new wine, a land of bread and vineyards. ^18Beware lest Hezekiah persuade you, saying, Jehovah will deliver us. Hath any of the gods of the nations delivered his land out of the hand of the king of Assyria? ^19Where are the gods of Hamath and Arpad? where are the gods of Sepharvaim? and have they delivered Samaria out of my hand? ^20Who are they among all the gods of these countries, that have delivered their country out of my hand, that Jehovah should deliver Jerusalem out of my hand? ^21But they held their peace, and answered him not a word; for the king's commandment was, saying, Answer him not. ^22Then came Eliakim the son of Hilkiah, that was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and Joah, the son of Asaph, the recorder, to Hezekiah with their clothes rent, and told him the words of Rabshakeh.

Isaiah 37

37

^1And it came to pass, when king Hezekiah heard it, that he rent his clothes, and covered himself with sackcloth, and went into the house of Jehovah. ^2And he sent Eliakim, who was over the household, and Shebna the scribe, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, unto Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz. ^3And they said unto him, Thus saith Hezekiah, This day is a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of contumely; for the children are come to the birth, and there is not strength to bring forth. ^4It may be Jehovah thy God will hear the words of Rabshakeh, whom the king of Assyria his master hath sent to defy the living God, and will rebuke the words which Jehovah thy God hath heard: wherefore lift up thy prayer for the remnant that is left. ^5So the servants of king Hezekiah came to Isaiah. ^6And Isaiah said unto them, Thus shall ye say to your master, Thus saith Jehovah, Be not afraid of the words that thou hast heard, wherewith the servants of the king of Assyria have blasphemed me. ^7Behold, I will put a spirit in him, and he shall hear tidings, and shall return unto his own land; and I will cause him to fall by the sword in his own land. ^8So Rabshakeh returned, and found the king of Assyria warring against Libnah; for he had heard that he was departed from Lachish. ^9And he heard say concerning Tirhakah king of Ethiopia, He is come out to fight against thee. And when he heard it, he sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying, ^10Thus shall ye speak to Hezekiah king of Judah, saying, Let not thy God in whom thou trustest deceive thee, saying, Jerusalem shall not be given into the hand of the king of Assyria. ^11Behold, thou hast heard what the kings of Assyria have done to all lands, by destroying them utterly: and shalt thou be delivered? ^12Have the gods of the nations delivered them, which my fathers have destroyed, Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the children of Eden that were in Telassar? ^13Where is the king of Hamath, and the king of Arpad, and the king of the city of Sepharvaim, of Hena, and Ivvah? ^14And Hezekiah received the letter from the hand of the messengers, and read it; and Hezekiah went up unto the house of Jehovah, and spread it before Jehovah. ^15And Hezekiah prayed unto Jehovah, saying, ^16O Jehovah of hosts, the God of Israel, that sittest above the cherubim, thou art the God, even thou alone, of all the kingdoms of the earth; thou hast made heaven and earth. ^17Incline thine ear, O Jehovah, and hear; open thine eyes, O Jehovah, and see; and hear all the words of Sennacherib, who hath sent to defy the living God. ^18Of a truth, Jehovah, the kings of Assyria have laid waste all the countries, and their land, ^19and have cast their gods into the fire: for they were no gods, but the work of men's hands, wood and stone; therefore they have destroyed them. ^20Now therefore, O Jehovah our God, save us from his hand, that all the kingdoms of the earth may know that thou art Jehovah, even thou only. ^21Then Isaiah the son of Amoz sent unto Hezekiah, saying, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, Whereas thou hast prayed to me against Sennacherib king of Assyria, ^22this is the word which Jehovah hath spoken concerning him: The virgin daughter of Zion hath despised thee and laughed thee to scorn; the daughter of Jerusalem hath shaken her head at thee. ^23Whom hast thou defied and blasphemed? and against whom hast thou exalted thy voice and lifted up thine eyes on high? even against the Holy One of Israel. ^24By thy servants hast thou defied the Lord, and hast said, With the multitude of my chariots am I come up to the height of the mountains, to the innermost parts of Lebanon; and I will cut down the tall cedars thereof, and the choice fir-trees thereof; and I will enter into its farthest height, the forest of its fruitful field; ^25I have digged and drunk water, and with the sole of my feet will I dry up all the rivers of Egypt. ^26Hast thou not heard how I have done it long ago, and formed it of ancient times? now have I brought it to pass, that it should be thine to lay waste fortified cities into ruinous heaps. ^27Therefore their inhabitants were of small power, they were dismayed and confounded; they were as the grass of the field, and as the green herb, as the grass on the housetops, and as a field of grain before it is grown up. ^28But I know thy sitting down, and thy going out, and thy coming in, and thy raging against me. ^29Because of thy raging against me, and because thine arrogancy is come up into mine ears, therefore will I put my hook in thy nose, and my bridle in thy lips, and I will turn thee back by the way by which thou camest. ^30And this shall be the sign unto thee: ye shall eat this year that which groweth of itself, and in the second year that which springeth of the same; and in the third year sow ye, and reap, and plant vineyards, and eat the fruit thereof. ^31And the remnant that is escaped of the house of Judah shall again take root downward, and bear fruit upward. ^32For out of Jerusalem shall go forth a remnant, and out of mount Zion they that shall escape. The zeal of Jehovah of hosts will perform this. ^33Therefore thus saith Jehovah concerning the king of Assyria, He shall not come unto this city, nor shoot an arrow there, neither shall he come before it with shield, nor cast up a mound against it. ^34By the way that he came, by the same shall he return, and he shall not come unto this city, saith Jehovah. ^35For I will defend this city to save it, for mine own sake, and for my servant David's sake. ^36And the angel of Jehovah went forth, and smote in the camp of the Assyrians a hundred and fourscore and five thousand; and when men arose early in the morning, behold, these were all dead bodies. ^37So Sennacherib king of Assyria departed, and went and returned, and dwelt at Nineveh. ^38And it came to pass, as he was worshipping in the house of Nisroch his god, that Adrammelech and Sharezer his sons smote him with the sword; and they escaped into the land of Ararat. And Esar-haddon his son reigned in his stead.

Isaiah 38

38

^1In those days was Hezekiah sick unto death. And Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz came to him, and said unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, Set thy house in order; for thou shalt die, and not live. ^2Then Hezekiah turned his face to the wall, and prayed unto Jehovah, ^3and said, Remember now, O Jehovah, I beseech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight. And Hezekiah wept sore. ^4Then came the word of Jehovah to Isaiah, saying, ^5Go, and say to Hezekiah, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of David thy father, I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears: behold, I will add unto thy days fifteen years. ^6And I will deliver thee and this city out of the hand of the king of Assyria; and I will defend this city. ^7And this shall be the sign unto thee from Jehovah, that Jehovah will do this thing that he hath spoken: ^8behold, I will cause the shadow on the steps, which is gone down on the dial of Ahaz with the sun, to return backward ten steps. So the sun returned ten steps on the dial whereon it was gone down.

^9The writing of Hezekiah king of Judah, when he had been sick, and was recovered of his sickness.

^10I said, In the noontide of my days I shall go into the gates of Sheol:

I am deprived of the residue of my years.

^11I said, I shall not see Jehovah, even Jehovah in the land of the living:

I shall behold man no more with the inhabitants of the world.

^12My dwelling is removed, and is carried away from me as a shepherd's tent:

I have rolled up, like a weaver, my life; he will cut me off from the loom:

From day even to night wilt thou make an end of me.

^13I quieted myself until morning; as a lion, so he breaketh all my bones:

From day even to night wilt thou make an end of me.

^14Like a swallow or a crane, so did I chatter;

I did moan as a dove; mine eyes fail with looking upward:

O Lord, I am oppressed, be thou my surety.

^15What shall I say? he hath both spoken unto me, and himself hath done it:

I shall go softly all my years because of the bitterness of my soul.

^16O Lord, by these things men live;

And wholly therein is the life of my spirit:

Wherefore recover thou me, and make me to live.

^17Behold, it was for my peace that I had great bitterness:

But thou hast in love to my soul delivered it from the pit of corruption;

For thou hast cast all my sins behind thy back.

^18For Sheol cannot praise thee, death cannot celebrate thee:

They that go down into the pit cannot hope for thy truth.

^19The living, the living, he shall praise thee, as I do this day:

The father to the children shall make known thy truth.

^20Jehovah is ready to save me:

Therefore we will sing my songs with stringed instruments

All the days of our life in the house of Jehovah.

^21Now Isaiah had said, Let them take a cake of figs, and lay it for a plaster upon the boil, and he shall recover. ^22Hezekiah also had said, What is the sign that I shall go up to the house of Jehovah?

Isaiah 39

39

^1At that time Merodach-baladan the son of Baladan, king of Babylon, sent letters and a present to Hezekiah; for he heard that he had been sick, and was recovered. ^2And Hezekiah was glad of them, and showed them the house of his precious things, the silver, and the gold, and the spices, and the precious oil, and all the house of his armor, and all that was found in his treasures: there was nothing in his house, nor in all his dominion, that Hezekiah showed them not. ^3Then came Isaiah the prophet unto king Hezekiah, and said unto him, What said these men? and from whence came they unto thee? And Hezekiah said, They are come from a far country unto me, even from Babylon. ^4Then said he, What have they seen in thy house? And Hezekiah answered, All that is in my house have they seen: there is nothing among my treasures that I have not showed them. ^5Then said Isaiah to Hezekiah, Hear the word of Jehovah of hosts: ^6Behold, the days are coming, when all that is in thy house, and that which thy fathers have laid up in store until this day, shall be carried to Babylon: nothing shall be left, saith Jehovah. ^7And of thy sons that shall issue from thee, whom thou shalt beget, shall they take away; and they shall be eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon. ^8Then said Hezekiah unto Isaiah, Good is the word of Jehovah which thou hast spoken. He said moreover, For there shall be peace and truth in my days.

Isaiah 40

40

^1Comfort ye, comfort ye my people, saith your God. ^2Speak ye comfortably to Jerusalem; and cry unto her, that her warfare is accomplished, that her iniquity is pardoned, that she hath received of Jehovah's hand double for all her sins. ^3The voice of one that crieth, Prepare ye in the wilderness the way of Jehovah; make level in the desert a highway for our God. ^4Every valley shall be exalted, and every mountain and hill shall be made low; and the uneven shall be made level, and the rough places a plain: ^5and the glory of Jehovah shall be revealed, and all flesh shall see it together; for the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken it. ^6The voice of one saying, Cry. And one said, What shall I cry? All flesh is grass, and all the goodliness thereof is as the flower of the field. ^7The grass withereth, the flower fadeth, because the breath of Jehovah bloweth upon it; surely the people is grass. ^8The grass withereth, the flower fadeth; but the word of our God shall stand forever. ^9O thou that tellest good tidings to Zion, get thee up on a high mountain; O thou that tellest good tidings to Jerusalem, lift up thy voice with strength; lift it up, be not afraid; say unto the cities of Judah, Behold, your God! ^10Behold, the Lord Jehovah will come as a mighty one, and his arm will rule for him: Behold, his reward is with him, and his recompense before him. ^11He will feed his flock like a shepherd, he will gather the lambs in his arm, and carry them in his bosom, and will gently lead those that have their young. ^12Who hath measured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meted out heaven with the span, and comprehended the dust of the earth in a measure, and weighed the mountains in scales, and the hills in a balance? ^13Who hath directed the Spirit of Jehovah, or being his counsellor hath taught him? ^14With whom took he counsel, and who instructed him, and taught him in the path of justice, and taught him knowledge, and showed to him the way of understanding? ^15Behold, the nations are as a drop of a bucket, and are accounted as the small dust of the balance: Behold, he taketh up the isles as a very little thing. ^16And Lebanon is not sufficient to burn, nor the beasts thereof sufficient for a burnt-offering. ^17All the nations are as nothing before him; they are accounted by him as less than nothing, and vanity. ^18To whom then will ye liken God? or what likeness will ye compare unto him? ^19The image, a workman hath cast it, and the goldsmith overlayeth it with gold, and casteth for it silver chains. ^20He that is too impoverished for such an oblation chooseth a tree that will not rot; he seeketh unto him a skilful workman to set up a graven image, that shall not be moved. ^21Have ye not known? have yet not heard? hath it not been told you from the beginning? have ye not understood from the foundations of the earth? ^22It is he that sitteth above the circle of the earth, and the inhabitants thereof are as grasshoppers; that stretcheth out the heavens as a curtain, and spreadeth them out as a tent to dwell in; ^23that bringeth princes to nothing; that maketh the judges of the earth as vanity. ^24Yea, they have not been planted; yea, they have not been sown; yea, their stock hath not taken root in the earth: moreover he bloweth upon them, and they wither, and the whirlwind taketh them away as stubble. ^25To whom then will ye liken me, that I should be equal to him? saith the Holy One. ^26Lift up your eyes on high, and see who hath created these, that bringeth out their host by number; he calleth them all by name; by the greatness of his might, and for that he is strong in power, not one is lacking. ^27Why sayest thou, O Jacob, and speakest, O Israel, My way is hid from Jehovah, and the justice due to me is passed away from my God? ^28Hast thou not known? hast thou not heard? The everlasting God, Jehovah, the Creator of the ends of the earth, fainteth not, neither is weary; there is no searching of his understanding. ^29He giveth power to the faint; and to him that hath no might he increaseth strength. ^30Even the youths shall faint and be weary, and the young men shall utterly fall: ^31but they that wait for Jehovah shall renew their strength; they shall mount up with wings as eagles; they shall run, and not be weary; they shall walk, and not faint.

Isaiah 41

41

^1Keep silence before me, O islands; and let the peoples renew their strength: let them come near; then let them speak; let us come near together to judgment. ^2Who hath raised up one from the east, whom he calleth in righteousness to his foot? he giveth nations before him, and maketh him rule over kings; he giveth them as the dust to his sword, as the driven stubble to his bow. ^3He pursueth them, and passeth on safely, even by a way that he had not gone with his feet. ^4Who hath wrought and done it, calling the generations from the beginning? I, Jehovah, the first, and with the last, I am he. ^5The isles have seen, and fear; the ends of the earth tremble; they draw near, and come. ^6They help every one his neighbor; and every one saith to his brother, Be of good courage. ^7So the carpenter encourageth the goldsmith, and he that smootheth with the hammer him that smiteth the anvil, saying of the soldering, It is good; and he fasteneth it with nails, that it should not be moved. ^8But thou, Israel, my servant, Jacob whom I have chosen, the seed of Abraham my friend, ^9thou whom I have taken hold of from the ends of the earth, and called from the corners thereof, and said unto thee, Thou art my servant, I have chosen thee and not cast thee away; ^10Fear thou not, for I am with thee; be not dismayed, for I am thy God; I will strengthen thee; yea, I will help thee; yea, I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteousness. ^11Behold, all they that are incensed against thee shall be put to shame and confounded: they that strive with thee shall be as nothing, and shall perish. ^12Thou shalt seek them, and shalt not find them, even them that contend with thee: they that war against thee shall be as nothing, and as a thing of nought. ^13For I, Jehovah thy God, will hold thy right hand, saying unto thee, Fear not; I will help thee. ^14Fear not, thou worm Jacob, and ye men of Israel; I will help thee, saith Jehovah, and thy Redeemer is the Holy One of Israel. ^15Behold, I have made thee to be a new sharp threshing instrument having teeth; thou shalt thresh the mountains, and beat them small, and shalt make the hills as chaff. ^16Thou shalt winnow them, and the wind shall carry them away, and the whirlwind shall scatter them; and thou shalt rejoice in Jehovah, thou shalt glory in the Holy One of Israel. ^17The poor and needy seek water, and there is none, and their tongue faileth for thirst; I, Jehovah, will answer them, I, the God of Israel, will not forsake them. ^18I will open rivers on the bare heights, and fountains in the midst of the valleys; I will make the wilderness a pool of water, and the dry land springs of water. ^19I will put in the wilderness the cedar, the acacia, and the myrtle, and the oil-tree; I will set in the desert the fir-tree, the pine, and the box-tree together: ^20that they may see, and know, and consider, and understand together, that the hand of Jehovah hath done this, and the Holy One of Israel hath created it. ^21Produce your cause, saith Jehovah; bring forth your strong reasons, saith the King of Jacob. ^22Let them bring forth, and declare unto us what shall happen: declare ye the former things, what they are, that we may consider them, and know the latter end of them; or show us things to come. ^23Declare the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that ye are gods: yea, do good, or do evil, that we may be dismayed, and behold it together. ^24Behold, ye are of nothing, and your work is of nought; an abomination is he that chooseth you. ^25I have raised up one from the north, and he is come; from the rising of the sun one that calleth upon my name: and he shall come upon rulers as upon mortar, and as the potter treadeth clay. ^26Who hath declared it from the beginning, that we may know? and beforetime, that we may say, He is right? yea, there is none that declareth, yea, there is none that showeth, yea, there is none that heareth your words. ^27I am the first that saith unto Zion, Behold, behold them; and I will give to Jerusalem one that bringeth good tidings. ^28And when I look, there is no man: even among them there is no counsellor, that, when I ask of them, can answer a word. ^29Behold, all of them, their works are vanity and nought; their molten images are wind and confusion.

Isaiah 42

42

^1Behold, my servant, whom I uphold; my chosen, in whom my soul delighteth: I have put my Spirit upon him; he will bring forth justice to the Gentiles. ^2He will not cry, nor lift up his voice, nor cause it to be heard in the street. ^3A bruised reed will he not break, and a dimly burning wick will he not quench: he will bring forth justice in truth. ^4He will not fail nor be discouraged, till he have set justice in the earth; and the isles shall wait for his law. ^5Thus saith God Jehovah, he that created the heavens, and stretched them forth; he that spread abroad the earth and that which cometh out of it; he that giveth breath unto the people upon it, and spirit to them that walk therein: ^6I, Jehovah, have called thee in righteousness, and will hold thy hand, and will keep thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, for a light of the Gentiles; ^7to open the blind eyes, to bring out the prisoners from the dungeon, and them that sit in darkness out of the prison-house. ^8I am Jehovah, that is my name; and my glory will I not give to another, neither my praise unto graven images. ^9Behold, the former things are come to pass, and new things do I declare; before they spring forth I tell you of them. ^10Sing unto Jehovah a new song, and his praise from the end of the earth; ye that go down to the sea, and all that is therein, the isles, and the inhabitants thereof. ^11Let the wilderness and the cities thereof lift up their voice, the villages that Kedar doth inhabit; let the inhabitants of Sela sing, let them shout from the top of the mountains. ^12Let them give glory unto Jehovah, and declare his praise in the islands. ^13Jehovah will go forth as a mighty man; he will stir up his zeal like a man of war: he will cry, yea, he will shout aloud; he will do mightily against his enemies. ^14I have long time holden my peace; I have been still, and refrained myself: now will I cry out like a travailing woman; I will gasp and pant together. ^15I will lay waste mountains and hills, and dry up all their herbs; and I will make the rivers islands, and will dry up the pools. ^16And I will bring the blind by a way that they know not; in paths that they know not will I lead them; I will make darkness light before them, and crooked places straight. These things will I do, and I will not forsake them. ^17They shall be turned back, they shall be utterly put to shame, that trust in graven images, that say unto molten images, Ye are our gods. ^18Hear, ye deaf; and look, ye blind, that ye may see. ^19Who is blind, but my servant? or deaf, as my messenger that I send? who is blind as he that is at peace with me, and blind as Jehovah's servant? ^20Thou seest many things, but thou observest not; his ears are open, but he heareth not. ^21It pleased Jehovah, for his righteousness' sake, to magnify the law, and make it honorable. ^22But this is a people robbed and plundered; they are all of them snared in holes, and they are hid in prison-houses: they are for a prey, and none delivereth; for a spoil, and none saith, Restore. ^23Who is there among you that will give ear to this? that will hearken and hear for the time to come? ^24Who gave Jacob for a spoil, and Israel to the robbers? did not Jehovah? he against whom we have sinned, and in whose ways they would not walk, neither were they obedient unto his law. ^25Therefore he poured upon him the fierceness of his anger, and the strength of battle; and it set him on fire round about, yet he knew not; and it burned him, yet he laid it not to heart.

Isaiah 43

43

^1But now thus saith Jehovah that created thee, O Jacob, and he that formed thee, O Israel: Fear not, for I have redeemed thee; I have called thee by thy name, thou art mine. ^2When thou passest through the waters, I will be with thee; and through the rivers, they shall not overflow thee: when thou walkest through the fire, thou shalt not be burned, neither shall the flame kindle upon thee. ^3For I am Jehovah thy God, the Holy One of Israel, thy Saviour; I have given Egypt as thy ransom, Ethiopia and Seba in thy stead. ^4Since thou hast been precious in my sight, and honorable, and I have loved thee; therefore will I give men in thy stead, and peoples instead of thy life. ^5Fear not; for I am with thee: I will bring thy seed from the east, and gather thee from the west; ^6I will say to the north, Give up; and to the south, Keep not back; bring my sons from far, and my daughters from the end of the earth; ^7every one that is called by my name, and whom I have created for my glory, whom I have formed, yea, whom I have made. ^8Bring forth the blind people that have eyes, and the deaf that have ears. ^9Let all the nations be gathered together, and let the peoples be assembled: who among them can declare this, and show us former things? let them bring their witnesses, that they may be justified; or let them hear, and say, It is truth. ^10Ye are my witnesses, saith Jehovah, and my servant whom I have chosen; that ye may know and believe me, and understand that I am he: before me there was no God formed, neither shall there be after me. ^11I, even I, am Jehovah; and besides me there is no saviour. ^12I have declared, and I have saved, and I have showed; and there was no strange god among you: therefore ye are my witnesses, saith Jehovah, and I am God. ^13Yea, since the day was I am he; and there is none that can deliver out of my hand: I will work, and who can hinder it? ^14Thus saith Jehovah, your Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel: For your sake I have sent to Babylon, and I will bring down all of them as fugitives, even the Chaldeans, in the ships of their rejoicing. ^15I am Jehovah, your Holy One, the Creator of Israel, your King. ^16Thus saith Jehovah, who maketh a way in the sea, and a path in the mighty waters; ^17who bringeth forth the chariot and horse, the army and the mighty man (they lie down together, they shall not rise; they are extinct, they are quenched as a wick): ^18Remember ye not the former things, neither consider the things of old. ^19Behold, I will do a new thing; now shall it spring forth; shall ye not know it? I will even make a way in the wilderness, and rivers in the desert. ^20The beasts of the field shall honor me, the jackals and the ostriches; because I give waters in the wilderness, and rivers in the desert, to give drink to my people, my chosen, ^21the people which I formed for myself, that they might set forth my praise. ^22Yet thou hast not called upon me, O Jacob; but thou hast been weary of me, O Israel. ^23Thou hast not brought me of thy sheep for burnt-offerings; neither hast thou honored me with thy sacrifices. I have not burdened thee with offerings, nor wearied thee with frankincense. ^24Thou hast bought me no sweet cane with money, neither hast thou filled me with the fat of thy sacrifices; but thou hast burdened me with thy sins, thou hast wearied me with thine iniquities. ^25I, even I, am he that blotteth out thy transgressions for mine own sake; and I will not remember thy sins. ^26Put me in remembrance; let us plead together: set thou forth thy cause, that thou mayest be justified. ^27Thy first father sinned, and thy teachers have transgressed against me. ^28Therefore I will profane the princes of the sanctuary; and I will make Jacob a curse, and Israel a reviling.

Isaiah 44

44

^1Yet now hear, O Jacob my servant, and Israel, who I have chosen: ^2Thus saith Jehovah that made thee, and formed thee from the womb, who will help thee: Fear not, O Jacob my servant; and thou, Jeshurun, whom I have chosen. ^3For I will pour water upon him that is thirsty, and streams upon the dry ground; I will pour my Spirit upon thy seed, and my blessing upon thine offspring: ^4and they shall spring up among the grass, as willows by the watercourses. ^5One shall say, I am Jehovah's; and another shall call himself by the name of Jacob; and another shall subscribe with his hand unto Jehovah, and surname himself by the name of Israel. ^6Thus saith Jehovah, the King of Israel, and his Redeemer, Jehovah of hosts: I am the first, and I am the last; and besides me there is no God. ^7And who, as I, shall call, and shall declare it, and set it in order for me, since I established the ancient people? and the things that are coming, and that shall come to pass, let them declare. ^8Fear ye not, neither be afraid: have I not declared unto thee of old, and showed it? and ye are my witnesses. Is there a God besides me? yea, there is no Rock; I know not any. ^9They that fashion a graven image are all of them vanity; and the things that they delight in shall not profit; and their own witnesses see not, nor know: that they may be put to shame. ^10Who hath fashioned a god, or molten an image that is profitable for nothing? ^11Behold, all his fellows shall be put to shame; and the workmen, they are of men: let them all be gathered together, let them stand up; they shall fear, they shall be put to shame together. ^12The smith maketh an axe, and worketh in the coals, and fashioneth it with hammers, and worketh it with his strong arm: yea, he is hungry, and his strength faileth; he drinketh no water, and is faint. ^13The carpenter stretcheth out a line; he marketh it out with a pencil; he shapeth it with planes, and he marketh it out with the compasses, and shapeth it after the figure of a man, according to the beauty of a man, to dwell in a house. ^14He heweth him down cedars, and taketh the holm-tree and the oak, and strengtheneth for himself one among the trees of the forest: he planteth a fir-tree, and the rain doth nourish it. ^15Then shall it be for a man to burn; and he taketh thereof, and warmeth himself; yea, he kindleth it, and baketh bread: yea, he maketh a god, and worshippeth it; he maketh it a graven image, and falleth down thereto. ^16He burneth part thereof in the fire; with part thereof he eateth flesh; he roasteth roast, and is satisfied; yea, he warmeth himself, and saith, Aha, I am warm, I have seen the fire. ^17And the residue thereof he maketh a god, even his graven image; he falleth down unto it and worshippeth, and prayeth unto it, and saith, Deliver me; for thou art my god. ^18They know not, neither do they consider: for he hath shut their eyes, that they cannot see; and their hearts, that they cannot understand. ^19And none calleth to mind, neither is there knowledge nor understanding to say, I have burned part of it in the fire; yea, also I have baked bread upon the coals thereof; I have roasted flesh and eaten it: and shall I make the residue thereof an abomination? shall I fall down to the stock of a tree? ^20He feedeth on ashes; a deceived heart hath turned him aside; and he cannot deliver his soul, nor say, Is there not a lie in my right hand? ^21Remember these things, O Jacob, and Israel; for thou art my servant: I have formed thee; thou art my servant: O Israel, thou shalt not be forgotten of me. ^22I have blotted out, as a thick cloud, thy transgressions, and, as a cloud, thy sins: return unto me; for I have redeemed thee. ^23Sing, O ye heavens, for Jehovah hath done it; shout, ye lower parts of the earth; break forth into singing, ye mountains, O forest, and every tree therein: for Jehovah hath redeemed Jacob, and will glorify himself in Israel. ^24Thus saith Jehovah, thy Redeemer, and he that formed thee from the womb: I am Jehovah, that maketh all things; that stretcheth forth the heavens alone; that spreadeth abroad the earth (who is with me?); ^25that frustrateth the signs of the liars, and maketh diviners mad; that turneth wise men backward, and maketh their knowledge foolish; ^26that confirmeth the word of his servant, and performeth the counsel of his messengers; that saith of Jerusalem, She shall be inhabited; and of the cities of Judah, They shall be built, and I will raise up the waste places thereof; ^27that saith to the deep, Be dry, and I will dry up thy rivers; ^28That saith of Cyrus, He is my shepherd, and shall perform all my pleasure, even saying of Jerusalem, She shall be built; and of the temple, Thy foundation shall be laid.

Isaiah 45

45

^1Thus saith Jehovah to his anointed, to Cyrus, whose right hand I have holden, to subdue nations before him, and I will loose the loins of kings; to open the doors before him, and the gates shall not be shut: ^2I will go before thee, and make the rough places smooth; I will break in pieces the doors of brass, and cut in sunder the bars of iron; ^3and I will give thee the treasures of darkness, and hidden riches of secret places, that thou mayest know that it is I, Jehovah, who call thee by thy name, even the God of Israel. ^4For Jacob my servant's sake, and Israel my chosen, I have called thee by thy name: I have surnamed thee, though thou hast not known me. ^5I am Jehovah, and there is none else; besides me there is no God. I will gird thee, though thou hast not known me; ^6that they may know from the rising of the sun, and from the west, that there is none besides me: I am Jehovah, and there is none else. ^7I form the light, and create darkness; I make peace, and create evil. I am Jehovah, that doeth all these things. ^8Distil, ye heavens, from above, and let the skies pour down righteousness: let the earth open, that it may bring forth salvation, and let it cause righteousness to spring up together; I, Jehovah, have created it. ^9Woe unto him that striveth with his Maker! a potsherd among the potsherds of the earth! Shall the clay say to him that fashioneth it, What makest thou? or thy work, He hath no hands? ^10Woe unto him that saith unto a father, What begettest thou? or to a woman, With what travailest thou? ^11Thus saith Jehovah, the Holy One of Israel, and his Maker: Ask me of the things that are to come; concerning my sons, and concerning the work of my hands, command ye me. ^12I have made the earth, and created man upon it: I, even my hands, have stretched out the heavens; and all their host have I commanded. ^13I have raised him up in righteousness, and I will make straight all his ways: he shall build my city, and he shall let my exiles go free, not for price nor reward, saith Jehovah of hosts. ^14Thus saith Jehovah, The labor of Egypt, and the merchandise of Ethiopia, and the Sabeans, men of stature, shall come over unto thee, and they shall be thine: they shall go after thee, in chains they shall come over; and they shall fall down unto thee, they shall make supplication unto thee, saying, Surely God is in thee; and there is none else, there is no God. ^15Verily thou art a God that hidest thyself, O God of Israel, the Saviour. ^16They shall be put to shame, yea, confounded, all of them; they shall go into confusion together that are makers of idols. ^17But Israel shall be saved by Jehovah with an everlasting salvation: ye shall not be put to shame nor confounded world without end. ^18For thus saith Jehovah that created the heavens, the God that formed the earth and made it, that established it and created it not a waste, that formed it to be inhabited: I am Jehovah; and there is none else. ^19I have not spoken in secret, in a place of the land of darkness; I said not unto the seed of Jacob, Seek ye me in vain: I, Jehovah, speak righteousness, I declare things that are right. ^20Assemble yourselves and come; draw near together, ye that are escaped of the nations: they have no knowledge that carry the wood of their graven image, and pray unto a god that cannot save. ^21Declare ye, and bring it forth; yea, let them take counsel together: who hath showed this from ancient time? who hath declared it of old? have not I, Jehovah? and there is no God else besides me, a just God and a Saviour; there is none besides me. ^22Look unto me, and be ye saved, all the ends of the earth; for I am God, and there is none else. ^23By myself have I sworn, the word is gone forth from my mouth in righteousness, and shall not return, that unto me every knee shall bow, every tongue shall swear. ^24Only in Jehovah, it is said of me, is righteousness and strength; even to him shall men come; and all they that were incensed against him shall be put to shame. ^25In Jehovah shall all the seed of Israel be justified, and shall glory.

Isaiah 46

46

^1Bel boweth down, Nebo stoopeth; their idols are upon the beasts, and upon the cattle: the things that ye carried about are made a load, a burden to the weary beast. ^2They stoop, they bow down together; they could not deliver the burden, but themselves are gone into captivity. ^3Hearken unto me, O house of Jacob, and all the remnant of the house of Israel, that have been borne by me from their birth, that have been carried from the womb; ^4and even to old age I am he, and even to hoar hairs will I carry you; I have made, and I will bear; yea, I will carry, and will deliver. ^5To whom will ye like me, and make me equal, and compare me, that we may be like? ^6Such as lavish gold out of the bag, and weigh silver in the balance, they hire a goldsmith, and he maketh it a god; they fall down, yea, they worship. ^7They bear it upon the shoulder, they carry it, and set it in its place, and it standeth, from its place shall it not remove: yea, one may cry unto it, yet can it not answer, nor save him out of his trouble. ^8Remember this, and show yourselves men; bring it again to mind, O ye transgressors. ^9Remember the former things of old: for I am God, and there is none else; I am God, and there is none like me; ^10declaring the end from the beginning, and from ancient times things that are not yet done; saying, My counsel shall stand, and I will do all my pleasure; ^11calling a ravenous bird from the east, the man of my counsel from a far country; yea, I have spoken, I will also bring it to pass; I have purposed, I will also do it. ^12Hearken unto me, ye stout-hearted, that are far from righteousness: ^13I bring near my righteousness, it shall not be far off, and my salvation shall not tarry; and I will place salvation in Zion for Israel my glory.

Isaiah 47

47

^1Come down, and sit in the dust, O virgin daughter of Babylon; sit on the ground without a throne, O daughter of the Chaldeans: for thou shalt no more be called tender and delicate. ^2Take the millstones, and grind meal; remove thy veil, strip off the train, uncover the leg, pass through the rivers. ^3Thy nakedness shall be uncovered, yea, thy shame shall be seen: I will take vengeance, and will spare no man. ^4Our Redeemer, Jehovah of hosts is his name, the Holy One of Israel. ^5Sit thou silent, and get thee into darkness, O daughter of the Chaldeans; for thou shalt no more be called The mistress of kingdoms. ^6I was wroth with my people, I profaned mine inheritance, and gave them into thy hand: thou didst show them no mercy; upon the aged hast thou very heavily laid thy yoke. ^7And thou saidst, I shall be mistress for ever; so that thou didst not lay these things to thy heart, neither didst remember the latter end thereof. ^8Now therefore hear this, thou that art given to pleasures, that sittest securely, that sayest in thy heart, I am, and there is none else besides me; I shall not sit as a widow, neither shall I know the loss of children: ^9but these two things shall come to thee in a moment in one day, the loss of children, and widowhood; in their full measure shall they come upon thee, in the multitude of thy sorceries, and the great abundance of thine enchantments. ^10For thou hast trusted in thy wickedness; thou hast said, None seeth me; thy wisdom and thy knowledge, it hath perverted thee, and thou hast said in thy heart, I am, and there is none else besides me. ^11Therefore shall evil come upon thee; thou shalt not know the dawning thereof: and mischief shall fall upon thee; thou shalt not be able to put it away: and desolation shall come upon thee suddenly, which thou knowest not. ^12Stand now with thine enchantments, and with the multitude of thy sorceries, wherein thou hast labored from thy youth; if so be thou shalt be able to profit, if so be thou mayest prevail. ^13Thou art wearied in the multitude of thy counsels: let now the astrologers, the star-gazers, the monthly prognosticators, stand up, and save thee from the things that shall come upon thee. ^14Behold, they shall be as stubble; the fire shall burn them; they shall not deliver themselves from the power of the flame: it shall not be a coal to warm at, nor a fire to sit before. ^15Thus shall the things be unto thee wherein thou hast labored: they that have trafficked with thee from thy youth shall wander every one to his quarter; there shall be none to save thee.

Isaiah 48

48

^1Hear ye this, O house of Jacob, who are called by the name of Israel, and are come forth out of the waters of Judah; who swear by the name of Jehovah, and make mention of the God of Israel, but not in truth, nor in righteousness ^2(for they call themselves of the holy city, and stay themselves upon the God of Israel; Jehovah of hosts is his name): ^3I have declared the former things from of old; yea, they went forth out of my mouth, and I showed them: suddenly I did them, and they came to pass. ^4Because I knew that thou art obstinate, and thy neck is an iron sinew, and thy brow brass; ^5therefore I have declared it to thee from of old; before it came to pass I showed it thee; lest thou shouldest say, Mine idol hath done them, and my graven image, and my molten image, hath commanded them. ^6Thou hast heard it; behold all this; and ye, will ye not declare it? I have showed thee new things from this time, even hidden things, which thou hast not known. ^7They are created now, and not from of old; and before this day thou heardest them not; lest thou shouldest say, Behold, I knew them. ^8Yea, thou heardest not; yea, thou knewest not; yea, from of old thine ear was not opened: for I knew that thou didst deal very treacherously, and wast called a transgressor from the womb. ^9For my name's sake will I defer mine anger, and for my praise will I refrain for thee, that I cut thee not off. ^10Behold, I have refined thee, but not as silver; I have chosen thee in the furnace of affliction. ^11For mine own sake, for mine own sake, will I do it; for how should my name be profaned? and my glory will I not give to another. ^12Hearken unto me, O Jacob, and Israel my called: I am he; I am the first, I also am the last. ^13Yea, my hand hath laid the foundation of the earth, and my right hand hath spread out the heavens: when I call unto them, they stand up together. ^14Assemble yourselves, all ye, and hear; who among them hath declared these things? He whom Jehovah loveth shall perform his pleasure on Babylon, and his arm shall be on the Chaldeans. ^15I, even I, have spoken; yea, I have called him; I have brought him, and he shall make his way prosperous. ^16Come ye near unto me, hear ye this; from the beginning I have not spoken in secret; from the time that it was, there am I: and now the Lord Jehovah hath sent me, and his Spirit. ^17Thus saith Jehovah, thy Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel: I am Jehovah thy God, who teacheth thee to profit, who leadeth thee by the way that thou shouldest go. ^18Oh that thou hadst hearkened to my commandments! then had thy peace been as a river, and thy righteousness as the waves of the sea: ^19thy seed also had been as the sand, and the offspring of thy bowels like the grains thereof: his name would not be cut off nor destroyed from before me. ^20Go ye forth from Babylon, flee ye from the Chaldeans; with a voice of singing declare ye, tell this, utter it even to the end of the earth: say ye, Jehovah hath redeemed his servant Jacob. ^21And they thirsted not when he led them through the deserts; he caused the waters to flow out of the rock for them; he clave the rock also, and the waters gushed out. ^22There is no peace, saith Jehovah, to the wicked.

Isaiah 49

49

^1Listen, O isles, unto me; and hearken, ye peoples, from far: Jehovah hath called me from the womb; from the bowels of my mother hath he made mention of my name: ^2and he hath made my mouth like a sharp sword; in the shadow of his hand hath he hid me: and he hath made me a polished shaft; in his quiver hath he kept me close: ^3and he said unto me, Thou art my servant; Israel, in whom I will be glorified. ^4But I said, I have labored in vain, I have spent my strength for nought and vanity; yet surely the justice due to me is with Jehovah, and my recompense with my God. ^5And now saith Jehovah that formed me from the womb to be his servant, to bring Jacob again to him, and that Israel be gathered unto him (for I am honorable in the eyes of Jehovah, and my God is become my strength); ^6yea, he saith, It is too light a thing that thou shouldest be my servant to raise up the tribes of Jacob, and to restore the preserved of Israel: I will also give thee for a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayest be my salvation unto the end of the earth. ^7Thus saith Jehovah, the Redeemer of Israel, and his Holy One, to him whom man despiseth, to him whom the nation abhorreth, to a servant of rulers: Kings shall see and arise; princes, and they shall worship; because of Jehovah that is faithful, even the Holy One of Israel, who hath chosen thee. ^8Thus saith Jehovah, In an acceptable time have I answered thee, and in a day of salvation have I helped thee; and I will preserve thee, and give thee for a covenant of the people, to raise up the land, to make them inherit the desolate heritages: ^9saying to them that are bound, Go forth; to them that are in darkness, Show yourselves. They shall feed in the ways, and on all bare heights shall be their pasture. ^10They shall not hunger nor thirst; neither shall the heat nor sun smite them: for he that hath mercy on them will lead them, even by springs of water will he guide them. ^11And I will make all my mountains a way, and my highways shall be exalted. ^12Lo, these shall come from far; and, lo, these from the north and from the west; and these from the land of Sinim. ^13Sing, O heavens; and be joyful, O earth; and break forth into singing, O mountains: for Jehovah hath comforted his people, and will have compassion upon his afflicted. ^14But Zion said, Jehovah hath forsaken me, and the Lord hath forgotten me. ^15Can a woman forget her sucking child, that she should not have compassion on the son of her womb? yea, these may forget, yet will not I forget thee. ^16Behold, I have graven thee upon the palms of my hands; thy walls are continually before me. ^17Thy children make haste; thy destroyers and they that made thee waste shall go forth from thee. ^18Lift up thine eyes round about, and behold: all these gather themselves together, and come to thee. As I live, saith Jehovah, thou shalt surely clothe thee with them all as with an ornament, and gird thyself with them, like a bride. ^19For, as for thy waste and thy desolate places, and thy land that hath been destroyed, surely now shalt thou be too strait for the inhabitants, and they that swallowed thee up shall be far away. ^20The children of thy bereavement shall yet say in thine ears, The place is too strait for me; give place to me that I may dwell. ^21Then shalt thou say in thy heart, Who hath begotten me these, seeing I have been bereaved of my children, and am solitary, an exile, and wandering to and fro? and who hath brought up these? Behold, I was left alone; these, where were they? ^22Thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Behold, I will lift up my hand to the nations, and set up my ensign to the peoples; and they shall bring thy sons in their bosom, and thy daughters shall be carried upon their shoulders. ^23And kings shall be thy nursing fathers, and their queens thy nursing mothers: they shall bow down to thee with their faces to the earth, and lick the dust of thy feet; and thou shalt know that I am Jehovah; and they that wait for me shall not be put to shame. ^24Shall the prey be taken from the mighty, or the lawful captives be delivered? ^25But thus saith Jehovah, Even the captives of the mighty shall be taken away, and the prey of the terrible shall be delivered; for I will contend with him that contendeth with thee, and I will save thy children. ^26And I will feed them that oppress thee with their own flesh; and they shall be drunken with their own blood, as with sweet wine: and all flesh shall know that I, Jehovah, am thy Saviour, and thy Redeemer, the Mighty One of Jacob.

Isaiah 50

50

^1Thus saith Jehovah, Where is the bill of your mother's divorcement, wherewith I have put her away? or which of my creditors is it to whom I have sold you? Behold, for your iniquities were ye sold, and for your transgressions was your mother put away. ^2Wherefore, when I came, was there no man? when I called, was there none to answer? Is my hand shortened at all, that it cannot redeem? or have I no power to deliver? Behold, at my rebuke I dry up the sea, I make the rivers a wilderness: their fish stink, because there is no water, and die for thirst. ^3I clothe the heavens with blackness, and I make sackcloth their covering. ^4The Lord Jehovah hath given me the tongue of them that are taught, that I may know how to sustain with words him that is weary: he wakeneth morning by morning, he wakeneth mine ear to hear as they that are taught. ^5The Lord Jehovah hath opened mine ear, and I was not rebellious, neither turned away backward. ^6I gave my back to the smiters, and my cheeks to them that plucked off the hair; I hid not my face from shame and spitting. ^7For the Lord Jehovah will help me; therefore have I not been confounded: therefore have I set my face like a flint, and I know that I shall not be put to shame. ^8He is near that justifieth me; who will content with me? let us stand up together: who is mine adversary? let him come near to me. ^9Behold, the Lord Jehovah will help me; who is he that shall condemn me? behold, all they shall wax old as a garment, the moth shall eat them up. ^10Who is among you that feareth Jehovah, that obeyeth the voice of his servant? he that walketh in darkness, and hath no light, let him trust in the name of Jehovah, and rely upon his God. ^11Behold, all ye that kindle a fire, that gird yourselves about with firebrands; walk ye in the flame of your fire, and among the brands that ye have kindled. This shall ye have of my hand; ye shall lie down in sorrow.

Isaiah 52

52

^1Awake, awake, put on thy strength, O Zion; put on thy beautiful garments, O Jerusalem, the holy city: for henceforth there shall no more come into thee the uncircumcised and the unclean. ^2Shake thyself from the dust; arise, sit on thy throne, O Jerusalem: loose thyself from the bonds of thy neck, O captive daughter of Zion. ^3For thus saith Jehovah, Ye were sold for nought; and ye shall be redeemed without money. ^4For thus saith the Lord Jehovah, My people went down at the first into Egypt to sojourn there: and the Assyrian hath oppressed them without cause. ^5Now therefore, what do I here, saith Jehovah, seeing that my people is taken away for nought? they that rule over them do howl, saith Jehovah, and my name continually all the day is blasphemed. ^6Therefore my people shall know my name: therefore they shall know in that day that I am he that doth speak; behold, it is I. ^7How beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace, that bringeth good tidings of good, that publisheth salvation, that saith unto Zion, Thy God reigneth! ^8The voice of thy watchmen! they lift up the voice, together do they sing; for they shall see eye to eye, when Jehovah returneth to Zion. ^9Break forth into joy, sing together, ye waste places of Jerusalem; for Jehovah hath comforted his people, he hath redeemed Jerusalem. ^10Jehovah hath made bare his holy arm in the eyes of all the nations; and all the ends of the earth have seen the salvation of our God. ^11Depart ye, depart ye, go ye out from thence, touch no unclean thing; go ye out of the midst of her; cleanse yourselves, ye that bear the vessels of Jehovah. ^12For ye shall not go out in haste, neither shall ye go by flight: for Jehovah will go before you; and the God of Israel will be your rearward. ^13Behold, my servant shall deal wisely, he shall be exalted and lifted up, and shall be very high. ^14Like as many were astonished at thee (his visage was so marred more than any man, and his form more than the sons of men), ^15so shall he sprinkle many nations; kings shall shut their mouths at him: for that which had not been told them shall they see; and that which they had not heard shall they understand.

Isaiah 53

53

^1Who hath believed our message? and to whom hath the arm of Jehovah been revealed? ^2For he grew up before him as a tender plant, and as a root out of a dry ground: he hath no form nor comeliness; and when we see him, there is no beauty that we should desire him. ^3He was despised, and rejected of men; a man of sorrows, and acquainted with grief: and as one from whom men hide their face he was despised; and we esteemed him not. ^4Surely he hath borne our griefs, and carried our sorrows; yet we did esteem him stricken, smitten of God, and afflicted. ^5But he was wounded for our transgressions, he was bruised for our iniquities; the chastisement of our peace was upon him; and with his stripes we are healed. ^6All we like sheep have gone astray; we have turned every one to his own way; and Jehovah hath laid on him the iniquity of us all. ^7He was oppressed, yet when he was afflicted he opened not his mouth; as a lamb that is led to the slaughter, and as a sheep that before its shearers is dumb, so he opened not his mouth. ^8By oppression and judgment he was taken away; and as for his generation, who among them considered that he was cut off out of the land of the living for the transgression of my people to whom the stroke was due? ^9And they made his grave with the wicked, and with a rich man in his death; although he had done no violence, neither was any deceit in his mouth. ^10Yet it pleased Jehovah to bruise him; he hath put him to grief: when thou shalt make his soul an offering for sin, he shall see his seed, he shall prolong his days, and the pleasure of Jehovah shall prosper in his hand. ^11He shall see of the travail of his soul, and shall be satisfied: by the knowledge of himself shall my righteous servant justify many; and he shall bear their iniquities. ^12Therefore will I divide him a portion with the great, and he shall divide the spoil with the strong; because he poured out his soul unto death, and was numbered with the transgressors: yet he bare the sin of many, and made intercession for the transgressors.

Isaiah 54

54

^1Sing, O barren, thou that didst not bear; break forth into singing, and cry aloud, thou that didst not travail with child: for more are the children of the desolate than the children of the married wife, saith Jehovah. ^2Enlarge the place of thy tent, and let them stretch forth the curtains of thy habitations; spare not: lengthen thy cords, and strengthen thy stakes. ^3For thou shalt spread aboard on the right hand and on the left; and thy seed shall possess the nations, and make the desolate cities to be inhabited. ^4Fear not; for thou shalt not be ashamed: neither be thou confounded; for thou shalt not be put to shame: for thou shalt forget the shame of thy youth; and the reproach of thy widowhood shalt thou remember no more. ^5For thy Maker is thy husband; Jehovah of hosts is his name: and the Holy One of Israel is thy Redeemer; the God of the whole earth shall he be called. ^6For Jehovah hath called thee as a wife forsaken and grieved in spirit, even a wife of youth, when she is cast off, saith thy God. ^7For a small moment have I forsaken thee; but with great mercies will I gather thee. ^8In overflowing wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment; but with everlasting lovingkindness will I have mercy on thee, saith Jehovah thy Redeemer. ^9For this is as the waters of Noah unto me; for as I have sworn that the waters of Noah shall no more go over the earth, so have I sworn that I will not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee. ^10For the mountains may depart, and the hills be removed; but my lovingkindness shall not depart from thee, neither shall my covenant of peace be removed, saith Jehovah that hath mercy on thee. ^11O thou afflicted, tossed with tempest, and not comforted, behold, I will set thy stones in fair colors, and lay thy foundations with sapphires. ^12And I will make thy pinnacles of rubies, and thy gates of carbuncles, and all thy border of precious stones. ^13And all thy children shall be taught of Jehovah; and great shall be the peace of thy children. ^14In righteousness shalt thou be established: thou shalt be far from oppression, for thou shalt not fear; and from terror, for it shall not come near thee. ^15Behold, they may gather together, but not by me: whosoever shall gather together against thee shall fall because of thee. ^16Behold, I have created the smith that bloweth the fire of coals, and bringeth forth a weapon for his work; and I have created the waster to destroy. ^17No weapon that is formed against thee shall prosper; and every tongue that shall rise against thee in judgment thou shalt condemn. This is the heritage of the servants of Jehovah, and their righteousness which is of me, saith Jehovah.

Isaiah 55

55

^1Ho, every one that thirsteth, come ye to the waters, and he that hath no money; come ye, buy, and eat; yea, come, buy wine and milk without money and without price. ^2Wherefore do ye spend money for that which is not bread? and your labor for that which satisfieth not? hearken diligently unto me, and eat ye that which is good, and let your soul delight itself in fatness. ^3Incline your ear, and come unto me; hear, and your soul shall live: and I will make an everlasting covenant with you, even the sure mercies of David. ^4Behold, I have given him for a witness to the peoples, a leader and commander to the peoples. ^5Behold, thou shalt call a nation that thou knowest not; and a nation that knew not thee shall run unto thee, because of Jehovah thy God, and for the Holy One of Israel; for he hath glorified thee. ^6Seek ye Jehovah while he may be found; call ye upon him while he is near: ^7let the wicked forsake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts; and let him return unto Jehovah, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon. ^8For my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your ways my ways, saith Jehovah. ^9For as the heavens are higher than the earth, so are my ways higher than your ways, and my thoughts than your thoughts. ^10For as the rain cometh down and the snow from heaven, and returneth not thither, but watereth the earth, and maketh it bring forth and bud, and giveth seed to the sower and bread to the eater; ^11so shall my word be that goeth forth out of my mouth: it shall not return unto me void, but it shall accomplish that which I please, and it shall prosper in the thing whereto I sent it. ^12For ye shall go out with joy, and be led forth with peace: the mountains and the hills shall break forth before you into singing; and all the trees of the fields shall clap their hands. ^13Instead of the thorn shall come up the fir-tree; and instead of the brier shall come up the myrtle-tree: and it shall be to Jehovah for a name, for an everlasting sign that shall not be cut off.

Isaiah 56

56

^1Thus saith Jehovah, Keep ye justice, and do righteousness; for my salvation is near to come, and my righteousness to be revealed. ^2Blessed is the man that doeth this, and the son of man that holdeth it fast; that keepeth the sabbath from profaning it, and keepeth his hand from doing any evil. ^3Neither let the foreigner, that hath joined himself to Jehovah, speak, saying, Jehovah will surely separate me from his people; neither let the eunuch say, Behold, I am a dry tree. ^4For thus saith Jehovah of the eunuchs that keep my sabbaths, and choose the things that please me, and hold fast my covenant: ^5Unto them will I give in my house and within my walls a memorial and a name better than of sons and of daughters; I will give them an everlasting name, that shall not be cut off. ^6Also the foreigners that join themselves to Jehovah, to minister unto him, and to love the name of Jehovah, to be his servants, every one that keepeth the sabbath from profaning it, and holdeth fast my covenant; ^7even them will I bring to my holy mountain, and make them joyful in my house of prayer: their burnt-offerings and their sacrifices shall be accepted upon mine altar; for my house shall be called a house of prayer for all peoples. ^8The Lord Jehovah, who gathereth the outcasts of Israel, saith, Yet will I gather others to him, besides his own that are gathered. ^9All ye beasts of the field, come to devour, yea, all ye beasts in the forest. ^10His watchmen are blind, they are all without knowledge; they are all dumb dogs, they cannot bark; dreaming, lying down, loving to slumber. ^11Yea, the dogs are greedy, they can never have enough; and these are shepherds that cannot understand: they have all turned to their own way, each one to his gain, from every quarter. ^12Come ye, say they, I will fetch wine, and we will fill ourselves with strong drink; and to-morrow shall be as this day, a day great beyond measure.

Isaiah 57

57

^1The righteous perisheth, and no man layeth it to heart; and merciful men are taken away, none considering that the righteous is taken away from the evil to come. ^2He entereth into peace; they rest in their beds, each one that walketh in his uprightness. ^3But draw near hither, ye sons of the sorceress, the seed of the adulterer and the harlot. ^4Against whom do ye sport yourselves? against whom make ye a wide mouth, and put out the tongue? are ye not children of transgression, a seed of falsehood, ^5ye that inflame yourselves among the oaks, under every green tree; that slay the children in the valleys, under the clefts of the rocks? ^6Among the smooth stones of the valley is thy portion; they, they are thy lot; even to them hast thou poured a drink-offering, thou hast offered an oblation. Shall I be appeased for these things? ^7Upon a high and lofty mountain hast thou set thy bed; thither also wentest thou up to offer sacrifice. ^8And behind the doors and the posts hast thou set up thy memorial: for thou hast uncovered thyself to another than me, and art gone up; thou hast enlarged thy bed, and made thee a covenant with them: thou lovedst their bed where thou sawest it. ^9And thou wentest to the king with oil, and didst increase thy perfumes, and didst send thine ambassadors far off, and didst debase thyself even unto Sheol. ^10Thou wast wearied with the length of thy way; yet saidst thou not, It is in vain: thou didst find a quickening of thy strength; therefore thou wast not faint. ^11And of whom hast thou been afraid and in fear, that thou liest, and hast not remembered me, nor laid it to thy heart? have not I held my peace even of long time, and thou fearest me not? ^12I will declare thy righteousness; and as for thy works, they shall not profit thee. ^13When thou criest, let them that thou hast gathered deliver thee; but the wind shall take them, a breath shall carry them all away: but he that taketh refuge in me shall possess the land, and shall inherit my holy mountain. ^14And he will say, Cast ye up, cast ye up, prepare the way, take up the stumbling-block out of the way of my people. ^15For thus saith the high and lofty One that inhabiteth eternity, whose name is Holy: I dwell in the high and holy place, with him also that is of a contrite and humble spirit, to revive the spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite. ^16For I will not contend for ever, neither will I be always wroth; for the spirit would faint before me, and the souls that I have made. ^17For the iniquity of his covetousness was I wroth, and smote him; I hid my face and was wroth; and he went on backsliding in the way of his heart. ^18I have seen his ways, and will heal him: I will lead him also, and restore comforts unto him and to his mourners. ^19I create the fruit of the lips: Peace, peace, to him that is far off and to him that is near, saith Jehovah; and I will heal him. ^20But the wicked are like the troubled sea; for it cannot rest, and its waters cast up mire and dirt. ^21There is no peace, saith my God, to the wicked.

Isaiah 58

58

^1Cry aloud, spare not, lift up thy voice like a trumpet, and declare unto my people their transgression, and to the house of Jacob their sins. ^2Yet they seek me daily, and delight to know my ways: as a nation that did righteousness, and forsook not the ordinance of their God, they ask of me righteous judgments; they delight to draw near unto God. ^3Wherefore have we fasted, say they, and thou seest not? wherefore have we afflicted our soul, and thou takest no knowledge? Behold, in the day of your fast ye find your own pleasure, and exact all your labors. ^4Behold, ye fast for strife and contention, and to smite with the fist of wickedness: ye fast not this day so as to make your voice to be heard on high. ^5Is such the fast that I have chosen? the day for a man to afflict his soul? Is it to bow down his head as a rush, and to spread sackcloth and ashes under him? wilt thou call this a fast, and an acceptable day to Jehovah? ^6Is not this the fast that I have chosen: to loose the bonds of wickedness, to undo the bands of the yoke, and to let the oppressed go free, and that ye break every yoke? ^7Is it not to deal thy bread to the hungry, and that thou bring the poor that are cast out to thy house? when thou seest the naked, that thou cover him; and that thou hide not thyself from thine own flesh? ^8Then shall thy light break forth as the morning, and thy healing shall spring forth speedily; and thy righteousness shall go before thee; the glory of Jehovah shall by thy rearward. ^9Then shalt thou call, and Jehovah will answer; thou shalt cry, and he will say, Here I am. If thou take away from the midst of thee the yoke, the putting forth of the finger, and speaking wickedly; ^10and if thou draw out thy soul to the hungry, and satisfy the afflicted soul: then shall thy light rise in darkness, and thine obscurity be as the noonday; ^11and Jehovah will guide thee continually, and satisfy thy soul in dry places, and make strong thy bones; and thou shalt be like a watered garden, and like a spring of water, whose waters fail not. ^12And they that shall be of thee shall build the old waste places; thou shalt raise up the foundations of many generations; and thou shalt be called The repairer of the breach, The restorer of paths to dwell in. ^13If thou turn away thy foot from the sabbath, from doing thy pleasure on my holy day; and call the sabbath a delight, and the holy of Jehovah honorable; and shalt honor it, not doing thine own ways, nor finding thine own pleasure, nor speaking thine own words: ^14then shalt thou delight thyself in Jehovah; and I will make thee to ride upon the high places of the earth; and I will feed thee with the heritage of Jacob thy father: for the mouth of Jehovah hath spoken it.

Isaiah 59

59

^1Behold, Jehovah's hand is not shortened, that it cannot save; neither his ear heavy, that it cannot hear: ^2but your iniquities have separated between you and your God, and your sins have hid his face from you, so that he will not hear. ^3For your hands are defiled with blood, and your fingers with iniquity; your lips have spoken lies, your tongue muttereth wickedness. ^4None sueth in righteousness, and none pleadeth in truth: they trust in vanity, and speak lies; they conceive mischief, and bring forth iniquity. ^5They hatch adders' eggs, and weave the spider's web: he that eateth of their eggs dieth; and that which is crushed breaketh out into a viper. ^6Their webs shall not become garments, neither shall they cover themselves with their works: their works are works of iniquity, and the act of violence is in their hands. ^7Their feet run to evil, and they make haste to shed innocent blood: their thoughts are thoughts of iniquity; desolation and destruction are in their paths. ^8The way of peace they know not; and there is no justice in their goings: they have made them crooked paths; whosoever goeth therein doth not know peace. ^9Therefore is justice far from us, neither doth righteousness overtake us: we look for light, but, behold, darkness; for brightness, but we walk in obscurity. ^10We grope for the wall like the blind; yea, we grope as they that have no eyes: we stumble at noonday as in the twilight; among them that are lusty we are as dead men. ^11We roar all like bears, and moan sore like doves: we look for justice, but there is none; for salvation, but it is far off from us. ^12For our transgressions are multiplied before thee, and our sins testify against us; for our transgressions are with us, and as for our iniquities, we know them: ^13transgressing and denying Jehovah, and turning away from following our God, speaking oppression and revolt, conceiving and uttering from the heart words of falsehood. ^14And justice is turned away backward, and righteousness standeth afar off; for truth is fallen in the street, and uprightness cannot enter. ^15Yea, truth is lacking; and he that departeth from evil maketh himself a prey. And Jehovah saw it, and it displeased him that there was no justice. ^16And he saw that there was no man, and wondered that there was no intercessor: therefore his own arm brought salvation unto him; and his righteousness, it upheld him. ^17And he put on righteousness as a breastplate, and a helmet of salvation upon his head; and he put on garments of vengeance for clothing, and was clad with zeal as a mantle. ^18According to their deeds, accordingly he will repay, wrath to his adversaries, recompense to his enemies; to the islands he will repay recompense. ^19So shall they fear the name of Jehovah from the west, and his glory from the rising of the sun; for he will come as a rushing stream, which the breath of Jehovah driveth. ^20And a Redeemer will come to Zion, and unto them that turn from transgression in Jacob, saith Jehovah. ^21And as for me, this is my covenant with them, saith Jehovah: my Spirit that is upon thee, and my words which I have put in thy mouth, shall not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy seed, nor out of the mouth of thy seed's seed, saith Jehovah, from henceforth and for ever.

Isaiah 60

60

^1Arise, shine; for thy light is come, and the glory of Jehovah is risen upon thee. ^2For, behold, darkness shall cover the earth, and gross darkness the peoples; but Jehovah will arise upon thee, and his glory shall be seen upon thee. ^3And nations shall come to thy light, and kings to the brightness of thy rising. ^4Lift up thine eyes round about, and see: they all gather themselves together, they come to thee; thy sons shall come from far, and thy daughters shall be carried in the arms. ^5Then thou shalt see and be radiant, and thy heart shall thrill and be enlarged; because the abundance of the sea shall be turned unto thee, the wealth of the nations shall come unto thee. ^6The multitude of camels shall cover thee, the dromedaries of Midian and Ephah; all they from Sheba shall come; they shall bring gold and frankincense, and shall proclaim the praises of Jehovah. ^7All the flocks of Kedar shall be gathered together unto thee, the rams of Nebaioth shall minister unto thee; they shall come up with acceptance on mine altar; and I will glorify the house of my glory. ^8Who are these that fly as a cloud, and as the doves to their windows? ^9Surely the isles shall wait for me, and the ships of Tarshish first, to bring thy sons from far, their silver and their gold with them, for the name of Jehovah thy God, and for the Holy One of Israel, because he hath glorified thee. ^10And foreigners shall build up thy walls, and their kings shall minister unto thee: for in my wrath I smote thee, but in my favor have I had mercy on thee. ^11Thy gates also shall be open continually; they shall not be shut day nor night; that men may bring unto thee the wealth of the nations, and their kings led captive. ^12For that nation and kingdom that will not serve thee shall perish; yea, those nations shall be utterly wasted. ^13The glory of Lebanon shall come unto thee, the fir-tree, the pine, and the box-tree together, to beautify the place of my sanctuary; and I will make the place of my feet glorious. ^14And the sons of them that afflicted thee shall come bending unto thee; and all they that despised thee shall bow themselves down at the soles of thy feet; and they shall call thee The city of Jehovah, The Zion of the Holy One of Israel. ^15Whereas thou hast been forsaken and hated, so that no man passed through thee, I will make thee an eternal excellency, a joy of many generations. ^16Thou shalt also suck the milk of the nations, and shalt suck the breast of kings; and thou shalt know that I, Jehovah, am thy Saviour, and thy Redeemer, the Mighty One of Jacob. ^17For brass I will bring gold, and for iron I will bring silver, and for wood brass, and for stones iron. I will also make thy officers peace, and thine exactors righteousness. ^18Violence shall no more be heard in thy land, desolation nor destruction within thy borders; but thou shalt call thy walls Salvation, and thy gates Praise. ^19The sun shall be no more thy light by day; neither for brightness shall the moon give light unto thee: but Jehovah will be unto thee an everlasting light, and thy God thy glory. ^20Thy sun shall no more go down, neither shall thy moon withdraw itself; for Jehovah will be thine everlasting light, and the days of thy mourning shall be ended. ^21Thy people also shall be all righteous; they shall inherit the land for ever, the branch of my planting, the work of my hands, that I may be glorified. ^22The little one shall become a thousand, and the small one a strong nation; I, Jehovah, will hasten it in its time.

Isaiah 61

61

^1The Spirit of the Lord Jehovah is upon me; because Jehovah hath anointed me to preach good tidings unto the meek; he hath sent me to bind up the broken-hearted, to proclaim liberty to the captives, and the opening of the prison to them that are bound; ^2to proclaim the year of Jehovah's favor, and the day of vengeance of our God; to comfort all that mourn; ^3to appoint unto them that mourn in Zion, to give unto them a garland for ashes, the oil of joy for mourning, the garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness; that they may be called trees of righteousness, the planting of Jehovah, that he may be glorified. ^4And they shall build the old wastes, they shall raise up the former desolations, and they shall repair the waste cities, the desolations of many generations. ^5And strangers shall stand and feed your flocks, and foreigners shall be your plowmen and your vine-dressers. ^6But ye shall be named the priests of Jehovah; men shall call you the ministers of our God: ye shall eat the wealth of the nations, and in their glory shall ye boast yourselves. ^7Instead of your shame ye shall have double; and instead of dishonor they shall rejoice in their portion: therefore in their land they shall possess double; everlasting joy shall be unto them. ^8For I, Jehovah, love justice, I hate robbery with iniquity; and I will give them their recompense in truth, and I will make an everlasting covenant with them. ^9And their seed shall be known among the nations, and their offspring among the peoples; all that see them shall acknowledge them, that they are the seed which Jehovah hath blessed. ^10I will greatly rejoice in Jehovah, my soul shall be joyful in my God; for he hath clothed me with the garments of salvation, he hath covered me with the robe of righteousness, as a bridegroom decketh himself with a garland, and as a bride adorneth herself with her jewels. ^11For as the earth bringeth forth its bud, and as the garden causeth the things that are sown in it to spring forth; so the Lord Jehovah will cause righteousness and praise to spring forth before all the nations.

Isaiah 62

62

^1For Zion's sake will I not hold my peace, and for Jerusalem's sake I will not rest, until her righteousness go forth as brightness, and her salvation as a lamp that burneth. ^2And the nations shall see thy righteousness, and all kings thy glory, and thou shalt be called by a new name, which the mouth of Jehovah shall name. ^3Thou shalt also be a crown of beauty in the hand of Jehovah, and a royal diadem in the hand of thy God. ^4Thou shalt no more be termed Forsaken; neither shall thy land any more be termed Desolate: but thou shalt be called Hephzi-bah, and thy land Beulah; for Jehovah delighteth in thee, and thy land shall be married. ^5For as a young man marrieth a virgin, so shall thy sons marry thee; and as the bridegroom rejoiceth over the bride, so shall thy God rejoice over thee. ^6I have set watchmen upon thy walls, O Jerusalem; they shall never hold their peace day nor night: ye that are Jehovah's remembrancers, take ye no rest, ^7and give him no rest, till he establish, and till he make Jerusalem a praise in the earth. ^8Jehovah hath sworn by his right hand, and by the arm of his strength, Surely I will no more give thy grain to be food for thine enemies; and foreigners shall not drink thy new wine, for which thou hast labored: ^9but they that have garnered it shall eat it, and praise Jehovah; and they that have gathered it shall drink it in the courts of my sanctuary. ^10Go through, go through the gates; prepare ye the way of the people; cast up, cast up the highway; gather out the stones; lift up an ensign for the peoples. ^11Behold, Jehovah hath proclaimed unto the end of the earth, Say ye to the daughter of Zion, Behold, thy salvation cometh; behold, his reward is with him, and his recompense before him. ^12And they shall call them The holy people, The redeemed of Jehovah: and thou shalt be called Sought out, A city not forsaken.

Isaiah 63

63

^1Who is this that cometh from Edom, with dyed garments from Bozrah? this that is glorious in his apparel, marching in the greatness of his strength? I that speak in righteousness, mighty to save. ^2Wherefore art thou red in thine apparel, and thy garments like him that treadeth in the winevat? ^3I have trodden the winepress alone; and of the peoples there was no man with me: yea, I trod them in mine anger, and trampled them in my wrath; and their lifeblood is sprinkled upon my garments, and I have stained all my raiment. ^4For the day of vengeance was in my heart, and the year of my redeemed is come. ^5And I looked, and there was none to help; and I wondered that there was none to uphold: therefore mine own arm brought salvation unto me; and my wrath, it upheld me. ^6And I trod down the peoples in mine anger, and made them drunk in my wrath, and I poured out their lifeblood on the earth. ^7I will make mention of the lovingkindnesses of Jehovah, and the praises of Jehovah, according to all that Jehovah hath bestowed on us, and the great goodness toward the house of Israel, which he hath bestowed on them according to his mercies, and according to the multitude of his lovingkindnesses. ^8For he said, Surely, they are my people, children that will not deal falsely: so he was their Saviour. ^9In all their affliction he was afflicted, and the angel of his presence saved them: in his love and in his pity he redeemed them; and he bare them, and carried them all the days of old. ^10But they rebelled, and grieved his holy Spirit: therefore he was turned to be their enemy, and himself fought against them. ^11Then he remembered the days of old, Moses and his people, saying, Where is he that brought them up out of the sea with the shepherds of his flock? where is he that put his holy Spirit in the midst of them? ^12that caused his glorious arm to go at the right hand of Moses? that divided the waters before them, to make himself an everlasting name? ^13that led them through the depths, as a horse in the wilderness, so that they stumbled not? ^14As the cattle that go down into the valley, the Spirit of Jehovah caused them to rest; so didst thou lead thy people, to make thyself a glorious name. ^15Look down from heaven, and behold from the habitation of thy holiness and of thy glory: where are thy zeal and thy mighty acts? the yearning of thy heart and thy compassions are restrained toward me. ^16For thou art our Father, though Abraham knoweth us not, and Israel doth not acknowledge us: thou, O Jehovah, art our Father; our Redeemer from everlasting is thy name. ^17O Jehovah, why dost thou make us to err from thy ways, and hardenest our heart from thy fear? Return for thy servants' sake, the tribes of thine inheritance. ^18Thy holy people possessed it but a little while: our adversaries have trodden down thy sanctuary. ^19We are become as they over whom thou never barest rule, as they that were not called by thy name.

Isaiah 64

64

^1Oh that thou wouldest rend the heavens, that thou wouldest come down, that the mountains might quake at thy presence, ^2as when fire kindleth the brushwood, and the fire causeth the waters to boil; to make thy name known to thine adversaries, that the nations may tremble at thy presence! ^3When thou didst terrible things which we looked not for, thou camest down, the mountains quaked at thy presence. ^4For from of old men have not heard, nor perceived by the ear, neither hath the eye seen a God besides thee, who worketh for him that waiteth for him. ^5Thou meetest him that rejoiceth and worketh righteousness, those that remember thee in thy ways: behold, thou wast wroth, and we sinned: in them have we been of long time; and shall we be saved? ^6For we are all become as one that is unclean, and all our righteousnesses are as a polluted garment: and we all do fade as a leaf; and our iniquities, like the wind, take us away. ^7And there is none that calleth upon thy name, that stirreth up himself to take hold of thee; for thou hast hid thy face from us, and hast consumed us by means of our iniquities. ^8But now, O Jehovah, thou art our Father; we are the clay, and thou our potter; and we all are the work of thy hand. ^9Be not wroth very sore, O Jehovah, neither remember iniquity for ever: behold, look, we beseech thee, we are all thy people. ^10Thy holy cities are become a wilderness, Zion is become a wilderness, Jerusalem a desolation. ^11Our holy and our beautiful house, where our fathers praised thee, is burned with fire; and all our pleasant places are laid waste. ^12Wilt thou refrain thyself for these things, O Jehovah? wilt thou hold thy peace, and afflict us very sore?

Isaiah 65

65

^1I am inquired of by them that asked not for me; I am found of them that sought me not: I said, Behold me, behold me, unto a nation that was not called by my name. ^2I have spread out my hands all the day unto a rebellious people, that walk in a way that is not good, after their own thoughts; ^3a people that provoke me to my face continually, sacrificing in gardens, and burning incense upon bricks; ^4that sit among the graves, and lodge in the secret places; that eat swine's flesh, and broth of abominable things is in their vessels; ^5that say, Stand by thyself, come not near to me, for I am holier than thou. These are a smoke in my nose, a fire that burneth all the day. ^6Behold, it is written before me: I will not keep silence, but will recompense, yea, I will recompense into their bosom, ^7your own iniquities, and the iniquities of your fathers together, saith Jehovah, that have burned incense upon the mountains, and blasphemed me upon the hills; therefore will I first measure their work into their bosom. ^8Thus saith Jehovah, As the new wine is found in the cluster, and one saith, Destroy it not, for a blessing is in it: so will I do for my servants' sake, that I may not destroy them all. ^9And I will bring forth a seed out of Jacob, and out of Judah an inheritor of my mountains; and my chosen shall inherit it, and my servants shall dwell there. ^10And Sharon shall be a fold of flocks, and the valley of Achor a place for herds to lie down in, for my people that have sought me. ^11But ye that forsake Jehovah, that forget my holy mountain, that prepare a table for Fortune, and that fill up mingled wine unto Destiny; ^12I will destine you to the sword, and ye shall all bow down to the slaughter; because when I called, ye did not answer; when I spake, ye did not hear; but ye did that which was evil in mine eyes, and chose that wherein I delighted not. ^13Therefore thus saith the Lord Jehovah, Behold, my servants shall eat, but ye shall be hungry; behold, my servants shall drink, but ye shall be thirsty; behold, my servants shall rejoice, but ye shall be put to shame; ^14behold, my servants shall sing for joy of heart, but ye shall cry for sorrow of heart, and shall wail for vexation of spirit. ^15And ye shall leave your name for a curse unto my chosen; and the Lord Jehovah will slay thee; and he will call his servants by another name: ^16so that he who blesseth himself in the earth shall bless himself in the God of truth; and he that sweareth in the earth shall swear by the God of truth; because the former troubles are forgotten, and because they are hid from mine eyes. ^17For, behold, I create new heavens and a new earth; and the former things shall not be remembered, nor come into mind. ^18But be ye glad and rejoice for ever in that which I create; for, behold, I create Jerusalem a rejoicing, and her people a joy. ^19And I will rejoice in Jerusalem, and joy in my people; and there shall be heard in her no more the voice of weeping and the voice of crying. ^20There shall be no more thence an infant of days, nor an old man that hath not filled his days; for the child shall die a hundred years old, and the sinner being a hundred years old shall be accursed. ^21And they shall build houses, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and eat the fruit of them. ^22They shall not build, and another inhabit; they shall not plant, and another eat: for as the days of a tree shall be the days of my people, and my chosen shall long enjoy the work of their hands. ^23They shall not labor in vain, nor bring forth for calamity; for they are the seed of the blessed of Jehovah, and their offspring with them. ^24And it shall come to pass that, before they call, I will answer; and while they are yet speaking, I will hear. ^25The wolf and the lamb shall feed together, and the lion shall eat straw like the ox; and dust shall be the serpent's food. They shall not hurt nor destroy in all my holy mountain, saith Jehovah.

Isaiah 66

66

^1Thus saith Jehovah, Heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool: what manner of house will ye build unto me? and what place shall be my rest? ^2For all these things hath my hand made, and so all these things came to be, saith Jehovah: but to this man will I look, even to him that is poor and of a contrite spirit, and that trembleth at my word. ^3He that killeth an ox is as he that slayeth a man; he that sacrificeth a lamb, as he that breaketh a dog's neck; he that offereth an oblation, as he that offereth swine's blood; he that burneth frankincense, as he that blesseth an idol. Yea, they have chosen their own ways, and their soul delighteth in their abominations: ^4I also will choose their delusions, and will bring their fears upon them; because when I called, none did answer; when I spake, they did not hear: but they did that which was evil in mine eyes, and chose that wherein I delighted not. ^5Hear the word of Jehovah, ye that tremble at his word: Your brethren that hate you, that cast you out for my name's sake, have said, Let Jehovah be glorified, that we may see your joy; but it is they that shall be put to shame. ^6A voice of tumult from the city, a voice from the temple, a voice of Jehovah that rendereth recompense to his enemies. ^7Before she travailed, she brought forth; before her pain came, she was delivered of a man-child. ^8Who hath heard such a thing? who hath seen such things? Shall a land be born in one day? shall a nation be brought forth at once? for as soon as Zion travailed, she brought forth her children. ^9Shall I bring to the birth, and not cause to bring forth? saith Jehovah: shall I that cause to bring forth shut the womb? saith thy God. ^10Rejoice ye with Jerusalem, and be glad for her, all ye that love her: rejoice for joy with her, all ye that mourn over her; ^11that ye may suck and be satisfied with the breasts of her consolations; that ye may milk out, and be delighted with the abundance of her glory. ^12For thus saith Jehovah, Behold, I will extend peace to her like a river, and the glory of the nations like an overflowing stream: and ye shall suck thereof; ye shall be borne upon the side, and shall be dandled upon the knees. ^13As one whom his mother comforteth, so will I comfort you; and ye shall be comforted in Jerusalem. ^14And ye shall see it, and your heart shall rejoice, and your bones shall flourish like the tender grass: and the hand of Jehovah shall be known toward his servants; and he will have indignation against his enemies. ^15For, behold, Jehovah will come with fire, and his chariots shall be like the whirlwind; to render his anger with fierceness, and his rebuke with flames of fire. ^16For by fire will Jehovah execute judgment, and by his sword, upon all flesh; and the slain of Jehovah shall be many. ^17They that sanctify themselves and purify themselves to go unto the gardens, behind one in the midst, eating swine's flesh, and the abomination, and the mouse, they shall come to an end together, saith Jehovah. ^18For I know their works and their thoughts: the time cometh, that I will gather all nations and tongues; and they shall come, and shall see my glory. ^19And I will set a sign among them, and I will send such as escape of them unto the nations, to Tarshish, Pul, and Lud, that draw the bow, to Tubal and Javan, to the isles afar off, that have not heard my fame, neither have seen my glory; and they shall declare my glory among the nations. ^20And they shall bring all your brethren out of all the nations for an oblation unto Jehovah, upon horses, and in chariots, and in litters, and upon mules, and upon dromedaries, to my holy mountain Jerusalem, saith Jehovah, as the children of Israel bring their oblation in a clean vessel into the house of Jehovah. ^21And of them also will I take for priests and for Levites, saith Jehovah. ^22For as the new heavens and the new earth, which I will make, shall remain before me, saith Jehovah, so shall your seed and your name remain. ^23And it shall come to pass, that from one new moon to another, and from one sabbath to another, shall all flesh come to worship before me, saith Jehovah. ^24And they shall go forth, and look upon the dead bodies of the men that have transgressed against me: for their worm shall not die, neither shall their fire be quenched; and they shall be an abhorring unto all flesh.

1 Samuel 2

2

^1And Hannah prayed, and said:

My heart exulteth in Jehovah;

My horn is exalted in Jehovah;

My mouth is enlarged over mine enemies;

Because I rejoice in thy salvation.

^2There is none holy as Jehovah;

For there is none besides thee,

Neither is there any rock like our God.

^3Talk no more so exceeding proudly;

Let not arrogancy come out of your mouth;

For Jehovah is a God of knowledge,

And by him actions are weighed.

^4The bows of the mighty men are broken;

And they that stumbled are girded with strength.

^5They that were full have hired out themselves for bread;

And they that were hungry have ceased to hunger:

Yea, the barren hath borne seven;

And she that hath many children languisheth.

^6Jehovah killeth, and maketh alive:

He bringeth down to Sheol, and bringeth up.

^7Jehovah maketh poor, and maketh rich:

He bringeth low, he also lifteth up.

^8He raiseth up the poor out of the dust,

He lifteth up the needy from the dunghill,

To make them sit with princes,

And inherit the throne of glory:

For the pillars of the earth are Jehovah's,

And he hath set the world upon them.

^9He will keep the feet of his holy ones;

But the wicked shall be put to silence in darkness;

For by strength shall no man prevail.

^10They that strive with Jehovah shall be broken to pieces;

Against them will he thunder in heaven:

Jehovah will judge the ends of the earth;

And he will give strength unto his king,

And exalt the horn of his anointed.

^11And Elkanah went to Ramah to his house. And the child did minister unto Jehovah before Eli the priest.

^12Now the sons of Eli were base men; they knew not Jehovah. ^13And the custom of the priests with the people was, that, when any man offered sacrifice, the priest's servant came, while the flesh was boiling, with a flesh-hook of three teeth in his hand; ^14and he struck it into the pan, or kettle, or caldron, or pot; all that the flesh-hook brought up the priest took therewith. So they did in Shiloh unto all the Israelites that came thither. ^15Yea, before they burnt the fat, the priest's servant came, and said to the man that sacrificed, Give flesh to roast for the priest; for he will not have boiled flesh of thee, but raw. ^16And if the man said unto him, They will surely burn the fat first, and then take as much as thy soul desireth; then he would say, Nay, but thou shalt give it me now: and if not, I will take it by force. ^17And the sin of the young men was very great before Jehovah; for the men despised the offering of Jehovah.

^18But Samuel ministered before Jehovah, being a child, girded with a linen ephod. ^19Moreover his mother made him a little robe, and brought it to him from year to year, when she came up with her husband to offer the yearly sacrifice. ^20And Eli blessed Elkanah and his wife, and said, Jehovah give thee seed of this woman for the petition which was asked of Jehovah. And they went unto their own home. ^21And Jehovah visited Hannah, and she conceived, and bare three sons and two daughters. And the child Samuel grew before Jehovah.

^22Now Eli was very old; and he heard all that his sons did unto all Israel, and how that they lay with the women that did service at the door of the tent of meeting. ^23And he said unto them, Why do ye such things? for I hear of your evil dealings from all this people. ^24Nay, my sons; for it is no good report that I hear: ye make Jehovah's people to transgress. ^25If one man sin against another, God shall judge him; but if a man sin against Jehovah, who shall entreat for him? Notwithstanding, they hearkened not unto the voice of their father, because Jehovah was minded to slay them. ^26And the child Samuel grew on, and increased in favor both with Jehovah, and also with men.

^27And there came a man of God unto Eli, and said unto him, Thus saith Jehovah, Did I reveal myself unto the house of thy father, when they were in Egypt in bondage to Pharaoh's house? ^28and did I choose him out of all the tribes of Israel to be my priest, to go up unto mine altar, to burn incense, to wear an ephod before me? and did I give unto the house of thy father all the offerings of the children of Israel made by fire? ^29Wherefore kick ye at my sacrifice and at mine offering, which I have commanded in my habitation, and honorest thy sons above me, to make yourselves fat with the chiefest of all the offerings of Israel my people? ^30Therefore Jehovah, the God of Israel, saith, I said indeed that thy house, and the house of thy father, should walk before me for ever: but now Jehovah saith, Be it far from me; for them that honor me I will honor, and they that despise me shall be lightly esteemed. ^31Behold, the days come, that I will cut off thine arm, and the arm of thy father's house, that there shall not be an old man in thy house. ^32And thou shalt behold the affliction of my habitation, in all the wealth which God shall give Israel; and there shall not be an old man in thy house for ever. ^33And the man of thine, whom I shall not cut off from mine altar, shall be to consume thine eyes, and to grieve thy heart; and all the increase of thy house shall die in the flower of their age. ^34And this shall be the sign unto thee, that shall come upon thy two sons, on Hophni and Phinehas: in one day they shall die both of them. ^35And I will raise me up a faithful priest, that shall do according to that which is in my heart and in my mind: and I will build him a sure house; and he shall walk before mine anointed for ever. ^36And it shall come to pass, that every one that is left in thy house shall come and bow down to him for a piece of silver and a loaf of bread, and shall say, Put me, I pray thee, into one of the priests' offices, that I may eat a morsel of bread.

1 Samuel 3

3

^1And the child Samuel ministered unto Jehovah before Eli. And the word of Jehovah was precious in those days; there was no frequent vision. ^2And it came to pass at that time, when Eli was laid down in his place (now his eyes had begun to wax dim, so that he could not see), ^3and the lamp of God was not yet gone out, and Samuel was laid down to sleep, in the temple of Jehovah, where the ark of God was; ^4that Jehovah called Samuel; and he said, Here am I. ^5And he ran unto Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou calledst me. And he said, I called not; lie down again. And he went and lay down. ^6And Jehovah called yet again, Samuel. And Samuel arose and went to Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou calledst me. And he answered, I called not, my son; lie down again. ^7Now Samuel did not yet know Jehovah, neither was the word of Jehovah yet revealed unto him. ^8And Jehovah called Samuel again the third time. And he arose and went to Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou calledst me. And Eli perceived that Jehovah had called the child. ^9Therefore Eli said unto Samuel, Go, lie down: and it shall be, if he call thee, that thou shalt say, Speak, Jehovah; for thy servant heareth. So Samuel went and lay down in his place.

^10And Jehovah came, and stood, and called as at other times, Samuel, Samuel. Then Samuel said, Speak; for thy servant heareth. ^11And Jehovah said to Samuel, Behold, I will do a thing in Israel, at which both the ears of every one that heareth it shall tingle. ^12In that day I will perform against Eli all that I have spoken concerning his house, from the beginning even unto the end. ^13For I have told him that I will judge his house for ever, for the iniquity which he knew, because his sons did bring a curse upon themselves, and he restrained them not. ^14And therefore I have sworn unto the house of Eli, that the iniquity of Eli's house shall not be expiated with sacrifice nor offering for ever.

^15And Samuel lay until the morning, and opened the doors of the house of Jehovah. And Samuel feared to show Eli the vision. ^16Then Eli called Samuel, and said, Samuel, my son. And he said, Here am I. ^17And he said, What is the thing that Jehovah hath spoken unto thee? I pray thee, hide it not from me: God do so to thee, and more also, if thou hide anything from me of all the things that he spake unto thee. ^18And Samuel told him every whit, and hid nothing from him. And he said, It is Jehovah: let him do what seemeth him good.

^19And Samuel grew, and Jehovah was with him, and did let none of his words fall to the ground. ^20And all Israel from Dan even to Beer-sheba knew that Samuel was established to be a prophet of Jehovah. ^21And Jehovah appeared again in Shiloh; for Jehovah revealed himself to Samuel in Shiloh by the word of Jehovah.

1 Samuel 4

4

^1And the word of Samuel came to all Israel.

Now Israel went out against the Philistines to battle, and encamped beside Eben-ezer: and the Philistines encamped in Aphek. ^2And the Philistines put themselves in array against Israel: and when they joined battle, Israel was smitten before the Philistines; and they slew of the army in the field about four thousand men. ^3And when the people were come into the camp, the elders of Israel said, Wherefore hath Jehovah smitten us to-day before the Philistines? Let us fetch the ark of the covenant of Jehovah out of Shiloh unto us, that it may come among us, and save us out of the hand of our enemies. ^4So the people sent to Shiloh; and they brought from thence the ark of the covenant of Jehovah of hosts, who sitteth above the cherubim: and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were there with the ark of the covenant of God.

^5And when the ark of the covenant of Jehovah came into the camp, all Israel shouted with a great shout, so that the earth rang again. ^6And when the Philistines heard the noise of the shout, they said, What meaneth the noise of this great shout in the camp of the Hebrews? And they understood that the ark of Jehovah was come into the camp. ^7And the Philistines were afraid, for they said, God is come into the camp. And they said, Woe unto us! for there hath not been such a thing heretofore. ^8Woe unto us! who shall deliver us out of the hand of these mighty gods? these are the gods that smote the Egyptians with all manner of plagues in the wilderness. ^9Be strong, and quit yourselves like men, O ye Philistines, that ye be not servants unto the Hebrews, as they have been to you: quit yourselves like men, and fight. ^10And the Philistines fought, and Israel was smitten, and they fled every man to his tent: and there was a very great slaughter; for there fell of Israel thirty thousand footmen. ^11And the ark of God was taken; and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were slain.

^12And there ran a man of Benjamin out of the army, and came to Shiloh the same day, with his clothes rent, and with earth upon his head. ^13And when he came, lo, Eli was sitting upon his seat by the wayside watching; for his heart trembled for the ark of God. And when the man came into the city, and told it, all the city cried out. ^14And when Eli heard the noise of the crying, he said, What meaneth the noise of this tumult? And the man hasted, and came and told Eli. ^15Now Eli was ninety and eight years old; and his eyes were set, so that he could not see. ^16And the man said unto Eli, I am he that came out of the army, and I fled to-day out of the army. And he said, How went the matter, my son? ^17And he that brought the tidings answered and said, Israel is fled before the Philistines, and there hath been also a great slaughter among the people, and thy two sons also, Hophni and Phinehas, are dead, and the ark of God is taken. ^18And it came to pass, when he made mention of the ark of God, that Eli feel from off his seat backward by the side of the gate; and his neck brake, and he died: for he was an old man, and heavy. And he had judged Israel forty years.

^19And his daughter-in-law, Phinehas' wife, was with child, near to be delivered: and when she heard the tidings that the ark of God was taken, and that her father-in-law and her husband were dead, she bowed herself and brought forth; for her pains came upon her. ^20And about the time of her death the women that stood by her said unto her, Fear not; for thou hast brought forth a son. But she answered not, neither did she regard it. ^21And she named the child Ichabod, saying, The glory is departed from Israel; because the ark of God was taken, and because of her father-in-law and her husband. ^22And she said, The glory is departed from Israel; for the ark of God is taken.

1 Samuel 5

5

^1Now the Philistines had taken the ark of God, and they brought it from Eben-ezer unto Ashdod. ^2And the Philistines took the ark of God, and brought it into the house of Dagon, and set it by Dagon. ^3And when they of Ashdod arose early on the morrow, behold, Dagon was fallen upon his face to the ground before the ark of Jehovah. And they took Dagon, and set him in his place again. ^4And when they arose early on the morrow morning, behold, Dagon was fallen upon his face to the ground before the ark of Jehovah; and the head of Dagon and both the palms of his hands lay cut off upon the threshold; only the stump of Dagon was left to him. ^5Therefore neither the priests of Dagon, nor any that come into Dagon's house, tread on the threshold of Dagon in Ashdod, unto this day.

^6But the hand of Jehovah was heavy upon them of Ashdod, and he destroyed them, and smote them with tumors, even Ashdod and the borders thereof. ^7And when the men of Ashdod saw that it was so, they said, The ark of the God of Israel shall not abide with us; for his hand is sore upon us, and upon Dagon our god. ^8They sent therefore and gathered all the lords of the Philistines unto them, and said, What shall we do with the ark of the God of Israel? And they answered, Let the ark of the God of Israel be carried about unto Gath. And they carried the ark of the God of Israel thither. ^9And it was so, that, after they had carried it about, the hand of Jehovah was against the city with a very great discomfiture: and he smote the men of the city, both small and great; and tumors brake out upon them. ^10So they sent the ark of God to Ekron. And it came to pass, as the ark of God came to Ekron, that the Ekronites cried out, saying, They have brought about the ark of the God of Israel to us, to slay us and our people. ^11They sent therefore and gathered together all the lords of the Philistines, and they said, Send away the ark of the God of Israel, and let it go again to its own place, that is slay us not, and our people. For there was a deadly discomfiture throughout all the city; the hand of God was very heavy there. ^12And the men that died not were smitten with the tumors; and the cry of the city went up to heaven.

1 Samuel 6

6

^1And the ark of Jehovah was in the country of the Philistines seven months. ^2And the Philistines called for the priests and the diviners, saying, What shall we do with the ark of Jehovah? show us wherewith we shall sent it to its place. ^3And they said, If ye send away the ark of the God of Israel, send it not empty; but by all means return him a trespass-offering: then ye shall be healed, and it shall be known to you why his hand is not removed from you. ^4Then said they, What shall be the trespass-offering which we shall return to him? And they said, Five golden tumors, and five golden mice, according to the number of the lords of the Philistines; for one plague was on you all, and on your lords. ^5Wherefore ye shall make images of your tumors, and images of your mice that mar the land; and ye shall give glory unto the God of Israel: peradventure he will lighten his hand from off you, and from off your gods, and from off your land. ^6Wherefore then do ye harden your hearts, as the Egyptians and Pharaoh hardened their hearts? When he had wrought wonderfully among them, did they not let the people go, and they departed? ^7Now therefore take and prepare you a new cart, and two milch kine, on which there hath come no yoke; and tie the kine to the cart, and bring their calves home from them; ^8and take the ark of Jehovah, and lay it upon the cart; and put the jewels of gold, which ye return him for a trespass-offering, in a coffer by the side thereof; and send it away, that it may go. ^9And see; if it goeth up by the way of its own border to Beth-shemesh, then he hath done us this great evil: but if not, then we shall know that it is not his hand that smote us; it was a chance that happened to us.

^10And the men did so, and took two milch kine, and tied them to the cart, and shut up their calves at home; ^11and they put the ark of Jehovah upon the cart, and the coffer with the mice of gold and the images of their tumors. ^12And the kine took the straight way by the way to Beth-shemesh; they went along the highway, lowing as they went, and turned not aside to the right hand or to the left; and the lords of the Philistines went after them unto the border of Beth-shemesh. ^13And they of Beth-shemesh were reaping their wheat harvest in the valley; and they lifted up their eyes, and saw the ark, and rejoiced to see it. ^14And the cart came into the field of Joshua the Beth-shemite, and stood there, where there was a great stone: and they clave the wood of the cart, and offered up the kine for a burnt-offering unto Jehovah. ^15And the Levites took down the ark of Jehovah, and the coffer that was with it, wherein the jewels of gold were, and put them on the great stone: and the men of Beth-shemesh offered burnt-offerings and sacrificed sacrifices the same day unto Jehovah. ^16And when the five lords of the Philistines had seen it, they returned to Ekron the same day.

^17And these are the golden tumors which the Philistines returned for a trespass-offering unto Jehovah: for Ashdod one, for Gaza one, for Ashkelon one, for Gath one, for Ekron one; ^18and the golden mice, according to the number of all the cities of the Philistines belonging to the five lords, both of fortified cities and of country villages, even unto the great stone, whereon they set down the ark of Jehovah, which stone remaineth unto this day in the field of Joshua the Beth-shemite.

^19And he smote of the men of Beth-shemesh, because they had looked into the ark of Jehovah, he smote of the people seventy men, and fifty thousand men; and the people mourned, because Jehovah had smitten the people with a great slaughter. ^20And the men of Beth-shemesh said, Who is able to stand before Jehovah, this holy God? and to whom shall he go up from us? ^21And they sent messengers to the inhabitants of Kiriath-jearim, saying, The Philistines have brought back the ark of Jehovah; come ye down, and fetch it up to you.

1 Samuel 7

7

^1And the men of Kiriath-jearim came, and fetched up the ark of Jehovah, and brought it into the house of Abinadab in the hill, and sanctified Eleazar his son to keep the ark of Jehovah. ^2And it came to pass, from the day that the ark abode in Kiriath-jearim, that the time was long; for it was twenty years: and all the house of Israel lamented after Jehovah. ^3And Samuel spake unto all the house of Israel, saying, If ye do return unto Jehovah with all your heart, then put away the foreign gods and the Ashtaroth from among you, and direct your hearts unto Jehovah, and serve him only; and he will deliver you out of the hand of the Philistines. ^4Then the children of Israel did put away the Baalim and the Ashtaroth, and served Jehovah only.

^5And Samuel said, Gather all Israel to Mizpah, and I will pray for you unto Jehovah. ^6And they gathered together to Mizpah, and drew water, and poured it out before Jehovah, and fasted on that day, and said there, We have sinned against Jehovah. And Samuel judged the children of Israel in Mizpah. ^7And when the Philistines heard that the children of Israel were gathered together to Mizpah, the lords of the Philistines went up against Israel. And when the children of Israel heard it, they were afraid of the Philistines. ^8And the children of Israel said to Samuel, Cease not to cry unto Jehovah our God for us, that he will save us out of the hand of the Philistines. ^9And Samuel took a sucking lamb, and offered it for a whole burnt-offering unto Jehovah: and Samuel cried unto Jehovah for Israel; and Jehovah answered him. ^10And as Samuel was offering up the burnt-offering, the Philistines drew near to battle against Israel; but Jehovah thundered with a great thunder on that day upon the Philistines, and discomfited them; and they were smitten down before Israel. ^11And the men of Israel went out of Mizpah, and pursued the Philistines, and smote them, until they came under Beth-car.

^12Then Samuel took a stone, and set it between Mizpah and Shen, and called the name of it Eben-ezer, saying, Hitherto hath Jehovah helped us. ^13So the Philistines were subdued, and they came no more within the border of Israel: and the hand of Jehovah was against the Philistines all the days of Samuel. ^14And the cities which the Philistines had taken from Israel were restored to Israel, from Ekron even unto Gath; and the border thereof did Israel deliver out of the hand of the Philistines. And there was peace between Israel and the Amorites.

^15And Samuel judged Israel all the days of his life. ^16And he went from year to year in circuit to Beth-el and Gilgal, and Mizpah; and he judged Israel in all those places. ^17And his return was to Ramah, for there was his house; and there he judged Israel: and he built there an altar unto Jehovah.

1 Samuel 8

8

^1And it came to pass, when Samuel was old, that he made his sons judges over Israel. ^2Now the name of his first-born was Joel; and the name of his second, Abijah: they were judges in Beer-sheba. ^3And his sons walked not in his ways, but turned aside after lucre, and took bribes, and perverted justice.

^4Then all the elders of Israel gathered themselves together, and came to Samuel unto Ramah; ^5and they said unto him, Behold, thou art old, and thy sons walk not in thy ways: now make us a king to judge us like all the nations. ^6But the thing displeased Samuel, when they said, Give us a king to judge us. And Samuel prayed unto Jehovah. ^7And Jehovah said unto Samuel, Hearken unto the voice of the people in all that they say unto thee; for they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me, that I should not be king over them. ^8According to all the works which they have done since the day that I brought them up out of Egypt even unto this day, in that they have forsaken me, and served other gods, so do they also unto thee. ^9Now therefore hearken unto their voice: howbeit thou shalt protest solemnly unto them, and shalt show them the manner of the king that shall reign over them.

^10And Samuel told all the words of Jehovah unto the people that asked of him a king. ^11And he said, This will be the manner of the king that shall reign over you: he will take your sons, and appoint them unto him, for his chariots, and to be his horsemen; and they shall run before his chariots; ^12and he will appoint them unto him for captains of thousands, and captains of fifties; and he will set some to plow his ground, and to reap his harvest, and to make his instruments of war, and the instruments of his chariots. ^13And he will take your daughters to be perfumers, and to be cooks, and to be bakers. ^14And he will take your fields, and your vineyards, and your oliveyards, even the best of them, and give them to his servants. ^15And he will take the tenth of your seed, and of your vineyards, and give to his officers, and to his servants. ^16And he will take your men-servants, and your maid-servants, and your goodliest young men, and your asses, and put them to his work. ^17He will take the tenth of your flocks: and ye shall be his servants. ^18And ye shall cry out in that day because of your king whom ye shall have chosen you; and Jehovah will not answer you in that day.

^19But the people refused to hearken unto the voice of Samuel; and they said, Nay: but we will have a king over us, ^20that we also may be like all the nations, and that our king may judge us, and go out before us, and fight our battles. ^21And Samuel heard all the words of the people, and he rehearsed them in the ears of Jehovah. ^22And Jehovah said to Samuel, Hearken unto their voice, and make them a king. And Samuel said unto the men of Israel, Go ye every man unto his city.

1 Samuel 9

9

^1Now there was a man of Benjamin, whose name was Kish, the son of Abiel, the son of Zeror, the son of Becorath, the son of Aphiah, the son of a Benjamite, a mighty man of valor. ^2And he had a son, whose name was Saul, a young man and a goodly: and there was not among the children of Israel a goodlier person than he: from his shoulders and upward he was higher than any of the people. ^3And the asses of Kish, Saul's father, were lost. And Kish said to Saul his son, Take now one of the servants with thee, and arise, go seek the asses. ^4And he passed through the hill-country of Ephraim, and passed through the land of Shalishah, but they found them not: then they passed through the land of Shaalim, and there they were not: and he passed through the land of the Benjamites, but they found them not.

^5When they were come to the land of Zuph, Saul said to his servant that was with him, Come, and let us return, lest my father leave off caring for the asses, and be anxious for us. ^6And he said unto him, Behold now, there is in this city a man of God, and he is a man that is held in honor; all that he saith cometh surely to pass: now let us go thither; peradventure he can tell us concerning our journey whereon we go. ^7Then said Saul to his servant, But, behold, if we go, what shall we bring the man? for the bread is spent in our vessels, and there is not a present to bring to the man of God: what have we? ^8And the servant answered Saul again, and said, Behold, I have in my hand the fourth part of a shekel of silver: that will I give to the man of God, to tell us our way. ^9(Beforetime in Israel, when a man went to inquire of God, thus he said, Come, and let us go to the seer; for he that is now called a Prophet was beforetime called a Seer.) ^10Then said Saul to his servant, Well said; come, let us go. So they went unto the city where the man of God was.

^11As they went up the ascent to the city, they found young maidens going out to draw water, and said unto them, Is the seer here? ^12And they answered them, and said, He is; behold, he is before thee: make haste now, for he is come to-day into the city; for the people have a sacrifice to-day in the high place: ^13as soon as ye are come into the city, ye shall straightway find him, before he goeth up to the high place to eat; for the people will not eat until he come, because he doth bless the sacrifice; and afterwards they eat that are bidden. Now therefore get you up; for at this time ye shall find him. ^14And they went up to the city; and as they came within the city, behold, Samuel came out toward them, to go up to the high place.

^15Now Jehovah had revealed unto Samuel a day before Saul came, saying, ^16To-morrow about this time I will send thee a man out of the land of Benjamin, and thou shalt anoint him to be prince over my people Israel; and he shall save my people out of the hand of the Philistines: for I have looked upon my people, because their cry is come unto me. ^17And when Samuel saw Saul, Jehovah said unto him, Behold, the man of whom I spake to thee! this same shall have authority over my people. ^18Then Saul drew near to Samuel in the gate, and said, Tell me, I pray thee, where the seer's house is. ^19And Samuel answered Saul, and said, I am the seer; go up before me unto the high place, for ye shall eat with me to-day: and in the morning I will let thee go, and will tell thee all that is in thy heart. ^20And as for thine asses that were lost three days ago, set not they mind on them; for they are found. And for whom is all that is desirable in Israel? Is it not for thee, and for all thy father's house? ^21And Saul answered and said, Am not I a Benjamite, of the smallest of the tribes of Israel? and my family the least of all the families of the tribe of Benjamin? wherefore then speakest thou to me after this manner?

^22And Samuel took Saul and his servant, and brought them into the guest-chamber, and made them sit in the chiefest place among them that were bidden, who were about thirty persons. ^23And Samuel said unto the cook, Bring the portion which I gave thee, of which I said unto thee, Set it by thee. ^24And the cook took up the thigh, and that which was upon it, and set it before Saul. And Samuel said, Behold, that which hath been reserved! set it before thee and eat; because unto the appointed time hath it been kept for thee, for I said, I have invited the people. So Saul did eat with Samuel that day.

^25And when they were come down from the high place into the city, he communed with Saul upon the housetop. ^26And they arose early: and it came to pass about the spring of the day, that Samuel called to Saul on the housetop, saying, Up, that I may send thee away. And Saul arose, and they went out both of them, he and Samuel, abroad. ^27As they were going down at the end of the city, Samuel said to Saul, Bid the servant pass on before us (and he passed on), but stand thou still first, that I may cause thee to hear the word of God.

1 Samuel 10

10

^1Then Samuel took the vial of oil, and poured it upon his head, and kissed him, and said, Is it not that Jehovah hath anointed thee to be prince over his inheritance? ^2When thou art departed from me to-day, then thou shalt find two men by Rachel's sepulchre, in the border of Benjamin at Zelzah; and they will say unto thee, The asses which thou wentest to seek are found; and, lo, thy father hath left off caring for the asses, and is anxious for you, saying, What shall I do for my son? ^3Then shalt thou go on forward from thence, and thou shalt come to the oak of Tabor; and there shall meet thee there three men going up to God to Beth-el, one carrying three kids, and another carrying three loaves of bread, and another carrying a bottle of wine: ^4and they will salute thee, and give thee two loaves of bread, which thou shalt receive of their hand. ^5After that thou shalt come to the hill of God, where is the garrison of the Philistines: and it shall come to pass, when thou art come thither to the city, that thou shalt meet a band of prophets coming down from the high place with a psaltery, and a timbrel, and a pipe, and a harp, before them; and they will be prophesying: ^6and the Spirit of Jehovah will come mightily upon thee, and thou shalt prophesy with them, and shalt be turned into another man. ^7And let it be, when these signs are come unto thee, that thou do as occasion shall serve thee; for God is with thee. ^8And thou shalt go down before me to Gilgal; and, behold, I will come down unto thee, to offer burnt-offerings, and to sacrifice sacrifices of peace-offerings: seven days shalt thou tarry, till I come unto thee, and show thee what thou shalt do.

^9And it was so, that, when he had turned his back to go from Samuel, God gave him another heart: and all those signs came to pass that day. ^10And when they came thither to the hill, behold, a band of prophets met him; and the Spirit of God came mightily upon him, and he prophesied among them. ^11And it came to pass, when all that knew him beforetime saw that, behold, he prophesied with the prophets, then the people said one to another, What is this that is come unto the son of Kish? Is Saul also among the prophets? ^12And one of the same place answered and said, And who is their father? Therefore it became a proverb, Is Saul also among the prophets? ^13And when he had made an end of prophesying, he came to the high place.

^14And Saul's uncle said unto him and to his servant, Whither went ye? And he said, To seek the asses; and when we saw that they were not found, we came to Samuel. ^15And Saul's uncle said, Tell me, I pray thee, what Samuel said unto you. ^16And Saul said unto his uncle, He told us plainly that the asses were found. But concerning the matter of the kingdom, whereof Samuel spake, he told him not.

^17And Samuel called the people together unto Jehovah to Mizpah; ^18and he said unto the children of Israel, Thus saith Jehovah, the God of Israel, I brought up Israel out of Egypt, and I delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all the kingdoms that oppressed you: ^19but ye have this day rejected your God, who himself saveth you out of all your calamities and your distresses; and ye have said unto him, Nay, but set a king over us. Now therefore present yourselves before Jehovah by your tribes, and by your thousands. ^20So Samuel brought all the tribes of Israel near, and the tribe of Benjamin was taken. ^21And he brought the tribe of Benjamin near by their families; and the family of the Matrites was taken; and Saul the son of Kish was taken: but when they sought him, he could not be found. ^22Therefore they asked of Jehovah further, Is there yet a man to come hither? And Jehovah answered, Behold, he hath hid himself among the baggage. ^23And they ran and fetched him thence; and when he stood among the people, he was higher than any of the people from his shoulders and upward. ^24And Samuel said to all the people, See ye him whom Jehovah hath chosen, that there is none like him along all the people? And all the people shouted, and said, Long live the king.

^25Then Samuel told the people the manner of the kingdom, and wrote it in a book, and laid it up before Jehovah. And Samuel sent all the people away, every man to his house. ^26And Saul also went to his house to Gibeah; and there went with him the host, whose hearts God had touched. ^27But certain worthless fellows said, How shall this man save us? And they despised him, and brought him no present. But he held his peace.

1 Samuel 11

11

^1Then Nahash the Ammonite came up, and encamped against Jabesh-gilead: and all the men of Jabesh said unto Nahash, Make a covenant with us, and we will serve thee. ^2And Nahash the Ammonite said unto them, On this condition will I make it with you, that all your right eyes be put out; and I will lay it for a reproach upon all Israel. ^3And the elders of Jabesh said unto him, Give us seven days' respite, that we may send messengers unto all the borders of Israel; and then, if there be none to save us, we will come out to thee. ^4Then came the messengers to Gibeah of Saul, and spake these words in the ears of the people: and all the people lifted up their voice, and wept. ^5And, behold, Saul came following the oxen out of the field; and Saul said, What aileth the people that they weep? And they told him the words of the men of Jabesh.

^6And the Spirit of God came mightily upon Saul when he heard those words, and his anger was kindled greatly. ^7And he took a yoke of oxen, and cut them in pieces, and sent them throughout all the borders of Israel by the hand of messengers, saying, Whosoever cometh not forth after Saul and after Samuel, so shall it be done unto his oxen. And the dread of Jehovah fell on the people, and they came out as one man. ^8And he numbered them in Bezek; and the children of Israel were three hundred thousand, and the men of Judah thirty thousand. ^9And they said unto the messengers that came, Thus shall ye say unto the men of Jabesh-gilead, To-morrow, by the time the sun is hot, ye shall have deliverance. And the messengers came and told the men of Jabesh; and they were glad. ^10Therefore the men of Jabesh said, To-morrow we will come out unto you, and ye shall do with us all that seemeth good unto you. ^11And it was so on the morrow, that Saul put the people in three companies; and they came into the midst of the camp in the morning watch, and smote the Ammonites until the heat of the day: and it came to pass, that they that remained were scattered, so that not two of them were left together.

^12And the people said unto Samuel, Who is he that said, Shall Saul reign over us? bring the men, that we may put them to death. ^13And Saul said, There shall not a man be put to death this day; for to-day Jehovah hath wrought deliverance in Israel.

^14Then said Samuel to the people, Come, and let us go to Gilgal, and renew the kingdom there. ^15And all the people went to Gilgal; and there they made Saul king before Jehovah in Gilgal; and there they offered sacrifices of peace-offerings before Jehovah; and there Saul and all the men of Israel rejoiced greatly.

1 Samuel 12

12

^1And Samuel said unto all Israel, Behold, I have hearkened unto your voice in all that ye said unto me, and have made a king over you. ^2And now, behold, the king walketh before you; and I am old and grayheaded; and, behold, my sons are with you: and I have walked before you from my youth unto this day. ^3Here I am: witness against me before Jehovah, and before his anointed: whose ox have I taken? or whose ass have I taken? or whom have I defrauded? whom have I oppressed? or of whose hand have I taken a ransom to blind mine eyes therewith? and I will restore it you. ^4And they said, Thou hast not defrauded us, nor oppressed us, neither hast thou taken aught of any man's hand. ^5And he said unto them, Jehovah is witness against you, and his anointed is witness this day, that ye have not found aught in my hand. And they said, He is witness.

^6And Samuel said unto the people, It is Jehovah that appointed Moses and Aaron, and that brought your fathers up out of the land of Egypt. ^7Now therefore stand still, that I may plead with you before Jehovah concerning all the righteous acts of Jehovah, which he did to you and to your fathers. ^8When Jacob was come into Egypt, and your fathers cried unto Jehovah, then Jehovah sent Moses and Aaron, who brought forth your fathers out of Egypt, and made them to dwell in this place. ^9But they forgat Jehovah their God; and he sold them into the hand of Sisera, captain of the host of Hazor, and into the hand of the Philistines, and into the hand of the king of Moab; and they fought against them. ^10And they cried unto Jehovah, and said, We have sinned, because we have forsaken Jehovah, and have served the Baalim and the Ashtaroth: but now deliver us out of the hand of our enemies, and we will serve thee. ^11And Jehovah sent Jerubbaal, and Bedan, and Jephthah, and Samuel, and delivered you out of the hand of your enemies on every side; and ye dwelt in safety. ^12And when ye saw that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon came against you, ye said unto me, Nay, but a king shall reign over us; when Jehovah your God was your king. ^13Now therefore behold the king whom ye have chosen, and whom ye have asked for: and, behold, Jehovah hath set a king over you. ^14If ye will fear Jehovah, and serve him, and hearken unto his voice, and not rebel against the commandment of Jehovah, and both ye and also the king that reigneth over you be followers of Jehovah your God, well: ^15but if ye will not hearken unto the voice of Jehovah, but rebel against the commandment of Jehovah, then will the hand of Jehovah be against you, as it was against your fathers. ^16Now therefore stand still and see this great thing, which Jehovah will do before your eyes. ^17Is it not wheat harvest to-day? I will call unto Jehovah, that he may send thunder and rain; and ye shall know and see that your wickedness is great, which ye have done in the sight of Jehovah, in asking you a king. ^18So Samuel called unto Jehovah; and Jehovah sent thunder and rain that day: and all the people greatly feared Jehovah and Samuel.

^19And all the people said unto Samuel, Pray for thy servants unto Jehovah thy God, that we die not; for we have added unto all our sins this evil, to ask us a king. ^20And Samuel said unto the people, Fear not; ye have indeed done all this evil; yet turn not aside from following Jehovah, but serve Jehovah with all your heart: ^21and turn ye not aside; for then would ye go after vain things which cannot profit nor deliver, for they are vain. ^22For Jehovah will not forsake his people for his great name's sake, because it hath pleased Jehovah to make you a people unto himself. ^23Moreover as for me, far be it from me that I should sin against Jehovah in ceasing to pray for you: but I will instruct you in the good and the right way. ^24Only fear Jehovah, and serve him in truth with all your heart; for consider how great things he hath done for you. ^25But if ye shall still do wickedly, ye shall be consumed, both ye and your king.

1 Samuel 13

13

^1Saul was forty years old when he began to reign; and when he had reigned two years over Israel, ^2Saul chose him three thousand men of Israel, whereof two thousand were with Saul in Michmash and in the mount of Beth-el, and a thousand were with Jonathan in Gibeah of Benjamin: and the rest of the people he sent every man to his tent. ^3And Jonathan smote the garrison of the Philistines that was in Geba: and the Philistines heard of it. And Saul blew the trumpet throughout all the land, saying, Let the Hebrews hear. ^4And all Israel heard say that Saul had smitten the garrison of the Philistines, and also that Israel was had in abomination with the Philistines. And the people were gathered together after Saul to Gilgal.

^5And the Philistines assembled themselves together to fight with Israel, thirty thousand chariots, and six thousand horsemen, and people as the sand which is on the sea-shore in multitude: and they came up, and encamped in Michmash, eastward of Beth-aven. ^6When the men of Israel saw that they were in a strait (for the people were distressed), then the people did hide themselves in caves, and in thickets, and in rocks, and in coverts, and in pits. ^7Now some of the Hebrews had gone over the Jordan to the land of Gad and Gilead; but as for Saul, he was yet in Gilgal, and all the people followed him trembling.

^8And he tarried seven days, according to the set time that Samuel had appointed: but Samuel came not to Gilgal; and the people were scattered from him. ^9And Saul said, Bring hither the burnt-offering to me, and the peace-offerings. And he offered the burnt-offering. ^10And it came to pass that, as soon as he had made an end of offering the burnt-offering, behold, Samuel came; and Saul went out to meet him, that he might salute him. ^11And Samuel said, What hast thou done? And Saul said, Because I saw that the people were scattered from me, and that thou camest not within the days appointed, and that the Philistines assembled themselves together at Michmash; ^12therefore said I, Now will the Philistines come down upon me to Gilgal, and I have not entreated the favor of Jehovah: I forced myself therefore, and offered the burnt-offering. ^13And Samuel said to Saul, Thou hast done foolishly; thou hast not kept the commandment of Jehovah thy God, which he commanded thee: for now would Jehovah have established thy kingdom upon Israel for ever. ^14But now thy kingdom shall not continue: Jehovah hath sought him a man after his own heart, and Jehovah hath appointed him to be prince over his people, because thou hast not kept that which Jehovah commanded thee. ^15And Samuel arose, and gat him up from Gilgal unto Gibeah of Benjamin.

And Saul numbered the people that were present with him, about six hundred men. ^16And Saul, and Jonathan his son, and the people that were present with them, abode in Geba of Benjamin: but the Philistines encamped in Michmash. ^17And the spoilers came out of the camp of the Philistines in three companies: one company turned unto the way that leadeth to Ophrah, unto the land of Shual; ^18and another company turned the way to Beth-horon; and another company turned the way of the border that looketh down upon the valley of Zeboim toward the wilderness.

^19Now there was no smith found throughout all the land of Israel; for the Philistines said, Lest the Hebrews make them swords or spears: ^20but all the Israelites went down to the Philistines, to sharpen every man his share, and his coulter, and his axe, and his mattock; ^21yet they had a file for the mattocks, and for the coulters, and for the forks, and for the axes, and to set the goads. ^22So it came to pass in the day of battle, that there was neither sword nor spear found in the hand of any of the people that were with Saul and Jonathan: but with Saul and with Jonathan his son was there found. ^23And the garrison of the Philistines went out unto the pass of Michmash.

1 Samuel 14

14

^1Now it fell upon a day, that Jonathan the son of Saul said unto the young man that bare his armor, Come, and let us go over to the Philistines' garrison, that is on yonder side. But he told not his father. ^2And Saul abode in the uttermost part of Gibeah under the pomegranate-tree which is in Migron: and the people that were with him were about six hundred men; ^3and Ahijah, the son of Ahitub, Ichabod's brother, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eli, the priest of Jehovah in Shiloh, wearing an ephod. And the people knew not that Jonathan was gone. ^4And between the passes, by which Jonathan sought to go over unto the Philistines' garrison, there was a rocky crag on the one side, and a rocky crag on the other side: and the name of the one was Bozez, and the name of the other Seneh. ^5The one crag rose up on the north in front of Michmash, and the other on the south in front of Geba.

^6And Jonathan said to the young man that bare his armor, Come, and let us go over unto the garrison of these uncircumcised: it may be that Jehovah will work for us; for there is no restraint to Jehovah to save by many or by few. ^7And his armorbearer said unto him, Do all that is in thy heart: turn thee, behold, I am with thee according to thy heart. ^8Then said Jonathan, Behold, we will pass over unto the men, and we will disclose ourselves unto them. ^9If they say thus unto us, Tarry until we come to you; then we will stand still in our place, and will not go up unto them. ^10But if they say thus, Come up unto us; then we will go up; for Jehovah hath delivered them into our hand: and this shall be the sign unto us. ^11And both of them disclosed themselves unto the garrison of the Philistines: and the Philistines said, Behold, the Hebrews come forth out of the holes where they had hid themselves. ^12And the men of the garrison answered Jonathan and his armorbearer, and said, Come up to us, and we will show you a thing. And Jonathan said unto his armorbearer, Come up after me; for Jehovah hath delivered them into the hand of Israel. ^13And Jonathan climbed up upon his hands and upon his feet, and his armorbearer after him: and they fell before Jonathan; and his armorbearer slew them after him. ^14And that first slaughter, which Jonathan and his armorbearer made, was about twenty men, within as it were half a furrow's length in an acre of land. ^15And there was a trembling in the camp, in the field, and among all the people; the garrison, and the spoilers, they also trembled; and the earth quaked: so there was an exceeding great trembling.

^16And the watchmen of Saul in Gibeah of Benjamin looked; and, behold, the multitude melted away, and they went hither and thither. ^17Then said Saul unto the people that were with him, Number now, and see who is gone from us. And when they had numbered, behold, Jonathan and his armorbearer were not there. ^18And Saul said unto Ahijah, Bring hither the ark of God. For the ark of God was there at that time with the children of Israel. ^19And it came to pass, while Saul talked unto the priest, that the tumult that was in the camp of the Philistines went on and increased: and Saul said unto the priest, Withdraw thy hand. ^20And Saul and all the people that were with him were gathered together, and came to the battle: and, behold, every man's sword was against his fellow, and there was a very great discomfiture. ^21Now the Hebrews that were with the Philistines as beforetime, and that went up with them into the camp, from the country round about, even they also turned to be with the Israelites that were with Saul and Jonathan. ^22Likewise all the men of Israel that had hid themselves in the hill-country of Ephraim, when they heard that the Philistines fled, even they also followed hard after them in the battle. ^23So Jehovah saved Israel that day: and the battle passed over by Beth-aven.

^24And the men of Israel were distressed that day; for Saul had adjured the people, saying, Cursed be the man that eateth any food until it be evening, and I be avenged on mine enemies. So none of the people tasted food. ^25And all the people came into the forest; and there was honey upon the ground. ^26And when the people were come unto the forest, behold, the honey dropped: but no man put his hand to his mouth; for the people feared the oath. ^27But Jonathan heard not when his father charged the people with the oath: wherefore he put forth the end of the rod that was in his hand, and dipped it in the honeycomb, and put his hand to his mouth; and his eyes were enlightened. ^28Then answered one of the people, and said, Thy father straitly charged the people with an oath, saying, Cursed be the man that eateth food this day. And the people were faint. ^29Then said Jonathan, My father hath troubled the land: see, I pray you, how mine eyes have been enlightened, because I tasted a little of this honey. ^30How much more, if haply the people had eaten freely to-day of the spoil of their enemies which they found? for now hath there been no great slaughter among the Philistines.

^31And they smote of the Philistines that day from Michmash to Aijalon. And the people were very faint; ^32and the people flew upon the spoil, and took sheep, and oxen, and calves, and slew them on the ground; and the people did eat them with the blood. ^33Then they told Saul, saying, Behold, the people sin against Jehovah, in that they eat with the blood. And he said, ye have dealt treacherously: roll a great stone unto me this day. ^34And Saul said, Disperse yourselves among the people, and say unto them, Bring me hither every man his ox, and every man his sheep, and slay them here, and eat; and sin not against Jehovah in eating with the blood. And all the people brought every man his ox with him that night, and slew them there. ^35And Saul built an altar unto Jehovah: the same was the first altar that he built unto Jehovah.

^36And Saul said, Let us go down after the Philistines by night, and take spoil among them until the morning light, and let us not leave a man of them. And they said, Do whatsoever seemeth good unto thee. Then said the priest, Let us draw near hither unto God. ^37And Saul asked counsel of God, Shall I go down after the Philistines? wilt thou deliver them into the hand of Israel? But he answered him not that day. ^38And Saul said, Draw nigh hither, all ye chiefs of the people; and know and see wherein this sin hath been this day. ^39For, as Jehovah liveth, who saveth Israel, though it be in Jonathan my son, he shall surely die. But there was not a man among all the people that answered him. ^40Then said he unto all Israel, Be ye on one side, and I and Jonathan my son will be on the other side. And the people said unto Saul, Do what seemeth good unto thee. ^41Therefore Saul said unto Jehovah, the God of Israel, Show the right. And Jonathan and Saul were taken by lot; but the people escaped. ^42And Saul said, Cast lots between me and Jonathan my son. And Jonathan was taken.

^43Then Saul said to Jonathan, Tell me what thou hast done. And Jonathan told him, and said, I did certainly taste a little honey with the end of the rod that was in my hand; and, lo, I must die. ^44And Saul said, God do so and more also; for thou shalt surely die, Jonathan. ^45And the people said unto Saul, Shall Jonathan die, who hath wrought this great salvation in Israel? Far from it: as Jehovah liveth, there shall not one hair of his head fall to the ground; for he hath wrought with God this day. So the people rescued Jonathan, that he died not. ^46Then Saul went up from following the Philistines; and the Philistines went to their own place. ^47Now when Saul had taken the kingdom over Israel, he fought against all his enemies on every side, against Moab, and against the children of Ammon, and against Edom, and against the kings of Zobah, and against the Philistines: and whithersoever he turned himself, he put them to the worse. ^48And he did valiantly, and smote the Amalekites, and delivered Israel out of the hands of them that despoiled them.

^49Now the sons of Saul were Jonathan, and Ishvi, and Malchishua; and the names of his two daughters were these: the name of the first-born Merab, and the name of the younger Michal: ^50and the name of Saul's wife was Ahinoam the daughter of Ahimaaz. And the name of the captain of his host was Abner the son of Ner, Saul's uncle. ^51And Kish was the father of Saul; and Ner the father of Abner was the son of Abiel.

^52And there was sore war against the Philistines all the days of Saul: and when Saul saw any mighty man, or any valiant man, he took him unto him.

1 Samuel 15

15

^1And Samuel said unto Saul, Jehovah sent me to anoint thee to be king over his people, over Israel: now therefore hearken thou unto the voice of the words of Jehovah. ^2Thus saith Jehovah of hosts, I have marked that which Amalek did to Israel, how he set himself against him in the way, when he came up out of Egypt. ^3Now go and smite Amalek, and utterly destroy all that they have, and spare them not; but slay both man and woman, infant and suckling, ox and sheep, camel and ass.

^4And Saul summoned the people, and numbered them in Telaim, two hundred thousand footmen, and ten thousand men of Judah. ^5And Saul came to the city of Amalek, and laid wait in the valley. ^6And Saul said unto the Kenites, Go, depart, get you down from among the Amalekites, lest I destroy you with them; for ye showed kindness to all the children of Israel, when they came up out of Egypt. So the Kenites departed from among the Amalekites. ^7And Saul smote the Amalekites, from Havilah as thou goest to Shur, that is before Egypt. ^8And he took Agag the king of the Amalekites alive, and utterly destroyed all the people with the edge of the sword. ^9But Saul and the people spared Agag, and the best of the sheep, and of the oxen, and of the fatlings, and the lambs, and all that was good, and would not utterly destroy them: but everything that was vile and refuse, that they destroyed utterly.

^10Then came the word of Jehovah unto Samuel, saying, ^11It repenteth me that I have set up Saul to be king; for he is turned back from following me, and hath not performed my commandments. And Samuel was wroth; and he cried unto Jehovah all night. ^12And Samuel rose early to meet Saul in the morning; and it was told Samuel, saying, Saul came to Carmel, and, behold, he set him up a monument, and turned, and passed on, and went down to Gilgal. ^13And Samuel came to Saul; and Saul said unto him, Blessed be thou of Jehovah: I have performed the commandment of Jehovah. ^14And Samuel said, What meaneth then this bleating of the sheep in mine ears, and the lowing of the oxen which I hear? ^15And Saul said, They have brought them from the Amalekites: for the people spared the best of the sheep and of the oxen, to sacrifice unto Jehovah thy God; and the rest we have utterly destroyed. ^16Then Samuel said unto Saul, Stay, and I will tell thee what Jehovah hath said to me this night. And he said unto him, Say on.

^17And Samuel said, Though thou wast little in thine own sight, wast thou not made the head of the tribes of Israel? And Jehovah anointed thee king over Israel; ^18and Jehovah sent thee on a journey, and said, Go, and utterly destroy the sinners the Amalekites, and fight against them until they be consumed. ^19Wherefore then didst thou not obey the voice of Jehovah, but didst fly upon the spoil, and didst that which was evil in the sight of Jehovah? ^20And Saul said unto Samuel, Yea, I have obeyed the voice of Jehovah, and have gone the way which Jehovah sent me, and have brought Agag the king of Amalek, and have utterly destroyed the Amalekites. ^21But the people took of the spoil, sheep and oxen, the chief of the devoted things, to sacrifice unto Jehovah thy God in Gilgal. ^22And Samuel said, Hath Jehovah as great delight in burnt-offerings and sacrifices, as in obeying the voice of Jehovah? Behold, to obey is better than sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of rams. ^23For rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft, and stubbornness is as idolatry and teraphim. Because thou hast rejected the word of Jehovah, he hath also rejected thee from being king.

^24And Saul said unto Samuel, I have sinned; for I have transgressed the commandment of Jehovah, and thy words, because I feared the people, and obeyed their voice. ^25Now therefore, I pray thee, pardon my sin, and turn again with me, that I may worship Jehovah. ^26And Samuel said unto Saul, I will not return with thee; for thou hast rejected the word of Jehovah, and Jehovah hath rejected thee from being king over Israel. ^27And as Samuel turned about to go away, Saul laid hold upon the skirt of his robe, and it rent. ^28And Samuel said unto him, Jehovah hath rent the kingdom of Israel from thee this day, and hath given it to a neighbor of thine, that is better than thou. ^29And also the Strength of Israel will not lie nor repent; for he is not a man, that he should repent. ^30Then he said, I have sinned: yet honor me now, I pray thee, before the elders of my people, and before Israel, and turn again with me, that I may worship Jehovah thy God. ^31So Samuel turned again after Saul; and Saul worshipped Jehovah.

^32Then said Samuel, Bring ye hither to me Agag the king of the Amalekites. And Agag came unto him cheerfully. And Agag said, Surely the bitterness of death is past. ^33And Samuel said, As thy sword hath made women childless, so shall thy mother be childless among women. And Samuel hewed Agag in pieces before Jehovah in Gilgal.

^34Then Samuel went to Ramah; and Saul went up to his house to Gibeah of Saul. ^35And Samuel came no more to see Saul until the day of his death; for Samuel mourned for Saul: and Jehovah repented that he had made Saul king over Israel.

1 Samuel 16

16

^1And Jehovah said unto Samuel, How long wilt thou mourn for Saul, seeing I have rejected him from being king over Israel? fill thy horn with oil, and go: I will send thee to Jesse the Beth-lehemite; for I have provided me a king among his sons. ^2And Samuel said, How can I go? if Saul hear it, he will kill me. And Jehovah said, Take a heifer with thee, and say, I am come to sacrifice to Jehovah. ^3And call Jesse to the sacrifice, and I will show thee what thou shalt do: and thou shalt anoint unto me him whom I name unto thee. ^4And Samuel did that which Jehovah spake, and came to Beth-lehem. And the elders of the city came to meet him trembling, and said, Comest thou peaceably? ^5And he said, Peaceably; I am come to sacrifice unto Jehovah: sanctify yourselves, and come with me to the sacrifice. And he sanctified Jesse and his sons, and called them to the sacrifice.

^6And it came to pass, when they were come, that he looked on Eliab, and said, Surely Jehovah's anointed is before him. ^7But Jehovah said unto Samuel, Look not on his countenance, or on the height of his stature; because I have rejected him: for Jehovah seeth not as man seeth; for man looketh on the outward appearance, but Jehovah looketh on the heart. ^8Then Jesse called Abinadab, and made him pass before Samuel. And he said, Neither hath Jehovah chosen this. ^9Then Jesse made Shammah to pass by. And he said, Neither hath Jehovah chosen this. ^10And Jesse made seven of his sons to pass before Samuel. And Samuel said unto Jesse, Jehovah hath not chosen these. ^11And Samuel said unto Jesse, Are here all thy children? And he said, There remaineth yet the youngest, and, behold, he is keeping the sheep. And Samuel said unto Jesse, Send and fetch him; for we will not sit down till he come hither. ^12And he sent, and brought him in. Now he was ruddy, and withal of a beautiful countenance, and goodly to look upon. And Jehovah said, Arise, anoint him; for this is he. ^13Then Samuel took the horn of oil, and anointed him in the midst of his brethren: and the Spirit of Jehovah came mightily upon David from that day forward. So Samuel rose up, and went to Ramah. ^14Now the Spirit of Jehovah departed from Saul, and an evil spirit from Jehovah troubled him. ^15And Saul's servants said unto him, Behold now, an evil spirit from God troubleth thee. ^16Let our lord now command thy servants, that are before thee, to seek out a man who is a skilful player on the harp: and it shall come to pass, when the evil spirit from God is upon thee, that he shall play with his hand, and thou shalt be well. ^17And Saul said unto his servants, Provide me now a man that can play well, and bring him to me. ^18Then answered one of the young men, and said, Behold, I have seen a son of Jesse the Beth-lehemite, that is skilful in playing, and a mighty man of valor, and a man of war, and prudent in speech, and a comely person; and Jehovah is with him. ^19Wherefore Saul sent messengers unto Jesse, and said, Send me David thy son, who is with the sheep. ^20And Jesse took an ass laden with bread, and a bottle of wine, and a kid, and sent them by David his son unto Saul. ^21And David came to Saul, and stood before him: and he loved him greatly; and he became his armorbearer. ^22And Saul sent to Jesse, saying, Let David, I pray thee, stand before me; for he hath found favor in my sight. ^23And it came to pass, when the evil spirit from God was upon Saul, that David took the harp, and played with his hand: so Saul was refreshed, and was well, and the evil spirit departed from him.

1 Samuel 17

17

^1Now the Philistines gathered together their armies to battle; and they were gathered together at Socoh, which belongeth to Judah, and encamped between Socoh and Azekah, in Ephes-dammim. ^2And Saul and the men of Israel were gathered together, and encamped in the vale of Elah, and set the battle in array against the Philistines. ^3And the Philistines stood on the mountain on the one side, and Israel stood on the mountain on the other side: and there was a valley between them. ^4And there went out a champion out of the camp of the Philistines, named Goliath, of Gath, whose height was six cubits and a span. ^5And he had a helmet of brass upon his head, and he was clad with a coat of mail; and the weight of the coat was five thousand shekels of brass. ^6And he had greaves of brass upon his legs, and a javelin of brass between his shoulders. ^7And the staff of his spear was like a weaver's beam; and his spear's head weighed six hundred shekels of iron: and his shield-bearer went before him. ^8And he stood and cried unto the armies of Israel, and said unto them, Why are ye come out to set your battle in array? am not I a Philistine, and ye servants to Saul? choose you a man for you, and let him come down to me. ^9If he be able to fight with me, and kill me, then will we be your servants; but if I prevail against him, and kill him, then shall ye be our servants, and serve us. ^10And the Philistine said, I defy the armies of Israel this day; give me a man, that we may fight together. ^11And when Saul and all Israel heard those words of the Philistine, they were dismayed, and greatly afraid.

^12Now David was the son of that Ephrathite of Beth-lehem-judah, whose name was Jesse; and he had eight sons: and the man was an old man in the days of Saul, stricken in years among men. ^13And the three eldest sons of Jesse had gone after Saul to the battle: and the names of his three sons that went to the battle were Eliab the first-born, and next unto him Abinadab, and the third Shammah. ^14And David was the youngest; and the three eldest followed Saul. ^15Now David went to and fro from Saul to feed his father's sheep at Beth-lehem. ^16And the Philistine drew near morning and evening, and presented himself forty days.

^17And Jesse said unto David his son, Take now for thy brethren an ephah of this parched grain, and these ten loaves, and carry them quickly to the camp to thy brethren; ^18and bring these ten cheeses unto the captain of their thousand, and look how thy brethren fare, and take their pledge. ^19Now Saul, and they, and all the men of Israel, were in the vale of Elah, fighting with the Philistines.

^20And David rose up early in the morning, and left the sheep with a keeper, and took, and went, as Jesse had commanded him; and he came to the place of the wagons, as the host which was going forth to the fight shouted for the battle. ^21And Israel and the Philistines put the battle in array, army against army. ^22And David left his baggage in the hand of the keeper of the baggage, and ran to the army, and came and saluted his brethren. ^23And as he talked with them, behold, there came up the champion, the Philistine of Gath, Goliath by name, out of the ranks of the Philistines, and spake according to the same words: and David heard them. ^24And all the men of Israel, when they saw the man, fled from him, and were sore afraid. ^25And the men of Israel said, Have ye seen this man that is come up? surely to defy Israel is he come up: and it shall be, that the man who killeth him, the king will enrich him with great riches, and will give him his daughter, and make his father's house free in Israel. ^26And David spake to the men that stood by him, saying, What shall be done to the man that killeth this Philistine, and taketh away the reproach from Israel? for who is this uncircumcised Philistine, that he should defy the armies of the living God? ^27And the people answered him after this manner, saying, So shall it be done to the man that killeth him.

^28And Eliab his eldest brother heard when he spake unto the men; and Eliab's anger was kindled against David, and he said, Why art thou come down? and with whom hast thou left those few sheep in the wilderness? I know thy pride, and the naughtiness of thy heart; for thou art come down that thou mightest see the battle. ^29And David said, What have I now done? Is there not a cause? ^30And he turned away from him toward another, and spake after the same manner: and the people answered him again after the former manner.

^31And when the words were heard which David spake, they rehearsed them before Saul; and he sent for him. ^32And David said to Saul, Let no man's heart fail because of him; thy servant will go and fight with this Philistine. ^33And Saul said to David, Thou art not able to go against this Philistine to fight with him; for thou art but a youth, and he a man of war from his youth. ^34And David said unto Saul, Thy servant was keeping his father's sheep; and when there came a lion, or a bear, and took a lamb out of the flock, ^35I went out after him, and smote him, and delivered it out of his mouth; and when he arose against me, I caught him by his beard, and smote him, and slew him. ^36Thy servant smote both the lion and the bear: and this uncircumcised Philistine shall be as one of them, seeing he hath defied the armies of the living God. ^37And David said, Jehovah that delivered me out of the paw of the lion, and out of the paw of the bear, he will deliver me out of the hand of this Philistine. And Saul said unto David, Go, and Jehovah shall be with thee. ^38And Saul clad David with his apparel, and he put a helmet of brass upon his head, and he clad him with a coat of mail. ^39And David girded his sword upon his apparel, and he assayed to go; for he had not proved it. And David said unto Saul, I cannot go with these; for I have not proved them. And David put them off him. ^40And he took his staff in his hand, and chose him five smooth stones out of the brook, and put them in the shepherd's bag which he had, even in his wallet; and his sling was in his hand: and he drew near to the Philistine.

^41And the Philistine came on and drew near unto David; and the man that bare the shield went before him. ^42And when the Philistine looked about, and saw David, he disdained him; for he was but a youth, and ruddy, and withal of a fair countenance. ^43And the Philistine said unto David, Am I a dog, that thou comest to me with staves? And the Philistine cursed David by his gods. ^44And the Philistine said to David, Come to me, and I will give thy flesh unto the birds of the heavens, and to the beasts of the field. ^45Then said David to the Philistine, Thou comest to me with a sword, and with a spear, and with a javelin: but I come to thee in the name of Jehovah of hosts, the God of the armies of Israel, whom thou hast defied. ^46This day will Jehovah deliver thee into my hand; and I will smite thee, and take thy head from off thee; and I will give the dead bodies of the host of the Philistines this day unto the birds of the heavens, and to the wild beasts of the earth; that all the earth may know that there is a God in Israel, ^47and that all this assembly may know that Jehovah saveth not with sword and spear: for the battle is Jehovah's, and he will give you into our hand. ^48And it came to pass, when the Philistine arose, and came and drew nigh to meet David, that David hastened, and ran toward the army to meet the Philistine. ^49And David put his hand in his bag, and took thence a stone, and slang it, and smote the Philistine in his forehead; and the stone sank into his forehead, and he fell upon his face to the earth.

^50So David prevailed over the Philistine with a sling and with a stone, and smote the Philistine, and slew him; but there was no sword in the hand of David. ^51Then David ran, and stood over the Philistine, and took his sword, and drew it out of the sheath thereof, and slew him, and cut off his head therewith. And when the Philistines saw that their champion was dead, they fled. ^52And the men of Israel and of Judah arose, and shouted, and pursued the Philistines, until thou comest to Gai, and to the gates of Ekron. And the wounded of the Philistines fell down by the way to Shaaraim, even unto Gath, and unto Ekron. ^53And the children of Israel returned from chasing after the Philistines, and they plundered their camp. ^54And David took the head of the Philistine, and brought it to Jerusalem; but he put his armor in his tent.

^55And when Saul saw David go forth against the Philistine, he said unto Abner, the captain of the host, Abner, whose son is this youth? And Abner said, As thy soul liveth, O king, I cannot tell. ^56And the king said, Inquire thou whose son the stripling is. ^57And as David returned from the slaughter of the Philistine, Abner took him, and brought him before Saul with the head of the Philistine in his hand. ^58And Saul said to him, Whose son art thou, thou young man? And David answered, I am the son of thy servant Jesse the Beth-lehemite.

1 Samuel 18

18

^1And it came to pass, when he had made an end of speaking unto Saul, that the soul of Jonathan was knit with the soul of David, and Jonathan loved him as his own soul. ^2And Saul took him that day, and would let him go no more home to his father's house. ^3Then Jonathan and David made a covenant, because he loved him as his own soul. ^4And Jonathan stripped himself of the robe that was upon him, and gave it to David, and his apparel, even to his sword, and to his bow, and to his girdle. ^5And David went out whithersoever Saul sent him, and behaved himself wisely: and Saul set him over the men of war, and it was good in the sight of all the people, and also in the sight of Saul's servants. ^6And it came to pass as they came, when David returned from the slaughter of the Philistine, that the women came out of all the cities of Israel, singing and dancing, to meet king Saul, with timbrels, with joy, and with instruments of music. ^7And the women sang one to another as they played, and said,

Saul hath slain his thousands,

And David his ten thousands.

^8And Saul was very wroth, and this saying displeased him; and he said, They have ascribed unto David ten thousands, and to me they have ascribed but thousands: and what can he have more but the kingdom? ^9And Saul eyed David from that day and forward.

^10And it came to pass on the morrow, that an evil spirit from God came mightily upon Saul, and he prophesied in the midst of the house: and David played with his hand, as he did day by day. And Saul had his spear in his hand; ^11and Saul cast the spear; for he said, I will smite David even to the wall. And David avoided out of his presence twice. ^12And Saul was afraid of David, because Jehovah was with him, and was departed from Saul. ^13Therefore Saul removed him from him, and made him his captain over a thousand; and he went out and came in before the people. ^14And David behaved himself wisely in all his ways; and Jehovah was with him. ^15And when Saul saw that he behaved himself very wisely, he stood in awe of him. ^16But all Israel and Judah loved David; for he went out and came in before them.

^17And Saul said to David, Behold, my elder daughter Merab, her will I give thee to wife: only be thou valiant for me, and fight Jehovah's battles. For Saul said, Let not my hand be upon him, but let the hand of the Philistines be upon him. ^18And David said unto Saul, Who am I, and what is my life, or my father's family in Israel, that I should be son-in-law to the king? ^19But it came to pass at the time when Merab, Saul's daughter, should have been given to David, that she was given unto Adriel the Meholathite to wife. ^20And Michal, Saul's daughter, loved David: and they told Saul, and the thing pleased him. ^21And Saul said, I will give him her, that she may be a snare to him, and that the hand of the Philistines may be against him. Wherefore Saul said to David, Thou shalt this day be my son-in-law a second time.

^22And Saul commanded his servants, saying, Commune with David secretly, and say, Behold, the king hath delight in thee, and all his servants love thee: now therefore be the king's son-in-law. ^23And Saul's servants spake those words in the ears of David. And David said, Seemeth it to you a light thing to be the king's son-in-law, seeing that I am a poor man, and lightly esteemed? ^24And the servants of Saul told him, saying, On this manner spake David. ^25And Saul said, Thus shall ye say to David, The king desireth not any dowry, but a hundred foreskins of the Philistines, to be avenged of the king's enemies. Now Saul thought to make David fall by the hand of the Philistines. ^26And when his servants told David these words, it pleased David well to be the king's son-in-law. And the days were not expired; ^27and David arose and went, he and his men, and slew of the Philistines two hundred men; and David brought their foreskins, and they gave them in full number to the king, that he might be the king's son-in-law. And Saul gave him Michal his daughter to wife. ^28And Saul saw and knew that Jehovah was with David; and Michal, Saul's daughter, loved him. ^29And Saul was yet the more afraid of David; and Saul was David's enemy continually.

^30Then the princes of the Philistines went forth: and it came to pass, as often as they went forth, that David behaved himself more wisely than all the servants of Saul; so that his name was much set by.

1 Samuel 19

19

^1And Saul spake to Jonathan his son, and to all his servants, that they should slay David. But Jonathan, Saul's son, delighted much in David. ^2And Jonathan told David, saying, Saul my father seeketh to slay thee: now therefore, I pray thee, take heed to thyself in the morning, and abide in a secret place, and hide thyself: ^3and I will go out and stand beside my father in the field where thou art, and I will commune with my father of thee; and if I see aught, I will tell thee. ^4And Jonathan spake good of David unto Saul his father, and said unto him, Let not the king sin against his servant, against David; because he hath not sinned against thee, and because his works have been to thee-ward very good: ^5for he put his life in his hand, and smote the Philistine, and Jehovah wrought a great victory for all Israel: thou sawest it, and didst rejoice; wherefore then wilt thou sin against innocent blood, to slay David without a cause? ^6And Saul hearkened unto the voice of Jonathan: and Saul sware, As Jehovah liveth, he shall not be put to death. ^7And Jonathan called David, and Jonathan showed him all those things. And Jonathan brought David to Saul, and he was in his presence, as beforetime.

^8And there was war again: and David went out, and fought with the Philistines, and slew them with a great slaughter; and they fled before him. ^9And an evil spirit from Jehovah was upon Saul, as he sat in his house with his spear in his hand; and David was playing with his hand. ^10And Saul sought to smite David even to the wall with the spear; but he slipped away out of Saul's presence, and he smote the spear into the wall: and David fled, and escaped that night. ^11And Saul sent messengers unto David's house, to watch him, and to slay him in the morning: and Michal, David's wife, told him, saying, If thou save not thy life to-night, to-morrow thou wilt be slain. ^12So Michal let David down through the window: and he went, and fled, and escaped. ^13And Michal took the teraphim, and laid it in the bed, and put a pillow of goats' hair at the head thereof, and covered it with the clothes. ^14And when Saul sent messengers to take David, she said, He is sick. ^15And Saul sent the messengers to see David, saying, Bring him up to me in the bed, that I may slay him. ^16And when the messengers came in, behold, the teraphim was in the bed, with the pillow of goats' hair at the head thereof. ^17And Saul said unto Michal, Why hast thou deceived me thus, and let mine enemy go, so that he is escaped? And Michal answered Saul, He said unto me, Let me go; why should I kill thee?

^18Now David fled, and escaped, and came to Samuel to Ramah, and told him all that Saul had done to him. And he and Samuel went and dwelt in Naioth. ^19And it was told Saul, saying, Behold, David is at Naioth in Ramah. ^20And Saul sent messengers to take David: and when they saw the company of the prophets prophesying, and Samuel standing as head over them, the Spirit of God came upon the messengers of Saul, and they also prophesied. ^21And when it was told Saul, he sent other messengers, and they also prophesied. And Saul sent messengers again the third time, and they also prophesied. ^22Then went he also to Ramah, and came to the great well that is in Secu: and he asked and said, Where are Samuel and David? And one said, Behold, they are at Naioth in Ramah. ^23And he went thither to Naioth in Ramah: and the Spirit of God came upon him also, and he went on, and prophesied, until he came to Naioth in Ramah. ^24And he also stripped off his clothes, and he also prophesied before Samuel, and lay down naked all that day and all that night. Wherefore they say, Is Saul also among the prophets?

1 Samuel 20

20

^1And David fled from Naioth in Ramah, and came and said before Jonathan, What have I done? what is mine iniquity? and what is my sin before thy father, that he seeketh my life? ^2And he said unto him, Far from it; thou shalt not die: behold, my father doeth nothing either great or small, but that he discloseth it unto me; and why should my father hide this thing from me? it is not so. ^3And David sware moreover, and said, Thy father knoweth well that I have found favor in thine eyes; and he saith, Let not Jonathan know this, lest he be grieved: but truly as Jehovah liveth, and as thy soul liveth, there is but a step between me and death. ^4Then said Jonathan unto David, Whatsoever thy soul desireth, I will even do it for thee. ^5And David said unto Jonathan, Behold, to-morrow is the new moon, and I should not fail to sit with the king at meat: but let me go, that I may hide myself in the field unto the third day at even. ^6If thy father miss me at all, then say, David earnestly asked leave of me that he might run to Beth-lehem his city; for it is the yearly sacrifice there for all the family. ^7If he say thus, It is well; thy servant shall have peace: but if he be wroth, then know that evil is determined by him. ^8Therefore deal kindly with thy servant; for thou hast brought thy servant into a covenant of Jehovah with thee: but if there be in me iniquity, slay me thyself; for why shouldest thou bring me to thy father? ^9And Jonathan said, Far be it from thee; for if I should at all know that evil were determined by my father to come upon thee, then would not I tell it thee? ^10Then said David to Jonathan, Who shall tell me if perchance thy father answer thee roughly? ^11And Jonathan said unto David, Come, and let us go out into the field. And they went out both of them into the field.

^12And Jonathan said unto David, Jehovah, the God of Israel, be witness: when I have sounded my father about this time to-morrow, or the third day, behold, if there be good toward David, shall I not then send unto thee, and disclose it unto thee? ^13Jehovah do so to Jonathan, and more also, should it please my father to do thee evil, if I disclose it not unto thee, and send thee away, that thou mayest go in peace: and Jehovah be with thee, as he hath been with my father. ^14And thou shalt not only while yet I live show me the lovingkindness of Jehovah, that I die not; ^15but also thou shalt not cut off thy kindness from my house for ever; no, not when Jehovah hath cut off the enemies of David every one from the face of the earth. ^16So Jonathan made a covenant with the house of David, saying, And Jehovah will require it at the hand of David's enemies.

^17And Jonathan caused David to swear again, for the love that he had to him; for he loved him as he loved his own soul. ^18Then Jonathan said unto him, To-morrow is the new moon: and thou wilt be missed, because thy seat will be empty. ^19And when thou hast stayed three days, thou shalt go down quickly, and come to the place where thou didst hide thyself when the business was in hand, and shalt remain by the stone Ezel. ^20And I will shoot three arrows on the side thereof, as though I shot at a mark. ^21And, behold, I will send the lad, saying, Go, find the arrows. If I say unto the lad, Behold, the arrows are on this side of thee; take them, and come; for there is peace to thee and no hurt, as Jehovah liveth. ^22But if I say thus unto the boy, Behold, the arrows are beyond thee; go thy way; for Jehovah hath sent thee away. ^23And as touching the matter which thou and I have spoken of, behold, Jehovah is between thee and me for ever.

^24So David hid himself in the field: and when the new moon was come, the king sat him down to eat food. ^25And the king sat upon his seat, as at other times, even upon the seat by the wall; and Jonathan stood up, and Abner sat by Saul's side: but David's place was empty. ^26Nevertheless Saul spake not anything that day: for he thought, Something hath befallen him, he is not clean; surely he is not clean. ^27And it came to pass on the morrow after the new moon, which was the second day, that David's place was empty: and Saul said unto Jonathan his son, Wherefore cometh not the son of Jesse to meat, neither yesterday, nor to-day? ^28And Jonathan answered Saul, David earnestly asked leave of me to go to Beth-lehem: ^29and he said, Let me go, I pray thee; for our family hath a sacrifice in the city; and my brother, he hath commanded me to be there: and now, if I have found favor in thine eyes, let me get away, I pray thee, and see my brethren. Therefore he is not come unto the king's table.

^30Then Saul's anger was kindled against Jonathan, and he said unto him, Thou son of a perverse rebellious woman, do not I know that thou hast chosen the son of Jesse to thine own shame, and unto the shame of thy mother's nakedness? ^31For as long as the son of Jesse liveth upon the ground, thou shalt not be established, nor thy kingdom. Wherefore now send and fetch him unto me, for he shall surely die. ^32And Jonathan answered Saul his father, and said unto him, Wherefore should he be put to death? what hath he done? ^33And Saul cast his spear at him to smite him; whereby Jonathan knew that is was determined of his father to put David to death. ^34So Jonathan arose from the table in fierce anger, and did eat no food the second day of the month; for he was grieved for David, because his father had done him shame.

^35And it came to pass in the morning, that Jonathan went out into the field at the time appointed with David, and a little lad with him. ^36And he said unto his lad, Run, find now the arrows which I shoot. And as the lad ran, he shot an arrow beyond him. ^37And when the lad was come to the place of the arrow which Jonathan had shot, Jonathan cried after the lad, and said, Is not the arrow beyond thee? ^38And Jonathan cried after the lad, Make speed, haste, stay not. And Jonathan's lad gathered up the arrows, and came to his master. ^39But the lad knew not anything: only Jonathan and David knew the matter. ^40And Jonathan gave his weapons unto his lad, and said unto him, Go, carry them to the city. ^41And as soon as the lad was gone, David arose out of a place toward the South, and fell on his face to the ground, and bowed himself three times: and they kissed one another, and wept one with another, until David exceeded. ^42And Jonathan said to David, Go in peace, forasmuch as we have sworn both of us in the name of Jehovah, saying, Jehovah shall be between me and thee, and between my seed and thy seed, for ever. And he arose and departed: and Jonathan went into the city.

1 Samuel 21

21

^1Then came David to Nob to Ahimelech the priest: and Ahimelech came to meet David trembling, and said unto him, Why art thou alone, and no man with thee? ^2And David said unto Ahimelech the priest, The king hath commanded me a business, and hath said unto me, Let no man know anything of the business whereabout I send thee, and what I have commanded thee: and I have appointed the young men to such and such a place. ^3Now therefore what is under thy hand? give me five loaves of bread in my hand, or whatsoever there is present. ^4And the priest answered David, and said, There is no common bread under my hand, but there is holy bread; if only the young men have kept themselves from women. ^5And David answered the priest, and said unto him, Of a truth women have been kept from us about these three days; when I came out, the vessels of the young men were holy, though it was but a common journey; how much more then to-day shall their vessels be holy? ^6So the priest gave him holy bread; for there was no bread there but the showbread, that was taken from before Jehovah, to put hot bread in the day when it was taken away.

^7Now a certain man of the servants of Saul was there that day, detained before Jehovah; and his name was Doeg the Edomite, the chiefest of the herdsmen that belonged to Saul. ^8And David said unto Ahimelech, And is there not here under thy hand spear or sword? for I have neither brought my sword nor my weapons with me, because the king's business required haste. ^9And the priest said, The sword of Goliath the Philistine, whom thou slewest in the vale of Elah, behold, it is here wrapped in a cloth behind the ephod: if thou wilt take that, take it; for there is no other save that here. And David said, There is none like that; give it me.

^10And David arose, and fled that day for fear of Saul, and went to Achish the king of Gath. ^11And the servants of Achish said unto him, Is not this David the king of the land? did they not sing one to another of him in dances, saying,

Saul hath slain his thousands,

And David his ten thousands?

^12And David laid up these words in his heart, and was sore afraid of Achish the king of Gath. ^13And he changed his behavior before them, and feigned himself mad in their hands, and scrabbled on the doors of the gate, and let his spittle fall down upon his beard. ^14Then said Achish unto his servants, Lo, ye see the man is mad; wherefore then have ye brought him to me? ^15Do I lack madmen, that ye have brought this fellow to play the madman in my presence? shall this fellow come into my house?

1 Samuel 22

22

^1David therefore departed thence, and escaped to the cave of Adullam: and when his brethren and all his father's house heard it, they went down thither to him. ^2And every one that was in distress, and every one that was in debt, and every one that was discontented, gathered themselves unto him; and he became captain over them: and there were with him about four hundred men.

^3And David went thence to Mizpeh of Moab: and he said unto the king of Moab, Let my father and my mother, I pray thee, come forth, and be with you, till I know what God will do for me. ^4And he brought them before the king of Moab: and they dwelt with him all the while that David was in the stronghold. ^5And the prophet Gad said unto David, Abide not in the stronghold; depart, and get thee into the land of Judah. Then David departed, and came into the forest of Hereth.

^6And Saul heard that David was discovered, and the men that were with him: now Saul was sitting in Gibeah, under the tamarisk-tree in Ramah, with his spear in his hand, and all his servants were standing about him. ^7And Saul said unto his servants that stood about him, Hear now, ye Benjamites; will the son of Jesse give every one of you fields and vineyards, will he make you all captains of thousands and captains of hundreds, ^8that all of you have conspired against me, and there is none that discloseth to me when my son maketh a league with the son of Jesse, and there is none of you that is sorry for me, or discloseth unto me that my son hath stirred up my servant against me, to lie in wait, as at this day? ^9Then answered Doeg the Edomite, who stood by the servants of Saul, and said, I saw the son of Jesse coming to Nob, to Ahimelech the son of Ahitub. ^10And he inquired of Jehovah for him, and gave him victuals, and gave him the sword of Goliath the Philistine.

^11Then the king sent to call Ahimelech the priest, the son of Ahitub, and all his father's house, the priests that were in Nob: and they came all of them to the king. ^12And Saul said, Hear now, thou son of Ahitub. And he answered, Here I am, my lord. ^13And Saul said unto him, Why have ye conspired against me, thou and the son of Jesse, in that thou hast given him bread, and a sword, and hast inquired of God for him, that he should rise against me, to lie in wait, as at this day? ^14Then Ahimelech answered the king, and said, And who among all thy servants is so faithful as David, who is the king's son-in-law, and is taken into thy council, and is honorable in thy house? ^15Have I to-day begun to inquire of God for him? be it far from me: let not the king impute anything unto his servant, nor to all the house of my father; for thy servant knoweth nothing of all this, less or more. ^16And the king said, Thou shalt surely die, Ahimelech, thou, and all thy father's house. ^17And the king said unto the guard that stood about him, Turn, and slay the priests of Jehovah; because their hand also is with David, and because they knew that he fled, and did not disclose it to me. But the servants of the king would not put forth their hand to fall upon the priests of Jehovah. ^18And the king said to Doeg, Turn thou, and fall upon the priests. And Doeg the Edomite turned, and he fell upon the priests, and he slew on that day fourscore and five persons that did wear a linen ephod. ^19And Nob, the city of the priests, smote he with the edge of the sword, both men and women, children and sucklings, and oxen and asses and sheep, with the edge of the sword.

^20And one of the sons of Ahimelech, the son of Ahitub, named Abiathar, escaped, and fled after David. ^21And Abiathar told David that Saul had slain Jehovah's priests. ^22And David said unto Abiathar, I knew on that day, when Doeg the Edomite was there, that he would surely tell Saul: I have occasioned the death of all the persons of thy father's house. ^23Abide thou with me, fear not; for he that seeketh my life seeketh thy life: for with me thou shalt be in safeguard.

1 Samuel 23

23

^1And they told David, saying, Behold, the Philistines are fighting against Keilah, and are robbing the threshing-floors. ^2Therefore David inquired of Jehovah, saying, Shall I go and smite these Philistines? And Jehovah said unto David, Go, and smite the Philistines, and save Keilah. ^3And David's men said unto him, Behold, we are afraid here in Judah: how much more then if we go to Keilah against the armies of the Philistines? ^4Then David inquired of Jehovah yet again. And Jehovah answered him, and said, Arise, go down to Keilah; for I will deliver the Philistines into thy hand. ^5And David and his men went to Keilah, and fought with the Philistines, and brought away their cattle, and slew them with a great slaughter. So David save the inhabitants of Keilah. ^6And it came to pass, when Abiathar the son of Ahimelech fled to David to Keilah, that he came down with an ephod in his hand.

^7And it was told Saul that David was come to Keilah. And Saul said, God hath delivered him into my hand; for he is shut in, by entering into a town that hath gates and bars. ^8And Saul summoned all the people to war, to go down to Keilah, to besiege David and his men. ^9And David knew that Saul was devising mischief against him; and he said to Abiathar the priest, Bring hither the ephod. ^10Then said David, O Jehovah, the God of Israel, thy servant hath surely heard that Saul seeketh to come to Keilah, to destroy the city for my sake. ^11Will the men of Keilah deliver me up into his hand? will Saul come down, as thy servant hath heard? O Jehovah, the God of Israel, I beseech thee, tell thy servant. And Jehovah said, He will come down. ^12Then said David, Will the men of Keilah deliver up to me and my men into the hand of Saul? And Jehovah said, They will deliver thee up. ^13Then David and his men, who were about six hundred, arose and departed out of Keilah, and went whithersoever they could go. And it was told Saul that David was escaped from Keilah; and he forbare to go forth. ^14And David abode in the wilderness in the strongholds, and remained in the hill-country in the wilderness of Ziph. And Saul sought him every day, but God delivered him not into his hand.

^15And David saw that Saul was come out to seek his life: and David was in the wilderness of Ziph in the wood. ^16And Jonathan, Saul's son, arose, and went to David into the wood, and strengthened his hand in God. ^17And he said unto him, Fear not; for the hand of Saul my father shall not find thee; and thou shalt be king over Israel, and I shall be next unto thee; and that also Saul my father knoweth. ^18And they two made a covenant before Jehovah: and David abode in the wood, and Jonathan went to his house.

^19Then came up the Ziphites to Saul to Gibeah, saying, Doth not David hide himself with us in the strongholds in the wood, in the hill of Hachilah, which is on the south of the desert? ^20Now therefore, O king, come down, according to all the desire of thy soul to come down; and our part shall be to deliver him up into the king's hand. ^21And Saul said, Blessed be ye of Jehovah; for ye have had compassion on me. ^22Go, I pray you, make yet more sure, and know and see his place where his haunt is, and who hath seen him there; for it is told me that he dealeth very subtly. ^23See therefore, and take knowledge of all the lurking-places where he hideth himself, and come ye again to me of a certainty, and I will go with you: and it shall come to pass, if he be in the land, that I will search him out among all the thousands of Judah.

^24And they arose, and went to Ziph before Saul: but David and his men were in the wilderness of Maon, in the Arabah on the south of the desert. ^25And Saul and his men went to seek him. And they told David: wherefore he came down to the rock, and abode in the wilderness of Maon. And when Saul heard that, he pursued after David in the wilderness of Maon. ^26And Saul went on this side of the mountain, and David and his men on that side of the mountain: and David made haste to get away for fear of Saul; for Saul and his men compassed David and his men round about to take them. ^27But there came a messenger unto Saul, saying, Haste thee, and come; for the Philistines have made a raid upon the land. ^28So Saul returned from pursuing after David, and went against the Philistines: therefore they called that place Sela-hammahlekoth. ^29And David went up from thence, and dwelt in the strongholds of En-gedi.

1 Samuel 24

24

^1And it came to pass, when Saul was returned from following the Philistines, that it was told him, saying, Behold, David is in the wilderness of En-gedi. ^2Then Saul took three thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and went to seek David and his men upon the rocks of the wild goats. ^3And he came to the sheepcotes by the way, where was a cave; and Saul went in to cover his feet. Now David and his men were abiding in the innermost parts of the cave. ^4And the men of David said unto him, Behold, the day of which Jehovah said unto thee, Behold, I will deliver thine enemy into thy hand, and thou shalt do to him as it shall seem good unto thee. Then David arose, and cut off the skirt of Saul's robe privily. ^5And it came to pass afterward, that David's heart smote him, because he had cut off Saul's skirt. ^6And he said unto his men, Jehovah forbid that I should do this thing unto my lord, Jehovah's anointed, to put forth my hand against him, seeing he is Jehovah's anointed. ^7So David checked his men with these words, and suffered them not to rise against Saul. And Saul rose up out of the cave, and went on his way.

^8David also arose afterward, and went out of the cave, and cried after Saul, saying, My lord the king. And when Saul looked behind him, David bowed with his face to the earth, and did obeisance. ^9And David said to Saul, Wherefore hearkenest thou to men's words, saying, Behold, David seeketh thy hurt? ^10Behold, this day thine eyes have seen how that Jehovah had delivered thee to-day into my hand in the cave: and some bade me kill thee; but mine eye spared thee; and I said, I will not put forth my hand against my lord; for he is Jehovah's anointed. ^11Moreover, my father, see, yea, see the skirt of thy robe in my hand; for in that I cut off the skirt of thy robe, and killed thee not, know thou and see that there is neither evil nor transgression in my hand, and I have not sinned against thee, though thou huntest after my life to take it. ^12Jehovah judge between me and thee, and Jehovah avenge me of thee; but my hand shall not be upon thee. ^13As saith the proverb of the ancients, Out of the wicked cometh forth wickedness; but my hand shall not be upon thee. ^14After whom is the king of Israel come out? after whom dost thou pursue? after a dead dog, after a flea. ^15Jehovah therefore be judge, and give sentence between me and thee, and see, and plead my cause, and deliver me out of thy hand.

^16And it came to pass, when David had made an end of speaking these words unto Saul, that Saul said, Is this thy voice, my son David? And Saul lifted up his voice, and wept. ^17And he said to David, Thou art more righteous than I; for thou hast rendered unto me good, whereas I have rendered unto thee evil. ^18And thou hast declared this day how that thou hast dealt well with me, forasmuch as when Jehovah had delivered me up into thy hand, thou killedst me not. ^19For if a man find his enemy, will he let him go well away? wherefore Jehovah reward thee good for that which thou hast done unto me this day. ^20And now, behold, I know that thou shalt surely be king, and that the kingdom of Israel shall be established in thy hand. ^21Swear now therefore unto me by Jehovah, that thou wilt not cut off my seed after me, and that thou wilt not destroy my name out of my father's house. ^22And David sware unto Saul. And Saul went home; but David and his men gat them up unto the stronghold.

1 Samuel 25

25

^1And Samuel died; and all Israel gathered themselves together, and lamented him, and buried him in his house at Ramah. And David arose, and went down to the wilderness of Paran.

^2And there was a man in Maon, whose possessions were in Carmel; and the man was very great, and he had three thousand sheep, and a thousand goats: and he was shearing his sheep in Carmel. ^3Now the name of the man was Nabal; and the name of his wife Abigail; and the woman was of good understanding, and of a beautiful countenance: but the man was churlish and evil in his doings; and he was of the house of Caleb. ^4And David heard in the wilderness that Nabal was shearing his sheep. ^5And David sent ten young men, and David said unto the young men, Get you up to Carmel, and go to Nabal, and greet him in my name: ^6and thus shall ye say to him that liveth in prosperity, Peace be unto thee, and peace be to thy house, and peace be unto all that thou hast. ^7And now I have heard that thou hast shearers: thy shepherds have now been with us, and we did them no hurt, neither was there aught missing unto them, all the while they were in Carmel. ^8Ask thy young men, and they will tell thee: wherefore let the young men find favor in thine eyes; for we come in a good day: give, I pray thee, whatsoever cometh to thy hand, unto thy servants, and to thy son David.

^9And when David's young men came, they spake to Nabal according to all those words in the name of David, and ceased. ^10And Nabal answered David's servants, and said, Who is David? and who is the son of Jesse? there are many servants now-a-days that break away every man from his master. ^11Shall I then take my bread, and my water, and my flesh that I have killed for my shearers, and give it unto men of whom I know not whence they are? ^12So David's young men turned on their way, and went back, and came and told him according to all these words. ^13And David said unto his men, Gird ye on every man his sword. And they girded on every man his sword; and David also girded on his sword: and there went up after David about four hundred men; and two hundred abode by the baggage.

^14But one of the young men told Abigail, Nabal's wife, saying, Behold, David sent messengers out of the wilderness to salute our master; and he railed at them. ^15But the men were very good unto us, and we were not hurt, neither missed we anything, as long as we went with them, when we were in the fields: ^16they were a wall unto us both by night and by day, all the while we were with them keeping the sheep. ^17Now therefore know and consider what thou wilt do; for evil is determined against our master, and against all his house: for he is such a worthless fellow, that one cannot speak to him.

^18Then Abigail made haste, and took two hundred loaves, and two bottles of wine, and five sheep ready dressed, and five measures of parched grain, and a hundred clusters of raisins, and two hundred cakes of figs, and laid them on asses. ^19And she said unto her young men, Go on before me; behold, I come after you. But she told not her husband Nabal. ^20And it was so, as she rode on her ass, and came down by the covert of the mountain, that, behold, David and his men came down toward her; and she met them. ^21Now David had said, Surely in vain have I kept all that this fellow hath in the wilderness, so that nothing was missed of all that pertained unto him: and he hath returned me evil for good. ^22God do so unto the enemies of David, and more also, if I leave of all that pertain to him by the morning light so much as one man-child.

^23And when Abigail saw David, she hasted, and alighted from her ass, and fell before David on her face, and bowed herself to the ground. ^24And she fell at his feet, and said, Upon me, my lord, upon me be the iniquity; and let thy handmaid, I pray thee, speak in thine ears, and hear thou the words of thy handmaid. ^25Let not my lord, I pray thee, regard this worthless fellow, even Nabal; for as his name is, so is he; Nabal is his name, and folly is with him: but I thy handmaid saw not the young men of my lord, whom thou didst send. ^26Now therefore, my lord, as Jehovah liveth, and as thy soul liveth, seeing Jehovah hath withholden thee from bloodguiltiness, and from avenging thyself with thine own hand, now therefore let thine enemies, and them that seek evil to my lord, be as Nabal. ^27And now this present which thy servant hath brought unto my lord, let it be given unto the young men that follow my lord. ^28Forgive, I pray thee, the trespass of thy handmaid: for Jehovah will certainly make my lord a sure house, because my lord fighteth the battles of Jehovah; and evil shall not be found in thee all thy days. ^29And though men be risen up to pursue thee, and to seek thy soul, yet the soul of my lord shall be bound in the bundle of life with Jehovah thy God; and the souls of thine enemies, them shall he sling out, as from the hollow of a sling. ^30And it shall come to pass, when Jehovah shall have done to my lord according to all the good that he hath spoken concerning thee, and shall have appointed thee prince over Israel, ^31that this shall be no grief unto thee, nor offence of heart unto my lord, either that thou hast shed blood without cause, or that my lord hath avenged himself. And when Jehovah shall have dealt well with my lord, then remember thy handmaid.

^32And David said to Abigail, Blessed be Jehovah, the God of Israel, who sent thee this day to meet me: ^33and blessed be thy discretion, and blessed be thou, that hast kept me this day from bloodguiltiness, and from avenging myself with mine own hand. ^34For in very deed, as Jehovah, the God of Israel, liveth, who hath withholden me from hurting thee, except thou hadst hasted and come to meet me, surely there had not been left unto Nabal by the morning light so much as one man-child. ^35So David received of her hand that which she had brought him: and he said unto her, Go up in peace to thy house; see, I have hearkened to thy voice, and have accepted thy person.

^36And Abigail came to Nabal; and, behold, he held a feast in his house, like the feast of a king; and Nabal's heart was merry within him, for he was very drunken: wherefore she told him nothing, less or more, until the morning light. ^37And it came to pass in the morning, when the wine was gone out of Nabal, that his wife told him these things, and his heart died within him, and he became as a stone. ^38And it came to pass about ten days after, that Jehovah smote Nabal, so that he died.

^39And when David heard that Nabal was dead, he said, Blessed be Jehovah, that hath pleaded the cause of my reproach from the hand of Nabal, and hath kept back his servant from evil: and the evil-doing of Nabal hath Jehovah returned upon his own head. And David sent and spake concerning Abigail, to take her to him to wife. ^40And when the servants of David were come to Abigail to Carmel, they spake unto her, saying, David hath sent us unto thee, to take thee to him to wife. ^41And she arose, and bowed herself with her face to the earth, and said, Behold, thy handmaid is a servant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord. ^42And Abigail hasted, and arose, and rode upon an ass, with five damsels of hers that followed her; and she went after the messengers of David, and became his wife.

^43David also took Ahinoam of Jezreel; and they became both of them his wives. ^44Now Saul had given Michal his daughter, David's wife, to Palti the son of Laish, who was of Gallim.